How do we become the people we are?
With our full-blown personalities, and our high IQs, our motivations, our dreams, our
skills — we all started out like this.
In the first two years of life, we go from being an extremely helpless individual to
being… someone who is capable of walking, talking, telling the difference between boys
and girls, starting to toilet themselves, feed themselves—it’s a phenomenal rate
of growth in the first two years of life.
I’ll be focusing on the early part of human development.
Developmental psychologists, in general, study change over time; in psychological phenomena
and across the entire lifespan.
A lot of developmentalists focus on infancy and early childhood because so much amazing
stuff happens in such a really short time.
Infancy has always fascinated people.
Infant means “without speech” and it’s traditionally considered the first two years,
even though babies do start using language after about the first twelve months of life.
But they don’t form sentences, really, or use language as their primary means of communication
until they’re about two years old.
Hence, “infant” referring to the first two years of life.
Now here’s a one week old person.
He’s pretty helpless.
Pretty uncoordinated.
Cute.
But apparently, not a whole lot going on.
Half-asleep.
Oh, there’s something.
Well that’s what they do.
That’s a baby who appears to be in a transitional state between being awake and being alert,
because he was sort of drifting in and out of sleep there.
When he was alert, you could see a bit of a spark in his eyes.
But, invariably, when people spend some time with a baby this age, they end up asking themselves
this question, what is going on inside there?
What is in that tiny mind?
He’s like me.
In fact, I was one of those just, in my case, 52 years ago.
Is there cognitive processing inside the baby’s mind that’s similar to that of adults?
Do they think the way we think?
Do they feel the way we feel?
Do they respond in anything like the way older people would?
In some ways you might think, well yes, of course!
There’s got to be continuity across human life.
He’s got a human brain, so probably he processes sensory information in similar ways to the
way we do.
But then of course, there’s no language there, and much of our thought is language-based.
And, he does looks pretty uncoordinated.
It was only in the last 40 years that people started trying to systematically address the
question of...
What is inside a baby’s mind?