https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CBYhVcO4WgI
That just sounds terrible
all around.
These all sounded really
bad,
but they turned out to be
good.
If they had sounded really
good,
there would have been too
many people working on them.
As Peter Tills discussed in
the fifth class,
you want an idea that turns
into a monopoly, but
you can't get a monopoly in
a big market right away.
Too much competition for
that.
You have to find a small
market in which you can get
a monopoly, and then quickly
expand.
This is why some great
startup ideas look
really bad at the beginning.
It's good if you can say
something like, today only
the small subset of users
are going to use my product.
But I'm gonna get all of
them.
And in the future,
almost everyone will use my
product.
>> Here's the thing that's
gonna come up a lot,
you need conviction in your
own beliefs, and
the willingness to ignore
others nay saying.
The hard part is that this
is a very fine line.
There's right on one side of
it, and crazy on the other.
But keep in mind that if you
do come up with
a great idea, most people
are going to think it's bad.
You should be happy about
that.
It means they won't compete
with you.
This is also a reason why
it's
not usually dangerous to
tell people about your idea.
The truly good ideas don't
sound like
they're worth stealing.
You want an idea about which
you can say,
I know it sounds like a bad
idea.
But hear specifically why
it's actually a great one.
You wanna sound crazy, but
you wanna actually be right.
And you want an idea that
not many
other people are working on.
And it's okay if it doesn't
sound big at first.
Common mistake among
founders,
especially first time
is they think that the first
version of their product,
the first version of their
idea,
needs to sound really big.
But it doesn't.
It needs to take over a
small,
specific market and expand
from there.
That's how most great
companies have started.
Unpopular but right is what
you're going for.
You want something that
sounds like a bad idea, but
is a good idea.
You also really wanna take
the time to
think about how the market's
going to evolve.
You need a market that's
going to be big in
ten years.
Most investors are obsessed
with the market size today,
and they don't think at all
about how the market is
going to evolve.
In fact, I think this is one
of the biggest
systemic mistakes that
investors make.
They think about the growth
of the startup itself,
they don't think about the
growth of the market.
I care much more about the
growth rate of
the market than it's current
size.
And I also care if
there's any reason that it's
gonna top out.
You should think about this.
I'd prefer to invest in
a company that's going after
a small but
rapidly growing market than
a big but slow growing one.
One of the big advantages of
these sorts of markets um,
these small but rapidly
growing markets, is that
customers are usually pretty
desperate for a solution.
And they'll put, put up with
an imperfect but
rapidly improving product.
And a big advantage of being
a student, one of
the two biggest advantages
is that you probably have
better intuition about which
markets are likely to
start growing rapidly than
older people do.
Another thing that students
usually don't understand, or
at least takes a while you
cannot create a market that
doesn't want to exist.
You can basically change
everything in
a startup but the market.
So you should actually do
some thinking, to be sure or
at least as sure as you can
be, that the market your
going after is going to grow
and be there.
There are a lot of different
ways to
talk about the right kind of
market.
For example, surfing someone
else's wave or
stepping into an up elevator
or being part of a movement.
But all of this is just a
way of saying you want
a market that's going to
grow really quickly.
It may seem small today.
It may be small today.
But you know, and
other people don't that it's
gonna grow really fast.
So think about where this is
happening in the world.
You need this sort of
a tail wind to make a
startup successful.
The exciting thing is there
are probably more of
these tail winds now than
ever before.
As Mark Andreessen says,
software is eating the
world.
It's just everywhere.
There are like, so many
great ideas out there and
you just have to pick one,
and
find one that you really
care about.
Another version of this,
that would, gets down to the
same idea,
is Sequoia's famous
question.
Why now?
Why is this the perfect time
for this particular idea and
to start this particular
company?
Why couldn't it have been
done two years ago?
And why will two years in
the future be too late?
For the most successful
startups we've been
involved with, they've all
had a great idea,
great answer to this
question.
And if you don't, you should
be at
least somewhat suspicious
about it.
In general, it's best if
you're building something
that you yourself need.
You'll understand it much
better than if you have to
understand it by talking to
a customer to build the very
first version.
If you don't know it
yourself and
you're building something
that someone else needs,
realize that you're at a big
disadvantage and get very,
very close to your
customers.
Try to work in their office
if you can.
And if not, talk to them
multiple times a day.
Another somewhat
counter-intuitive thing
about good start up ideas,
is that they're almost
always very easy to explain,
and very easy to understand.
If it takes more than a
sentence to
explain what you're doing
um,
it's almost always a sign
that it's too complicated.
It should be a clearly
articulate,
articulated vision with a
small number of words.
And the best ideas are
usually either,
very different from existing
companies in one
important way.
Like Google being a search
engine that worked
just really well and none of
the other stuff of
the portals or totally new,
like Space X.
Any company that's a clone
of
something else that already
exists with some small or
made up differentiator,
like we're gonna be x
beautiful design or
we're gonna be y for people
that like red wine instead.
That usually fails.
So as I mentioned one of the
great things about being
a student is you
have a very good perspective
on new technology.
And learning to get good at
having new
ideas takes a while.
So start working on that
right now.
That's one thing we hear
from people all the time,
that they wish they had
done more when they were a
student.
The other is meeting
potential co-founders.
You have no idea how good of
an environment you are in
right now for meeting people
that you
can start a company with
down the road.
And the one thing that we
always tell college
students, is more
important than starting any
particular startup
is getting to know a lot of
potential co-founders.
So I want to finish this
section of my talk
with a quote from 50 Cent.
This is from when he was
asked about vitamin water.
I won't read it, its up
there.
But it's about the
importance of
thinking about what
customers want, and
thinking about the demands
of the market.
Most people don't do this,
most students especially
don't do this.
If you can just do this one
thing, if you can just
learn to think about the
market first, you will have
a big leg up on most people
starting startups.
All right, and this is
something.
This is probably the thing
that we
see wrong with Y Combinator
apps most frequently, is
that people have not thought
about the market first.
And what people want first.
So for the next section,
I'm gonna talk about
building a great product.
And here again,
I'm gonna use a very broad
definition of product.
It includes customer support
and
copyright explaining the
product.
Anything involved in your
customer's interaction with
what you built for them.
To build a really great
company, you first have to
turn a great idea into a
great product.
This is really hard, but
it's crucially important,
and fortunately it's pretty
fun.
Although great products are
always new to the world and
it's hard to give you advice
about what to build,
there are enough
commonalities that we
can give you a lot of advice
about how to build it.
One of the most important
tasks for a founder is to
make sure that the company
builds a great product.
Until you've built a great
product,
almost nothing else matters.
When really successful
startup founders tell
the story of their early
days.
It's almost always sitting
in front of the computer,
working on their product or
talking to their customers.
That's pretty much all the
time.
They do very little else,
and
you should be very skeptical
if your time allocation is
much different.
Most other problems that
founders are trying to
solve, raising money,
getting more press,
hiring, business
development, et cetera.
These are significantly
easier when you
have a great product.
It's really important to
take care of that first.
Step 1, is to build
something that users love.
At YC, we tell founders to
work on their product,
talk to users, exercise eat
and
sleep and very little else.
All the other stuff I just
mentioned, PR conferences,
recruiting advisers, doing
partnerships,
you should ignore all of
that and
just build a product.
And get it as good as
possible by
talking to your users.
Your job is to build
something that users love.
Very few companies that go
on to be
super successful get there
without first doing this.
A lot of good on paper
startups fail because they
merely make something that
people like.
Making something that people
want,
but only a medium amount is
a great way to fail and
not understand why you're
failing.
So these are the two jobs.
Something that we say at
YC a lot is that it's better
to build a small number,
it's better to build
something that a small
number of users love than a
large number of users like.
Of course, it'd be best to
build something that a small
number of users love.
But opportunities to do that
for V1 are rare, and
they're usually not
available to startups.
So in practice,
you end up choosing either
the grey or the orange.
You make something that a
lot of users like a little
bit, or something that a
small number of users,
like, love a lot.
And this is a very important
piece of advice.
Build something that a small
number of users love.
It's much easier to expand
from something that