https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H8Dl8rZ6qwE
And that could managing
people.
It could be taking on a
project.
But the implicit contract
with that is that if
your going to ask somebody
to take a really big risk on
that, it shouldn't be like
one-way through the door and
if you don't succeed,
otherwise it creates fright
to give it a shot.
So we have some folks that
are managing large teams
that started as individual
programmers, where they were
engineering and they said
hey, I would love to try.
I'd love to try leading a
project and
then leading a group and
then taking responsibility
for
management, taking a group.
And we've had other folks
that tried it and
they were like, I'm really
glad I tried it because I
never wanna do that again.
We try to make sure that,
for those people, like you
can have just as much impact
at a company through your
individual contributions as
an engineer or designer.
You don't have to manage.
But it's really hard to
predict until you give
people a shot.
And so my strong preference
is that you give as many
people a shot as possible,
in the few areas where you
really feel like there's too
much learning curve relative
to the business objective
you're trying to achieve.
That's when you look for
somebody who might be able
to walk in and really
execute well in that job.
Are you going to answer the
other question?
>> Oh, so the question was
how has the vision changed
since we initially started?
>> Yes,
>> Sure,
well I think on the vision,
when we first started,
I think we started hiring
very inductively.
We were like, oh, we're
gonna build this really cool
tool.
People are gonna enjoy it.
I love collecting things.
Maybe other people like
collecting things.
And what we didn't expect,
that kind of revealed itself
early on,
was that looking at other
people's collections turns
out to be this really
amazing way to discover
things that you didn't know
you were looking for.
It becomes kind of a
solution to a problem that
a lot of other technologies
don't have.
And so, over the last couple
years especially,
we've poured enormous kind
of technical and design
resources into building out
recommendations products,
search products, feed
products.
Leveraging the unique data
that we have which
are these pins that were all
hand-picked by someone and
hand-categorized.
And then on the audience
side, the first big
surprise was truthfully when
we first started,
we didn't really know if
anyone would use it.
And we were just happy that
anybody that wasn't related
to us and
obligated by familial
relationship would use it.
And so one of the biggest
surprises has been how many
people and how diverse those
groups of people have been.
I think that's been one of
the things that's really
exciting.
And, the funny thing is,
that is often like the
company goes farther along,
your aspirations therefore
get bigger.
So there's this gap that
always exists,
I tell my team, between
where we are and
where I think we should be,
and
even though objectively,
we're much farther along,
I feel like the gap has
widened even farther.
But I think that's a really
common trait among
people who found companies.
>> Yes?
>> You said that like,
while selling a vision of
the company you had to
describe and
go into detail that how hard
it is going to be.
And like they won't see
their families for
three years but then they
will also get a thing that
their grandchildren can be
proud of.
But how do you really know?
Both of you know that the
second part is
not guaranteed but the first
part,
if they're not gonna see
their family for
the next year, it's gonna be
a different show.
So like, how can you be
authentic by selling that
vision of the company or is
it about giving high returns
for the high risk they are
taking when the number of
equity that already
>> Great question.
So the question is,
most start-ups are not the
iPhone.
You can't guarantee that
people's grandchildren
are gonna remember this
because most start-ups fail.
How do you convince people
to sort of
make sacrifices to join a
start-up?
>> I think, part of the way
in which it resonates with
people is because it's not
guaranteed, right?
If it were guaranteed then
it'd be boring.
And so it's that there is
the prospect of affecting
this outcome, but nothing
more than that potential.
To the not seeing their
families or
kids, start-ups often do
involve longer hours in
the beginning, but I think,
well.
I, I think that that
particular story is
probably somewhat
overstated.
I guess, it was, I think
Scott Forestall was trying
to recruit these people.
But I mean, even though
startups,
especially in the earlier
days,
tend to involve somewhat
longer working hours.
I think it was kind of this
tendency to,
to exaggerate it.
And sort of,
I mean it's like the startup
version of fishing.
Like, every startup thinks
they worked even more insane
hours than, you know,
the next one back in the
early days.
Like, we literally never
sleep or slept rather,
for two years.
So I don't know.
I think that realistically
for most people,
it's not that big a
sacrifice, right?
You're, maybe on average,
being really realistic about
it, you'll work two hours
more on average per day.
It's certainly a sacrifice,
but
it is not forgoing all you
know, pleasure and
enjoyment for the next half
decade.
>> Yeah, I mean, I think
even the iPhone
wasn't the iPhone before it
got done, right?
I mean, no smart person
you're hiring is
under the illusion that you
have a crystal ball into
the future that only you
have, and
that joining is a guaranteed
thing.
And in fact, if you're
telling him that and
they select in, you probably
shouldn't hire them.
Because they,
they didn't pass like a
basic intelligence test
about uncertainty in the
future.
But I, but I think it's fair
to say, like you know,
what's exciting and where
you think you can go, and
where it's going to be hard
and chart your best plan.
And then tell them why their
role in it can be
instrumental, because it is.
You know I really liked what
you said.
You know, if you tell people
like hey we're gonna go
to Mars, it attracts the
best people and
then you're incrementally
closer to getting to Mars.
And they know that going in.
What I would discourage
doing is
just whitewashing all of
that.
And if people kind of are
joining because they want
sort of oh, I want all this
certainty and guarantee of
working at Google, plus like
the perk of working in
a small start up and more
email, and transparency.
Like that's, that's a
really,
really negative sign.
And for
example, when I interview
people they'll often say oh,
I'm really passionate at
what you're doing, and
then I'm like well, what
else are you interviewing?
And then they'll just list
seven companies that have
nothing to do with each
other except they're sort of
at the same stage we're at.
They're like, you know,
I love the problem of
discovery, so
I'm interviewing at Stripe,
Dropbox, Airbnb, Uber.
Now I'm also putting into my
resumé into Google X,
into that part of the
division.
And that's a sign that
they're probably not
being authentic with which
they care about.
>> Yeah.
>> And those folks often,
when things get really hard,
they won't stick it out and
work through it.
Because they were really
signing up for
an experience, not for
achieving a goal.
>> I think the other thing
that motivates people
a great deal, in addition to
the prospect of sort of
them you know, affecting
some outcome is just sort of
the personal development
angle.
And that a start up,
just because it's much, kind
of more lightly staffed.
It's much less forgiving,
right?
In that, like,
even if you're the best
person in the world,
if you're not going to.
Well, whether or not you're
the best or
the worst person in the
world, you're probably not
going to significantly alter
Google's trajectory, right?
Whereas if you sort of,
really wanted to benchmark
yourself, and
see how much a contribution
and an impact you can make.
And I think that prospect is
quite compelling to a lot of
the best people, then a
start up is
a much better place to, to
go test that.
>> All right.
>> Last question, who'd you
want?
Last question.
So this question is for
Ben, but you guys can all
answer it.
But how has your user base
effected your
hiring strategies?
So Pinterest is a site
that's used like 80% by
women, so
how did that effect your
initial hiring decisions?
>> How has your user base
effected your
hiring strategy?
>> Yes, so, You know,
conventional wisdom is like
you only hire people that
religiously use your product
every single day.
And that probably works
really well if
you're making an API,
probably amazing.
For us, we screen for people
that are ambitious and
excited about the vision of
cracking discovery online.
And they have to know
exactly how
our service works and have
to have used it.
But they may not be a
lifelong user.
And that, for us it's this
great opportunity because we
can be like, what is the
barrier that's
preventing you from using
it?
Come join, remove that
barrier,
and help us get closer to
that vision.
I don't know, there's a lot
of,
if you read any sort of
book, there's all this
startup wisdom that sounds
like really reasonable.
But it's only useful if it
works in
your particular
circumstance.
And so for us, we've had to
sort of
broaden the lens a little
bit in looking broadly about
people that are ambitious
about the mission.
That care about the product
and
our approach to building
products,
even if from day one, they
weren't our earliest users.
>> The one thing I'll just
tack on to that is that when
we talked about the fact
that, you know,
it's really hard to hire for
those early employees.
And you know, you have
people who have
other good options.
You're very much at the ugly
duckling stage.
Finding people who are
passionate about your
product can be a great way
to find people.
Because there you kind of
have an unnatural advantage
over other companies.
And so I know, for
sure, in Stripe's case, we
definitely, we hired I think
it was four Stripe users in
the very early days.
And you know, those were
people who,
who we probably couldn't
have gotten otherwise.
I'm sure it was the same in
Pinterest's case,
where you'll get all this
benefit of working at
Pinterest and hey, it's
Pinterest.
And you get to work where
you pin.
Yeah.
>> Thank you guys very much
for coming in today.
>> Thank you.