https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H8Dl8rZ6qwE
And I think there's a lot of
truth to that.
But for our particular first
ten people, the things we
sort of figured out that
seemed to be important were
they were also very genuine
and straight.
I think that actually
matters quite a lot in that
sort of they're people that
sort of that others want to
work with, that they're
people that others trust.
They sort of have an
intellectual honesty in
how they approach problems
and, and so forth.
They were people who
really liked getting things
finished.
There's a lot of people who
are really excited about
tons of things.
Only a subset of those are
actually excited about like
completing things.
You know, there's a lot of
talk about, for
example hiring people off
their GitHub resumes,
whatever, actually think
that doesn't quite ring,
kind of correct to me.
In the sense that place is a
large premium on sort of
lots of different things.
I think it's actually a
priori,
sort of much more
interesting to work with
someone who has spent two
years really investing in
going deep in a particular
area.
And then the third trait
they all seem to have in
common is they just sort of
cared a great deal.
Like, it was offensive to
them when something was
just a little bit off.
And kind of again,
in hindsight, there are all
these like crazy things we
used to do that I mean, do
in fact seem crazy like we
probably shouldn't have done
them,
but everyone was always like
well, was borderline insane
in sort of how much they
cared about tiny details.
Like we used to, like every
single API request that
ever generated an error went
to all of our inboxes and
phoned all of us.
Because it seems terrible to
ever have an error that
didn't go and
get a resolution from the
user standpoint.
Or we used to like copy
everyone else on
every outgoing email.
And we'd like point out
slight grammar or
spelling mistakes to each
other, because it's terrible
to ever send an email with a
spelling mistake.
So anyway those were the
three traits come
from that area.
A genuine, caring a great
deal.
And, so what was my second
one?
>> The other one.
>> Yeah so.
Sorry yes completing things
like list of three items.
>> Yeah, I'm only gonna say
I just don't think
there's any wrong place to
find people, so when I
look back at our first few
folks that we hired.
They came from all over the
place.
Like I put up ads on
Craigslist.
I went to random tech talks.
You know, we met people at,
we used to throw weekly
barbeques at the office.
It was like bring your own
food and drinks.
And then we would just talk
to folks.
I think every time I ever
went and
got coffee in Palo Alto.
Like one of you guys was
recruiting at
Coopa because their office
was like
strategically situated next
to the best coffee shop.
But I think that the really
good people generally,
they're generally doing
something else, and
so you have to go seek them
out,
rather than expecting that
they're gonna seek you out.
Triple so, when no one's
ever heard of or
is using the product that
you're working on.
>> Yeah it's probably really
important to
have a great elevator pitch.
Not even for investors, but
just because everyone you
run into right now is maybe
six months, a year down the
road, a potential recruit.
And so, the right time to
have gotten them
excited about your company,
the right time for
them to have started
following us,
and be thinking about it if
they think about what
they're going to do next, is
as soon as you can start.
It's gonna take a very long
time to recruit people so to
being able to consistently
get people excited about
what you're doing will pay
back dividends later.
>> Maybe this is a little
tangential but John and
I were also chatting
yesterday afternoon sort of
like a bunch of our friends
have sort of
started companies right out
of school.
We were sort of thinking
about,
what seems to go wrong in
those companies.
And I think something,
that may be the most common
failure mode.
Since we said of doing
something kind of
overly niche, or overly sort
of specific and banded.
I think maybe it comes from
sort of like there's a major
shift in time horizon.
As you go from classes to
building a start-up.
Right?
A class kind of plays out in
a quarter or a semester or
whatever.
Whereas a start-up is like a
five or ten year thing.
And I think this is really
problematic because it's
actually quite hard to hire
people for
niche things, in that if you
tell somebody,
look we're going to build a
rocket that goes to Mars.
Like I mean that sounds
almost impossible, but
also sounds fucking awesome.
Right?
And so it's actually pretty
easy to convince people to
work on it.
Of course, if it's well, you
know,
we're going to build this, I
don't wanna single out any
particular idea, because
probably sound like I'm
picking some actual start up
that's doing it.
But you know, if you pick
something pretty narrow,
something that maybe kind of
inductively comes out of
the kinds of problems you
solve as part of a class
project, that's actually a
much harder effort.
>> One specific question
that has come up a lot is,
how as a relatively
inexperienced founder do
you identify who the really
great people are?
So, you know, you meet
people at these barbecues or
for your friends or
whatever, and
maybe you've worked with
them a little bit.
But what specifically did,
did you guys do in your
processes to identify like,
you know, what this person's
going to be really great?
Or when did you really get
it wrong?
But what have you learned
about how to
identify raw talent if you
can't just say, well they
worked at Google or
Facebook, they must be good?
>> Well, I mean, you'll
never
like 100% know obviously
until you work with folks.
Which is why the flip side
of it is, you know,
if someone you hired just
wasn't a good fit,
you owe it to the company
and
to them, to tell them how
they can improve, and
if they're not working out
to fire them.
But I think that the
generally,
the question of talent falls
into two big buckets.
Like, one is you have some
sense of
what makes them good at
their job, and
there are some areas where
you have taste in that area,
and there's some where you
don't.
And the ones where you
don't are actually much more
difficult.
So what we would do is, is
we would do a few things.
Like first,
before talking to anyone we
try to get a sense for like
what is really world class
in that discipline mean.
And this becomes very
important later,
when you're hiring things
like Head of Finance and
you don't anything about
finance.
Except what was contained in
like a library book you
got about like an
introduction to finance,
or head of marketing.
So, I always made it a habit
of, like, talking to
people that I knew de facto
were world class and
then asking them,
specifically, what are the
key traits or
characteristics that you
look for?
What are the questions that
you ask, and
how do you find them?
And if you're looking for
the next person that's as
good as you, like,
where are, where is that
person working right now,
and, like, what's, what's
her phone number?
I think that, like, learning
what good and bad is during
the interview process, is
extremely expensive.
It's an expensive use of
your time, and
it's an expensive use of
everyone else's time,
so precalibration of that
really matters.
And then, once you have
someone in, sort of,
the interview process,
you'll build the process
over time,
to both screen quality.
And so at Pinterest, you
know, we have
an evolving set of standard
questions that we're
always rotating through, and
we're always measuring,
are these good indicators or
bad indicators of quality?
But the other thing that the
questions are meant to do,
is they're supposed to give
a sense for,
is this the right place for
that person to come and
work?
And this to the point you
guys made about being very
transparent about what's
gonna be easy or hard.
Really great people wanna do
things that are hard,
they wanna solve tough
problems.
And so, there was a certain
brilliance in
Google setting out these
interview questions that
were thought to be really
difficult.
Because then people who like
solving really
difficult problems, they
come out and seek those.
I think it's really
important,
even as companies get
bigger,
that you don't whitewash the
risks.
I heard that PayPal, you'd
go in and
after interviewing with like
Peter Thiel and
Max Levchin, then they would
say by the way like Visa and
MasterCard wanna kill us,
and
we might be doing something
that's illegal.
But if you succeed, you'll
redefine payments.
Or when they were recruiting
for iPhone,
they didn't even tell people
what they were doing.
They were like you won't see
your families for
three years, but when you're
done,
your kid's kids will
remember what you built.
And I think that's a really
good thing in recruiting as
well that you're very
transparent about why you
think it's an amazing
opportunity, but
you lay out in gory detail
why it's gonna be hard.
And then the right people
select in, or
they select out of that
opportunity.
>> Evidence suggest it's
worth a lot of
people to see their kids,
though.
I feel like one thing you
have to do as you try to
identify talent is have the
confidence to interview for,
in a way that works for you.
I think you know, if you're,
say you're not,
the world's best engineer
and
you're trying to interview
engineering candidates.
I think it's tempting to try
to
color code what everyone
else does.
And you know, get them to
call it on white board.
And do other engineering,
interviewee things.
You know in the case of
Stripe,
hiring our first engineer.
We flew the guy out, and we
spent a weekend coding with
him, and you know looked
over his shoulder and
kind of, it was the only way
we could really tell and
get ourselves confident
that, that person was good.
And I think you can actually
extend that to other roles,
where again you're not an
expert, and
that you know I'm no
business development guru.
But when we interview people
for
business development roles,
we'll ask them to do a
project, you know?
Where they talk about how
they would
improve an existing
partnership that Stripe has.
Or which new partnerships
they would go out and do.
And again, you know,
even though it's not my
domain area, I am actually
confident enough that I can
judge those pretty well.
And I think people often
have this imposter syndrome
when it comes to
interviewing for roles.
Yeah.
I think a pretty specific,
just kind of just tactical
thing, and to do for
again the first 10 people,
is to work with them as much
as you can before committing
to hiring them.
I mean, once you
reach a certain scale it's
kind of impractical,
because it's a huge time
commitment on their side.
And ultimately I mean it
just would be unskilled,
would be expensive from your
side.
But it's really worth it
to get the first ten people
right.