https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQ7ZvO5DpIw
Who cares?
But let's go.
And so this kind of combines
that, you know, this,
this image which I think is
the best of the,
of the, of, of the images we
found for
this yet, is kind of the sense
of how to think about.
Now, back to what I was saying
in terms of having
an investment thesis, part of
having an investment thesis
is, you chart it out, it's
kind of a list of bullets.
You say, like for example,
in early LinkedIn it was like
look everyone is actually
going to be benefited by
public professional network.
Everyone will realize
including companies that it's
better to have it play out
this way the initial set of
adoption will come from
essentially people who were
like visualize the role, thus
were willing to play with it,
and then eventually the mass
market will come on as
they begin to have a network
that is
already delivering a value
proposition to them.
That's what kind of
an investment thesis can look
like and then,
you know, you've got economics
like initial recruiting and
then, and then broadening and
other things.
You have that investment
thesis and
you say, is my investment
thesis increasing or
decreasing in confidence?
Do I think that the data I get
from the market,
when I talk to smart people,
how does that,
how does that change my
confidence in it?
And this is actually how you
essentially minimize risk.
So, for example, very early,
very early days in PayPal the,
part of what happened is, they
said,
okay well, we're going to do
cash on mobile phones.
We'll do cash on Palm Pilots
because it's really easy.
We actually realized that cash
on Palm Pilots wouldn't work
even before we launched the
product.
Because basically what
happened is,
I went in and said to Max and
Peter.
I said look here's our
challenge,
our challenge is, we're
probably doesn't remember what
Palm Pilot's are.
They were like, like early
PDAs And so
yeah we lived in what was Palm
Pilot central.
And the whole use case case
was splitting dinner tab.
And, how many people,
everyone at the table would
have a PalmPilot Zero to
one in every single
restaurant.
So, you could even just by
thinking it through,
you realize that the direction
you're on is
going to hit a minefield and
you need to pivot, and
that's when Max Legend came up
with the idea of saying,
actually in fact we could
synch by emails,
we could have email payments
as backbone of this, and
we were like oh, that's a good
idea.
And of course,
that's what the whole thing
kind of pivoted into.
And that's part of thinking
through minimizing the risks,
as you're actually executing.
Here's another one that's kind
of classic.
Which is, well, should I have
this long term vision?
Or should I be solving local,
near term problems?
And again, the answer is both.
It's these paradoxes and
the question is, is you jump
between them.
You should always have a long
term vision in mind because if
you actually completely lose
your, your directions
eventually you'll find
yourself in some field there's
not a good path out of, but if
you're not focused on solving
the problem that's immediately
in front of you, you're hosed.
Right.
And so part of the the
question about how you
put these things together is
you say, okay,
short term what's the thing I
need to be doing today?
Have I made progress today?
have I made progress this
week?
But is it largely on path?
So, I'll give you an example
of how this plays out in
terms of financing or in terms
of strategy.
So people frequently think
product strategy is
fundamental to how, start-ups.
Like I have a have a product
idea, that's a thing,
I'm a founder.
Actually in fact, the next
level down on
strategy is usually a product
distribution.
Whether it's consumer Internet
or or enterprise or
anything else.
Because actually in fact no
matter how good your
product is, if it doesn't get
to customers you're hosed.
So usually you have to have
product distribution as
more fundamental than the
actually what the product is.
And the one below it is
financing.
And the reason why it's
financing is if you run out of
money and the whole effort
goes away,
even if you have a really good
idea it doesn't work.
So frequently when you're
executing on a good
strategy you're actually in
fact, when I'm raising money,
this fundraising, I'm thinking
about the next fundraising.
I'm thinking about how I'm set
up for it, I'm establishing
relationships that would be
key to that and I'm,
I'm not executing like oh, the
only thing that matters is I
get to the next, is, is get to
the next fundraising because
you have this business that
you're building.
But I am thinking that as a
core strategy in
terms of how I'm executing and
frequently you're thinking
about okay, how does my
product distribution work such
that the financing works well?
And that's kind of how
you architect these things
together.
So how do you know if you
might be a great founder?
Well, it's, you should have
some superpowers.
It's generally speaking in
software useful to be a good
product person.
It's useful to have good
skills about kind of
leadership of bringing
networks in,
of persuading people.
And it's useful to be able to,
and this is kind of the most
fundamental,
is recognize whether or not
you're on track or not.
To have both that kind of
belief, but also
paranoia about, am I tracking
against my investment thesis?
And when you do that the right
way, and you're learning, and
you're assembling people, and
you're assembling networks
around you,
that's generally speaking,
how you end up being a great
founder.
Now, classically and
I deliberately put up five
white men, male pictures.
It's classically,
you have a kind of a these are
the iconic founders.
But in fact, founders can be
very diverse,
they can be extraordinarily
talented at
different areas because
there's different kinds of
entrepreneurial companies,
problems they're trying to
solve.
And I don't just mean
diversity in terms of classic,
you know, kind of gender,
race, et cetera.
I, diversity in age, diversity
in experience.
You know, Jack Baugh was a, a,
was a,
a teacher before he got into
this.
That's the kind of thing that
you can,
that you should think about.
And so the, the question is,
is how you cross uneven
ground.
How you assemble networks
around you.
How you get people to assemble
this,
it's a constantly changing
problem to face when you
are trying to found a company.
And so, I think that the thing
that I was trying
to get people to think about
with this is to say,
there's not one skill set.
There's an ability to learn
and adapt,
an ability to constantly have
a vision that's driving you,
but to be taking input from
all sources and
then to be cre, creating
networks around you,
and that's essentially what
makes a great founder.
And your ability to
do that while crossing uneven
ground in a fog.
Which is kind of the, the,
the, the way that
entrepreneurs, because you
don't really know like,
did you always know this was
going to work?
No.
Unless you are crazy.
Right.
Sometimes crazy works.
So with that I will now go to
a few questions.
But it was kind of this mind
set of founders.
Which is kind of key.
And if there's no ques, oh,
here.
>> I'm curious about how
Nathan, how you
you targeted the earlier, or
you selected the guys for
getting the right doctors who
knew would strengthen your
investment thesis to really
help it take off because it
seems like every start up is
faced with that.
>> Yep.
>> That same challenge.
>> So one of the really
fundamental things is to,
is to think about product
distribution as key.
And for LinkedIn, we had a
couple things going for us.
So one, the web was boring in
2003.
That basically what happened
is everyone had
thought the consumer net was
over.
And so people were doing clean
tag and
enterprise software and
everything else.
It's a much harder problem
now.
because everyone thinks the
Internet and
mobile is interesting.
And so breaking through the
noise is really key.
So the strategy we use
wouldn't work.
We just set up,
sent out some invitations to a
group of people and then
tuned the mechanism to have,
and did PR to get people.
Like one of the decisions we
made early that was right was
to say should we only allow it
as invite only?
Or should we allow cold sign
ups?
The reason we should allow
cold sign ups is
because the people who are
super enthusiastic about this
weren't necessarily the people
you know,
so they would sign up and
spread it.
That sort of thing were all
the kind of decisions we made.
Now that challenge is much
harder because the challenge
when you think about product
distribution is,
it's how are you competing for
potential customers' or
potential members time and
what do they think,
what do they have to believe
in.
Back in 2003 it was like
well,a professional network.
That's potentially a good
idea, what the hell.
I'll play with that.
There's not a lot of other
things for me to look at.
Today, there's tons of things
and so your strategy today,
when you're looking at product
distribution,
has to be, what is my really
decisive edge?
What is the hack that I know
that other people don't know?
>> Someone come to you,
how do you tell
>> So
how do I know someone's a good
founder or not?
well, it's not I'm a huge
believer in references.
Usually I only ever, actually
no.
100% of the time in this case,
I only meet with someone when
they come to me through a
reference.
So one of the things, by the
way is,
the thing is I, after this I
have to run off because I
have a meeting I need to get
to.
If you want to actually get
time and
attention Lee, find a
reference.
It's not a pitch to using
LinkedIn, it's a question of,
this is how you sort out time.
You can find out, like Sam
knows me.
Lift up, throw Sam under the
bus.
Right?
Yes.
And so a reference to me is in
fact the way that I do this.
And so for example, when I met
with the AirBnB guys.
Part of the reason why I
could interrupt them two
minutes into their pitch, and
say, I'm going to make you an
offer to invest.
I want to hear the rest of the
pitch,
because I think what you're
doing here is,
is, is magical and awesome.
Was because I'd already had
references on them.
Like that was only two
minutes,
not even thirty minutes.
Because I already knew about
them before coming in.
And by the way, by and large
that's some version of
that is true of most of the
great industries.
And it's that, it's that
network that's really key.