https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6fQHLK1aIBs
If you had more endorsements,
did you look at yourself in
the mirror more often?
Turns out you did.
So, we actually figured out
like
what was actually underneath
utilitarian product that
the product team thought they
were
building was actually a lot of
emotional vanity.
They didn't exactly translate
it to the best possible
feature, like the PayPal
example,
which you couldn't easily put
a button that,
said be more vain today, you
know, on the homepage.
>> That would probably not
work perfectly, so it
never really like took off the
way the PayPal example did.
But it clarified what the user
what users of
the product really wanted and
we wouldn't have found that
without looking for
anomalous data.
The final topic I want to talk
about is details.
And there's, in my assigned
reading,
there's a great book I really
like by BIll Walsh called,
The Score Takes Care of
Itself.
And the basic point of the
book is that if
you get all the details right,
you don't worry about how to
build a billion dollar
business,
how to have $100 million of
revenue,
how to have a billion users.
That's a byproduct of getting
all the details of what you
do everyday to be excellent.
So the example he talks about
in the book that really
resonated with me was he took
over the 49ers in 1979.
They were the worst team in
football.
I believe they were 2 and 14
the year before,
which is really bad for this,
if you don't know football.
In the next ten years, he
managed to transform the team
into the NFL's best, won three
Super Bowls.
And what's the first thing he
did to start going from
a terrible team to the best
team ever in many ways?
He actually taught the
receptionists how to
answer the phone properly.
He wrote a three-page memo
about how to
actually answer the phone.
Now, that may sound absurd.
But his point was, if the
organization as a whole
does everything exactly the
right way, then receivers, for
example, will start running
their routes at
seven-and-a-half yards, not
seven yards, not eight yards.
And that actually will matter.
And then everybody on the team
executes exactly up to
the same standard of
performance.
You will have an organization
that is performing at
the highest possible level,
and
then with enough random
variation, the highest
possible performance team will
do the best.
So the way you translate this
to a company are to
a lotta details that may not
matter.
They may not seem that they
matter superficially.
Most people would agree about
the details matter when it
faces the user.
But where the real debate is
on
things that don't face the
user.
So Steve Jobs famously in the
Mac,
insisted on an immaculate
circuit design board.
You can read about this in
various books.
The Mac, for those of you who
don't remember the Mac,
probably everybody here but
some of you may have seen it,
actually couldn't be opened.
So the circuit board design
couldn't be
seen by any single person in
the world.
There was no way to open the
Mac except the people who
worked at Apple, and Steve
insisted that it be
absolutely perfect and
beautiful.
That's the kind of detail
obsession that this sort of
philosophy of building a
company requires.
Examples that maybe more
practical for you instead of
circuit boards are things like
what food do you serve people.
This actually matters more
than you might guess.
When people don't like the
food you serve them,
what do they do.
They go gossip.
They go complain to their
friends.
They go walk over to someone's
desk.
And all the sudden at lunch,
what they're complaining about
is, it,
their mostly spending time
gossiping and
complaining instead of
brainstorming.
So you don't have this
serendipitous idea.
Not saying other serendipitous
idea that creates a spark,
instead they're all wandering
and wallowing around.
So the best thing you could do
is actually give
people the food they want or
food that's good for them.
That makes them more
productive.
So it may seem a lot like this
glorious job
that you thought you had is
actually more like
running around being a task
rabbit for people.
But it's to
take the things off the plate
that are a distraction.
So that they can be
high-performance machines.
And if you take enough things
away from people that distract
them and give them the tools
to be successful, all of
a sudden your organization
produces a lot more.
Similarly, another example
that's often got wrong is
office space.
So, one natural instinct is
when you need an office is to
have an office manager or
someone on your team go out
and find offices.
And they'll go on tours with
agents and
they'll come back with photos
and ideas.
You need to do that yourself.
The office environment that
people live in and
work in everyday dictates your
culture and
how people make decisions, it
dictates how hard people work.
There's almost no important
more decision other than
what company you're going to
be, than what's the office
environment you're actually
in,
and most people don't do that.
And then the final thing and
then I'll take some questions
is around effort.
Ultimately, I don't believe
that you
can build a company without a
lot of effort and
that you'd need to lead by
example.
So Bill Wallace,
the first chapter of his books
is, get's asked this question
of how did you know whether
you're doing your job?
And this is the answer he
gives coaches that used to ask
him that question So if this
is what you
feel like every day, you're
probably on the right track.
And if that doesn't sound
appetizing,
you probably shouldn't start a
company, truthfully.
All right, with that I'm doing
with the prepared part.
Let me see if anybody has
questions I
can try to be helpful with.
Any questions?
Yes?
>> So you talked about making
compensation transparent.
How would you do this,
especially when people equate
themselves to value, you know,
of how much their salary is?
>> I would, I would do it in,
probably, bands.
because you could do it,
either just everybody in the
company gets paid the same, or
you could have, like, all
discipline, all engineers, or
you could do it by experience
like extreme exp.
The way Steve did it actually
at Next was,
there was a high band and a
low band.
And you either had a lot of
experience or
low experience, and that was
it, so low band back then, you
know, now it would probably be
like $85,000 kind of everybody
just flatly gets paid $85,000,
and if your super experienced
everybody gets paid like
$130,000, and that's just it
like this sort of the Next
translated for inflation.
>> Instead of what's the how
many details
>> You'd be amazed.
>> Well, yeah, so the question
was besides food what
other kind of details do
people care about?
The laptops they use.
I mean, this is now the
default that everybody has.
But five years ago,
it was a benefit to give
people high-quality machines
as opposed to optimizing our
costs and
having Dell machines and ugly
monitors, just as an example.
So if you think about all
these people that
are relentlessly resourceful,
incredibly talented in
a massively competitive
ecosystem competing for
talent, you want to give the
people the best
possible tools to do the best
possible job.
And so, right rigorously
thinking through how do I
make people more successful?
What things do they not need
to be
working on that are
distracting?
And what things can I
actually given them that make
them more valuable per day?
And then just break that down
every day and
solve that stuff yourself.
>> So, when you're in a
start-up environment,
how you you optimize for those
things?
because, you know, resources
are scarce and.
>> It's a good, it's a good
question.
I actually think that you
should start,
first of all, you must have
your own office.
I don't believe ever in shared
office spaces.
Peter talks a little bit about
this,
that every start-up, every
good start-up is a cult.
It's really hard to
create a cult if you're
sharing space with people.
Because a cult means that you
think that you're better than
everybody else in the world,
that you have a special way of
doing
things that's different than
everybody else in the world.
And if you're sharing physical
space with people,
it's very hard to inculcate
that.
So, I would start there, but
it is a prioritization
question.
When you have, everybody is
going to have scarce
resources, just a question of
magnitude like how many zeros
are you paying attention to?
You know, probably not $10.
Expenditures, put $100, then
$1,000,
then 10,000, then a million,
and then 10 million.
Starts being a rounding error.
So, what I would do is figure
out like,
what's most important?
And in a high quality office,
that creates a good vibe.
That allows you to recruit
people,
because recruits are very
savvy about this.
They walk into your office,
and
they can tell a lot about the
culture instantly.
I sometimes, I walk into a
company office and I can tell,
often, whether I'm going to
invest, as soon as I walk in.
Like, I can absolutely rule
things out that I
just don't want to invest in
as soon as I walk in.
And there's times walking into
the office is like,
wow, this is very impressive.
You can tell how people worked
together,
how hard they're working, how
distracted they are.
Roelof Botha at Sequoia made a
point to me about YouTube.
So, when I invested in
YouTube,
in the very, very beginning,
it wasn't obviously going to
be successful.
And then, Roelof led this
series A investment for
Sequoia in YouTube.
And we were at a board meeting
together and he said,
you know, I think YouTube's
really going to work.
And I said, why?
And he said well,
every time I go to one of my
portfolio companies,
half the office is watching
YouTube at lunch.
>> And I was like, pretty good
sign.
So like, if you pick up on
these little things you
can predict a lot.
Yeah?
>> What do you think is the
best way to gain street cred
for a new manager?
>> Oh boy yeah so the question
is how's the best way to
grain, gain street cred for a
new manager?
Almost all good managers in
Silicon Valley are promoted
because of their individual
performance in cultures that
are meritocratic, you know,
the percentage is even higher.
So we tried at PayPal to only
promote people that
were basically kicking **** at
their discipline.
So Peter didn't believe in
general managers.
In fact, I remember going for
a jog around campus within my
first week at PayPal and
he's asking me, you know,
how are things going, the
usual kind of CEO questions.
And then we got into this
debate about whether the
company needed any managers.
And he's like, nope.
No managers.
We're only going to promote
people.
So the VP of Engineering is
going to be the single best
engineer.
The VP of Design's going to be
the single best designer.
The VP of Product's going to
be the single best product
person and they're going to
learn to manage later.
And the advantage of that is
you don't demoralize people,
because everybody knows that
their boss actually is
better at their job than they
are, and they can learn stuff.
And you can learn a little bit
of the management techniques
later as opposed to promoting
people who
are just good people managers
that don't actually have
the discipline and skill, and
that does demoralize people.
So I think, just being
excellent at something, and
then getting excellent at
getting a bunch of people to
do something is the next task.
But people, you just have to
learn,