https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6fQHLK1aIBs
So I'm going to talk about how
to operate.
So I've watched some of the
prior classes, and
I'm going to assume that
you've already sort of
hired a bunch of horrendously
resourceful people.
That you've built a product
that at
least some people love.
And you're probably raised
some capital.
And now you're trying to build
a company.
So you're, you're enforging a
product and
now you have to forge a
company.
And it actually argue for
GM company is much more
difficult than for
a GM product.
Basic reason is people are
irrational.
So you probably all know this
either your parents,
your significant other or your
brother or sister, or
your teacher, somebody in your
life is irrational.
Building a company is
basically taking all
the irrational people you
know, putting them in one
building and then living with
them 12 hours a day at least.
So, it's very challenging.
Now, there's techniques for
coping with that and
some people get good at it and
small people don't but
that's where really what
operating is about.
So basically what you're doing
when you build a company is
you're building an engine.
And at first you have a
drawing literally on a white
board, and you're architecting
it, and it
looks very conceptually clean,
and beautiful, and pretty.
But when you start actually
translating to
practice actually it looks
more like this, and
you're holding it together
with duct tape.
And it takes a lot of heroic
effort to people to
actually hold it together.
That's why people work 80, 100
hours a week,
is that heroic effort is
actually necessary to keep
this thing together.
Because you don't actually yet
have polished metal in place.
Eventually you
want to construct a high
performance machine.
A machine that actually almost
nobody really has to
worry about every hour.
Every minute and you know as
we
used to joke about Ebay that
if Martians took over Ebay it
would take like six months for
the world to notice.
That's what eventually what
you want to get to.
Or as Warren Buffet says, you
know, build a company that
idiots could run because
eventually they will.
So this is what you want
basically a performance
machine that idiots can run.
Now, as a leader, what is your
real job?
What's your role?
Strictly speaking there's only
one book that's ever written
that actually explains how to
do this, it's a little old.
It was written in 1992 by Andy
Grove,
who's quite famous, quite
successful, and
his definition of what your
job is,
is to maximize the output of
an organization,
your organization that you're
responsible for, CEOs,
everything and a VP would be
part of the organization.
And the organizations around
you, so if you're VPE,
you're actually are
responsible for
the performance of the product
team too, or
the marketing team, because
you have influence there.
So this is how measure people
and you want to focus on
the output not the input the
old adage about measuring,
not measuring motion and
confusing that will progress,
you're measuring only
progress.
And this is going to sound
like a fancy and
glamorous thing to do.
Maybe people get excited about
managing a whole
large organization, and being
responsible for the output.
But in practice, what you're
going to learn today hopefully
is that it's more about things
like ordering smoothies,
teaching your receptionist how
to answer the phone properly,
and serving as a $10 an hour
task rabbit for
your employees.
So let's talk about that.
So at first when you
start a company everything's
going to feel like a mess.
And it really should if you
have too much process,
too much predictability you're
probably not
innovating fast enough and
creatively enough.
So it should feel like
everyday there's a new
problem and what you're doing
is fundamentally triaging.
So some things will look like
a problem, and
they're actually a colds,
they're just going to go away.
So, somebody's annoyed about
this or that.
That may be a cold, and you
shouldn't stress about it,
and you certainly shouldn't
allocated a lot of
your time to it.
And some things are going to
present themselves as colds.
But just like in the emergency
room, if they're not
diagnosed properly they
actually can become fatal.
So what I'm going to try to do
is help give you
frameworks for thinking about
which things are colds and
which things are potentially
fatal.
So one of the most important
things I've learned at
Square is actually a concept
of editing.
And this is the,
I think the best metaphor I've
ever seen in like 14 years of
running stuff of how to think
about your job.
It's natural, it's a natural
metaphor so
it's easy to take with you
every day.
And actually it's easy to
transmit to each of
your employees so that they
can figure out
wether they are editing or
writing.
It's a natural construct.
You generally know when
someone asks you to
do something.
Am I more writing or am I more
editing?
So an editor, as, is the best
metaphor for your job,
and we're talking about the
specific things you're doing
in editing.
The first thing an editor
does, and
you probably all had this
experience in school,
is you submit a paper to a TA,
a draft to your friend.
And the first thing an editor
does is
they take out a red pen or
nowadays, you know online, and
they start striking things.
Basically eliminating things.
The most important task as an
editor is to simplify,
simplify, and that usually
means omitting things.
So that's your job too, is to
clarify and simplify for
everybody on your team,
the more you simplify the
better people will perform.
People cannot understand and
keep track of a complicated
set of initiatives.
So you've got to distill it
down to one, two, or
three things.
And use a framework that they
can repeat,
they can repeat without
thinking about,
they can repeat to their
friends,
they can repeat at night.
Don't except the excuse of
complexity.
A lot of people will tell you
that well this is
too challenging, this is too
complicated.
Well yeah, I know other people
simplify but
that's not for me.
This is a complicated
business.
They're wrong.
You can change the world, in
140 characters.
You can build the most
important companies in
history in a very simple to
describe concept.
You can market products in
less than about 50 characters.
There's no reason why you
can't build your company the
same way.
So force yourself to simplify
every initiative,
every product, every
marketing, every,
everything you do.
And, and basically take out
that red,
and start eliminating stuff.
Second thing is, what editors
do,
is they ask you clarifying
questions.
So when you present a paper to
somebody,
what do they usually do?
Do they, find some ambiguity
somewhere and
they say, well did you really
mean this, do you mean that,
do you have an example of
this?
That's what your job is, so
you're in a meeting and
people are going to look to
you, and the real thing you
do is you actually ask a lot
of questions.
And they can be simple, basic
questions like,
should we try this seven days
a week or six days?
They can be fundamental
questions like,
where's our competitive
advantage here?
We try to this actually as
investors too
some investors will ask you a
billion questions about
a billion things and they'll
have you do diligence forever.
We try to narrow it down to
what are one, two or
three four things that
actually matter for
this company and only focus on
those things.
So it allows us to be more
decisive, and
we can make decisions rapidly.
It allows us not to distract
you from your day job,
which is actually building a
company.
And yet, I think we still get
to the higher fide,
highest fidelity answers.
We don't have all these extra,
extraneous details, pieces of
data.
Now it's hard, it's something
you have to practice, but
when you're good at it, every
step you eliminate, Andy Grove
estimated that you can improve
performance by 30-50%.
The next thing you do is
allocate resources.
So the editing construct,
this is what editors do all
the time.
They take editors from the
mid-East and
covering the mid-East and they
move them to Silicon Valley,
because Silicon Valley is now,
now more interesting.
Or they move them to a sports
section because they want to
compete on the basis of sports
with other journals and
other publications.
So that can be top down where
I take a bunch of,
allocate resources and
people would say, we're now
going over here,
we're going to compete on this
basis.
And then next month, next
quarter, next year,
I'm like well,
that Middle East coverage is
getting boring and bland.
We don't want to do that
anymore.
Let's go chase after something
else, or it can be bottom up,
just like journalists mostly
come up
with their own stories, the
people who work with you.
Generally should be coming up
with their own initiatives.
So, a reporter will generally,
who covers Google, come up
with the interesting stories
that they're hearing in
aether, and propose one or two
to their editor for approval.
But it's not like the editor
is saying, go cover Google,
and this is the angle I want.
Once in a while they do that,
but
that's not the date, the day,
the meat and
potatoes of what a journalist
does every day.
Your goal over time is to
actually use less red
ink every day.
So one way of measuring how
well you're doing in
communicating to
your colleagues about what's
important and what's not.
What, why some things are
important,
some things are not,
is how much red ink you're
pulling out every day.
It's okay if you have a bad
day and
the red inks all over the
place.
But it's not okay if the red
ink next month is
more is more than it was last
month,
if the next quarter is more
than this.
So measure yourself of how
much red ink you're creating.
The other thing that's very
important that actually isn't
as intuitive to a lot of
people is,
the job of an editor is to
ensure consistent voice.
So if any of you read The
Economist,
you can tell that there's one
consistent voice.
You can pick up any article,
any post in The Economist, and
if feels like it's written by
the same person.
Ideally your company should
feel like,
on your website and your PR
release,
on your packaging, if it's a
physical product.
Anywhere on your recruiting
pages to feel like it
was written by one person.
That's extremely difficult to
do,
and first you're going to be
tempted to do
that yourself which is okay
for a founder to that.
Him or herself initially.
Over time you do not want to
be doing all of
the consistent voice editing
by yourself.
You are a trained people so
that they can recognize the
differences in voice.
So if you see this website
page it
looks very different than the
recruiting page.
You start by asking questions
why is that?
Is the reporting messed up?
Is the leaders over here not
really understanding the voice
of the company?
So, you've gotta, you have to
fix that over time.
But you want to start with the
objective of
everything should feel exactly
the same.
It's quite, quite difficult in
practice.
Almost every company has at
least one piece
of the organization that isn't
exactly on the same voice.
At Apple, which is notorious,
you know,
even under Steve's regime,
which was notorious for
getting this right.
If you asked someone who
worked at Apple, talk,
asked them about the internal
tools about recruiting.
Do they really feel like Apple
products?