https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6fQHLK1aIBs
some things you have to learn
by doing.
You can't learn to play the
guitar by reading a book.
You've actually gotta try to
manage a bit, and
you won't do it well.
I had another sort of set of
tactics and
classes on what you actually
do when you transition from
an individual contributor to a
manager.
It's hard.
One of the first things people
don't get right is their time
allocation.
And so actually, I would
recommend doing what I
call calendar audit and
tracking for a month what you
spend your time on and how
much is managing and
editing, and how much is
writing, et cetera, and
then optimize it over time.
You can get a mentor, find
somebody who's been a manager
before that will work with
you, not your boss.
Because your boss has a set
complicated objectives,
including how much are we
shipping?
A mentor can just focus on
you, and
making you more successful.
>> Can you give some more
examples of things you can
do which show a consistent
voice of the company,
especially with the company
growing?
>> Yeah.
so, I would look at every
piece of
copy in every department.
So like another area that
almost never is a done.
So look at your recruiting
website.
Almost never done to
the same quality as your
conversion funnel.
I look at customer support,
another classic area that
isn't up to the same quality,
and treat customer support
like a product.
So that you actually have an
engineering team and
a design team over time,
that actually focuses on
making that world-class.
Usually, where you have
different executives at
a scaled company, most
executives were
trained differently at
different companies, and
they bring some of that with
them.
So you've got to cross train
that.
So, if you've hired a VP of
Engineering from Google.
It's very different than a
design leader who
came from Apple,
they don't actually learn how
to do anything the same way.
So you're going to have to
stitch that together somehow,
either one or the other is
going to have to learn in
the other style or you're
going to have to create your
own style and really teach
that to your executives.
So it shows up all the time
but
all you do, all you need to do
is just pick up the company's
products and look for things
that have a different voice.
And you can see it.
Visual voice, word choice,
all, all over the map.
Sam?
>> Could you talk a little bit
about the tactics of how
you manage people?
Like how you
>> So the canonical advice
in this now sounds obvious but
actually was
pretty radical in 1982 when
Andy wrote his first book is
you should have a one on one
roughly every two weeks.
Some people say every week,
and I don't think you want to
go longer than two weeks,
one week can be ideal actually
in many companies.
The reason why in fact there's
ano, another adage which is,
you should only have five to
seven direct reports.
That actually derives from the
concept of a one on one
every week.
So that the direct reports, so
you can fit enough one on ones
in your calendar and still get
other things done.
So I think one on one's per
week are a good idea.
The agenda should be crafted
by the employee who reports to
the manager, not the manager.
The one on one is mostly for
the benefit of the employee,
so they should walk in with,
here's the three or four
things I want to talk about.
Ideally, they circulate that.
It can be even bullet points
in advance by email.
But, in advance you have time
to chew on it and
you're not on the fly, winging
your responses.
But that's probably the best
structure.
Now if someone's really good
and really talented and
has been doing something for
a long time with a lot of
internal credibility,
you might push out the one
every week, and
relax that to one every two
weeks, possibly once a month.
I don't know that I would go
beyond once a month ever.
>> When is it acceptable to
compromise and
hire someone who is ammunition
rather than a barrel?
>> Yeah, so the question is
when,
when do you compromise and
hire more ammunition instead
of a barrel?
Truthfully, you're going to
hire more ammunitions by
definition than you are
barrels.
So there's a ratio between the
two.
The question is the ratio.
So at some point the ratio is
going to get out of wack.
So if you're the only barrel
in the company and
you have 50 engineers, you
might as well only have ten
engineers because you're not
going to get anymore done.
So you're just wasting
resources.
You're going to have
frustrated engineers,
because everybody's going to
need your approval,
your sign off, your editing.
It's just going to stack and
frustrate people.
So, it's really, now different
disciplines, engineering,
like I actually think like
roughly one to ten to 20 is
probably about the right
range.
Like you don't need more
engineers until you
have more barrels.
Designers a little different,
but it's always going to be
hiring more ammunitions.
And a good leader,
a good barrel will kind of
have a feel for that.
So one way to, one way to
correct for this.
Natural tendency is to
increase that your headcount
on your team, like sort of an
empire building tendency.
Like, oh so I manage 20
people, and
Sam only manages ten, and you
manage three.
So, I'm more important than
Sam and
you're more important than
you.
One way to do that is you put
an X here of
the number of people that the,
the output, sorry, specify how
many things they've done
successfully then divide by
the number of people on their
team, and tell them that this
is going to be their grade in
their performance review.
Shockingly this y doesn't
start increasing on that team.
It's amazing how this works.
And be really explicit about
it.
>> As, venture capitalist,
how often you intervene this
and, what's.
>> So how often do I meet
with?
>> Yeah.
How you.
[CROSS-TALK].
>> So the question is,
as a venture capitalist,
how often do I interact with
my companies, meet with them.
Generally when we invest and
we do,
do some seed investments where
we invest less money but
when we invest a fair amount
of money and
lead a round like a series a a
series b round
we join the board, and roughly
I meet with
the founder CEO every two
weeks, that's the default.
Now there can be obviously
there's inflection moments and
things go right well or wrong.
And, you know, that's on an
ad-hoc basis.
These days, actually,
surprisingly, I do a lot by
text message.
I even have one CEO who
Snapchats me all the time.
Which I'd actually rather not,
but, That, so.
The world, the world has
changed a lot.
But I try in-person meetings
every two weeks.
>> Are you the no.
I mean, really it's,
like, being a venture
capitalist is more,
to me, like being a
psychologist.
So if you come to
my office you'll see actually
we have two chairs,
kind of arrayed like this with
a little table in the middle.
And we sit down.
And I'm basically, like, so
tell me your problems.
You know?
[LAUGHTER] Then,
it's like a question.
It's like, so have you.
And then the, and then my
response is usually,
well have you thought about
this?
Have you talked to this
person?
Have you tried this?
Et cetera.
And it's just asking a lot of
questions and going back that
way.
But that's 90% of what I do.
So I see when you, when you've
got these barrels,
you say your starter company
is up doing really good,
you know, and you're working
on this project.
I've heard that you should
always be recruiting.
>> Yes.
>> How do you,
how do you balance that.
Well it depends on where your
prioritizations are.
So you know, Sam talked a
little bit
about this in his lecture,
but every company will move
recruiting you know, first,
second, or third somewhere in
that sort of spectrum.
If it's your number one
priority then about 25% is
probably a pretty good
allocation.
Actually I like the calendar
audit for
CEO's even more, so than for
new managers.
So when I work with CEO's
sometimes who aren't.
Thriving in that role for the
first time.
Actually forced them to show
me their calendar.
And before I do that, and now
I'm going to ruin this trick
because if I tell it to you,
actually asked them to
write their priorities, write
them down on a piece of paper.
And, you know, discuss
whatever they are.
Then we go pull up their
calendar, and
see if it matches.
And it never matches.
They, never.
They, recruiting is the one
that's most often.
Awry so you know, let's say
half the CEO's you meet with
will say recruiting's the
number one priority.
It's almost never the biggest
block of
time on anybody's calendar,
and so
that's what you're trying to
do is match resources and
inputs against priorities, and
a calendar audit unfortunately
there's no software that does
this really well.
It would be great.
Like actually the,
we literally pull up someone's
Google calendar and
kind of manually add up the
hours.
Which in, somewhat insane.
But that's, that's the best
way is just,
well what are your priorities.
If your priorities are raising
money, you
don't want to allocate 100% of
your time for recruiting.
You want to allocate a fair
amount of time to raising
money for that block of time
until you're successful at it.
>> One more question.
>> One more question anybody,
okay, go ahead.
>> On the surface some of the
advice students contradictory
because you emphasized
focusing on a plus pass, and
delegating less important
things, but then you said it's
good to write like few page
script for your receptors.
Focus on all the details.
How do you harmonize those
goals?
>> It's a good question.
I think the way to harmonize.
The question is really, how do
you harmonize things like,
where details can really
matter but
you only get one thing, you
know, to do and
you've gotta allocate to the
top one, two, or three things.
How do you, how do you put
those two things together?
And actually there is some
tension in, even in a healthy
organization, there's some
tension of like why are we
actually focused on, you know,
writing the script.
As opposed to something a user
may see.
I think the underlying
philosophy of
getting the details right is
pretty important to
install in the very, very,
very beginning of
a company because people will
start acting that way and
making decisions that way
themselves.
So, you won't have to actually
literally do that.
And if you have to do that, it
actually shows you
that the foundation isn't
actually that, that solid.
So eh, when you first start
the company.
It's about getting the details
right,
that everybody is precise,
everybody on every task is
always thinking that way.
And then that scales, and
then the people you bring in,
it's a little self-fulfilling,
people who can think that way
will tend to get hired,
people who can't won't get
hired.
Each team, and
each leader, will tend to
enforce that themselves,
to see whose almost never
doing it.
So, it's partially, like,
how do you start, and at
cultures like that,
I mean, the, key to culture is
it's a rule.
It's a frame work for making
decisions.
And if you have a cultured
people learn how to
make decisions across that
culture and
you're never day anything,
except just yeah watch.
And you know and promote and
move people around.
Cool, well I guess that's it,
thank you.