https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uVhTvQXfibU
Because, it's,
like, well, I don't want,
like, a lot of formalities.
I don't want a lot of process.
I want it to be organic.
We want to do yoga.
>>
>> We want to
only smoke organic weed.
Sorry that was like a Peter.
Peter got very focused on
who was smokin' weed a little
while ago.
But like, the process actually
protects it
protects the culture because
what it does it says look,
we're going to look at all the
inputs.
We're going to have a formal
way of saying anybody who
wants a raise come talk to me.
Like, I'm not going to give
you a raise, but
I'm happy to hear your story.
I'm going to talk to all the
people you work with so
I get like a, understanding of
it.
I'm going to evaluate all the
work that you've done so
I know like, where I actually
rate you, and
what my actual opinion on
them.
I'm going to do that
periodically,
I'm not going to do it daily.
But like yeah, maybe if I were
fast moving I'll do it
ever six months or even maybe
once a quarter.
And at the end of that process
I
will tell you want your raise
is.
And I will tell you if you're
getting one of if you're not
getting one, but I'm not
going to do things off cycle.
I'm not going to do things
when asked.
There's like one process, and
that's it.
And I, you know, when I used
to be CEO, and
I had, like, executive, it's
the bigger this gets,
the harder this gets because
the more
aggressive the people working
for you are.
Because to get to be an
executive, it turns out,
you often have to be pretty
aggressive in this world.
And in most companies, like,
that's how you get to that
level.
You know, I would go, like,
you can lobby me all you want,
you know, after the process is
done, and
I give you your raise, but you
know what?
I'm not hearing it,
because I already went through
my process.
I got your input going in.
I got everybody else's input,
I've got so many people,
I've got so much money and you
got what I believe is right.
And having a process like that
basically gets people to be
actually more comfortable.
They're more comfortable
because they don't always have
to be on edge about like am I
asking for what I deserve?
Or am I getting like aced out
because of who I am,
what I look like,
I'm not buddy buddy, I'm not
at the golf course with you.
Or I'm not doing whatever you
like to do.
Or, you know?
I don't have to worry about
any of that.
'because I know your process.
I know your processes like
you're going to evaluate
everybody, and then you're
going to give 'em what's fair.
And so that's a, a much better
way to handle that.
And it means that you're
actually understanding what
everybody thinks.
Not just the people you're
talking to at the moment.
Okay, so now we're going to
get into some fun stuff.
We're going to evaluate Sam's
blog post, how.
Which is actually, there are
some very good things in it.
And then there are some things
I'm going to discuss.
>>
>> So Sam, so
this is the expert, excerpt.
Most employees have nine, only
90 days after they leave a job
to exercise their options.
Unfortunately, this requires
money to
cover the strike price and the
tax bill.
I'll explain this a little
later, just.
But I want to read it first.
For the year of exercise,
blah, blah, blah,
this is often more cash than
an employee has.
And this is the key.
And so the employee has to
choose between like, leaving
the job and walking away from
the invested options of either
money that she has because she
can't afford to exercise or
being like locked into staying
at the company basically for
all the wrong reasons.
So particularly bad
situation when an employee
gets terminated and
I'll get into that and that's
a really key point.
This doesn't seem fair, the
best solution I have heard is
from Adam D'Angelo, a very,
very smart guy at Quora.
The idea is to grant options
that are exercisable for
ten years from the grant date,
which should cover,
you know like, all the cases
you know,
whatever happens with the
company.
There are some tricky issues
to this.
Blah, blah, blah.
But it's still far better than
just losing the assets.
I think this is a policy that
all startups should adopt.
So our question is well, like,
was Sam right?
Is this a policy that all
startups should adopt.
So let me first explain again
what the policy is.
So currently the way almost
every stock option package in
Silicon Valley works and in
all of startup world is this.
That your stock vests, you get
stock invest over a period of
time but if you leave the
company,
when you leave you have, and
it depends on the company, but
I think it's 90 days to
exercise, so yeah, so 90 days.
And if you do not buy your
stock in that period,
Like it's not yours anymore.
Which, depending on when you
entered the company,
could be a big problem.
So a lot of companies today
that are valued a lot,
like if you take like a really
valuable startup like say
an Airbnb, or an Uber, or
something like that.
When they bring you in, they
go wow, you know?
Like if you look at your 409A
price.
And to the preferred price.
Like the stock we're giving
your right now,
the options are already worth
like $10 million.
And you're like, whoa, $10
million.
I'm rich.
But what they don't
necessarily tell you is,
in order for you to get that
money.
Because their,
the preferred is worth $10
million, your options probably
are going to cost you like
$2.5 million.
When you leave, and
if you don't have that $2.5
million in 90 days, it's gone.
Like you just lost all your
money.
And so Sam was like, wow,
that's **** up.
>> And so he wrote a blog
post.
>> And he said everybody
should change it.
And so the first question that
you have to
ask yourself on something like
this is well why is that even,
like this has kind of been
around since like the 80s so
why is a rule like this around
for 30 years.
And it turned out, Sam, and I
don't even,
I, I don't know whether he
like figured this our or
just intuited it, but he was
right.
Like something actually had
changed.
So up until 2004 there used to
be this law called,
APB opinion number 25.
That law was the old way to
account for stock options.
And, you know,
it's also the law that all the
guys went to jail on.
So I got a lot of people who
cut a case on APB 25.
So I'm glad it's gone.
because it was a very
confusing law.
And a lot of people did not
understand it.
And they literally went to
jail.
But when that was a law,
if you gave somebody ten years
to exercise their
options you would never have
been able to go public.
And you would never have been
able to be acquired.
Because you basically were
taking an expense that was
tied to your stock price.
So basically, the more your
stock went up,
the more compensation expense
you'd have to take.
And the worst thing about it
would be,
is, you wouldn't know what it
was going to be.
So it'd be totally
unpredictable.
So you could never forecast
earnings ever.
Because your earnings would be
a function of
all of your stock price.
And so the more your stock
price went up
the more money you would lose.
And in those days people did
not look through expe,
stock option expenses.
So like it just wasn't doable.
And that's why
everybody's agreement was
written at 90 days.
So that's why it's there.
So absolutely it's the right
thing to
question it being there.
Are you guys following?
You get this?
This is like more complicated
than the first two examples
but a very important one.
Okay.
Then so your perspective on
this,
if you've got employees, you
want to be fair.
Like nobody wants to like
higher, hey,
you've got all this stock in
four years, psych.
And especially like when you
fire someone.
Hey, you're fired!
I feel real bad about it, but,
you know, guess what?
I'm also going to take all
your money too.
>>
>> You must not feel that bad.
So, like, that's kind of.
Like a problem.
But you also, and
this is the thing that you've
got to keep in mind.
You also have to think about
the people who are staying,
and you want to reward the
people who are staying.
Now the employee,
the perspective of the
employee who leaves.
And this is really critical
because,
this is your reputation,
right?
Like, I worked.
Like, you know, a year's work.
Like, where's my year's pay?
And then, okay, so
now you're telling me about
this 90 day exercise.
And I know it was in,
like, the fine print of my
stock option agreement.
But, my hiring manager never
told me about that.
They never told me I was
going to
need like $2 million to get my
stock, which I don't have.
And like so if I was rich,
like, I'd get my stock.
Like, that's not fair.
And so, like, you know, now
I'm fired, and
then I'm screwed.
And guess what?
You know, I'm going to tell
everybody like, how you like,
screwed me over.
And so that's a real
reputational problem.
So that's something that
you've gotta consider in
setting this policy.
But then you also have to
consider the employee who
stays.
And, one thing that they're
going to ask themselves is,
look they're leaving.
And every time anybody leaves
it's like, was that smart?
Like that's something you,
because these are people who
write,
your employees know each other
better than they know you.
In any company, I don't care
what company you are.
But like often the,
the person they're really
working with is,
is going to be the person they
know more.
And so if that person leaves
they are going to go,
well like, should've I left
too?
Like, what did they get,
and how does that compare to
my deal?
And so, like, if we look at
the situation, and we try and
analyze it, there is a lot of
components to it.
So first is,
look, companies tread a lot of
people around here.
And I think, like,
really the average is
somewhere around 10%,
it's probably getting higher.
Particularly if you're in San
Francisco,
it's getting higher.
Just because of the nature of
the culture there.
And then, Silicon Valley
companies dilute,
like 6 to 8 or even 10% a year
for employee options.
And you have to keep in mind
that, as mean as it may be,
if that employee leaves and
can't exercise their options.
Then those options come back
to the pool, where you can
potentially give them to
people who are already there.
So, you're actually taking
less dilution.
So that's something that you
have to think about.
I'm not saying you have to act
on it,
but it's something that you
have to think about.
Then secondly, look,
losing all your stock is a
very big incentive to stay.
And that can be good news or
bad news, right?
Like, it can be good news in
that like,
you get to keep somebody you
might have lost.
It could be bad news in that
you kept them for
the exact wrong reason, right?
because they have handcuffs on
them.
And so you know, you may get
like,
the an employee who's worse
than not having an employee.
But on the other hand,
a ten year option on a highly
volatile security, for
those of you who have taken
that class.
Anybody taking that class?
That's valuable, right?
Ten years options are
volatility and length.
That's the value of an option.
Well, ten years on a start up
stock,
that's a big valuable thing.
And then remember,
the employee who stays doesn't
get that.
The employee who stays just
gets the stock.
They get that, but they don't
get the new job and
the new stock.
So they get one thing but they
don't get both things.
And so, you've gotta weigh
that in.
So this is a hard one.
Like, I think that it should
be
reevaluated by every company.
I wouldn't go as far as to say
it should be adopted by
every company.
I think you have to think
about what you want.
And I would just offer kind of
two alternative cultural
statements.
One is, look we treat
employees with
the utmost
straightforwardness.
We're going to be fair.
And therefore,
like you get ten years to
exercise your stock.
And like what we said we're
going to give you,
you're going to get regardless
of how rich or poor you are.