https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uVhTvQXfibU
So when Sam originally sent me
an email to do this course,
he said Ben can you teach a 15
minute course on management.
And I immediately thought to
myself, wow,
I just wrote a 300 page book
on management, so
that book was entirely too
long.
And I, I didn't actually have
time to collapse the 300 pages
into 50 minutes.
So like Mark Twain, I didn't
have time to write
a good short letter, so I'm
going to write a long letter.
But in this case,
I'm going to teach exactly one
management concept.
So, one long thing.
And this management concept
though,
is the thing that I see CEOs
mess up more consistently than
anything else, and from when
they're very,
very early to when they're
very, very big as a company.
It's the easiest thing to say,
and
the most difficult to master.
And, the concept in musical
form, whoops, pardon me,
very sensitive.
But musical form.
This is from Sly And The
Family Stone.
Sometimes I'm right.
>> So.
No difference what group I'm
in.
So that's, that's the musical
version of today's lesson.
For those of you, you are
musical, you can leave now.
In management concept form,
basically it's this.
When you're making a critical
decision,
you have to understand how
it's going to be interpreted
from all points of view, not
just your point of view and
not just the person you're
talking to, but
to people who aren't in the
room, everybody else.
In other words, you really
have to be able, when
making critical decisions, to
see the decision.
Through the eyes of the
company, and the company as
a whole, which means you've
got to kind of add up
every employee's view, and
then incorporate that into
your own view, otherwise your
management decisions are going
to have have very weird,
side effects and,
and potentially very dangerous
consequences.
And it's a really hard thing
to do,
because at the point when
you're making
a decision you're often under
a great deal of pressure.
So let's get into the agenda.
So I'm going to cover a kind
of four cases,
first I'm going to cover
demotions,
which is a very emotional
thing.
Then raises, which is also an
emotional thing.
Then we're going to evaluate
one of Sams blog posts.
Which is news to Sam, so I'd
figure out I'd tease him
since he invited me to a do a
50 minute management class,
after I wrote a 300 page book.
And then I'm going to talk
about,
history's greatest
practitioner at this, and
I'm wearing a shirt with him
on it, and kind of how he used
it to do something he has
done, had ever done before in
human history and has never
done since in human history.
But basically complete
mastery, of,
of the technique I'm going to
talk about.
So, first business example.
You've got an executive, and
do you demote, or
do you fire him?
And this comes from an actual
conversation, an actual real
life situation that I was
working on with a CEO.
And so, the basic situation
was this.
He had a great executive, or
like an executive who,
just a great effort.
Like, he hired him.
He was working harder than
anybody else in the company,
doing you know, like,
everything he was supposed to.
Everybody liked him, because
he worked so hard, and
like was a general smart
person.
But he was just in over his
head knowledge wise.
He did not have the knowledge
and the skills to basically do
what the company needed him to
do or,
like, really compete against
the competition, so
he couldn't actually keep him
in the job.
But he's a great guy.
And you know, so the question
is, well.
Should I fire this person?
Or can I just move him into a
lower role and
bring in a person above him.
And then, like, you know, that
would be real cool.
So, let's look at how you
kind of make that decision.
So you in this, in this case
this was the CEO, so
you as a CEO.
So, one like, look, it's
really hard if somebody comes
to work everyday like at, you
know, 6 a.m.,
and is like working till 10
p.m.
And like doing it,
like, harder than anybody in
the company.
It's really hard to just say,
well, sorry, like,
nice effort, but you don't get
an A for an effort.
You get an F because I fired
you.
>>
>> Nobody nobody wants to
have that conversation.
>>
>> And then, a demotion is
kind of neat because from the
CEO's point of view, and this
is, he's like, Look, like, we
can keep him in the company.
He works so hard.
He's a good example of
somebody who gives a great
effort.
And you know, like, and then
he's got a lot of
friends in the company, and
they're, you know,
from a cultural standpoint
like, it's a, it's a win,
win because like, he gets to
stay and, and, you know,
like and then I can bring in
somebody that can solve my
problem, but I, I don't have
to create another problem.
And then if you think about it
from the executive's
perspective,.
And what they would think,
it's like, well, I,
you know, I don't want to be
demoted.
But I really don't want to be
fired,
because if I get fired that's
a way harder more complicated
thing to explain to my next
employer than I got demoted.
Like, getting demoted is like,
well, I didn't really get
demoted, I got a new job.
>> A smaller title.
And then, you know, the, the,
the last thing is it enables,
you know, like theoretically,
while, like, you know,
the company, you know, we
value all our employees.
We brought you in.
We made a commitment to you as
an employee.
And, like, we value everybody.
And it kind of
will enable you to keep
growing with the company.
And so.
You know and this was the kind
of initial conversation I
had with a CEO and, and
I said well wait a minute, I
said, let me ask you this.
Like what is the,
what's the equity package that
this exec has?
And he goes well what do you
mean?
And I was like,
well like does he have like,
director level compensation,
does he got like a vice
president level compensation?
Does he have a point and a
half?
Does he have 0.4% or what?
and, you know?
That kind of gave the CEO
pause.
He's, like, well, he does have
a point and a half.
And I was, like, okay.
So you're an engineer in your
company.
How do you feel about somebody
who used to be the head of
sales, who got brought in with
a point and a half.
Now, mind you, you're an
engin-,
what do your engineers get?
Like, they get.
.1%, .2%, what are they
getting at this point?
So how are they going to feel
about somebody who's
not the head of sales with
1.5% of the company.
And he was like oh.
And I was like, yeah, oh.
Because like how fair is that?
So are you going to take the
equity away, are you up for
doing that, are you up for
going back and
taking back his compensation?
And like how productive do
you think he'll be if you take
away his compensation?
And then secondly, like Will
people give him
the same respect now that
you've demoted him,
because they knew him as this,
and now he's this.
And so like, I knew you when
you were head of sales,
now you're the regional
manager, and
you're telling me what the to
do?
You're telling me I need to
make that call?
Like, seems to me you got
demoted.
You know, who are you to talk
to me?
I'm an up and comer.
I'll be the next VP of sales
at the next company.
So all these things come into
play.
And so when you look out at
the end,
like you may think you're
dealing with one person.
You may think that this is a
demotion, or a firing of one
person, and what does it mean
according to that one person.
But what you're really doing
is you're saying look.
What does it mean to fail on
the job?
Particularly, a very,
the highest paid, highest
compensated job
in the company from an equity
standpoint, and then,
like, what's required to
maintain your equity?
Like is it good enough to put
in an effort?
Or do you have to get a
result.
And in different situations at
different levels, look,
these answers will come out
differently.
And if this had been a person
not that
was an executive brought in
from the outside but
was somebody who you maybe
promoted past where they
should have been, and didn't
ever get that equity, like,
maybe you make a different
decision.
But you've gotta understand
what it's going to mean to
everybody, not just the person
you're talking to.
Example two.
An excellent employee asks for
a raise.
Good employee.
This isn't like a, like the
last employee.
This is like really good
employee.
So excellent employee asks for
a raise.
So, look.
Your first thing is like,
they're really good, they
asked me for
a raise, they didn't ask me
for no reason.
They ask me because they think
they deserve it.
I want to retain them.
Like, I want to be fair.
They've done a great job.
I want to be fair, and, like,
you know,
I know that if I give them
this raise, like,
it's going to be all love
coming my way,.
That's going to be if I gave
you a raise, we're good,
you know, like we're boys.
>> Look at you.
You got a raise.
>> It's awesome.
So like, you know from your
perspective you know what you
want to do when somebody asks
you for a raise.
And then if you look at it,
okay, so
what about from their
perspective, what,
how would they, like, take it
if you gave them the raise.
And now you have to remember
the employee from, for
them to get to the point where
they've asked you for a raise.
This is not something they
just like woke up one
morning and like, I'm going in
and asking for a raise, right?
Like this is something where
they've thought about it
a lot, they've you know,
compared their other options,
they may have an offer from
another company, you know,
they're, it's something their
spouse probably has
been talking to them about.
And so it's a serious thing.
And so, if you give it to
them,
they're very likely to feel
very good about it.
Like, they may be like
paranoid,
about like why are you giving
me a raise?
But, very unlikely.
Much more and they'll feel
like.
I'm sorry, I have to just let
the whole thing play.
And that's, that's for
those of you who don't know,
that's Bobby Shmurda.
>>
>> And,
Rowdy Rebel doing the Shmoney
Dance.
>>
>> But that's,
that's likely the reaction
you'll get.
So there's a lot of momentum
to say yes, look,
they read Sheryll's book, they
leaned in and I'm going to
reward them for, for doing all
that, which is, you know?
And, and by the way, that book
has very good advice,
so I'm, I'm not knocking on
that.
I don't want you to be
misinterpreting me.
however, you know, there was
going to be a however.
What about, you have to think
about it through the point of
view of the employee who did
not ask for the raise.
So the employee who didn't for
the raise, they may be doing
a better job than the employee
who did do, ask for the raise.
And in their mind they're
going, okay, so I didn't ask
for a raise and I didn't get a
raise, and they asked for
a raise and they got a raise,
and so what does that mean?
That means one, like you're
not
really evaluating people's
performance.
You're just going well whoever
asks, gets.
So that means like, I either
need to be that guy,
who asks for the raise.
Like and I, I, you know,
that's just no how I feel you
know, I do my work and
I don't necessarily want to
ask for a raise.
Or like I should, I just need
to quit and go to
a company that like actually
evaluates performance.
And then you know, so you
could really make the person
who doesn't get the raise feel
like, pretty pissy about it.
And don't think that when
somebody's walking down your
company doing the shmoney
dance that
other people aren't going to
notice, like.
So they're going to be fired
up about that raise.
They're saying, oh you can
say, oh this is
highly confidential that I'm
giving you this raise.
It's not confidential.
And then the cultural
conclusion is going to
be everybody in your company
is going to feel that
they now have a fiduciary
responsibility to their
family to ask for a raise all
of the time.
Because if they don't, then
they may be missing out on
a raise that they would have
otherwise gotten.
And like you talk to any
experienced CEO and
they will tell you this is
true.
Like if you give out raises
when people just ask you for
them, like that,
you will have a lot of people
asking you for raises.
That is called encouraging
behavior.
So what do you do?
And really, the right answer
on raises is you have
to be formal.
And you have to be formal to
save your own culture.
And I know this is always,
this is the thing that causes
people running startups, fits.