https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAws7eXItMk
All right, good afternoon.
Today's guest speaker is
Emmett Shear,
Emmett is the CEO of Twitch.
>> Hello.
>> Which was acquired by
Amazon, where he now works.
And Emmett is going to do a
new formal of class today, and
talk about how to do great
user interviews?
So this is the talking to
users part
of starting a startup, should
be really useful.
Thank you very much for
coming.
>> Thanks Tim.
>> Contact server knows where
I'm coming from, from this.
We started our, I started my
first startup with Justin Kan
right out of college we,
started this company called
Kiko Calendar It didn't go so
well, it, it went, all right.
We, we, we built it we sold
it, but we sold it on Ebay so
that's not necessarily, the
end you want for
your startup,
>> And
It was it was a good time.
We learned a lot, we learned a
lot about programming.
We didn't know anything about
calendars,
neither of us were users of
calendars nor did we.
During the period of time,
we're thinking you've got to
talk to anyone who actually
did use a calendar.
So that was, that was not
optimal.
we, we got the build stuff
part of the, startup down,
we did not get the talk to
users part.
The second startup we started
we used, a very common trick,
that lets you get away with
not talking to users,
which is that we were our own
consumer.
We, we had this idea for a
television show, Justin TV,
a reality show about Justin
Kan's life.
And we built a whole set of
technology and
website around the reality
show we wanted to run.
And so we were the user for
that for that product.
And that's actually one way to
cheat and
get away with not talking to
many other users is if you're
just building something that
literally is just for you.
You don't need to talk to
anyone else because you know
what is you want.
And what you need.
But that's if you're really
limiting,
where to start a startup.
Most startups are not just
built for
the person who is who is using
them.
And when you do that, every
now and
then, you get really lucky.
And you are representative of
some huge class of
people who all want the exact
same thing you do.
But very often also that just
turns into
a side project that doesn't go
any where.
so, we kept working on
Justin.TV for a while and
we actually achieved a good
deal of success,
because it turned out that
there were
people out there who wanted to
do the same thing we did.
Which was broadcast ourselves
live on the Internet.
But, the issue with Justin.TV,
the thing that,
the thing that sort of, kept
us
from achieving greatness is we
hadn't figured out yet.
How to how to build towards
anything beyond that
initial TV show.
We knew how to, we built a
great product actually.
If you wanted to run a live
24/7 reality TV show about
your life, we had the website
for you.
We had exactly, what you
needed.
But if we wanted to go do more
than that.
If we wanted to open it up to
a broader number of people,
a broader spectrum of people,
a broader use cases.
We didn't have we didn't have
the insight to figure that out
because we weren't that user
and so
at some point we decided to
pivot JustinTV.
We decided we needed to go in
a new direction.
We thought we'd built a lot of
valuable technology but hadn't
identified the use case that
would let it get really big.
And there were two directions
that seemed promising.
One of them was mobile.
And one of them is gaming.
And I led the gaming
initiative inside of the
company.
And what we did with gaming
that was very very different,
from what we'd ever done
before.
Was, we actually went and
talked to users,
because while I loved watching
gaming video, I was very aware
that neither I nor anyone else
in the company knew about
broadcasting video games.
And so I would amp up the
content, I thought there was
a market there, that was sort
of the insight that
I had which wasn't common at
the time,
which was how much fun it was
to watch video games.
Quick show of hands, people
know about watching video game
on the internet here?
Okay, I'm just going to assume
that people listening to
this also know about it.
If you don't know about, if
you don't know about watching
video games on the internet,
you should go read about that.
Because it's sort of,
an important context for the
stuff I'm going to talk about.
But the main point is I
thought
that was awesome but I didn't
know anything about
the side of it that was really
important, which is
actually acquiring the content
to start broadcasting.
So we went out, and we ran a.
Actually a very large number
of user interviews.
We talked to a lot of people
and brought that data back,
and that formed the core of
all of the decision-making
that was for the next three
years of product features on
Twitch was sort of some of the
insights we got from that.
And we continued to talk to
users, and
in fact built an entire.
Part of the company whose job
it is basically to talk to
our users.
Which is an, which is
a whole division that we just
didn't even have at JustinTV.
We had no one at the company
whose job it
was to talk to our most
important users.
So so that was Twitch.
And I'm, I want to give you
guys a little bit of
a a little bit of an insight
into.
With Twitch.
What, what that,
what that meant, going to go
talk to users.
So, we determined that
the broadcasters are the most
important people.
And the reason we determined
that, was, when we went and
looked into the market,
we we looked into what, what
determined.
Why people watched a certain
streamer or
went to a certain website.
They would just follow the
content, right?
You had a, you had a piece of
content you loved and
the broadcaster would come
with you.
And that's actually the one
really important point about
user interviews,
which is that who you talk to
is as important.
As what questions you ask and
you pull away from it.
Because if you go and talk to
a set of users, if we'd gone
and talked to viewers only, we
have, a complete different set
of feedback than talking to
the broadcasters.
And talking to the
broadcasters gave us
insight into how to build a
link for them.
That you're not to be
strategically correct.
I wish I could tell the recipe
for
figuring out who the target
user is for your product and
who your target user should
be.
But there isn't a recipe.
It comes down to think really
hard and, and use your,
use your judgement to figure
out,
who you're really building
this for?
So what I want to do is a
little bit,
something a little bit
interactive now, which is.
sometging We're going to,
I've got a bunch of ideas
from, from you guys actually.
So, sort of suggested ideas.
And i'm going to pick one of
them.
And I want every one to sort
of sit down and
do, do step one of this
process for me, right now.
Which is think about who would
you go ask about this.
Like which people.,
Where would you go to find the
people you needed to talk
to about this.
In order to in order to learn
about what you should build.
And so the idea you're going
to use is, let me see here.
Of these ideas, so
here it's a lecture focused
note taking app.
The idea is I don't think that
the state of the art for
note taking is good enough
yet.
And I want to make a note
taking app that improves.
You know, improves that
experience.
Makes taking notes in class
better.
Or taking notes by listening
to a lecture online better.
So you know, maybe it has
collaboration features.
Maybe it, like, helps you
focus better somehow.
It has multimedia
enhancements.
I don't know, right?
All sorts of possible
features.
But that's the, that's the
idea.
So take, like,.
Take 120 seconds right now,
and think about not what you
would ask, or what the right
features for
this app is, but who would you
talk to?
Who should the, who,
who's going to give you that
feedback that's going to tell
you whether this is good or
not?
I actually mean it, right now.
Take your laptop out, like
type, write some stuff down.
Think, think about, like, the,
you can,
it, it's good enough to.
Like think of that in your
head.
But actually, like if you
actually just write it down,
and like just come up with the
five people you talk to,
the five types of people you
talk to.
And who you think the most
important one was.
LIke, actually do it.
Because there's nothing like
actually running
through a practice of
something and trying to do it
to actually get into your
head, the right way to do it.
I"m gratified to see here
clicking in,
of the keyboards now.
If you're following along at
home, pause, actually do it.
Think about who you, who would
you talk to?
Because that's a, that is the
first question
for almost any startup that
you need
to answer is like who is my
user and,
and where am I going to find
them?
Alright that's like way
shorter than
you normally used to think
about this problem.
It's actually a really tricky
problem in, like, figuring out
where to source the people is
pretty hard, but ,.
We're going to move along
anyways in the,
in this highly abbreviated
version of learning how to
build a product and run a user
interview.
So can can I get one volunteer
from the audience to
come up and tell, tell us what
who you would talk to?
And we'll talk about it.
You guys are all pre-selected.
>>
>> Here you go.
I don't know, how to turn this
thing on, here we go.
So who do you talk to?
I would definitely talk to n
college students first,
obviously because we sit in a
lot of lectures, and
specifically I want to talk to
college students studying
different subjects to see if
maybe, you know,
if you're an English major,
if that makes a different,
versus you're studying.
Of not, Computer Science in
terms of how you want to
take notes in lectures.
>> And so you,
you're going to talk to a
bunch of college students
Would you pick any particular
subset of college students?
Like we're going to talk to
all college students or
like a broad array.
>> I, I went out and talked to
college students.
like, and break down the
divisions by like people who
study different areas maybe.
And then also maybe it would
make sense for
people who have like different
study techniques.
Because some people take a lot
of notes.
Some people don't take that
many notes,
but still jot stuff down.
>> Right.
So I mean that', that's a
really good start.
like that's, that is actually
obviously a group of users you
want to go talk to, especially
if you're targeting something
at, you know, at college
students as the consumer.