https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAws7eXItMk
new information there.
Which is why it's important to
talk to different extremes of
people right.
Go, go find people who
are different different points
because this is just six or
seven Stanford college
students, you're going to get
a very different response when
we talk to six or
seven high school students, or
six or seven parents.
All right, one second, let me
look at the So
based on that though, right, I
think the.
I think it's possible you
could come up with,
a set of ideas, right?
You have this information
about how someone takes notes,
you've, you've come up with,
potentially when you came up
with this idea you had,
you had some ideas as to, you
heard this idea, you had
some ideas as to like how you
could build something cool.
And so, if you're going to
build
just one feature on top of
Google Docs.
What would that feature be,
right?
And that's for, for, for a new
product like this, it might be
a good way to like get started
thinking about where to go.
Which is,
okay, they're extensively
using this things, right now.
How can we make that
experience just one quantum
better?
Something that would be.
Really exciting to this person
to be one one step ahead, and
so let me take two minutes,
right now.
And think about, what that
feature might be?
Actually like try to, try to
come up with what,
what you might do based on
what you heard from,
from Stephanie, that could
convince her to
switch away from her current
collaborative, multi-person,
all-working-together workflow
on Google Docs?
To your new, your new thing
that is,
has all the features of Google
Docs plus this one
special thing that's, like,
going to make it,.
It's going to make it more be,
more useful, and, and
convincing the stop using that
they are using.
Awesome, all right.
So, I'm going to invite our,
our third guest, if you,
if you have something up.
I, I don't want to put you on
the spot if
you feel like you don't,
you're not sure, but.
>> Yeah.
>> So what I, what I, is
it on?
>> Yes.
>> What I thought about was
like the, the reason she uses
Everknow is like, of like,
sticky note type notes like,
like more thoughts and like
details.
So, I feel like, Google Docs
has like documents and
not like, smaller notes.
So, I feel like a feature that
will be like,
super like, a mobile version
of draw it
that doesn't like, isn't that
clunky and like, doesn't make
you make real documents could
be like, really useful.
Awesome.
So right.
That's a,
that's a good insight.
Right, that's exactly,
what's one of the thing that
you get out of that,
that user interview?
And then, you've got this
idea.
Right, you've gotten this, I
guess, user-fed feedback.
You've got this idea.
What if we've had a Google
Docs that had
the collaborative aspects and
the group aspects of that, but
where you you could pull in
more little one off notes.
And, it was, it was designed
more around note taking.
And so, the question is, now,
once you have this idea,
which I think it's the,
it's actually probably a
reasonable approach.
Is this enough?
Is this something people would
actually switch just to have?
And, the way to validate,
there's two ways to validate
that.
One is if you're quick at
programming,
you can literally just go
build it, and
throw it out in the world and
see what happens.
and, that's that's great.
And, if that, when that works
that's
that's an excellent way to
approach it.
But, a lot of the time that
one little thing that's just
a little bit better might take
you three months to
actually build something
worthy of actually using.
And so, you actually want to
go out and
validate that idea further
before you go ahead and
start building it.
And so, you might take that
idea, and
you might go back go back out
and
you know, you can sit down
with with diagrams.
You can, you can draw what the
what it looks like.
Draw the work flow, and go
bring that in front of people,
but the one thing you really
don't want to do is
ask them this, this is sort of
a trap, and
I just want to warn you
against doing it.
Just don't go out and say, to
come up with a feature idea,
and go out and ask people.
Are, you know?
I've got this great idea
for a feature.
Are you excited about it?
Because, the, the feedback you
get from users, if you tell
them about a feature, and ask
them, is this feature good?
It's often, oh yeah, that's
great.
Like, that sounds like such a
good idea.
but, when you actually take
that in front of people, and
you actually build it.
You then, find out that while
they thought it
was such a clever idea, no one
actually, like,
cares to switch to get it.
And so, the one question you
can't ask is this feature
actually good or not?
Yes, Sam?
>> What is
the minimum that you
could do in your experience to
actually if asking, you know,
between asking and actually
building that whole thing.
>> Yeah.
So, Sam's asking if
what's the, what's the minimum
you can actually get away with
to validate, given that you
can't actually just go and
ask them is this good or not?
and, it's, it's highly
dependent the answer to
that is highly dependent on
the particular feature.
But, usually the, the best
thing you can do is, is, is,
really just hack something
together, right?
It's, you find, if your, if
your idea is to build
something on top of Google
Docs, don't, for your V1,
go rebuild, an awesome Google
Documents, but
for note taking application.
Find a way to write a browser
extension, that, that,
that stuffs just that little
bit of incremental feature in,
and, and see if it's actually
useful for people.
go, like actually, go,
go find a way to cheat is what
it comes down to,
because if you can't actually
put it in front of people
it's really, really hard to to
find that out.
For bigger things, where
you're actually trying to,
get people to spend money, it
actually gets a lot easier.
So, if you're selling it it's
great actually sales is
this cure all for this
problem.
Get people to put, give you
their credit card and
I guarantee you they're
actually using the feature.
It's it's one of the most
validating thing you
can do for a product, is go
out there and
actually get them to commit to
pay you up fron.
And, the problem is when
you're working on
a student note taking app,
that's going to be
relatively hard because you
probably unless your idea is
that you're actually going to
sell it.
It's probably something where
you're thinking at least the,
if the trial version's free,
and you're not necessarily
going to learn that much by
trying to charge people money.
But, if you go out there and
you can, if you can get people
to say hey I'm going to,
I'm going to give you money?
The money test is amazing, it
really does clarify whether or
not, they're rereally excited,
because if you're not
five-dollars-excited about it,
you're probably not very
excited about it.
so, the last thing I wanted to
do was actually work
through with you guys, what
happened at Twitch.
So I brought some slides of
feedback that I would like to
get put up.
It's my, my only slides for
the for the thing and it's,
it's.
What it is it's,
it's, it's representative
excerpts of Twitch feedback.
I had a whole like,
26 page document full of all
the feedback.
And then, I realized that
reading that was going to be a
little bit tedious and
there was no way I'd make it
through it in a lecture.
So, pretend that like this is
stuff is all representative of
like, lots of people sent this
kind of thing out to,
to ask for me ask them
questions.
And, I've already pre
condensed it for
you in to the real feedback
you got.
So, when we were working on
Twitch to go launch it,
we we wouldn't talk too
much about existing Justin.tv
Broadcasters and asked them.
About their experience
broadcasting,
what they liked about
why they broadcasted, what
they broadcasted,
what else was going on in
their life.
And, the interesting thing is
when you talk to users of
your product who are,
who are detailed users of your
product, they come back to
you with actually very detail
things about features.
Because they actually get
mired in the feature and
you have to sort of read
between the lines.
But they asked for first
things like I want to be
able to, way to clear the
banlist in my chat room.
Like, this, that was actually
a very
common request because there
was
a particular issue with how
our chat rooms worked.
People had asked for the
ability to edit the titles of
highlights after creating
them.
And, and it's,
it's, the, this was like, this
stuff was really consistent.
As we talked to broadcasters,
you probably talked to 12 fif,
fo, 14, something like that
broadcasters from the
Justin.tv gaming platform.
We got, we got all this
feedback and,
you know, what else do we
have?
We have your, your competitors
have all these cool features
like polls and scrolling text,
you, I can personalize chat
there and so, we have some
positive feedback.
They're like, oh, you guys
don't have ads, that's great.
I need to be able to ban.
So, a bunch of stuff around
chat.
A bunch of stuff around
interactivity with,
with interactivity with the
with their viewers.
And, that was all really
interesting.
So, this was what the, this is
what the Justin TV
broadcasters wanted us to
build.
And, this is what they, what,
what, where they felt pain
using the, using the product.
And so, if you thought that
what we
did was going to address these
problems, you would be wrong.
Because, actually, people who
are using your service already
and are willing to put up with
all these issues, kind of,
kind of means that
these are probably not
actually the biggest problems.
Because if you're willing to
ignore the fact that you can't
edit the band lesson, titles
are uneditable, and
there's no way to get trolls
out of your channel.
And, you're using the service
anyways,
maybe those aren't huge
problems.
And so, that sort of
brings up another really
important point.
Which is, you have to compare
you have to
compare groups of people, and
compare the level at which
they they argued with us.
So, if you go to the next
slide yes.
Nice.
We got competitor broadcaster
feedback,
which is really interesting.
So, this is stuff that you've,
we heard a lot from people who
are using other broadcast
platforms.
They wanted to be able to
switch multiple people onto
their channel at the same
time.
they, they complained about us
not
having a rev share program or
they talked a lot
about how they're trying to
make a living.
They really wanted to make
money pursuing this