https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAws7eXItMk
Yes.
>> Since you mentioned
recording did you try to
insist on
doing Skype interviews rather
than over email or?
>> What was your impression
of?
>> Yeah.
So you definitely want to do
Skype or sorry the question
was,
do we insist on Skype
interviews for recording.
You don't want to
do interviews over email if
you can avoid it
because interviews over email
are non interactive.
And the most interesting
things you learn in
interviews come from the
interesting, tell me more.
because the instant that you
hit, you hope this vein of
they'll say something you
didn't expect, and
the instant they say something
you didn't expect or didn't
already know, you should drop
into detective mode, and
detective mode is huh, that's
interesting.
Can you tell me more about
that?
And people don't like silence,
so
they'll keep talking to fill
the void.
And the best part about doing
it over Skype or
doing it in person is you have
that interactive feedback.
And you can actually pull a
lot more out of people.
E-mail interviews are, they're
okay.
But they're basically useless.
If you're in person or
over Skype, they're actually
also easy to record.
Make sure you ask them if it's
okay to record it.
It's not polite to record
people without their consent.
But if they're willing to like
give you like an in,
a user interview, they're
probably willing for
you to record it as well.
>> Sorry, but what about the
international market?
Like you mentioned if that you
had a lot of
interviews in Korea, and
I don't know maybe feel
comfortable with English, or.
>> Yeah, so the question is
like what about people in
the international market where
you're trying to do
youth interviews with people
who don't speak your language.
That's just really hard.
And actually to this day
Twitch works way better in
English speaking countries
than it
does in non English speaking
countries.
And I think a big part of that
is, we are much better at
talking to people in English
speaking countries, and
learning what their needs are.
And we're not as good at it,
in other countries.
We've tried to address that by
hiring people who speak
Korean.
Having them translate.
We've tried to address that
by, finding representative
people in those countries who
speak both English and
Korean, and reaching out to
them.
But the problem with that, is,
like the, you're
not actually getting a
representative sample.
No matter how hard you try.
The very fact that they are a
fluent English
speaker means they're not
representative of
all the people who don't speak
fluent English.
It's just a hard problem.
It's why companies find it
easier to wi,
build markets that went in
their home,
in their home country.
Much more easily than abroad.
Because it's really hard to
talk to users abroad.
Yes.
>> What channels did you use
to reach out to them, and
do you ever compensate them?
>> So the channels we used to,
what channels did we use to
reach out to them and
what did we ever compensate
them?
The channels we used to reach
out to them,
were, on site messaging
systems.
So like, if you're, most site
websites have some way to
contact the user, so if
they're a visible user of
another website you use that
sites messaging system and
say hey, I was watching your
stream, or
whatever this person was doing
on the site.
I'd love to ask you some
questions about your use
would you mind hopping on a
Skype call?
And as for, the other thing we
do is we find out who people
were and we send them emails.
we'd, like, rented some at
events.
because a lot of these people
go to the same events and we,
like, would go to the events
and,
like, get, we wouldn't run the
user interview at the event,
but you get to know them, you
exchange business cards or,
you know, whatever it is you
actually do now aren't,
isn't business cards.
And, and you, you get in touch
with them.
We tended not to compensate
people.
I think that if you, if no,
if people don't care enough
about the problem to,
like, talk to someone who's
trying to solve it.
You're probably barking up the
wrong tree.
We never had any trouble
getting people to
talk to us about paying them.
>> What about on site user
feedback tools?
Do you get a little feedback
from that?
>> So, so there's this whole
second set of user feedback
that's really important, that
I should talk about,.
The question was,
what about, like, on site user
feedback tools?
And I think this stuff you're
talking about is
where you have like a, a new
product and
you want to see how, if it's
actually going to work or not.
And so you put it in front of
people and
you see how they use it or
not.
That's really important.
That kind of work is super
important and
it can tell you lots of things
about where you went wrong
building something before you
launch it, which is great.
It doesn't tell you what to
build.
It it helps you iron out the
kinks and
edges of the thing you did
build.
But generally speaking we that
wasn't kind of the user
feedback we were getting I
mean that's stuffs good
it's good it's like it's much
more similar to the,
to the data driven approach.
Right?
You're finding out,
why are people dropping off in
this flow, you're not
finding out what problems
should I really be solving for
them, and what, what do they
care about as a human.
And, for
this kind of like really early
stages interview which
the kind of user interview
that's crucial startups do,.
>> That's the, that's where
you want to focus, so
we didn't bring on site
actually it
almost all over phone or
Skype.
Yes.
>> So for the three different
groups of people there are
different kinds of feedback so
as a startup time and
resources, is that a good area
to focus on first?
>> Yeah.
So
with the three different kinds
of people did we focused on
one of them given that we had
very limited resources, yes.
We focused on the competing
people using
competing products.
Because, we knew that they
already were interested in
the behavior that we needed
and
they were willing to do it at
all.
And therefore all we had to do
is convince them to switch,
which is a much easier thing
to do than to try to
create new behavior where none
existed before.
And we had to do that because
we had to get some quick wins,
because my gaming project
inside of
Justin.tv would have been
killed if it wasn't
showing 25% month over month
growth every single month.
So we did, and that meant
focusing on
short term get the people in
right now.
And that turned out to be good
in general because it turns
out that building something
that some people want
generally generalizes and so I
want to bring in
people who weren't even users
of the service as well.
Yes.
>> Twitch has been around from
the beginning so
it filled up, for example the
video game industry.
In the beginning this industry
was very like, decentralized,
like there wasn't a lot of
cohesion with like, you know,
different video game
companies consolidating where
tournaments are and stuff.
But now it's very different.
So you said originally you
spoke to like broadcasters and
you know streamers themselves,
how does that change when
like, for example like Riot
has you know, banned users or
professional players from
streaming their own stuff.
Have you tried to you know,
gain leverage with that or?
>> Yeah, so the question is
what about the game publishers
basically, right?
The game publishers is huge
important people in this
space.
a, the game publisher is and
any big company for
that matter isn't going to
give you the time of day as
a small start up.
Which is both good and bad.
It means you don't really
need,
need to talk to them because,
they're they're not interested
in you.
But it means you actually just
can't talk to them,
I mean we tried but no one
wanted to talk to us.
And they did once we started
getting some traction and, and
becoming a little bit,
slightly bit of a player in
the space.
I don't want to like, talk
that bad about of them
because they, they, they were
nice about it enough about it
it's just that you know, when
you're, when you're
a tiny little start up there's
lots of tiny start ups and
they, they don't have the time
to talk to all of you.
As we've gotten bigger
actually the point that,
you know, game publishers have
become an increasingly
important constituency for us.
And if I was to talk about who
Twitch does user interviews
with now, who we who we pulled
information from now it would
include game publishers
definitely because they'd be,
they've become much more
active in the space.
It was something that they
weren't particularly active
three or four years ago as
much as they are now.
And that's another really
important point about user
interviews in general.
Which is that the pool of
people you care about is
going to shift over time.
The people who get you
started,
like the crucial people to get
your product started for
the first six months,
are not who will be using it
three years later.
And it's very important you
keep, doing this stuff.
Because one thing that's
really easy to do,
is to do a little bit of it in
the beginning.
And, and achieve some level of
success, and then you sort of,
stop talking to new people.
And that's a good way to make
the, the next set of
features you build be not as
good as the first ones.
>> How about one more
question?
>> Yeah.
Yes?
>> How do you give good user
feedback, if you're a user?
>> so, how do you give good
user feedback,
it's a really good question.
So I think what I, what I want
a user to do is I
want a user to tell me about
what they, like,
what they're really thinking,
right?
And what, what, what they're
problems really are.
And to just sort of ramble.
Like I want someone to just
tell,
tell me about stuff in their
life.
Because the, the more you
learn about them as a person.
And sort of the, the, their,
what's going on in the context
of what they're doing the is
easier to understand why they
want the things they want.
And that's really the critical
question.
So I'd say like, you know,
what I'm looking for in a,
in someone, when I'm doing a
user interview, it's someone
who is going to be willing to
talk a lot and be willing to,
to really give me a full, give
me a full picture.
So that's what, I guess on the
flip side,
if you want to be a good, if
you want to help people out
with good user interview
feedback ramble, like, be,
just, just talk about stuff
and everything.
All right, great.
Well, thank you very much.
>> Thank you very much.