https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EHzvmyMJEK4
General consul.
>> Oops.
>> Christine and Caroline.
And they're going to talk
about finance and
legal mechanics for startups.
This is certainly not the most
exciting of
the classes, sorry.
But if you get this right this
is probably the class that.
So thank you very much for
coming, and yeah, go ahead.
>> Okay.
So like Sam said,
this lecture is about the
mechanics of start up.
And Kristi and I are going to
be talking about some of
the basic legal and accounting
issues that your
startup may face in the very
beginning.
I was watching Paul Graham's
video, and at one
point he says, founders don't
need to know the mechanics of
starting a startup.
I thought, oh no,
that's exactly what Sam titled
this lecture.
>> Ha.
>> But what PT actually says
is that founders don't need to
know the mechanics in detail.
Because it's very dangerous
for
founders to get bogged down in
the details.
And that's exactly right.
And Kirsten,
I can't give you the details
in 45 minutes anyway.
So our goal here today is to
make sure that you
do know better than to form
your startup as a Florida LLC.
>> So, as Sam mentioned, we
are also
worrying this is going to be
pretty boring for you to
listen to an accountant and a
lawyer talking about this.
You know?
You've had some really
amazing founders talking about
really interesting things.
But like, like Sam said, you
know,
this is the kind of stuff that
if you know the basics you can
get yourself set up in the
right way of always paying.
Stop worrying about it and
then concentrate on what you
actually want to do.
Which is make your company a
success.
And so, you know,
we refer to this term startup
all the time.
And probably in the back of
your head,
you kind of know that by
startup we mean there has to
be some legal entity.
And that's, you know, kind of
separate legal entity.
We'll talk a little bit more
about how we
actually set that up and what
that means to you.
And you also probably know
that a startup will have
assets.
IP, inventions, other things.
And that the company needs to
protect those.
So we'll talk a little bit
more about that.
About how to raise money
hiring employees, and
entering into contracts.
So there's a few other things
that talk, that you need
to talk about whilst your
setting up your company,
which kind of ferrets out a
few issues amongst founders.
Things like who's going to be
in charge and
how much equity is everybody
going to own.
So those are really good
things to talk about too.
You know, we can switch
slides.
>> Uh-oh.
>> There we go.
>> Okay.
This is us.
Kirsti has the calculator.
I have like, the geriatric
glasses,
which is actually pretty fair.
Okay, so
the first thing we're going to
talk about is formation.
Kirsti actually just mentioned
that.
Your startup is going to be a
separate legal entity.
And the, and you guys probably
already know this, but the
primary purpose for forming a
separate legal entity is
to protect yourselves from
personal liability.
And what that means is, if
you're company ever gets sued
you know, it can't, it's not
your money in your
bank account that the, that
the person can take.
It's the corporations.
So that's why you form one.
So then the question is, where
do you form one?
And theoretically you have 50
choices but
the easiest place is Delaware,
and
I'm sure you're all familiar
with that as well.
But Delaware is in
the business of forming
corporations.
The law there is very clear
and
very settled, it's the
standard.
The other thing is that
investors are very
comfortable with Delaware.
They already invest in
companies that
are Delaware corporations.
Most of
their investments are probably
Delaware corporations.
So if you are also a Delaware
corporation then
everything just becomes much
more simple, right?
There's less diligence for the
investor to do.
You don't have to have a
conversation about whether or
not to reincorporate your
Washington company into
Delaware.
So there's a reason that so
many companies do it.
It's standard.
It's familiar.
So I'll tell you a story.
We had a company at YC about
two years ago,
that was originally formed as
an LLC in a state that I'll,
that I'll say, Connecticut.
The founders had some lawyer
friends there who said,
this is the right way to do
it.
And when they came to
YC we said you guys need to
convert to Delaware.
So the lawyers in Connecticut
did the conversion
paperwork and unfortunately
they didn't do it right.
They made a very simple
mistake but
it was a very crucial mistake.
The company was recently
raising money.
Like a lot a lot of money and
this mistake was uncovered.
That the basically the mistake
was this company thought it
was a Delaware corporation for
a couple years, but
in fact it was still a
Connecticut LLC.
And I'll just say this four
different law
firms were needed to figure
that one out.
Two in Delaware one in
Connecticut,
one here in the Silicon Valley
and the bill right now is at
$500,000, for a conversion
mistake.
So, so what's the takeaway
here, pretty simple.
Keep it really simple and
familiar for yourself.
The reason we incorporate all
companies the same way at
Y Combinator is because it's
easy.
So don't get fancy.
Just save yourself some time
and money.
>> Okay.
So once you've decided that
you're going to be a Delaware
corporation,
how do you actually set that
up?
And it requires a few
different steps, but
the first one is actually
really easy.
You literally just fax two
pieces of paper into
Delaware saying, we're
going to set up a corporation.
All that does though is create
a shell of a company.
It doesn't actually do
anything within the company.
So after that,
you then need to complete a
set of documents that
among other things approve the
bylaws of the company.
It creates a board of
directors,
it creates offices of the
company.
Delaware requires that
somebody has the title of
CEO or president, and of
secretary.
So also at this point,
you need to complete documents
that assign any inventions or
any code or anything that you
as an individual create,
so that the company actually
owns that.
And remember at this point,
it's,
it's a really good thing to
think about.
You as founders have to
think about things in two
different ways.
You always have to be
thinking,
am I doing this as an
individual?
As me?
Or am I doing this on behalf
of the company,
which is a separate entity.
So you have to maintain that
split in
your mind going through all of
this.
And we'll talk more about
where that comes in
a little bit later.
So there are services that can
help you get incorporated,
of course you can use a law
firm but there are also
other online services that
help, and the one we often use
with a lot of the YC companies
is call Clearkie Clearkie.com.
And they are set up so
that all the standard, basic
documents are used and
they get you set up in a very
vanilla way.
So that you can just move on
and
keep, keep focusing on what
you need to do.
So a note on paperwork.
You're creating documents.
These are really important
documents that are going to be
affecting what the company
does, and what the company is.
So it's really, really
important that you
actually keep these signed
documents in a safe place.
And it sounds so basic, but we
get so
many founders coming to us
saying oh, I don't know.
These, these, some documents.
And they have no idea what
they are or where they are.
So really, really make sure
that you keep them in
a safe place.
And let's be, let's be honest,
this is not the glamorous part
of running a startup, you
know, filing documents.
But actually at
the times where this is
crucial are going to
be at really high stress times
in the startup's life.
It's likely to be if the
company's raising a big
series A round, or if the
company's being acquired.
The company will have to go
through due diligence, and
there will be lawyers asking
for all this stuff.
And if you don't have it and
you don't know where it is,
it's just making a really
stressful situation even
more stressful.
So really, the, you know, the
key thing here is,
like we say, keep it simple,
but
keep those documents in a safe
place and keep it organized.
It will make your life so much
easier.
>> Okay.
So now,
we're going to talk about
equity.
And we're going to touch on a
couple of
different things in this
section.
The first thing that
we're going to talk about is
equity allocation.
So what am I talking about
here?
I'm talking about.
If your company stock is a
pie,
you're talking about how to
divide the pie and
you're talking about this with
your cofounders.
Why is this important?
Well if you're a solo founder,
this really isn't important.
But if you are a team of two
or
more than this issue is
absolutely critical.
So the first thing that you
need to know is that
execution had greater value
than the idea.
What do I mean by that?
A lot of founder teams give
way too much credit and
therefore a lot of the
company's equity to the person
who came up with the idea for
the company.
And ideas are obviously very
important but
they have zero value.
Who's ever heard of a billion
dollar payment for
just an idea.
So value is really created
when the whole founder team
works together to execute on
an idea.
And so you need to resist the
urge to
give a disproportionate amount
of stock to the founder who is
credited with coming up for
the idea for the company.
The next thing you want to
think about is, okay, so
how much stock, or
should the stock be allocated
equally among the founders?
And from our perspective, the
simple answer is probably yes.
Our mantra at Y Combinator is
that
stock allocation doesn't have
to be exactly equal, but
if it's very disproportionate,
that's a huge red flag for us.
We wonder what conversation is
not happening in,
among the founder team when
the ownership isn't equal.
For example, is one founder
secretly thinking that this
whole startup thing is
temporary?
Is one founder over inflating
the work that he or
she has already done on the
company or
over inflating his or her
education or prior experience?
Do the founders really trust
each other and have they
been honest with each other
about their expectations for
this startup and for the
future?
So when ownership is
disproportionate,
what we worry about is
that the founders are not in
sync with one another.
Thirdly it's really important
to look forward in
the startup and now backwards.
Instead another way all the
founders in it 100%?
Are they in it for the long
haul?
If the expectation at your
startup is that each founder
is in it 100% and you're all
in it for the long haul,
then everything that happened
before the formation of
the company shouldn't matter.
It doesn't matter who thought
of the idea.
It doesn't matter who did the
coding, or
who built the prototype, or
which one has an MBA.
It will feel better to the
whole team if
the allocation is equal,
because the whole team is
necessary for execution.
So, here's the take away on
this point.
In the top YC companies, which
we call those, you know,
with the highest evaluations,
there are zero instances where
the founders have
had significantly
disproportionate equity split.
>> Alright, so you've had the
conversation about how to
split the equity.
But then what?
again, we talked to many
founders who