https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EHzvmyMJEK4
were actually surprised that
they have to do something in
order to own this stock.
They think about, they think
that talking about this is,
is actually enough.
And this again is another
situation where you have to
think about you as an
individual,
versus you as a representative
of the company.
And if you, if you equate this
to a large company,
you know if you, if you worked
at Google and
you were told as part of your
compensation package,
that you would be receiving
some shares,
you would expect to sign
something to get those shares.
And if you didn't, you'd be
thinking,
oh what's going on here?
Well, it's the same thing
with,
with a small company as well.
So in this case the paper,
the, the documents that
you're signing is a stock
purchase agreement.
So you as an individual, buy
the shares from the company.
And in any situation, if
you're buying something,
there's a two-way transaction
where you pay for
something and you get
something in return.
And in this case you're
getting shares in return for
either a cash payment, or for
contributing IP, or
inventions, or code to the
company, so that the company
actually owns everything that
you've done in the past.
So, we also refer to that
stock being restricted
because it vests over time.
And we're going to cover that
next in more detail.
But, as a result of the stock
being restricted investing,
there's one very very crucial
piece of paper.
That we talk about until we're
blue in the face to everybody,
because there's actually no
way to go back and fix this.
And this is actually one of
the things that,
because there's no, there's no
way to fix this,
this has blown up deals in the
past.
We've, we've seen companies
where, because they haven't
filed what's called an 83 b
election deals have blown up.
And I'm not going to go into
detail about what that 83 b
election is actually about,
but
just leave it as it affects
your individual taxes, and
it affects the company's
taxes.
And so, it can have a big
impact.
So, you know, here we have the
main,
the main things here are sign
the paperwork.
Sign the, sign the stock
purchase agreement,
sign the 83 b election, and
make sure that you
actually have proof that you
sent that in.
Because if you don't have the
proof,
it just goes into a black hole
at the IRS, and
investors and acquirers will
walk away from a deal if
you can't prove that.
>> Okay.
So the next thing we're going
to talk about is vesting.
And I imagine that many of you
are familiar with what
vesting is.
But just in case,
really simply vesting means
that you get full ownership of
your stock over a specific
period of time.
So we're talking about the
stock that Chrissie just said,
you bought your stock of your
company, and
you own it and you get to vote
it.
But if you leave before this
vesting period is over,
then the company can get some
of those unvested shares back.
So and I'm just going to, just
so you guys know the other
ways to refer to vesting,
you'll hear restricted stock.
That means that,
that stock that's subject to
vesting, the IRS speak for
this is, shares that are
subject to forfeiture.
So, so, it's a little
terminology there.
okay.
So,
what should a typical vesting
period be?
In Silicon Valley, the
so-called standard vesting
period is four years with a
one year cliff.
This means that after one
year, the founder vests in or
fully owns, 25% of the shares.
Then the remaining shares vest
monthly over the next
three years.
So here's an example.
Founder buys stock on
Christmas Day, let's say, and
then quits the company on the
following Thanksgiving, so
before the year is passed.
In that case, the founder
leaves with zero shares,
right, cliff period hasn't
been met.
If the founder though, quits
the day after the next
Christmas, so a year and a day
later, he or
she's vested in exactly 25% of
the shares, right?
In that case, the one year
cliff has been met.
So, what happens to the shares
when a co,
when a founder stops working
at the company?
Company can repurchase those
shares.
An example I just gave, where
the founder quit, a year and
a day after purchasing the
shares,
75% of those shares are still
invested.
And the company will
repurchase all the,
that full 75% of those shares
from the founder.
How?
Just writes the founder a
check.
That's how the founder bought
it, right?
So, it's the same price per
share that the founder paid,
and it's really just
giving the founder his or her
money back.
So then the question is, why
would you have vesting?
Why would founders do this to
themselves, right?
because it's just the founders
they're,
they're doing this on their
own shares.
Doing this to their own
shares.
So, and probably the number
one reason why vesting is
important has to do with
founders leaving the company.
So without, say you didn't
have vesting and
a founder leaves, a huge chunk
of the equity ownership leaves
with a him, him or her.
And obviously that is not fair
to the founders left behind.
And we're actually going to
talk about this a little bit
more when we get to the
founder employment slide,
I'll go into that in more
detail.
But the other reason to have
vesting is the concept of
skin in the game.
The idea that founders need to
be incentivized,
to keep working on their start
up.
If a founder can walk away
with his or
her full ownership at any
point in time, then why would
you stay and grind away, start
ups are hard.
So do single founders need
vesting?
They do, and the reason is
because the skin in the game
concept applies to solo
founders as well.
And investors really want to
see all founders, even
solo founders incentivized to
stay at the company for
a long time.
And the other reason that
single founder should put
vesting on their shares is to
set an example for employees.
Because you can imagine it
would be, you know,
inappropriate for a founder to
tell an employee that he or
she has to have four year
vesting on his or her shares.
But the founder doesn't think
that he or
she needs any on their own
shares.
It's really a culture point.
A founder who has vesting on
his or
her shares, then sets the,
sets the tone for
the company, saying, we're all
in it for the long haul.
We all have vesting on our
shares,
we're doing this together.
So, what are the takeaways
from here?
I would say vesting alliance
incentives among the founders,
if they all have to stick it
out and
grow the company before any of
them get any of that company.
And then number two,
investors don't want to put
money in a company where
the founders can quit whenever
they feel like it and still
have a big equity ownership
stake in that company.
>> Okay, so moving on.
We've now got a beautifully
formed corporation
in Delaware.
Everybody's got their stock.
It's all the, the plain
vanilla standard paperwork.
So, so then what?
You know, probably the next
stage of a company's life
is needing to raise some
money.
So we're going to, we're going
to talk a bit more about that.
And you, and, you know,
we know that you've already
heard a lot from investors and
from founders already in, in
this set of classes.
And they've been talking much
more around the tactics and
how to raise money but, what
about the paperwork?
What about when somebody
actually agrees to
invest, then what?
So, first of all in terms of
logistics,
in very simple terms there are
two ways to raise money.
So, either the price is set
for
what the, the money that comes
in or the price isn't set.
And by price, we mean the
valuation of the company it's,
it's the same things.
So rounds can't actually be
called anything people can,
can name them whatever they
want.
But generally if you hear the
term,
seed round, it would mean that
the price has not been set,
and anything that's a Series A
or a Series B,
would be something where the
price has been set.
So not setting the price is
the most straightforward,
fast route to getting money.
And usually the way that this
is done is through convertible
notes or safes.
And, again this is a two way
transaction.
So, there's a piece of paper
that says, for
example, that an investor is
paying $100,000 now.
And in return, has the right
to receive stock at a future
date when the price is set by
investors in a priced round.
So it's important to note that
at, at the time the paper work
is set, that investor is not a
shareholder, and
therefore doesn't have any
voting rights on the company.
They will have some other
rights which Carolynn is
going to talk about
separately.
Of course, investors want
something in return for
putting in money at the
earliest,
ie riskiest, stage of the
companies life.
And this is where the concept
of evaluation cap comes in,
which I'm sure many of you
have heard mentioned before.
So usually the documents for
an un,
unpriced round set a cap for
the conversion into shares.
And that's not the current
valuation of the company
it's actually an upper bound
on the valuation used in
future to use used in future
to calculate how
many shares that investor is
going to get.
So, for an example, an
investor that invests $100,000
on a safe with a $5 million
cap.
Then a year later the company
raises a priced round with
evaluation of, let's say $20
million.
And then the early investor
would have a much,
much lower price per share,
about a quarter.
And therefore that $100,000
would buy them approximately.
Four times more shares than an
investor that was coming in
and putting in 100,000 in that
Series A priced round.
So that's where they get
their, their reward for
being in early.
So again, this is another
situation where you need to
make sure you have the signed
documents and you,
you know where they are,
because different investors
may have different rights.
And so you need to know what
those things are.
And again services like Clerky
can, can help with that.
They have very standard
documents that most of
our YC companies use to raise
money on.
A couple of other things to
think about when
you are raising money.
Hopefully you've got a really
hot company that's,
that's doing great and it's
really easy to raise money.
But you should be aware that
all
these people throwing money at
you does have some downsides.
So the first thing is to
understand your
future dilution.
So if you raise, let's say,
$2 million on safes with a
valuation cap of $6 million.
Then when those safes convert
into equity, those early
investors are going to own
about 25% of the company.
And that's going to be in
addition to the investors that
are coming in at that priced
round,
who may want to own 20% of the
company.
So you've already at that
point given away 45% of
the company.
So is this really what you
want?
And, you know, the answer
might be yes.
Remember that some money on a
low valuation cap
is infinitely better than no
money at all.
And if those are the terms
that you can get,
then, then take that money.
But it's just something to be
aware of,
and to follow through the
whole process, so that you can
see where this is going to
lead you down the road.
The other thing to bear in
mind is that the invest,
investors should be
sophisticated.
And by that we mean that they,
they have enough money to be
able to invest and that they,
they understand that
investing in startups is a
risky business.
You know we, we see so many
companies coming into us that
say, oh yeah, my, my uncle put
money in, or my neighbor put
money in, and they've put in
$5 or $10,000 each.
And often, those are the
investors that
cause the most problems going
forward,
because they don't understand
how this is a long term game.
And so, you know, they get to
the point where they're
sitting, thinking hm, I could
actually do with that
money back because I need a
new kitchen.
Or, you know this,
this startup investing is not
actually as exciting as
all the TV shows and movies
made it out to be.
So, and those, those cause
problems to the company,
you know, if they're, they're
asking for their money back.
So, just be aware that, that
you should really be
getting money from people who
are sophisticated and
know what they're doing.
And the term that you'll hear
that, that refers to
these people are that they are
accredited investors.
So really the main,
the main points here is keep
it simple, raise your
money using standard documents
keep, make sure that you have