https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SHAh6WKBgiE
but really getting consumers
to
download apps is obviously
very difficult.
Yeah.
I don't, I don't.
In.
I don't usually
just download apps.
Yeah.
To send a message.
[CROSS-TALK].
In, in most businesses we have
a called action,
which says text the owner
directly.
Oh.
We've tested actually a bunch
of
copy that works the best in
small print.
We have, the messages are
anonymous,
they also lowers the barrier
to entry.
I think the most
counterintuitive thing we've
learned in the kind of launch
that we've had where,
in 350 locations in the Bay,
we've been doing this for
about three months we're about
11%
weekly growth rate in terms of
acquiring businesses.
But the most counter-intuitive
thing that we learned,
because we weren't actually
sure,
is, will people send messages
when they walk
into [CROSS-TALK] and they do.
What's the number one type of
message that people send?
So you would, so originally,
we started this product off
thinking this is going to be,
like, in-location feedback.
That was the premise,
in-location feedback.
What we found is more than
half the messages,
are actually not about
feedback at all,
they ask things like we,
we were in this location in
San Jose this Kabob stand,
father and son, it's just a
take out place, and
we saw messages that go
through,
that went through that said
like are you hiring?
And that's like very strange
because you
would think like why wouldn't
you just ask the owner.
Yeah.
But we realized that we know
this is the owner, and
the person who's walking in
doesn't and so
they, they do prefer to
actually just text the owner
because they think that's a,
that's an easier medium.
Okay, so it's like a
suggestion box, or
it's like a way to just like
message a business.
Yeah, initially that's what we
thought it was, but
what we actually discovered
was the vast majority,
I shouldn't say vast majority,
over half
the messages are actually just
things like when do you open,
when do you close because
that's not on Google.
Do you, do, you know, are you
catering can you,
do you have any reservations
available tonight, et cetera.
Okay, okay.
Well, look,
in terms of your traction it
sounds like you said you had
some businesses, like.
Yeah.
Tell me about what,
what you guys have right now.
So we have about 350
businesses,
all from San Jose to San
Francisco.
We sold them ourselves as
three founders.
We're all technical, but we
actually did all the sales
because we learned a lot about
how these businesses work.
We actually come from a retail
background.
We originally built this
product for
large enterprise players like
Starbucks and Walmart.
But we recognize that closing
those contracts, and
our limited amount of runway
wouldn't really be possible.
So we wanted to get the
product in the hands of users.
So we did SMBs.
And that's when we discovered
hey,
this like, this messaging
product.
>> Okay, okay, that sounds
interesting.
It sounds like you have some
customers.
>> Yes, so we get.
>> How, how
could this be big though?
Like, okay, maybe you can
100,000 customers.
>> Yeah, so, in terms of like,
numbers, we, we see one and
half messages on average per
location per day.
That might not sound a lot,
but
for a business, that's
skidding 30 messages.
You take like a Yelp review or
a Google review.
In a lifetime of visits, they
might get five or seven.
So they're getting a, a huge
volume of messages relative to
what they tend to experience
and they're private, so
they're not public.
So in terms of, how do we
actually make money, it's not,
you know, frankly speaking,
we don't have a very clear
answer there.
The two paths are the SMB side
or
the LCS side, the large
customer side.
Large customers, we know from
our retail experience,
just regular feedback tools
are 3 to 4 million per year,
so a like a Sear's, where we
came from.
SMBs we've tested with are
willing to pay $50 a month,
so, I, I, you know, I
certainly I think this is.
>> Okay.
>> This can be a large
business, but, and there's
clear ways to make money, but.
I could see, I could see that.
Just a couple things like,
can you tell me about your
distribution strategy and
also just a little bit about
the team.
>> Yeah.
So
distribution so the thing that
we learned in
selling to these SMBs is it's
really freaking hard.
there, the formula LTV minus
CPA, lifetime value minus cost
price acquisition in SMB is
never going to work out.
Right.
>> And so we
have two solutions.
One is to go up market,
like we originally planned,
the Starbucks or
Walmarts or two is actually
essentially pair with
consumer facing companies
Yelp, Google, Facebook.
>> Have you been talking to
them,
do they actually want to do
it?
>> Yeah, so we've talked to
Google and
Facebook we're meeting with
Yelp.
What we're basically want to
do is every time you
search for a business there
should be a message button.
We want to get consumers in
the habit of knowing,
they can send, essentially a
text message to any business.
That can help us get broad
distribution.
Our real vision is to become
kind of that infrastructure,
that messaging infrastructure
between consumers and
business.
If that doesn't work, let's
say Google, Facebook, and
Yelp don't want to give up
that valuable property.
It's really an ad unit.
>> Okay.
>> we, we do want to sell this
as a feedback tool to large,
large players.
>> All right.
Can you tell me
a little about the team?
We're running low on, on time.
>> Yeah, there's three of us.
All technical.
We Mike and I did a company
before.
Sunny is an ex-Google
engineer.
We come from retail.
So and our first startup was a
failure.
So, I don't know if that's
good or
bad but, we've, we've worked
together and, yeah.
We're all technical, we built
everything ourselves.
And we sold everything
ourselves.
>> Okay.
>> So we've already had
a couple conversations with
your firm.
We're raising 500,000 and 8.5
million convertible note.
Of that 500, 250's committed
by Mike Mapels,
Eli Gill, and Aiden Sinkit.
And Mike with Floodgate is
willing to fill the round.
We think your, you know,
you particularly, you and your
firm can bring a lot to
the team with your retail
experience.
Is this something that's
interesting to you?
>> Yeah, you know, I, I think
this is really interesting.
I mean, I would need to talk
to a couple more folks on my
side, but I do think this
this,
this could be pretty big.
>> Yes, since we've had a
couple conversations before
and and we're certainly
willing to meet again,
we are closing a round this
Friday.
And so, certainly take time
and let, you know, and
let, your other partners know.
I'll be available between now
and Friday.
I'll give you another call
before Friday.
Before we close the round.
But we'd love to actually see
you, see you in the round.
>> Okay.
Well sounds good.
I gotta go, but thanks for
talking to me.
>> Great.
Thanks.
Okay.
All right,.
>> So
very different class type of,
type of a conversation.
>> Yeah, so do you have a
clicker.
>> Yes.
>> So in terms of that one,
you know, some key points here
is, try to
actually tell a narrative that
makes sense to people.
You notice there was
narratives there.
He was talking about people,
how they really use it.
Were able to tie it down to
the real world, which is good.
He was able to demonstrate
insights, and
actually tell me something I
didn't already know about
the market, like, there were,
there were some tidbits there.
It was more, it was more of a
collaborative meeting where it
felt more like a conversation
than just like a,
like I was interviewing him
about something in,
in my opinion.
He actually asked for money.
And this is the other key
thing is at the end,
you saw I could have easily
just been like,
okay, gotta go.
But he, he did talk about
fundraising as,
as Michael mentioned.
And he was able to provide all
the context and
all the questions I would need
to actually have a serious
conversation with him.
If he was cagey about it or
shy about it,
and not clear on the numbers,
that there's a very high,
good chance that, you know, I
probably would have just ended
the conversation, due to time
pressure.
>> Yeah, it's interesting.
And we, we sit on this side a
lot.
You really, you can tell when
people are very passionate and
know their business very, very
well.
And that's what you have to
become.
okay.
So closing thoughts here
before we, what you want to do
after the meeting.
Before we get into the Q&A.
We're running a little short
on time.
After the meeting, the first
thing,
just like Tyler said in the
sales thing, follow up.
This is, this is important.
And anything other than a
check, or wired funds is a no.
So if they say, we gotta keep
talking to partners,
I assume that's a no.
And so, you do want to put
some pressure.
The way that you can do that
is get deal heat.
Deal heat is just a term which
means there's a demand for
your, to, to be in your round.
This is the easiest way and
an important way to actually
drive up price, et cetera.
Due diligence on the
investors.
So let's say you have that
500,000 raise for your
seed round on the 8.5 million
like we used in this example.
Due diligence investors.
If you do find it, I, I do,
due diligence on adults, and
I find, hey, he's actually not
a great investor.
I can get Elaud, or Mike
Maples, or
whoever to actually fill the
rest of the round.
It's surprising to us,
how many entrepreneurs don't
do this.
You would, it's like,
you would actually spend a lot
of time hiring somebody.
You're selling a part of your
company to somebody,
you should know who you're
selling it to.
To make sure they,
you know, they're the type of
people you think they are.
And then last, know when to
stop.
So some founders get so good
at fundraising they just
want to do it all the time
because it's much easier to
do than actually building the
company.
>> Yeah, you think you can
fundraising does not equal
success and just because.
>> Yeah.
>> You fund-raise does not
mean you succeeded and nobody
realizes that and
I'm, we say this and we'll say
this now, but
I'm sure everyone will still
equate fundraising with
success and read about
someone's fundraising and
assume that means they're
successful.
>> Well my, my, my intuition
as to why this is
the case is because a lot of
smart people their whole life,
they've like, applied to good
schools and applied to
good jobs, and they, they just
think fundraising is
another like application they
can just kind of check off.
And building a company is much
more ambiguous, but.
Anyways, that's, that's the
session.
I don't if we have time for,
oh.
The edge is under,
underlining, building your
company.
Fundraising is not the goal.
>> Can you guys just stick
around for
a few minutes after, and
answer questions?
>> Sure.
>> Yeah, we can do that.
>> All right.
Thank you very much,
that was great.