https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CVfnkM44Urs
is to have vesting on the
equity.
Uh, we pretty much won't
fund a company now,
where the founders don't
have vested equity
vesting equity, cuz it's
just that bad.
The other thing to do is as
soon as problems come up
in the relationship between
the cofounders,
which happens to some degree
in every company.
Um, talk about it early,
don't let it just sit off
there and fester.
If you have to choose
between hiring an employee
that's not ideal and losing
your customer, you lose one
of the particular working
>> If you have to choose
between hiring a suboptimal
employee and losing
your customers to your
competitor what do you do?
Um, if it would be one of
the first five,
say employees of the
company.
Uh, I would lose those
customers.
Um, I just,
I think the damage that it
does to the company.
Um, you, you know, you don't
wanna, it's better to lose
some customers than kill the
company.
Um, later on I might have a
slightly different opinion,
but it's really hard to say
in the general case.
How about one more question,
and I'll keep going, yes?
>> Uh, what's your
experience with cofounders
who aren't working uh, in
the same location?
>> I'm gonna get to that
later.
The question is what about
cofounders that are not
working in the same
location.
>> Um, don't do it.
I am skeptical of remote
teams in general.
But in the early days of a
startup where
communication and speed
outweigh everything else.
Um, for whatever reason,
video conferencing or
calls just don't work that
well.
The data on this is look at
the say, like,
30 most successful software
startups of all time.
And try to point to a single
example
where the cofounders were in
different locations.
It's really, really tough.
Um, all right.
We'll skip a little bit of
this.
All right.
So, now we're gonna talk
about execution.
Um, execution for most
founders is
not the more fun part of
starting a company.
But it is often the most
critical.
Um, most people that start a
company think that they
are signing up to have this
brilliant idea.
And, you know, then they're
just going to be,
like, be on magazine covers
and go to parties.
>> But really what it's
about more than
anything else, what, what
being a founder means is, is
signing up for this year's
long grind on execution, and
you can't outsource this.
Um, the way to have a
company that executes well
is to execute well yourself.
Everything in startup gets
modeled after the founders.
Whatever the founders do
becomes the culture.
So if you want a culture
where people work hard and
pay attention to detail and
focus on the customer and
are frugal um,
you have to do it yourself
there is no other way.
You cannot hire a COO and
have them, you know,
do this while you go off to
conferences.
The company just needs to
see you as
like this maniacal execution
machine.
As I said in the first
lecture,
there's like a hundred times
at least more people with
great ideas.
Than people that are willing
to put in the effort,
um, to execute them well.
Ideas by themselves are not
worth anything.
Only executing well is what,
what adds value,
or what creates value.
A big part of execution is
just putting in the effort.
Um, but there is a lot you
can learn about how to
be good at it and so we're
gonna have I
think three classes that
just talk about this.
Uh, so the CEO, people have
asked me a bunch of
times like the jobs of the
start up CEO.
And there are probably more
than five but, you know,
here are five that come up a
lot in the early days.
Um, the first four,
I think everyone thinks of
as CEO jobs.
Set the vision.
Raise money.
Evangelize the company to
people you're trying to
recruit.
Existing employees,
partners, press,
customers, everybody.
Hire and manage the team.
Um, but the fifth one is
setting the execution bar,
and this is not something
that
most founders get excited
about.
Probably think about
themselves doing that I
think is actually one of the
critical CEO roles.
And no one but the CEO can
do this.
Um execution gets divided
into two, two key questions.
One can you figure out what
to do?
And two can you get it done?
Um so I wanna talk about two
parts of getting it done.
Assuming that you've already
figured out what to do.
Um, and those are focus and
intensity.
Ah, so, so focus is
critical.
Um, one of my favorite
questions to ask founders
is what they're spending
their time and money on.
Um, this reveals almost
everything,
about what founders think is
important.
One of the hardest parts
about being a founder.
Is it there are 100
important
things competing for your
attention every day.
Um, and you have to identify
the right two or three, work
on those and then ignore or
delegate or defer the rest.
And a lot of these things
that,
that founders think are
really important, you know.
Interviewing a lot of
different law firms,
going to conferences,
recruiting advisors,
whatever, they just don't
matter, right?
And what really does matter,
varies with time but
it's an important piece of
May Day advice.
You need to figure out what
the two or
three most important things
are and then just do those.
And you can only have two or
three things every day,
because everything else will
just come at you.
You know fires of the day,
and
if you don't get really good
at setting what these two or
three priorities are every
day.
Um, you'll never be great at
actually getting stuff done.
This is really hard for
founders right.
Founders are people that get
excited by starting new
things.
Unfortunately, the trick to
great execution is to
say no a lot.
You know, you're saying no
97 times out of 100,
um, and most founders find
that they have to
make a very conscious effort
to do this.
Most startups are not nearly
focused enough.
They work really hard,
maybe, but
they don't work hard on the
right things.
And you'll still fail.
Um, one of the great and
terrible things about
starting a startup is that
you get no credit for
trying.
You only get points when you
make something that the
market wants.
So if you work really hard
on the wrong things.
Uh, no one will care.
So then there's this
question of how do
you figure out what to focus
on each day?
And this is where it's
really important to
have goals.
Most good founders that I
know uh,
at any given time have a
small number of
overarching goals for the
company.
Everybody in the company
knows.
Could be things like ship a
product by this date.
You know, maintain this
growth rate,
get this certain engagement
rate, hire for
these key roles, get this
deal done.
But anybody could tell you
in the company every week
what are our, what are our
key goals?
And then everybody executes
based off of that.
The founder really does set
the focus.
Um, whatever the founder
cares about,
whatever the founders think
are the key goals.
Um, that's going to
be what the whole company
focuses on.
And, and the best founders
repeat these goals over and
over far more often than
they
think they should need to.
They put em up on the walls,
they talk about them in one
on one's,
all hands meeting every
week.
Um, but it keeps the company
focused.
One of the keys to focus on
why I said I think.
Co-founders in different
places struggle is that
you can't be focused without
really great communication.
Um, even if you only have
say four or
five people in a company.
A small communication
breakdown is enough for
everybody to be working on
slightly different things.
Um, and then you lose focus
and
the company just scrambles.
I'm going to talk about this
a little bit more later.
Um, but growth and
momentum are something you
can never lose focus on.
Uh, growth and momentum are
what a start up lives on.
Uh, and you always have to
focus on maintaining these.
You should always know how
you
are doing against your
metrics.
You should have a weekly
review meeting every
week and you should be
extremely suspicious if
you're ever talking about.
We're not focused on growth
right now,
we're not growing that well
right now, but
we're doing this other
thing, you know.
We don't have, we don't have
a timeline for when we're
gonna ship this cuz were
focused on this other thing.
We're doing a rebrand,
whatever, almost always a
disaster.
So you wanna have the right
metrics and
you want to be focused on
growing those metrics and
having momentum.
Um, don't, don't let the
company get distracted or
excited by other things.
Um, a common mistake is that
company's gets excited by
their own PR.
It's really easy to get PR
with no results and
it feels like your actually
really cool.
But in a year, you'll still
have nothing, and
at that point you won't be
cool anymore.
And you'll just be
talking about these articles
from a year ago.
That oh, you know, like
these Standford students
start this new startup, it's
gonna be the next big thing.
And now you have nothing,
and that sucks.
Um, and then,
as I mentioned already, be
in the same space.
Ah, this is like,
I think this is pretty much
a non starter.
Remote co-founding teams is
just really really hard.
It slows down the cycle time
more
than anybody ever thinks
it's going to.
The other piece, besides
focus for
execution is intensity.
Um, startups only work at a
fairly intense level.
Um, a friend of mine says
that the secret to startups
is extreme focus and extreme
dedication.
You know you can like a have
a startup in one
other thing, you can have a
startup in a family but
you probably can't have many
other hobbies.
Startups are not the best
choice for
work life balance.
And that's sort of just, the
sad reality.
Um, there's a lot of great
things about a startup, but
this is not one of them.
Um, they are all consuming
in
a way that is difficult to
explain.
You, you generally need to
be willing to outwork your
competitors.
The good news here, uh, why
that's hard to see um, is
that a small amount of extra
work on the right thing.
Makes a huge difference.
One example that I like to
give is thinking about
the viral coefficient for a
consumer web product.
Um, how many users how many
new users each
existing user brings in.
If it's .99 the company will
eventually flatline and then
die.
Uh, and if it's 1.01 you'll
be in this happy place of
exponential growth forever.