https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=59ZQ-rf6iIc
founders usually understand
this is good,
investors are very
shortsighted and
don't want to dilute
themselves.
So they'll like fight you over
every equity grant.
But we've seen a lot of data
at YC now,
and the most successful
companies, and
the ones where the investors
do the best,
end up giving a lot of stock
out to employees,
year after year after year.
So I tell founders like, you
should think about,
you know, for the next ten
years, you're going to
be giving out 3 to 5% of the
company every year,
because you just get bigger
and bigger.
So the individual grants get
smaller, but in aggregate,
it's a lot of stock.
And I think this is really
important to do,
if you value your people, you
should be doing this.
specifically, you need to do
this with refresher grants and
you should get a, a plan in
place for this early.
You know, I think, you never
want an employee in a place
where they vested three out of
their four years of stock and
they start thinking about
leaving.
So you should always stay in
front of
people's vesting schedules.
And you know, how they plan
early where you have
refresher grants in place.
There are a lot of new
structures that people have
been using here.
I personally like six year,
big grants, but
six years investing.
because I think these
companies just take
a while to build.
There's Pyramid Vesting where
you back weight
someone's grant, so in year
four they get a lot more of
the vesting than year one.
There's a concept, different
names for it,
but something like continuous
forward vesting,
where people's grants are
automatically reupped
every year, at the same number
of shares.
Whatever you decide, get an
option management system
in place at about this point.
The normal way people do
this is just someone keeps an
Excel spreadsheet.
I have seen mistakes that have
cost employees or
companies tens of
millions of dollars because
they didn't get this right.
So there's really good option
management systems or
software and
you should get those in place
around this point.
The other sort of HR stuff to
touch on, there are a bunch of
rules that change around 50
employees.
Common examples are that you
have to
start sexual harassment
training and
diversity training there's a
bunch of others as well.
But just put a little pin in
your mind that when you
cross 50 employees there's a
new set of HR rules that you
have to comply with.
Monitor your team for burnout.
Again, it's up to product
market fit it's just to
Sprint, now it becomes a
marathon.
At this point, you actually
don't want people to
work a hundred hours a week
forever.
You want them to go on
vacation.
You want them to have new
challenges and do new things.
And if you let the whole
company get burned out all at
once, that, that is often a
company-ending thing.
This is also a good time to
put in place a,
a hiring process.
Another thing that most
founders regret is they
don't hire as soon as
everything is working,
I think you should hire a
full-time recruiter.
If you do this too early,
that's bad because you'll hire
too fast, and
that usually implodes.
But, most founders get behind
the ball on this.
The other, there are a lot of
other,
sort of just hiring process
tips.
For example, I think most
companies,
even until they get up to say
3 or 400 employees
should announce every offer on
some internal mailing list or
something before they make it,
because like half the time you
do that,
someone in the company will
know something good or
bad about that employee.
And the companies that I
know that have instituted this
have been really happy.
Also a good time to have a
program in place to ramp up
employees, so when someone
starts, you know,
what does their first week
look like?
How do they get, how do they
get spun up?
How do they learn everything
they need to learn?
Are they going to have
a buddy that's going to think
through them?
That's going to help them
think through kind of
everything about the company.
Here's one that you actually
do need to think about before
the 12 to 24 month mark, which
is diversity on the team ,.
The most common place this
comes up honestly is people
that hire, you know, all guys
on their engineering team for
the first 15 or 20 people.
And in that point you get a
culture in place that sort of
takes on a life of it's own,
and most founders that I've
spoken to that have made this
mistake regret it and
they wished they had hired
some diversity of
perspective on the team early
on.
Engineering teams are not the
only place where it comes up,
but that's where you see it
the most often, and
if you get this right early
you'll be able to grow
the team much more quickly
over, over the long-term.
The other thing to
think about is what happens to
your early employees.
So, a common situation that
happens is,
the company evolves fast the
early employees
you know, the company, so like
you hire an engineer who is
a really great engineer, but
then as the engineering team
grows you need a VP of
Engineering.
The early engineer wants to be
the VP of Engineering,
you can't do that, and but you
don't the early employee to
leave, they're an important,
important part of the culture,
they know a lot, people love
them, and so
I think you want to be very
proactive about this.
You know, you want to like
think about what's the path
for my first 10 or 15
employees going to
be as the company grows, and
then just talk to them about
it very directly, be up front,
you know,.
I want, like sit them down and
say, I want to talk about,
sort of where you want to see
your career go inside of this
company.
All right, so
company productivity, this is
something you don't need to
think about in the early days
because small teams are just
sort of naturally productive
most of the time.
But as you grow,
it the productivity I think
goes down with the square of
the number of employees if you
don't make an effort because
it sort of one of these like
connections between nodes,
every pair of people adds
communication overhead.
And so if you don't start
thinking about the systems
that you're going to put in
place, when the company is 25
to 50 people, to stay
productive as you grow
things will grind to a halt
faster than you can imagine.
The single word that matters
most, I think,
to keep the company productive
as it grows is alignment ,.
The reason companies become
unproductive is
people are either not on the
same page and you know, don't
know what the same priorities
are, or they're actively
working against each other
which is obviously worse.
But if you can keep the entire
company aligned in
the same direction, you'll
have one well over half of
the battle, and, and the way
to
start with this is just a very
clear roadmap and goals.
Everyone in the company should
know what the roadmap for
the next three or six months,
or a year, depending on
where the company is in its
life cycle, looks like.
You know, a classic test that
I love to give is if
I walk into a company getting,
beginning to struggle with
these scaling issues, I'll ask
the founders, like,
if I walked around and polled
ten random employees and
asked them what the top three
goals for the company are,
right now, would they all say
the same thing?
And a 100% of the time, the
founder says, yes,
of course they would, and I'd
go do it, and 100%
of the time, no two employees
even say the same three,
top three goals, in order.
And founders can never believe
it, because they're like well
I announced that in all hands
like three months ago what our
goals were going to be, and
how can they not remember?
But it's really important to
keep reiterating the,
the message about the roadmap
and
the goals, and almost no
founder does this enough.
And if you do it, you know the
company will say, you know,
all right, these are our
goals, we understand them,
we're going to get them done,
I know self-organize around
that.
But if people don't know what
the roadmap of
their goals are it won't
happen.
We already talked about
figuring out your
values early, but
I want to reiterate that
because that also really help
the company make the right
decisions.
If everyone knows what the
framework to decide is.
They'll make hopeful the same
decisions if
they're smart people.
You want to continue to be run
by great products and
not process for its own sake,
this is a fine, fine line.
Because you do need to put
some process in place, but
you never want to put process
in
place that rewards the
process.
The focus has to always be on
great product.
One easy way to do this that a
lot of companies try is they
just say, we're going to ship
something every day, and
if you do that you know,
there's at least a continued
focus on delivery.
And then transparency and
rhythm in how you communicate
are really important, most
founders wait way too long on
these, but having a management
meeting every week,
of just the people that report
directly to the founder or
the CEO, critical ,.
All hands meetings not quite
sure how often is optimal for
those, at least once a month
where you go through
the results and
the real map with the entire
company really important.
And then, you know, doing a
plan every quarter of
what we're going to get down
over the next three months and
how that fits into our goals
for
the year, also becomes really
important.
I put offsites up there,
because I don't think people
do these nearly enough.
A surprising number of the
successful companies we've
been involved with do a lot of
offsites.
Where they'll take their best
people for a weekend to
a cabin in the woods or
somewhere and just talk about.
What do we want to be when we
grow up?
What are our most important
things to be doing?
What are we not doing that we
should be doing?
But get people out of the
office and
out of the day-to-day,
everyone I
know that does those thinks
they're well worth the time.
So the goal in all of this
productivity planning is that
you're trying to build a
company that creates a lot of
value over a long period of
time,
and the long period of time is
what's important here.
You can avoid all of this and
just like with the authority
of the founder make
sure the company ships a great
next version.
But that won't work for
version ten, it won't work for
version 11.
I, I really believe that this
single hardest thing in
business is building a company
that does repeatable
innovation and
just has this ongoing culture
of excellence as it grows.
If you look at the examples of
this most companies fail here.
Most companies do one great
thing where the founder just
pushes to get it done and
then don't innovate that well
on follow on products.
And it really takes founders
that think about how I'm
going to do this second thing.
This really hard thing.
To get something like an Apple
that can churn out great
products for 30 or 40 years,
or longer.
All right, these are super
tactical mechanics.
This is, this is definitely to
just put on a list and
remember these things for
later.
All right in the early days,
people basically ignore all
accounting and they have,
like, maybe if they're lucky,
a shoebox full of receipts.
They certainly don't have
anything that
looks like a financial report.
This is a good time to get it
in place.
You know, when things are
working, say,
month 18 or whatever.
You can do this with an
outsourced person.
Just say, you know what?
We want, like to get our books
in order.
We want to start getting
audits every year.
We want to
start a relationship with an
accounting firm.
Easy to do.
Definitely worth it.
This is also a good time to
collect your legal documents.
Because it's easy to fix
things now.
So, if you actually assign
someone to go through and
collect every agreement the
company has ever signed.
Then when your landlord tries
to **** you out of your
lease and no-one can find the
lease which happens like,
half the time somehow someone
will be able to find it.
Also, you're almost certainly
missing something.
Some employee didn't sign
their PIIA or
whatever and you'll find it
now.
It's easy to fix now.
It gets really hard to fix,
like,
in the middle of your next
round of financing.
So, again, this is time to
bring, like,
a little bit of the order to,
to chaos.
FF stock is a special class of
stock for
founders that the founders can
sell in a later round,
without messing up the
common-stock valuation.
It used to be that most people
set this up
right when they started the
company.
Founders fund sort of
popularizes.
Which is why it's called FF
stock.
But it became a really bad
signal, right?
Founders that were obsessed
with their own
personal liquidity when the
company had nothing turned out
to like fail most of the time.
And so investors learn that if
founders pushed on this in
the seed round it was a very,
very bad sign.
Most founders don't actually
want to sell stock until
the company is worth, like a
billion dollars or
something like that.
So, I think you can actually
safely set this up after
things start working, in the
next financial round, and then
you can sell it two, three,
four years down the road.
But it's a good thing to
remember by about the time you
get to the B round.
IP, trademarks and patents.
actually, just IP and
trademarks.
So, you have 12 months,
after you announce something,
if you want to patent it.
And, if you miss that window,
it's very hard to do.