https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yP176MBG9Tk
>> Thanks for having me.
So today I am going to be
talking about how to go
from zero users to many
users.
I'm just assuming that you
have many great ideas in
your head at this moment and
you're kind of thinking
about what the next step is.
So I wrote this up early
this morning,
and a lot of this is based
off of mistakes I've
made in the past.
So as Sam mentioned, I went
through YC in 2010 and
spent a number, three years
basically, going back and
forth pivoting a bunch of
times,
starting over a bunch of
times.
And have learned a lot about
what not to do if I
were to start another
startup after Homejoy if
that should ever happen.
And so a lot of it comes
from failure and
just telling you about what
you shouldn't do and kind of
making generalizations of
what you should do
from that.
So just a reminder that this
is,
sort of, you know, all
advice you should take as
directionally good guidance,
like if all,
like it's, it's kind of in
the right direction.
But every business is
different,
you are different, I'm not
you, and so
just take everything with,
you know, that in mind.
So since this is a college
course, you know,
when you start a startup you
should basically have lots
of time on your hands to
concentrate on the start up.
And I'm not saying you
should you know,
quit school or you should
quit work.
What I'm saying is you
should have a lot of time,
compressed time in a row.
Really dedicated to
immersing yourself in
the idea and developing
problems, or developing
the solutions to the problem
you're trying to solve.
So for example if you're in
school, you know,
it's better to have one or
two days straight of per
week on working on your idea
versus you know, spending
two hours here and there
every single day during the
course of the week.
It's sort of like, I think
this is an engineering class
so it's sort of like coding.
Like there's a lot of
context switching and
just being able to really
focus, really, really focus
and immerse yourself is very
very important.
So, like I said, I sort of
first,
when I wrote this up was
thinking what
are things that some people
do or most people do that is
not the correct way to do a
startup and sort of
the novice approach I think
is what you see up here.
Which is, you know, I have
this really great idea.
I don't wanna tell anyone
about it.
I'm gonna build, build,
build, build.
I'm gonna be telling one or
two people and then I'm
gonna launch it on,
you know, I'm gonna launch
it on TechCrunch or some,
somewhere like that, then
I'm gonna get lots of users.
But what really happens is
because you did not
get a lot of that feedback
and stuff like that,
you know maybe you get a lot
of people to your site,
but no one sticks around
because you didn't get
that initial user feedback.
And then, you know, if you,
you know, if lucky enough
you have some money in
the bank you might go buy
some users but sort of,
it just whittles out over
time and you just give up.
This is sort of a vicious
cycle and
you know, I actually did
this once, and
I did this while I was in
YC,
and that was you know like,
when I went through YC I
didn't even launch a
product,
like I didn't even launch in
TechCrunch which is a thing
you should definitely do.
And so you don't want to
ever get into that
cycle because you'll just
end up with nothing good.
So, the next thing is you
know, you have an idea and
you should really think
about what the idea
is really solving.
Like what is the actual
problem?
And so their problem
statements you should be
able to describe it in one
sentence.
And then you should think,
how does that problem relate
to me?
Am I really passionate about
that problem?
And then you should think,
okay, it's a problem I have,
is it a problem that other
people have?
And sort of verify that by,
you know, just going out and
talking to people.
One of the biggest mistakes
I've made is you know,
we started, my co-founder
and I,
who is also my brother, he
and
I started a company called
Pathjoy in 2009, 2010.
And our goal was basically
to you know,
we had two goals in mind one
is to create a company that
made people really happy,
and create a company that
was very, very impactful, so
a good proxy for
that is to just create a
huge, big company.
And so we thought, okay,
here's sort of what we're
gonna solve is you know,
make people happier, and we
first went to the notion of
who are the people that made
people happy?
And you know,
we came up with life coaches
and therapists.
So it seemed kind of obvious
to
just create a platform for
life coaches and therapists.
And what happened as a
result though was that you
know, when we started using
the product ourselves we,
you know, we're not cynical
people by any means,
but life coaches and
therapists are just not
people we would use
ourselves.
It was sort of useless to
us.
And so, it wasn't even a
problem we had, and
certainly wasn't something
we
were super passionate about
building out.
Yet we spent, you know,
almost a year trying to do
this.
And so, if you just start,
you know,
from tegel zero, just like
think about this before you
even build any product.
I think you can save
yourself a lot of
headache down the road
from doing something you
don't wanna do.
So, say you have a problem
and you're able to state it.
Where do you start?
Like, how do you think of
solutions?
So the first thing you
should do is think of
what the industry that you
are getting yourself into.
Whether it's big, whether
it's huge,
you should really immerse
yourself in that industry.
There's a number of ways to
do this.
One is, you know, to really
become a cog in
that industry for a little
bit.
And so it might seem a
little counter-intuitive to
do this, because most people
say, you know,
if you really wanna disrupt
an industry, you
should really not be this,
you know, player in it.
You should, you know,
someone who spent 20 or
30 years in an industry
probably you know, is set in
their ways and is just used
to the way things work and
really can't think about
what the inefficiencies are
or the things that you can,
quote, unquote, disrupt.
But, however as a noob like
coming into the industry,
you really should take one
or
two months just really
understanding what all
the little bits and pieces
of the industry are, and how
it works because it's when
you get into the details,
that's when you start seeing
things you can exploit.
Things you can really,
things that are really,
really inefficient and
provide you know huge
overhead costs that you can
cut down.
And, so an example of this
is, you know,
when we start Homejoy and
we, we decided to go,
we started with the cleaning
industry and when we
started, you know, we just
were cleaners ourselves.
And we started to clean
houses and
we found out really quickly
was that
we were very bad cleaners.
And so as a result, you
know, we said, okay, we
got to learn more about this
and we went to buy books.
And we bought books about
how to clean,
which helped maybe a little
bit,
we learned a little bit more
about cleaning supplies.
But it's sort of like
basketball you know,
you can watch and you can
learn,
or you can watch and you can
read about basketball, but
you're not gonna get any
better at
it if you don't actually you
know, train and you know,
throw a basketball around
and throw it into the hoop.
And so we decided one of us
basically had to go and
learn how to clean.
And so we went or
get trained by you know, a
professional, some sort of
a professional training
programs that existed.
And that meant, we actually
went to get a job at
a cleaning company itself.
And the cool thing was that
you know, I learned how to
clean from you know,
training for the few weeks
that I was there at the
cleaning company.
But the even better thing
was that I learned a lot
about how a local cleaning
company worked.
And in that sense you know,
I learned why a local
cleaning company could not
become huge like Homejoy is
today and that's because
they have, you know,
they're pretty old school
and
they have a lot of things,
just from anywhere from
booking the customer to
optimizing the cleaner
schedules was just done very
inefficiently.
And so there is, so, if you
are in a situation like mine
where you know, there's a
service element to it,
you should go and do that
service yourself.
You know, if your thing is
related to restaurants you
should become a waiter it's
really to you know,
if it's painting you know
become a painter kind of
get in the shoes of your
customers from all angles of
what you're trying to build.
The other thing is there's
also levels of obsessiveness
that you should have with it
too as well.
You should be so obsessed to
know what everybody in
the space is doing.
And it's things like, you
know,
running a list of all the
potential competitors or
similar types of companies,
Google searching it, and
clicking on every single
link and
reading every single article
from like,
search result 1 to 1,000.
You know, I found all
potential competitors,
big and small, and
if they're public, I would
go read their S1's,
I would go read all their
quarterly financials,
I would, you know, sit on
the earnings calls.
There's, you know, most of
these you don't get much out
of it, but there's just
these golden nuggets that
you'll find once in a while
and you can't,
you won't be able to find
that unless you
actually go through the work
of,
you know, getting all that
information in your head.
So yeah, you should become
an expert in the industry.
There should be no doubt
when you're building this
that you are the expert so
that people will trust you
when you're building this
product.
The second thing is
identifying customer
segments.
So you know, ideally at the
end of the day,
in the end game, you built a
product or
a business that everybody in
the world is using.
But realistically in the
beginning you kind of
want to corner off a certain
part of the customer base so
that you can really optimize
for them, and that's just
you know, it's just about a
matter of focus and a matter
of you know, just catering
towards whether it's
teenage girls or whether
it's you know, soccer moms.
You would just be able to
you know,
like I said focus a lot on
their needs.
And, lastly before before
you even create the product,
before you put code down,
you should really storyboard
out the ideal user
experience of how you're,
how you're gonna solve the
problem.
And that, and that's not
just meaning, you know,
the web site itself, it's
meaning, you know,
how does the customer find
out about you.
You know, whether it's, you
know,
it could be through an ad or
through word of mouth or
whatever, so they find out
about you.
They come to your site, they
learn more about you, what's
all that text say, what are
you communicating to them.
So the actual, when they
sign up for the product or
they purchase the service,
what are they actually
getting,
to after they finish using
the product or
after they finish using the
service.
What's you know, there's
sort of
like an evaluation period,
like they leave a review, or
they leave comments or
whatnot, and just being able
to go through that whole
flow and visualize in your
head, like just envision
what the perfect user
experience is and then put
it down on paper and
then put it into code, and
then start from there.
So you have all these ideas
in your head now,
you kind of know what the
core customer base you
want to go after is.
And you know like everything
about the industry,
what do you do next?
So you start building your
products.
And you know, the common
phrase that most people
use these days is you should
build a minimum viable,
the MVP, minimum viable
product.
And I know I'm viable
because I
think a lot of people skip
that part,
and they just go out with a
feature and then the whole
user experience in the very
beginning like is flat.
So the minimum viable
product pretty much
means you know,
what is the smallest feature
set that you should build
to solve the problem that
you're trying to solve.
And I think if you go
through the whole storyboard
experience, you can kind of
figure that very quickly.
But again you have to be
talking to users right,
potential users, you have to
be
seeing what exists out there
already and what you
should be building to solve
their immediate needs.
And the second thing is,
before you put