https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5_0dVHMpJlo
That they don't know what to
do with it
beyond a certain point.
And so let me
say a few things about how
to build a monopoly.
And, I think one of the sort
of very counter
intuitive ideas that comes
out of this monopoly thread.
Is that you want to go after
small markets.
If you're a startup.
You want to get to monopoly.
You're starting a new
company,
you want to get to monopoly.
Monopolies you have a large
share of a market,
how do you get to a large
share of a market?
You start with a really
small market and
you take over that whole
market, and then.
And then over time you find
ways to expand that market
in concentric circles.
And the thing that's always
a big mistake is going
after a giant market on day
one.
Because that's typically
evidence that you
somehow haven't defined the
categories correctly.
And it normally means that
there is going to be
too much competition.
In one way or another.
And so I think almost all
the successful companies
in Silicon Valley had some
model of
starting with small markets
and expanding.
And if you take Amazon, you
start with.
Just a bookstore.
We have all the books in the
world.
So it's a better bookstore
than anybody else
has in the world.
When it's starts in the
90's, it's online,
there's things you can do
you can't do before.
And then you gradually
expand into all sorts of
different forms of
e-commerce and
other things beyond that.
You know, eBay you start
with Pez dispensers.
You move on to Beanie Babies
and
eventually it's all these
different auctions for
all these sorts of different
goods.
And what was very counter
intuitive about many of
these companies is they
often start with
markets that are so small
that people don't think
that they're valuable at all
when you get started.
The PayPal version of this
was, we started with
power sellers on eBay which
was about 20,000 people.
When we first saw this
happening in December of 99,
January of 2000 right after
we launched,
there was a sense that these
were all,
it was such a small market
it was terrible.
We thought these were
terrible customers to have.
It's just people selling
junk on the internet.
Why in the world do we want
to
be going after this market?
But, you know, there was a
way to get a product that
was much better for
everybody in that market.
You could, and we got to
something like 25, 30%,
you know, market penetration
in two or three months.
And you got some walk in.
You got brand recognition
and
your able to build the
business from there.
So I always think these,
these very small markets are
quite underrated.
The Facebook version of this
I always give is that you
know if the initial market
of
Facebook was 10,000 people
at Harvard, it went from
zero to sixty percent market
share in ten days.
That was a very auspicious
start.
The way this gets analyzed
in business schools is
always, that's ridiculous,
it's such a small market it
can't have any value at all.
And so, I think the business
school analysis of
Facebook early on, or of
PayPal early on, or
of eBay early on is that the
markets were perhaps, so
small as to have, almost no
value.
And they, they would have
had little value had
they stayed small, but it
turned out they were ways to
grow them concentrically
and, that's what made them,
that's what made them so
valuable.
Now I think the opposite
version of this,
is always where you have
super big markets.
And, and I, there's so much,
so many different things
that went wrong with all
the clean tech companies in
the last decade.
But, but, one,
one theme that ran through
almost all of them,
was that they all started
with massive markets.
And every clean tech
PowerPoint presentation that
one saw in the years 2005 to
2008,
which was the clean tech
bubble in Silicon Valley.
Started with, we're in the
energy market,
we're in a market that's
measured in hundreds of
billions of trillions of
dollars.
And then once you're a
minnow in a vast ocean.
That's not a good place to
be.
That means that you have
tons of competitors and
you don't even know who all
the competitors are.
And so you want to be a one
of a kind company,
where it's the only one in a
small ecosystem.
You don't want to
be the fourth online pet
food company.
You don't want to be
the tenth thin film solar
panel company.
You don't want to be the
100th restaurant in
Palo Alto.
Your restaurant industry is
a trillion dollar industry,
so if you do a market size
analysis you conclude
restaurants are a fantastic
business to go into, and
it's often, large markets,
large existing markets
typically mean that you have
tons of competition, very,
very hard to differentiate.
So the first very
counterintuitive into a idea
is to go after small
markets, often markets that
are so small people don't
even notice them.
They don't think that they
make sense.
That's where you got a
foothold, and
then if those markets are
able to expand,
you can scale into a big
monopoly business.
You know, a second sort of,
the sort of several
different characteristics of
these monopoly businesses,
that I like to focus on.
There's probably no sort of
single formula to it.
I also ways think that that
in technology there
is always a sense that you
know,
the history of technology is
such that every.
Every moment happens only
once, so you know the next
Mark Zuckerberg won't build
a social network.
The next Larry Page won't be
building a search engine.
The next Bill Gates won't be
building an operating
system.
And if you're copying these
people,
you're not learning from
them.
But it's, and so,
there is always these very
unique businesses that
are doing something that's
not been done before,
end up, end of having the
potential to be a monopoly.
The opening line in Anna
Karenina that all
happy companies, sorry, all
happy families.
All happy families are
alike.
All unhappy families are
unhappy in
their own special way.
And the opposite is true in
business,
where I think all happy
companies are different
because they're doing
something very unique.
All unhappy companies are
alike because they fail to
escape the essential
sameness that
is competition, and so
one sort of characteristic
of a monopoly technology
company is some sort of
proprietary technology.
My sort of crazy, somewhat
arbitrary,
rule of thumb is you want to
have a technology that's
an order of magnitude better
than the next best thing.
So Amazon had over ten times
as many books,
maybe not that high tech,
but you figure out a way to
sell ten times as many books
in an efficient online way.
You know, PayPal, the
alternative for
PayPal was using checks to
send money on eBay,
took seven to ten days to
clear.
PayPal could do it more than
ten times as fast.
So you wanna have some sort
of very
powerful improvement in some
order, maybe an order of
magnitude improvement on
some key dimension.
Of course, you know,
if you actually come with
something totally new it's,
it's just, it's just like an
infinite improvement.
So I would say the,
the iPhone was the first
smartphone that worked and
so that's, you know that's
like I mean,
I mean maybe not infinite,
but
it's sort of definitely
order of magnitude or
more of improvement.
So I think, the, the
technology is designed to
give you a massive delta
over, over the next,
the next best thing.
I think, I think there often
are network effects that
can kick in that, really
help.
The thing that's very, and
these,
these lead to monopolies
over time,
the thing that's very tricky
about network effects is,
they're often.
They're often very hard to
get started.
So even though everyone
understands how
valuable they are, there is
always this incredibly
tricky question why is it
valuable to the first person
who is doing something?
Economies of scale, if you
have something of
a very high fixed costs,
very low marginal cost.
That's typically a monopoly
like business.
And then there's this thing
of branding.
Which is sort of like this
idea that gets lodged in
people's brains.
I never quite understand how
branding works, so I never
invest in companies where
it's just about branding.
But it is, I think,
a real phenomenon that
creates real value.
I think one of the things,
I'm gonna come back to
this a little bit, towards
the end.
But one of the things that's
very striking,
is that software businesses
are often, are, for
some reason, very good at
some of these things.
They're especially good at
the economies of scale part.
Because, the marginal cost
of software is zero.
And so if you get something
that works in software.
It's often significantly
better
than the existing solution.
And then you have these
tremendous economies of
scale, and you can scale
fairly quickly.
So even if the market starts
small,
you can grow your business
quickly enough to stay at
the same size as the growing
market.
And maintain the sort of
monopoly power.
Now, the critical thing
about these monopolies is,
it's not enough to have a
monopoly for just a moment.
The critical thing is to
have one that lasts over
time.
And so in Silicon Valley
there's always this idea
that you wanna be the first
mover.
And I, I always think it's,
it's, in some ways,
the better framing is you
wanna be the last mover, or
you wanna be the last
company in a category.
Those are the ones that are
really valid.
Microsoft was the last
operating system,
at least for many decades.
Google is the last search
engine.
Facebook will be valuable if
it turns out to be the last,
social networking site.
One way to think of
this last mover of value is
this idea that most of
the value in these companies
exists far in the future.
If you do a discounted cash
flow analysis of a business.
You look at, you have sort
of all these profit streams.
You have a growth rate.
The growth rate's much
higher than
the discount rate.
And so most of the value
exists far in the future.
I did this exercise At
PayPal in March of 2001.
We'd been in business for
about 27 months.
And we sort of had, the
growth rate was 100% a year.
We were discounting future
cashflows by about 30%.
And it turned out that about
three quarters of
the value of the business,
as of 2001,
came from cash flows in
years 2011 and beyond.
And whenever you do the math
on any of these tech
companies, you get an answer
that's something like that.
So if you are trying to
analyze any other
tech companies in Silicon
Valley, Arabian B, Twitter.
Facebook, any emerging
internet companies,
any of the ones in
Y-Combinator.
The math tells you that
three quarters, 80,
85% of the value is coming
from cash flows in
years 2024 and beyond.
It's very, very far in the
future.
And, so one of the things
that we always overvalue in
Silicon Valley is growth
rates, and
we undervalue durability.
Because, growth is something
you can measure in the here
and now, and you can always
track that very precisely.
The question of whether a
company's still gonna be
around a decade from now.
That's actually what,
what dominates the value
equation and
that sort of is a much more
qualitative sort of a thing.
And so if we, if we went
back to this idea of these
characteristics of monopoly,
proprietary technology,
network effects, economies
of scale, You can think
of these characteristics as
ones that exist at a moment
in time when you capture a
market and take it over.
But you also want to think
about,
are these things going to
last over time.
And, so, there's a time
dimension to all these
characteristics.
So, net worth effects also
have a great time element,
where as the network scales
the network
effects actually get more
robust, and so
if you have a network effect
business that's often one
that can become a bigger and
stronger monopoly over time.
Proprietary technology is
always a little bit of
a tricky one, so
you want something that's
order magnitude better.
Than, the state of the art
in the world today.
And that's how you get
people's attention.
That's how you initially
break through.
But then, you don't wanna be
superseded by somebody else.
And so there are all these
areas of innovation where,