https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n_yHZ_vKjno
How many of those convert to
my site?
How many of those then
import?
To get an idea of your k
factor.
But the really,
important thing is still to
think about retention, and
not to think about virality.
And only do this after you
have a large
number of people retained on
your product per person
who signs up.
So, couple more things we
were gonna touch on.
SEO, email, SMS and push
notifications.
So, in SEO,
there are three things you
need to think about.
First one is keyword
research.
People do this badly all the
time.
So I launched this cocktail
site that I
talked to you about.
I spent a year optimizing it
to rank for
the word cocktail making.
Turns out in the UK no one
searches for
cocktail making.
About 500 people a month.
I dominated that search
term.
It was awesome.
>> I got 400 visitors a
month.
It was amazing.
Everyone searches for
cocktail recipes In the UK.
And in the US, which is the
biggest market,
everyone searches for drink
recipes.
So I optimize for the wrong
word.
So you've gotta do
your research first about
what you're gonna go after.
So, research consists of
what do people search for
that's related to your
sites, how many people
search for it, how many
other people are ranking for
it, and how valuable is it
for you.
Supply, demands and value.
Simple economics I guess.
So you do your keyword
research.
You figure out which
keywords you
want to rank for.
There are great tools out
there to
enable you to do that.
Honestly the best is quite
often the Google AdWords,
keyword planner tool.
Really.
Once you've done, that
the next most important
thing is links.
So, page rank is how all of
SEO is essentially,
is driven and Google is
based on authority.
Now there's a lot of other
things in Google's
algorithm now like do people
search for your website?
There's a lot stuff about
the distribution of what
the anchor text is.
That's send to your site.
So, if you abuse it and
spam it they can pop up with
spam.
White on a white background
five pages below the fold
doesn't work anymore.
But, the single most
important thing is to
get valuable links from
high authority websites
future ranking Google.
Most important thing.
Then you need to distribute
that log inside your site,
by internally linking
effectively.
And when I joined Facebook.
We'd launched SEO in
September 2007,
which was before I joined.
I joined November 2007.
And we'd launched it, and we
were getting no traffic from
the pages we'd launched,
public user profiles.
So, when I went in and
looked at it.
The only way you could get
to any public user
profile was to click on the
footer of the page, for
the about link.
Then click on one of the
blog articles,
then click on one of the
authors, and then spider out
through their friends to get
to all their friends.
Turns out that,
Google was like they buried
these papers,
they're not very valuable,
and
we're not going to rank
them.
We made one change.
We added a directory so that
Google could quickly get to
every page on the site.
And we 100 xd SEO traffic.
Very, very simple change
drove a lot of
upside about distributing
the link love internally.
And then the last thing is
there's a bunch of
table stakes stuff, HML
sitemaps,
making sure you have the
right headers, it's all
covered really well online
for what you wanna do.
I'm gonna stop now and make
sure, cuz we have
a few questions, but, what
other questions are there?
Go for it.
>> We're going to email
actually,.
>> Let's go into email.
Okay great.
Email is dead for people
under 25 in my opinion.
Right?
Young people don't
use email.
They use WhatsApp, they use
SMS,
they use Snapchat, they use
Facebook.
They don't use email.
If you're targeting an older
audience, email is,
pretty successful.
Email still works for
distribution, but
realistically, email is not
that great for
teenagers, especially, and
even people at university.
You know, how much you use
instant messaging apps and
how little you use email.
And you guys are probably,
on the high end of the scale
for email,
because you're in Silicon
Valley.
That being said, on email
the things to think about.
Email, SMS, and
push notifications all
behave the same way.
They all have questions of
deliverability.
So to finish first, first
you have to finish.
Your email has to get to
someones inbox.
So if you send a lot of spam
and
you end up with dirty IP's,
or you send spam from
shared servers where other
people are.
Or if you send email
notifications, from shared
servers where other people
are sending spam from,
you are gonna end up being
put in the spam folder
consistently, and your email
will fail completely.
You may end up, being
blocked and
have your email bounce.
There's a lot of
stuff around email where you
have to look.
When you receive feedback
from the servers you
are sending email too.
500 series errors versus 400
series errors,
you have to be respectful of
how those are handled.
If someone gives you a hard
bounce, retry once or
twice and, then stop trying.
Because if you are someone
who abuses people's inboxes,
the email companies spam
folder you and
it's very hard to get out.
If you get caught, on a
Spamhaus link, or
anything like that, it's
very hard to get out.
It's really important with
email,
that you are a high-class
citizen,
that you do good work with
email because you want to
have deliverability for the
long run.
That counts for push
notifications and SMS2.
With SMS, you can go and buy
SMS traffic, via gray routes
with people with their
having phones strung up.
Attached to a like computer
and pumping out SMS's.
That works for a time but it
always get shut down.
And I've seen so
many companies make these
mistakes.
Where they think they're
gonna grow
by using these kind of
tactics.
If you can't get your email,
your SMS or
your push delivered.
You will never get any
success from these.
Push, you spam your power
users, I know
that's slightly different to
what I said earlier.
But you actually, spam your
power users and
give them notifications that
they don't care about and
make it really hard for them
to opt out.
So, there's no settings
where they can opt out,
and they start blocking you.
You can never push them
once,
they've opted out of your
push notifications.
And it's very hard actually,
to prompt them to
turn them on once they've
turned them off.
So, number one thing to
think about about email,
SMS, and
push notification is you
have to get them delivered.
Beyond that,
it's a question of open
rate, click through rate.
So, what is the compelling
subject line you
can put there.
So, that people are gonna
open your email.
And how can you get them to
click when they visit?
Everyone focuses towards
doing,
marketing email that are
just spam.
In my opinion Newsletters
are stupid.
Don't do newsletters,
because you'll
send the same message to
everyone on your site.
Someone, who signed up
to your site yesterday
versus someone,
who's been using your
product for three years.
Do they need the same
message?
No.
The most effective email you
can do is notifications.
So, what are you sending?
What should you be notifying
people of?
And this is a great place
where we're in
the wrong mindset.
As a Facebook user I don't
want Facebook to email me
about every like I receive,
because I receive a lot of
likes cuz I've got a bunch
of Facebook friends.
But as a new Facebook user,
that first like you receive
is a magic moment.
Turning on that notification
across all of
of our channels, increased
the click through rate
on our email, SMS and
push-notifications.
But we only turned it on,
for low-engaged users who
weren't coming back to the
site so
it wouldn't be spamming
them.
So, it was a great
experience.
To think about that.
What notifications should we
be sending
is the first thing you need
to think about on email,
SMS, and push.
And then the second thing
you need to
be thinking about is.
How can you create great
triggered marketing
campaigns?
So, when someone creates
their first,
cross border trade
transaction was one of
the best email campaigns, I
was ever part of at eBay in
terms of click-through
rates.
It was awesome.
Because it was really
timely,
really in context the right
thing to do for the user.
So I'd say, make sure you
have deliverability.
Most important thing.
Focus on notifications and
trigger based email,
SMS, and push notifications
beyond that.
So, I think we're out of
time.
There's one thing I wanted
to finish with which is.
And if you guys have any
questions, I guess, like,
you can reach me and
if I get spammed, I just
won't reply.
We have great spam filters,
no, my only favorite quotes
is from General Patton,
and it's so cliche it's
crazy but it's awesome.
A good plan, violently
executed today is
better than a perfect plan
tomorrow and
one of the things the most
instilled in us.
And Harvey still instills in
us and Mark instills across
the whole of Facebook is
this move fast and
don't be afraid to break
stuff ethos.
If you can run more
experiments than
the next guy, if you can be
hungry for growth.
If you fight and die for
every extra user.
And you stay up late at
night to get those extra
users to run those
experiments to
get the data and do it over
and over and over again.
You will grow faster.
Marcus said he thinks we won
'cause we wanted it more,
and I really believe that.
We just worked really hard.
It's not like we're crazy
smart, or
we've all done these crazy
things before.
We just worked really,
really hard,
and we executed fast.
And I strongly encourage you
to do that.
Growth is optional.
Thank you.