https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sz_LgBAGYyo
back end services is as easy
as sort of dragging up and
down, different sort of nobs
and levers.
It's gonna be beautifully
used, and
it looks fairly easy to
scale.
Since we're in a room full
of computer science people,
I think you'll appreciate
this.
This is Chocolat.
This is a code editor, and
they only have one call to
action.
When the time limit is up,
they say, everything in
terms of all the pieces are
exactly the same except we
change the font.
To comic sans.
And what they're basically
saying is like hey
we know who our users are,
who our real customers are.
They're gonna be the people
who care about this.
This is Hurl, this is a
website for
checking htp requests, and
sometimes the places where
you get errors are
opportunities for
first moments,
you had a four of four this
is what you get it,
when we need help oftentimes
what we do is where we
create like really beautiful
mark, marketing materials.
But when you actually need,
like, documentation we sort
of like skimp out on sort of
design features.
And this is a point that,
like,
you see happen over and over
again.
A company that gets this
right is MailChimp.
And what they did was they
redesigned all of their
help guides so that they
looked like magazine covers.
And overnight, basically,
readership goes up on all
these features.
And customer support for
these things that sort of
help people optimize emails
goes down.
Speaking of documentation,
stripe.
What's interesting about an
API company is that there is
no UX.
The UX is actually just
documentation, right?
And there's opportunities
even in documentation.
Sort of the enchant and
amaze.
So one of the things that I
love about them is their
examples are wonderful.
But if you're actually,
like,
sort of logging into the
app,
one of the things that is a
super pain for most people,
when you're dealing with
most people's APIs, is,
like, grabbing your API
credentials and keys.
And what Stripe does is it
says oh,
if you're logged into the
app.
We automatically put
your API credentials into
the examples, so you only
have to copy paste once when
trying to learn their API.
When Wufoo wanted to launch
the third version of our API
we realized like, Okay, that
finally this is good enough
that we want people to sort
of build on top of it.
We were trying to figure
out,
like, how do we launch this
out to the world,
that sort of has our
personality behind it.
Because a lot of people,
they usually do things like
a programming API contest,
and they give out iPads and
iPhones.
And it makes you look like
everyone else.
And so, in our company one
weird value to
have it's a quirk of us,
is that the co-founders are
big medieval nuts.
And we take everyone out to
Medieval Times every single
year, on the anniversary of
the founding of the company.
And so, we said we have to
do something in that flavor.
And so we contacted the guys
at armor.com,
we said can you forward us a
custom battle-ax.
And what we said was if
you win our programming
contest you would win one.
The result is like people
wanted to talk about this.
It's something that people
wanted to work on cuz
they wanted to be able to
say it like I'm programming.
For a weapon.
And what's cool is we had
over 25 different
applications created for us
of quality and quantity that
we could not have paid for
on the budget and
the sort of time that we had
for this.
We got things like an iPhone
app and
Android and WordPress
plugins, right?
And all because what we did
was we changed how
people wanna talk about the
origin story of
how they're interacting with
one of our services.
And go like all day long of
going over these examples.
But I'm gonna short cut this
by saying,
you should just subscribe a
little bit of details.
It's just basically tons of
screen shots of software
that's just doing it right.
That shows that they're
being
conscientious of the user
and the customers.
When it comes to long term
relationships or
marriages, the only research
that we ended up having to
read was the stuff that was
done by John Gottman.
He's been featured in This
American Life,
in Malcolm Gladwell's books.
He's a marriage researcher
up in Seattle.
And he has an interesting
parlor trick that he can do.
He can watch a video tape of
a couple fighting about some
issue for 15 minutes.
And predict with an 85%
accuracy rate whether that
couple will be together or
not, or divorced in four
years.
If he increases that video
up to an hour.
And asks them to also talk
about their hopes and
dreams.
That prediction rating goes
up to 94%.
They showed these same video
tapes to marriage
counselors, successfully
married couples,
sociologists, psychiatrists,
priests, et cetera and
they can't predict with
random chance whether people
are gonna be together or
not.
So John Gauntman understands
something fundamental about.
How relationships work in
the long term.
And that basically how we
fight, even in a short term
period can indicate sort of
the whole system and
what it's gonna look like.
And one of the surprising
things he discovered,
it's not that
successfully married people
don't fight at all.
It turns out everybody
fights.
And we all fight about the
exact same things money,
kids, sex, time and others.
And others are things like
jealousy and in-laws.
To bring this around, right,
you can actually attribute
every single one of these to
problems that you see in
customer support when you're
building out your products.
Right, so.
This costs too much.
I'm having problems with a
credit card.
If you're building a service
that helps people deal with
their clients they're very
sensitive about anything
happening with that.
Performance.
How long you're up and how
fast.
Others are I said jealousy
and in-laws.
Right, so that's competition
and partnerships.
So anything weird happening
there,
people are gonna write to
you about.
And the reason I like to
think about this in
terms of customer support is
that in every ones that
are processing of like a
conversion funnel,
customer support is the
thing that happens in
between every one of these
steps.
It's the reason why people
don't make it
further down there.
It's the thing that prevents
conversion from happening.
Now, as we were thinking
through all these ideas and
as we were building up the
company,
we realized that there's a
big problem about how
everyone sort of starts
their company or
build up their sort of
engineering teams.
And that is that there's a
broken feedback loop there.
People are divorced from the
consequences of
their actions.
And this is the result of
actually the natural
evolution of how most
companies get founded,
especially by technical
co-founders, right.
Before launch it is a time
of bliss, nirvana, and
opportunity, right?
Nothing that you do is
wrong, right?
By your hand, which you feel
is like god, everything that
you write, every line of
code feels perfect, right,
and is ingenious to you.
The thing that happens is
after launch reality sort of
sets in and then all these
other tasks sort of
come into place that we have
to deal with.
Now what technical
co-founders wanna do is get
back to that initial state
and so what we often do,
and what we often see is
that companies start
siloing off all these other
things that actually is
what makes a start up or a
company sort of real, right?
And have other people do
them.
To, in our minds, these
other tasks are inferior.
Right?
And we have other people in
the company do them.
And so for us, what we're
trying to figure out
is how do we change software
development so that we
inject some values that we
don't talk about enough?
Responsibility,
accountability,
humility, modesty.
Right, and we called this,
like a lot of other people,
we had an acronym, Support
Driven Development, and
it's very similar to TDD or
other agile practice.
It's a way of creating high
quality software, but
it's super simple.
You don't need like, a
SCRUM,
you don't need a bunch of
post-it notes, all you
have to do is make everyone
do customer support.
And what you end up having
is
you fix the feedback loop,
right?
The people who build the
software are the ones
supporting it and
you get all these sort of
nice benefits as a result.
So one of them is, support
responsible developers and
designers and people who
build the stuff,
they give the very best
support.
Now we're not the first
person to think of this.
Paul English was a big
proporter of this at Kayak,
and what he did was install
a red customer support phone
line in the middle of the
engineering floor.
And they were just regular
customer support calls.
And people would ask him
often times,
why would you pay engineers
$120,000 or
more to do something that
you can pay other people
a fraction of to handle in
like a call center?
And he says, well, after the
second or
third time that phone rings
and the engineer gets
the same problem they stop
what they're doing, they fix
the bug, and we stop getting
phone calls about it.
It, it's a way of having Q-A
in a sort of
nice elegant solution.
Now, John Gotman talks about
the reason that we often
break up with one another as
due to four major causes and
their warning signs.
He calls them the four
horsemen, right?
Criticism, contempt,
defensiveness,
and stonewalling.
Now, criticism is basically
people starting to focus,
not just on the specific
issue at hand, but
on the overarching issues.
Like, you never, right,
listen to your users or
you never think about us all
the time.
Right?
Contempt is when someone is
purposely trying to
insult somebody.
Defensiveness is not trying
to take accountability
trying to make excuses for
the actions.
And stonewalling is
basically shutting down.
Stonewalling, to John
Gotman, is, is one of
the worst things that we can
do in a relationship.
Hold up.
And oftentimes, you know, we
don't worry much about this
in customer se, criticism
and contempt.
Right?
Defensiveness,
you see this all the time,
all the times in companies,
especially as they get
older.
But stonewalling, this is
something I
see happen with start-ups
all the time.
You get a bunch of customer
support sort of
coming in and you just think
I don't need to answer it.
I don't need to respond.
Right?
And
that act of just not even
getting back to
them is one of the worst
things you can do.
And it's probably some of
the biggest causes of
churn in the early stages of
start-ups.
This is how support worked
out with Wufoo.
When we were acquired we had
about 500,000 users on
the system, 5 million people
used Wufoo forms and
reports, whether they knew
it or not, and
all those people got support
from the same ten people,
and usually it was