https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sz_LgBAGYyo
It's like some times the
people that work for
you, they have a strong
opinion about where it,
where it should go.
And it's a good way to sort
of democratize it
a little bit, by rotating it
around.
Yes.
>> You said you guys all
work from home.
Usually seems like a
nightmare.
In that office, how do you
make that work?
>> Okay, so we all work from
home.
So, I will tell you this.
We all still work within the
Tampa Bay area.
We would allow anybody to
work from any where but
usually.
As we tried to recruit
them,they sort of
meet our team, and they just
decide,
okay we just want to come
and move here anyway.
Remote working, is
especially tricky,
a lot of people like to
romanticize it,
especially people, who are
like employees.
But the thing is, An office
gives you a lot of, sort of,
benefits, right, and
efficiencies that you now
have to compensate for when
you remote working.
But remote working also has
these other sort of
efficiencies in place, for
example,
I don't have to worry about
my employees losing two
hours of their day to
commuting, for instance.
So the biggest thing that we
had to do for
remote working is to respect
people's time.
And so the way we had it set
up is we actually had
a four and a half day work
week at Wufoo.
Half day on Friday was for
all the meetings and stuff.
We said like no business
deal,
meetings, no talking with
other outside parties.
They all have to be done on
Friday, on that half day.
It couldn't be done in the
middle of the week.
And then also one day of
everyone was
already dedicated customer
support.
So everyone in our company
effectively only had
three days each week to
actually build or
work on whatever they were
doing.
But I actually firmly
believe that if you
have three solid days,
right, eight to ten hours,
where you are only working
on what you need to build,
you can get a ton of shit
done.
And so what we said was,
you have to respect
everyone's time during that
three day period, if they're
in that three day period.
And what we came up with is
a 15 minute rule and the way
it worked is you can have a
discussion like a chat or
a phone call or whatever
with someone but it could go
no longer than 15 minutes so
if you have some complicated
issue that you couldn't
figure out we'd say,
at 15 minutes you are to
immediately table that item.
Right and have us discuss it
on Friday and
you'd move on to the next
item on your list right,
the enhanced productivity.
More often than not I, I
would say 90% of the time
the item never got brought
up on Friday because usually
what would happen is people
would sleep on it and then
they'd just magically say
like, hey I found a solution
or like hey that's not a big
problem whatsoever.
Because most problems inside
of companies,
they don't need to be solved
in real time, or right away.
The only things are like
when the site is down, or
payments aren't working.
Right?
Everything outside of
that is basically kind of
luxury, so
focus on your primaries as
much as possible.
And, as a result,
our ten person team did far
more than many,
many other companies, as a
result.
But, it takes extra work to
make remote working happen.
We are an extremely
disciplined sort of team.
And I would have to say
there's almost not many YC
companies that actually have
been able to replicate sort
of what we do.
I think there's only two
other companies in YC that
sort of have the same sort
of discipline working style.
It takes more work in a very
different fashion.
Right?
An office allows you to be a
little bit lazier, right,
in terms of all these things
around productivity.
Okay.
Over here.
>> Right.
Just to go off that question
as the leader of the team
how did you manage to
instill a company culture
but and also the count,
accountability the employees
especially cuz.
Working space.
>> Okay, how do we, how do
we set up accountability for
employees?
As, as a manager.
Alright, so, at Wufoo we
were profitable nine months
after launch, so, we had
profit sharing, right?
And so, it makes pretty
simple and clear.
It, it would be a multiple
of whatever bonus pull that
we sort of had, and
the performance measures
would be based on sort of,
how they did in customer
support.
All right, on their duties
there, and sort of
what they said they were
wanting to accomplish or do.
I don't like process, and I
don't like lots of
tools to help get people to
be productive.
So the only thing that we
had for
helping people manage, like,
sort of their projects, is
to-do lists.
And that is, like, simple
text files that we
shared in our Dropbox
account.
Each person had their name
on it, and you got to
see every time somebody
updated their to-do list.
What we said is every single
night just
set everything that you did
that day.
Right?
And then on Friday,
we would just go over.
Okay, this is what you
said last week that you're
gonna do.
This is what you actually
got done, or
the sort of the problems at
hand.
And it's super simple,
right?
It creates this like nice
written trail for
how to sort of handle stuff,
right?
And I don't have to worry
about managing them, right?
They sorta set the tone for
how they want to be sort of
assessed.
And it makes it really
simple.
And for people who are
excellent at what they do.
Right?
It works very, very well.
And then when you actually
have problems,
it's very easy to fire
people.
I was fortunate that I
never had to fire anyone at
Wufoo, right?
But we were able to correct
a lot of
people's behavior very, very
quickly.
Cuz we just kinda look at
this, and
it's like look, this is your
pattern of behavior.
You finish a fraction of the
items on your list.
You do most of
the items at the last second
right before Friday.
That's a problem, you've
gotta manage your time
better and this is evidence
that you've provided to us.
All we have to do is sort of
describe it back to you and
because everyone in the
company sort of sees it,
right, there's social
pressure that's put
into place that helps make
it all sort of happen.
Right here.
>> How did you hire people
that, you know,
you felt would be able to
work with in this kind of
environment that's, that's
>> So,
how do you hire people that
can work, remotely?
And then sort of work in
this sort of fashion.
So, pretty easily,
you have them work on a side
project for you.
So you contract them out,
and
they have to work remotely.
As such, usually, the
projects I like to
have them work on is about a
month long, right?
I could do things much
faster for a week.
But usually get a good sense
of,
like, how well people sort
of manage themselves, and
work on things from a
project like that.
So that was always the first
assessment.
Like we never did anything
just by interviews.
The other thing we had to,
sort of, screen them for
is their ability to do
customer support.
Because not any,
every engineer sort of has
the empathy skills to
handle that stress.
So sometimes I would have
people write breakup letters
to me, right, in an
interview, just like hey,
pretend you have to break up
with me you have 15 minutes
to write in on there and you
can only write it by hand,
what are you gonna say?
And so you get a good sense
of sort of their writing
skills, because like 90% of
what you do in customer
support is tell them bad
news, like, oh, we don't
support that feature, sorry
that's not gonna work, or.
It's not gonna be available.
And so people have to have
sort of tacked at that.
>> How 'bout one more
question?
>> One question, right here
the glasses.
>> So, since Wiki has all
these like tricks and
experiments that have really
helped the company.
Do you INAUDIBLE] of ones
that didn't work out?
>> Have all these tricks and
experiments to help the
company,
are there any ones that
didn't work out?
All right, I'll talk about
one.
So one of the things that we
did early on to try to
motivate ourselves was try
to get,
like we understood this idea
of like crunch mode and
that it's really bad for
people.
Like if you're doing the
subscription business you
need people to last for the
long term, and
video games a lot of times
they like crunch people.
All, all the time.
For like a specific deadline
or
have multiple sprints every
two weeks and
you have to shoot up to this
deadline and
it's like exhausting.
And so, because, when it's
happening it's like you
might get an increase in
productivity but
the recovery period that you
need for people is
always greater, right, than
the productivity you gain.
And at a company where you
need everyone doing customer
support and
being on their game and
constantly put, pushed out
features you don't have time
for recovery.
So, we were thinking about,
okay, we want to build like,
a company vacation into how
Wufoo sort of works to
reward our users every
single year.
And we said okay,
if the vacation is sort of
built in there for
the recovery, we could have
one crunch period, right,
before that vacation set up.
And we'll just only do
customer support that will
just sort of scale with
people.
So.
The way we did the very
first crunch mode
is that it was just between
the three founders.
And we had each of us draw a
ten-item to-do list.
That would be fairly
aggressive.
And the first person to
get through seven of their
items would win.
And the the last person to
get through seven of their
items.
Would become what we called
trippage.
And trippage meant that you
carried other
person's luggage and got
people drinks when you're on
the company vacation.
So we did that and during
that period,
everyone was like pretty
excited about it and
motivated, and only the
winner got to
choose the next company
vacation the following year.
And then all the sudden Ryan
had basically poorly
estimated the items on his
list.
And he realized very quickly
I'm going to fucking lose.
And so he was just like I
give up.
And he just sort of stopped.
So crunch mode turned out to
be blah mode for
him because he knew he was
gonna lose and
became pretty demoralized.
So as a result of doing
that, we
decided not to do it in that
similar fashion anymore.
So, good idea that we like
to talk about.
But is one that we, we never
did again.
All right, guys.
Thanks a lot.
You can email me at kevin@