https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQOC-qy-GDY
just have an email exchange,
right?
Because it's very easy for
them to like forget about
it, ignore it.
So you wanna like, actually
try to get in contact with
them, set up a meeting.
Okay.
So, then
the next step is actually
pitch them.
What I usually do is
actually write out all
my new, like the story that
I would want to see
published like in bullet
points.
And I like, will write out
the story,
like my ideal story and I
will memorize it.
Like the entire like set of
bullet points and when I
have a conversation with
them, if it's in person,
I'll like walk them through
this, like I'll have
a conversation that's like
structured like my outline.
And they'll be like taking
notes, right?
And then they'll go and
transcribe those notes into
a story.
And so it's like a tell it,
like what I wrote will
eventually be translated
into a actual story.
And, you know, by preparing
you can actually you know,
much more easily control the
conversation and
not forget critical things
like, you know,
your co-founder, mentioning
your co-founder's name.
Or like,
what all the features in
your awesome app are.
If it's, I'm doing this on
the phone, I will like,
have this bullet points in
front of me and
I will make sure to like
walk through
a conversation that includes
all of those things.
So, you know, you do that,
they,
you have a pitch, they, they
take notes.
They're gonna write the
story of this time.
And then, the next thing is
like, follow up,
like a couple days, or day
before your actual news goes
out, you want to send them
an email that says, like.
You know, this is the time
we're launching the app.
Like, thanks for meeting,
here's like collateral like
maybe if you have like a
video or photos or
something you want them to
include screen shots.
Like how to spell your
co-founders' names and
your name.
Just like include all the
information that I
really care about and I bold
it right?
And then that's it.
Then hopefully the day comes
you press submit on
the release to the app store
and
at the same time they
release their article on
TechCrunch and you are
famous.
Okay, so a lot of people ask
us about PR firms.
so.
You know, I think in the
beginning.
It's kind of like everything
else you do at a start,
you want to do it
yourself before you hire
someone else to do it.
And it's actually pretty
easy,
especially with tech press
who,
you know, and bloggers who,
like, constantly need new
things to write about.
You know.
I strongly encourage people
to, like,
try it themselves and kind
of get started by learning
the process themselves
before they hire anyone.
One thing I'll say is that
like firms can,
can only help you with like
kind of the contacts and
the logistics, but it can't
help you
know what's interesting
about your company or very,
you know, I've never had
anyone whose been able to
tell me what the stories
that I'm producing are.
They've only been able to
tell me,
you know, like you're you
know, like here's a the,
here's a list of reporters
that you might wanna contact
So, you know, you really
have to be responsible for
thinking about like,
what's interesting about
your company and
what are you doing, you
know, what's the road map of
interesting things that
you're working on.
They're also really
expensive.
You know, I think we were
spending between $5,000 and
$20,000 a month which is
like a very, for
various firms that's a lot
for a start up, right?
You should, it's generally.
Not a good use of money, I
would say.
Especially in the very early
days.
You know, getting press is,
is a lot of work.
So you should really make
sure it's worth it.
You know, like I said it
really,
getting press doesn't mean,
it feels like,
it's like a vanity metric.
Right?
It feels like you're being
successful because lots of
succesful companies.
You know, like Google and
Facebook, are covered in the
press all the time.
But it doesn't actually mean
you're successful.
It doesn't, you know,
actually give you, you know,
mean that you're getting,
you're making money,
you're getting users, you're
making those users happy.
it's, you know,
sometimes it's a really good
strategy for
getting your first 100, or
200, or 1,000 customers.
But it's really not a
scalable user acquisition
strategy, so it's something
that's really just like a,
you know, a boot strap.
You can't, like,
just get, like, infinity
articles written about you.
Like, eventually people are
going to,
like, get tired of hearing
about your company, and
usually that happens pretty,
pretty quickly, right.
The whole point about news
is that it's new, and so
it's, it's pretty, pretty,
pretty hard, unless your
Google, to get covered in
the press like every week,
you know, with something.
to, you know, if you decide
it's worth it though,
like you do wanna have like
a regular heartbeat of news.
So that's like something
where, you know,
you're planning out those
types of the, what,
your thing about what your
doing, that matches those,
you know, maybe seven story
types in the future like,
you know, when I was You
know, working primarily on
marketing and, and PR, it
would be, I would like,
make a schedule on like a
calendar.
Have what, when we're gonna
launch things and like,
make sure to space them out,
but like have them,
you know, appear regular, at
regular intervals so
that people like didn't want
to forget about us.
And we could kind of
maximize our coverage.
And, you might really want
keep your, you know,
contacts fresh.
It like, really a
relationships business.
So once you, someone writes
about you,
you should keep going back
to them for, for
more, for writing about,
you know, to write about you
in the future.
It's kind of like, you know,
when, when basically people,
you know, you're more likely
to do something for
someone you've, like,
already done something for.
Yeah, you really, like,
it's, if you just, you know,
I would try to establish
good,
good relationships with a
couple reporters over time
that you can go to to, you
know, break news.
And it, it will come in
handy later if you ever
have, are in the position,
if you're fortunate enough
to be in the position where
people are writing negative
things about you, you know,
having relationships will
help you, you know, kind of
get your side of the story
out, The last thing is like,
you know, it's kind of
Golden Rule really, or
maybe more like a pay it
forward really applies here.
Like, you should really help
your
fellow entrepreneurs get,
get coverage because they
will help you get coverage.
The best way to get covered
is really through these like
warm introductions.
And so you know, whenever
I'm meeting with reporters,
I always help like.
Throwing out the names of
like other things that I
think would be interesting
stories for them.
And usually that comes back.
They, the, the reporters
like it, because they,
it's like helping them find
interesting stories.
And you're more likely to
get, you know, leads
back from entrepreneurs that
you help out.
So, if you're interested in
learning more about press,
here's two resources that I
really liked.
Jason Kincaid, who was a
former TechCruch reporter,
just a really, really great
overview that covers a lot
of things I just talked
about, in more depth and
from the, you know, blogger
side.
That was a really great
book.
And then kind of an evil
resource is this book
Trust Me, I'm Lying.
Which was written by the,
one of the a former marketer
at American Apparel.
And he talks about like a
lot of ways that he
pretty like, evilly actually
manipulated the press, but
I think it's a pretty good
look
into like the psychology of
like how people, you know,
things spread on the
internet.
You know, how stories spread
on the internet and
that, it's a.
Might be valuable to take a
look at.
Cool, that's, that's
basically it.
One question?
Just 1?
>> 2, 2.
>> 2 que, Okay, 2 questions.
Or zero questions.
>> When is the right time to
start worrying about
press altogether?
>> When is the right time to
start worrying about press
altogether?
I think it's a really good
way.
Like if you just.
The first time I launched,
you know,
my first products in our
first startup.
For a lot of them we got
like zero attention.
And we didn't really know
how to even get
a hundred users.
I think it's a really fine
way to
get a hundred users and a
lot of.
Companies in YC where they
first launch their
product will encourage them
to get out and
just do one TechCrunch story
to, like, get a few
people to see it, and it's
good to get in the practice.
I wouldn't, like, obsess
over getting, like,
coverage in multiple outlets
or
anything like that in the
very beginning.
All right, anything else.
There.
>> It seems like
the biggest story
>> Yeah.
>> Great, so like much of a,
how much of
a role did you guys actually
play in getting that
out
>> so,
Twitch, you know, had this
thing called Twitch plays
Pokemon where developers set
up like a Pokemon,
like Gameboy game that was
controlled by chat, so
millions of people would be
typing in A or B, and like.
The character would wander,
wander around aimlessly.
And that was like a huge
news story and I think that
what we did was you know,
there's a couple parts.
One, we set the stage by
having other news
stories that, so when
someone from the BBC would
Google like Twitch and be
like what is this
crazy thing that everyone on
Reddit is talking about?
They would, like, have some
context.
The other thing is,
like, we didn't come up with
the idea for twit, right?
That was, like fortuitous.
But we helped, like, give it
legs by, you know,
making the company available
to talk to the reporters,
and, suggesting follow-up
stories about, like.
You know, there were
stories,
not just about Twitch plays
Pokemon,
because a hundred thousand
people were watching this.
Pokemon game, but because
you know, it finally like,
there were stories when they
beat the game.
And there were stories when
they launched Twitch
plays Pokemon, you know,
Crystal, or
whatever the next Pokemon
version was.
And like, and so
we kind of gave that story a
little more legs.
But we didn't, you know,
originate it.
It was the community really
who originated it.
All right.
I think that's it.
Thank you very much.