https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uFX95HahaUs
A big reason for that is so
we can fix our mistakes and
we can pay up to get in
later when we screw up early
on.
The other thing i'll
highlight though
is the other reason why we
pull the trigger at
a high evaluation, when we
did was because of our,
we had spent time at the
point with the founders.
With Brian and with Joe and
Nate and there's a friend of
mine in private equity has
this great line,
Egon Durban has this great
line.
He says when people progress
through their careers,
they get bigger and bigger
jobs, and
at some point they get the
really big job.
And it's,
some people, half people
grow into the big job, and
about the other half of
people swell into it.
Right?
And you can
kinda tell the difference.
There's a point where people
just lose their minds.
And one of the issues with
these companies that
are sort of super successful
hyper growth companies is
you know, this would be the
sorta the classic case.
These super young founders
who
haven't run anything before,
so how are they gonna be at
running this sorta giant
global operation, and
we just were tremendously
impressed and our, today,
every time we deal with all
three of those guys.
How mature they are, how
much they are progressing.
You know, it, it's like they
get more and
more mature, they get better
and better adjustment and
they get more and more
humble as they grow.
And so that made us feel
really good.
That not just was this
business gonna grow, but
that these were guys who
were gonna be
able to build something.
And be able to run it in a
really good way.
>> You know, people always
ask me.
Why do you think Airbnb is
such a great company.
It's funny we're obsessing
over Airbnb but and
I say to people it's because
all three founders are as
good as the other founder.
That is very rare.
In the case of Google.
Two founders,
one of them is a little
better than the other one.
>> [LAUGHTER}
>> Hey, he is the CEO every
company has a CEO.
>> I think we just got the
tech crunch headline.
>> Every company, every
company has a CEO.
Why am I saying this?
>> When you start a company,
you have to go find somebody
as good or better than you.
To be the cofounder.
If you do that,
your chances of success grow
astronomically.
And that's why Airbnb became
so successful, so quickly.
The anomaly is Mark
Zuckerberg at Facebook.
Yes, he has an awesome team.
But the Mark Zuckerberg
phenomenon where it's
mainly one person, that is
the outlier.
>> Hm-mm.
>> So when you start a
company you have got to find
phenomenal co-founders.
>> All right.
Audience questions.
Yes.
>> So obviously the
conventional wisdom about
why you raise money is
because you need it.
But the more I get off
conventional wisdom the more
I'm starting to hear another
story about why you
raise money and I"m actually
hearing founders say it's
more to facilitate the big
exit, or in the worst case
to facilitate the acqui hire
that are just fizzling out.
What extent is that accurate
thinking or
>> Does raising money help
you with an exit, or an
acqui hire?
>> Well if you,
if you pick good investors
who have good Rolodexes and
domain expertise in what
your company does.
They're gonna add a lot more
value than the money.
And those are the types of
investors you should be
looking for.
>> Yeah.
>> So the answer to
the question is clearly yes.
But also in a sense it
doesn't matter.
Cuz you can't plan these
things according to
the downside.
And so.
I mean, that's the scenario
you are not
are obviously not hoping
for.
And so while the answer is
yes.
Probably that shouldn't
enter into
the decision making process.
Too much, but it might enter
into which investor to
raise money from,
it probably doesn't enter
into the whether to
raise money question that
much I don't think.
>> I intend to start a
business,
just grow the capital
investment,
I do want to end up with
some equity.
Do you guys have any advice
about how to
deal with extra amounts,
people are taking so
long, not everything is like
software.
It's viral.
What should congress do for
capital investment companies
>> So this is,
I would double down on my
previous comments on
the onion theory of risk and
the staging of risk in cash
which is the more capital
has in the business the more
intense and serious you have
to be about exactly what's
going to be required to make
the business work and
what the staging of
milestones and risks are.
Cuz in that case, you wanna
line up,
you wanna be very precise of
lining up.
Because the risk is so
high that it'll all go
sideways right?
So, like, you wanna be very
precise what you're
gonna accomplish with your A
round.
And what's going to be
a successful execution of
the A round.
Because if you raise too
much money in the A round,
that'll seriously screw you
up, right,
later on down the road.
In the, cuz you know you're
gonna raise the C,
D, E rounds.
You know, and then the
cumulative,
dilution will get to be,
will get to be too much.
And so you have to be
precise on
every single round.
You have to raise as close
to the exact right amount of
money as possible and then
you have to be as pure and
clean and, and precise with
the investors as you
can possibly be about the
risks and the milestones.
But, this by the way is a
big thing.
This is actually, I'm really
glad you asked the question.
It kind of goes back to what
Parker said.
Like, look if you walk into
our firm and
you've got Twitter, or
you've got Pinterest,
you've got something and
it's just viral growth and
it's just on fire and it's
just gonna go.
Like, those are the easy
ones.
Like it's just, like, let's
put money in it.
And let's just feed the
beast and off it goes.
But if you walk in and
you're like, I got this
really great idea.
But it's gonna take $300
million,
staged out over the next
five years.
Probably across five rounds.
You know, It has
a potentially very big
outcome.
But boy, like this is not
Twitter.
Like, this is gonna be
serious heavy lifting.
To be able to get there.
We will still do those but
the operational excellence
of the part of the team
matters a lot more.
And one of the ways that you
can convey the operational
excellence is in the quality
of the plant.
And back to the Steve Martin
thing be so
good they can't ignore you.
The plans should be very
precise.
>> And there are ways if
your capital equipment.
Intensive.
There are ways of borrowing
money in addition to
venture capital.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> You, you can kick in.
You can kick on a venture
data and
then later on lease
financing.
But again that underlines
the need for operational
excellence because if you're
gonna raise debt, then you
really need to be precise in
how you're running the
company because it's very
easy to trip the convenance
on a loan and it's very easy
to lose the company.
And so it's a thread the
needle progress that
demands a just sort of a
more advanced level of
management then sort of, you
know, the next SnapChat.
>> What are some bad sides
for
investors that you shouldn't
work with their company?
>> Yeah that's a good
question.
How do you know with an,
what's a sign that you
should avoid a particular
investor?
>> Well, it's the inverse of
what I
said about a good investor.
If it's an investor who has
no domain expertise in your
company, does not have a
Rolodex where they can
help you with introductions.
Both for business
development and
in helping you do the
intro's for series a.
And you should not take that
person's money,
especially if they're in it
just to make money and you
can suss those people out,
you know, pretty quickly.
>> Yeah I would, glad you
asked that question.
Bring up sort of a broader
point which is
If your company is
successful.
You know, we're talking
about our,
you know, I think,
generally, or at least as a
company, is we want,
our investors are the ones
that wanna build big,
independent franchise
companies.
So we're talking about a 10
or 15 or 20 year journey.
You know, 10 or 15 or 20
years you may
notice is longer than the
average American marriage.
>> This is significant.
The choice of key investors,
of particular investors who
are gonna be on the board
for a company, I think,
is just as important as who
you get married to,
which is extremely
important.
These are people you're
gonna be living with, and
partnering with and
relying on, and dealing with
in position, you know,
in conditions of great
stress and
anxiety for a long period of
time.
And the big argument I
always make is, and
ours like make this all the
time,
sometimes people believe it
and sometimes they don't.
Which is like if everything
just goes great,
it kind of doesn't matter
who investors are,.
But almost never does
everything just go great.
Right?
Even the big successful
companies even the big you
know, Facebook and all these
big companies that are now
considered very successful.
You know, along the way all
kinds of shit went,
you know, shit hit the fan
over and over and
over and over again.
And there are any number of
stressful board meetings and
discussions and
late night meetings with the
future of the company at
stake where everybody really
has to be on the same team.
And have the same goals and
be pulling in the same
direction and
have a shared understanding.
That have the right kind of
ethics and the right kind of
staying power, you know, to
be able to actually weather
the storms that come up.
And one of the things that
you'll find that is a big
difference between first
time founders versus second
time founders is almost
always second time
founders take that point
much more seriously.
After they've been through
it once, and so
it really, really, really
matters.
I always thought, and I
believe that it does.
It really matters who your
partner is, it really is
like getting married, and it
is worth putting the same
amount of time, maybe not
quite as much time and
effort into picking your
spouse, but
it is worth spending
significant time really
understanding who you're
about to be partnered with.
>> Yeah,
>> Because that's way
more important than.
You know, did I get another
$5 million in
the valuation or did, you
know,
did I get another $2 million
in the check?
>> The marriage analogy is
great.
I know at SV Angel, our
attitude is when we
invest in an entrepreneur,
we are investing for life.
Because we wanna invest in,
if we made the right
decision, we're gonna invest
in every company they start.
And, once an entrepreneur,
always an entrepreneur.
So we actually do consider
it a marriage.
We're, investing for life.
>> One thing that I,
that, which is another of
saying what Mark just said,
is I always look for.
In that first meeting,
do you feel like you respect
this person?
And do you feel like
you have a lot to learn from
them?
Cuz sometimes you walk in
and they have this like just