https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uFX95HahaUs
such an incredible amount of
insight in your business.
That you walk out of there
being like, man, I don't,
even if these guys didn't
invest, that sort of hour
that I spent with them was
such a great use of my time.
I felt like I came out with
a much clearer picture of
what I need to do and where
I need to go.
And that's such a great
microcosm of what
the next couple of years are
gonna be like.
You know like, don't if you
feel like you would want
this person really involved
in the company even if they
didn't have like a checkbook
that they brought with them.
And if not that's probably a
very bad sign.
>> What's the constraint on
the V
making accurate use of
angels and VCs?
Time, money, or the lack of
company?
>> Well what's the
constraint on
how many companies you guys
invest in?
>> SV Angels has kinda
gotten comfortable with one
a week.
You certainly can't do more
than that, and
that's a staff of 13.
So it's, it's really the
number of companies.
>> Ron, if you had,
if you all worked twice the
number of hours,
would you invest in twice
the number of companies?
>> I would advise against
that,
I would rather just add
value,
more value to the existing
companies.
>> Maybe you could,
I'll take the role of
questioner for a second.
>> [LAUGHTER] Maybe you
could,
could you talk a little bit
about conflict policy?
>> Or not, or not conflict
policy.
>> Well SV Angel actually
does
have a written conflict
policy.
But most, when we end up
with a conflict it's usually
because one company has
morphed into another space.
We don't normally,
invest in companies that
have a direct conflict.
If we do we will disclose it
to the other company,
to both companies.
And keep in mind at our
stage,
we don't know the company's
project strategy anyway.
We probably don't know
enough to disclose.
But our conflict policy also
talks about
this really important word,
which is trust.
In other words,
we're off to a bad start if
we don't trust each other.
And, and with SV Angel, the
relationship between
the founder and us, is based
on trust.
And if somebody doesn't
trust us
then they shouldn't, they
shouldn't work with us.
>> Mark, would you invest in
companies?
>> yeah.
So this is actually-
So, let me go back to the
original question.
I'll come back to that.
So the original question is
this is the thing we
talk about most often in our
firm.
So this is kind of the,
the question is at the heart
of I think how all venture
capital operates which is a
question of constraints.
So the big constraint on
a top tier venture capital
firm the big
constraint is the concept of
opportunity cost.
So, it's the concept that
basically everything you
do means that there are a
whole bunch of
other things that you can't
do.
And so, it's not so much the
cost.
And, and we think about this
all the time.
It's not so much the cost
of,
we invest five million
dollars in a company, and
the company goes wrong and
we lose the money.
That's not really the loss
that we're worried about.
Because the theory is will
have
the winners that'll make up
for that in theory.
The cost that we're worried
about,
is, every investment we make
has,
has two implications for how
we run the firm.
Every investment we make,
number one rules out
conflicts, and so, for
sure our policy for sure on
venture and growth rounds,
is that we don't invest in
conflicting companies.
And so we only invest in one
company in a category.
And, so, if we invest in
MySpace, and
then Facebook comes along a
year later.
Like, we're out.
We can't do it, right?
And so we basically lock,
every investment we make
locks us out of a category.
Right?
And, the nature, that's
a very complicated topic
when you're discussing these
things internally in these
firms at first because.
You only know the companies
that already exist right?
You don't know the companies
that haven't even
been founded yet right?
And God help you had you
invested in you know,
an early company that was
not gonna be the winner and
you were locked out by the
time you know,
the winner emerged three
years later and
you just couldn't make the
investment.
So that's one issue, is
conflict policy.
The other issue is
opportunity cost.
The time and bandwidth of
the general partners and so
going back to the concept of
adding value,
you know we're a firm
typical, typical firm we're
fairly typical firm we've
eight general partners,
each general partner can
maybe be on 10, 10 to 12
boards in total if they're
completely fully loaded.
So it's basically Warren
Buffet talks a lot
about investing as you
basically want to think of
it as a ticket that you have
a limited amount of
holes you can punch and
every time you
make an investment you punch
the hole.
And when you're out of,
when you're out of holes to
punch like you're done,
you can't make any new
investments.
And that's very much how
venture capital operates and
so the way to think about is
every open board
slot that one of our GPs has
at any given point in
time is an asset of the firm
that can be
deployed against an
opportunity.
But every time we make an
investment it takes
the number of slots that we
can punch down by one.
So, it reduces the ability
for
the firm to do new deals.
And so every investment we
make forecloses not just the
competitive set, but
other deals where we will
simply run out of time.
And so, and this is sort of
a big thing of like well.
This goes back to what I
said earlier.
Like this company's pretty
good.
It seems fairly obvious that
it's going to
raise extra funding.
Why didn't you fund it?
Well, on its own if we
had unlimited capacity we
probably would have.
Like it'll probably make
money.
But relative to getting
blocked out of
the competitive set and
relative not having that
open seat for a, for
an even better opportunity
we pass on that basis a lot.
>> It's pretty widely agreed
that, that that's it's
easier than ever to build an
MVP launched get traction.
Same time we know that there
are CPOs that have been
pre-MVP or even pre-launch
and pre-traction.
So in those instances where
you do a seed round with
a company either doesn't
have a or
doesn't have a launch
impressive traction.
What do those deals look
like and
what do you make that
judgment based on?
What convinces you to invest
with product with and
no traction?
>> What would convince us,
which is what usually
convinces us,
is the founder and their
team themselves.
So we invest in people
first.
Not necessarily the product
idea.
The product ideas tend to
morph a lot.
So we will invest in, in the
team first.
If it's, if it's pre-users,
the valuation is gonna tend
to be corresponding lower
unless one of the founders,
you know, has a, a success
track record.
>> Yeah, for us it's almost
always, if there's nothing
at the time of investment,
then it's almost, other than
a plan it's almost always
the founder who we've worked
with before or a founder
who's very well known.
By the way the other thing
worth highlighting is,
you kind of, in these
conversations,
in all these conversations,
you kinda, the default
assumptions is that we're
all starter web companies or
consumer mobile companies.
There are, you know other
categories or companies,
capital intensive is one
that's been brought up,
but it's I'll just say for
example, enterprise software
companies.
Or enterprise these days
Saas, you know,
application companies or
cloud companies.
It's much more common that
there's no MVP right.
they're a cold start.
And it's much more common
that they
build a product in the A
round.
Then there's no point to
have an MVP cuz
the customer's not gonna buy
an MVP the customer actually
needs the full product when
they first start using it.
And so the company actually
needs to raise 5 or
10 million dollars to get
the first product built.
But in almost all those
cases that's gonna be
a founder who's done it
before.
I think we have time for one
more question.
Yeah.
>> Could you talk
about the ideal Boris
structure and
when do you think expect to
publish that?
>> Yes, talk about the ideal
Boris structure.
>> Gosh, I think So, so in
our board we're fortunate
that we have, there's myself
and my cofounder, and a.
Partner from Adruse and
Horowitz.
Which I think probably
removes the fear.
It probably creates a little
more trust cuz it sort of
removes the fear that like,
you know, someone's going to
come in and just like, fire
you arbitrarily because it's
like, time for a big company
CEO.
Kind of thing.
But I,
in most cases I think if
you, if you trust,
if you trust the people that
you're working with it,
it shouldn't really be an
issue.
Cuz there are so, there are
so few.
I mean things almost never
come to like a board vote.
And by the time that they do
it's like somethings deeply
broken at that point anyway.
and, and most of.
And most of the power that
VCs have comes outside of
the board structure, it's
protective covenants that
are build into the financing
round so it's like you can't
you know, take on debt, you
can't sell the company.
There are certain things
that you
can't do without them
agreeing to it anyway.
So it's probably like less
of a big deal than people
make it out to be.
What I found, sort of,
is, is that it seems to me
that, as a founder.
If things are going well at
the company,
you have sort of unlimited
power, vis a vis,
your investors.
Like, almost unlimited.
Like, no matter what the
board structure is, and
no matter what the covenants
are in the round.
Like, if you say, listen, I
wanna do this, and
I think this is what we need
to do.
And even if it's, like, a
good investor or
a bad investor.
Even the bad investors will
be, like, you know?
Like, let's, let's, let's
make it happen.
Cuz they wanna like ride
this rocket ship with you.
And when things are going
badly it does not
matter what protections
you've built into
the system for yourself.
Like, you know, at the end
of the day, like,
you need to go back to the
trough to get more money.
And you know, if, if, like,
things aren't going well,
like they're gonna have all,
all of the cards in their
hand.
>> And they're gonna get to
renegotiate all the terms.
>> And, exactly they'll
change all the terms.
>> This is what happens
actually when
a company gets in dire
straights.
Their it actually doesn't
matter what the terms, but
at fire rounds they all get
renegotiated.
>> This is I think
the fundamental rule of
raising money.
Other than never having down
turns is that if
things are going well the
founder is in control and
this company needs more
money and
things going badly, if
investors are in control.
>> I've been on boards for
20 years public and
private, I have never been a
board vote that mattered.
It's always been never,
never a vote.
Many discussions, many
controversies, many issues.
Never a vote.
It's the decision has always
been clear by the end.
And it's either by unanimous
or very close to unanimous.
And so I think it is almost
all around the intangibles
and almost not at all around
the details.
>> Okay.
Thank you
guys very much for coming in
today.
>> Pleasure.