https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CBYhVcO4WgI
you're working with great
partners,
they're gonna wanna be
working really hard,
they're gonna want you to be
working really hard uh, and
again, you're gonna wanna
work really hard.
So some some companies like
to tell the story about you
can have your cake and eat
it too, you can have, like,
four day week, work weeks
maybe if you're, if you're,
Tim Ferris maybe you can
have a 12-hour work week.
It's a really attractive
idea and
it does work in a particular
instance.
Which is if you wanna like
actually have a small
business or go after a niche
market.
Then you're a small business
entrepreneur.
That makes total sense.
But as soon as you get past
like two or
three people uh, you really
need to step it up and, and
be full time committed.
cool.
So, this is the big one this
is the, the one I
hear the most especially
like candidates applying to
a Asana they tell me, you
know, I,
I'd really like to work for,
for
a much smaller company, or
start my own because.
Then I have a much bigger
slice of the pie,
I'll have much more impact
on how that company does and
I'll have more equity so
I'll make more money as
well.
So let's examine when this
might be true.
So I'll explain these tables
they're a little complex but
let's focus on the left
first so these is,
this is just explaining.
Dropbox and Facebook.
These are their current
valuations.
And this is how much money
you might
make as employee number 100
coming into these companies.
Especially if you're like,
an experience,
a relatively experienced
engineer, like,
you have five years of, of
industry experience.
You're pretty likely to
have an offer that's around
10 basis points.
So if you joined DropBox a
couple years ago,
the upside you'd have
already locked in.
As about ten million,
there's plenty more growth
from there.
If you leave the company if
you joined Facebook a couple
years into its,
its existence you made $200
million.
This is a huge number.
And if you.
Even if you joined Facebook
as employee number 1,000.
So you joined it in like
2009 you still
made $20 million.
That's a giant number.
And that's how you should be
benchmarking when you're
thinking about what might I
make as an entrepreneur.
So moving over to the table
on the right uh,
these are two theoretical
companies you might start.
So Uber for Pet Sitting,
pretty good idea.
If you're, if you're really
well suited to this,
you might have, uh, a really
good shot at
building a $100 million
company.
And then your share of that
company is pretty likely to
be about 10%.
That certainly fluctuates.
Some founders have a lot
more than this,
some have a lot less.
But after multiple rounds of
dilution multiple rounds of
option table, option pool
creation,
you're pretty likely to end
up about here.
If you have more than this,
I recommend Sam's post on
like the equity split
between founders and
employees.
You probably should be
giving out more.
And then but so basically,
if you're extremely
confident about building
this $100 million business,
which is a big ask it should
go without saying that
you should have a lot more
confidence than Facebook in
2009 or Dropbox in 2014 and
you might, for a start up
that doesn't even exist yet.
Then this is worth hearing.
So if you have a $100
million idea and
you're pretty confident you
can execute it,
I would consider that.
If you think you're the
right entrepreneur to build
Uber, Uber for space travel,
that's really huge idea.
$2 billion idea.
You're actually gonna have a
pretty good return for that.
You should definitely do
that.
This is also only the value
after four years.
And this idea probably has
legs.
So definitely go after that.
If, if you're thinking of
building that,
you probably shouldn't even
be in this class right now.
You should go and, go and
build that company.
So why is this, financial
reward and, and impact, I
really think that financial
reward is very strongly
correlated with the impact
you have on the world.
If you don't believe that
let's talk
through some specific
examples and
not think about the equity
at all.
So why might joining a, a
late-stage company actually
provide you a lot of impact?
You get this multiplier They
have an existing massive
user base.
If it's Facebook, it's a
billion users.
Or if it's Google it's a
They have existing
infrastructure you
get to build on.
That's also increasingly
true for new startups.
Things like AWS.
Like awesome independent
service providers.
But you usually get some,
like,
proprietary technology and
it's all maintained for you.
It's a pretty great place to
start uh, and
you get to work with a team
and they'll help you
just leverage your idea into
something great.
So, a couple of specific
examples Bret Taylor came
into employee around or
came into Google as around
employee number 1,500.
And he invented Google Maps.
This is a product you guys
probably use every day.
I used it to get here.
And it's used by hundreds of
millions of
people all around the world.
Didn't need to start a
company to do that,
did happen to get a big
financial reward.
But the, the point is he had
massive impact.
My co-founder Justin
Rosenstein.
Joined go, Google a little
later after Brad he was
a PM there.
And just as a side project
he
ended up prototyping a chat
which, which used to be
a standalone app as
integrated into Gmail,
like you see it on the upper
right there.
And before he did that, like
people didn't even think you
could do chat over AJAX, or
chat in the browser at all,
and he just kind of like
demonstrated it, and
showed it to his team, and
made it happen.
Again, this is probably a
product most of
you use maybe every day.
And then, perhaps even more
impressively,
shortly after that,.
JR left,
he became employee around
number 250 at Facebook.
And he led a hack-a-thon
project along with
people like Andrew Bosworth
and
Leah Pearlman uh, to create
the like button.
So, this is one of the most
popular elements anywhere
on the web.
Totally changes how people
use it.
And again didn't need to
start a company to do it and
almost certainly would have
failed if he had tried.
Because he really needed the
distribution of
Facebook to make it work.
So important to, to keep in
mind the context for uh,
what kind of company you're
trying to start and like,
where will you actually be
able to make it happen.
So what's the best reason?
So, Sam already talked about
this a little bit but
basically, you can't not do
it.
You're super passionate
about this idea.
You're the right person to
do it.
You've gotta make it happen.
So how does this break down?
>> Cuz we're getting close
to end here.
How am I doing on time?
>> Cool.
Sweet.
Perfect.
So this, this is sort of
like a word play.
You can't not do it in two
ways.
One is, you're so
passionate about it that
you're just like,
you have to do it.
You're gonna do it anyway.
And this is really
important.
Cuz you'll need that passion
to get through all of
those like hard parts of
being an entrepreneur that
we talked about earlier.
You'll also need it to
effectively recruit.
Candidates can smell when
you don't have passion.
And there are enough
entrepreneurs out there who
do have passion.
That they may as well work
for one of those.
So this is sort of like
table stakes for
being an entrepreneur.
Your subconscious can also
tell when you
don't have passion and
that'll be a huge problem.
And then so the other way to
interpret this is the world
needs you to do it.
So this is sort of
validation that the idea is
important.
It's gonna make the world
better, so
the world needs it.
If it's not em, if it's not
something the world needs,
go do something the world
needs.
Your time's really valuable.
Um,
there are plenty good ideas
out there.
Maybe it's not one of your
own.
Maybe it's an existing
company.
But you may as well work on
something that's gonna be
good.
And then the second way to
interpret this is the world
needs you to do it.
You're actually well suited
to this problem in some way.
If this isn't true it may be
a sign that
your time is better spent
somewhere else.
But also just best case
scenario if this isn't true,
you out compete the team for
which it is true.
And you just end
up with like a sub-optimal
outcome for the world.
That doesn't feel very good.
So drawing this back to my
own experience at Asana,
you know, Justin and
I were kind of like
reluctant entrepreneurs.
We, before we founded Asana
so
we're working at Facebook.
We were already working on a
great problem.
And we would basically work
all day
long on our normal projects
and
then at night we would keep
working on this internal
task manager that was used
internally at the company.
And it was just cuz we were
like so
passionate about the idea
that was so
clearly valuable, that we
couldn't do anything else.
And at some point we had to
have the hard
conversation of like, okay
well what does it
mean if we don't actually
start this company.
We were pretty, we were able
to
see the impact it was having
on Facebook.
We were pretty convinced it
could be really valuable for
the world.
We were also pretty
convinced nobody else was
gonna build it.
The problem had been around
a long time and
we just kept seeing sort of
incremental solutions to it.
So if we didn't go out with
the one that we
thought was best,
we thought there'd be a lot
of value left on the table.
And yeah.
So we just couldn't,
couldn't stop working on it.
And literally the idea was
like beating itself out of
our chest, like forcing
itself into the world.
And I think that's the
feeling you should really be
looking for when you start a
company.
That's how you know you have
the right idea.
So I'll go ahead and stop
there.
I'll put some recommended
books up here,
but won't narrate them.
And maybe, that's the end of
the class.
>> Yeah, thank you.
Maybe you guys could stick
around for
a few minutes if you have
questions for him.
And uh, see you Thursday.
Thank you.