https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tFVDjrvQJdw
Can we keep playing, wait,
okay good.
Can we turn it up a little
bit, so it's more pumped up?
>> That's loud.
>> Okay, here we go, okay.
>> Okay, so we gotta find
the beat and
then we gotta clap to the
beat.
>> Okay.
All right.
Okay, that's pretty good
guys.
All right, we're good.
We're good.
Thank you.
Okay, please stop.
Okay, stop the music.
Thank you.
Okay, cool.
Can you put on
the presentation, thank you.
>> That'll be the most
pumped up
thing that ever happens in
enterprise software, so
the rest is sort of downhill
from here.
>> So, thank you for that
intro,
that well-rehearsed intro,
thank you.
>> Confirming the facts as
you're saying them,
very good.
So I'm Aaron Levie, CEO and
co-founder of Box.
Welcome to this edition of
how to
build an enterprise software
company.
That's my understanding.
This is the course that
you're taking, right, is
that correct?
>> No, okay, so.
>> Here's my job today.
My job is to try and
convince you that everybody
else who speaks throughout
this whole class is wrong
and that you
actually wanna build an
enterprise software company.
And so hopefully we'll be
able to
kinda work through this, and
you'll have a good sense of
why it's super cool to be in
the enterprise.
And why a lot of the
perceptions of
going into the whole
consumer space, where it's,
you know, so much fun and
everything.
Why that's wrong and
why you wanna do enterprise
software.
Who wants to build an
enterprise software company?
Good, all right.
Thank you very much.
Hopefully we'll do a vote at
the end and
hopefully that will not have
shrunk.
So that's really actually
the only goal I
have at this point.
So, we're gonna talk about
three things today.
The first is the quick
background and
history of Box.
Cuz when we started the
company, we didn't know that
we wanted to do enterprise
software and so I wanna kind
of get through a little bit
about why we decided to
go after the enterprise and
what we do today.
And then I'm gonna talk a
little bit
about what are the major
kind of factors that
have changed in enterprise
software that make it
possible to do a start up
today in this category.
And then finally we'll talk
a little
about some patterns that you
can kind of exploit and
some ways to recognize and
ways to actually go
build an enterprise software
company yourself and
hopefully that'll be some
practical, useful advice.
Just as a forewarning, my
voice,
as I've been speaking a lot
the past couple days.
So hopefully, I'll be able
to get to that third part of
the advice and actually be
able to talk, so we'll see
how we make it but I'm gonna
be downing a lot of water so
I apologize for that.
So building for the
enterprise.
This is what we're gonna
talk about.
So just quick kinda high
level stats about Box.
We've about 240,000
businesses that use
the product.
There are over 27 million
users that have brought Box
into their organization and
used it as individuals and
we're in about 99% of the
Fortune 500.
Unfortunately that last 1%
is really just Microsoft.
And they don't seem to wanna
buy from us.
So.
>> We have to work on that a
little bit.
But certainly, a decent
amount of scale,
a lot of users that have
brought Box into
enterprise environments,
these are some of
the large organizations that
are using the product.
So, a very wide range of
industries, everything from
manufacturing and consumer
products to companies like
General Electric.
Stanford Healthcare actually
uses the product for
collaboration within the
hospital environments and
the research.
But between healthcare,
media, manufacturing.
These are the sort of the
range of
industries that we serve.
So, the question's how did
we get here?
Cuz we didn't really start
the company to try and
go build an enterprise
software company even
though that is how things
ended up happening.
So when we started the
product, so
we launched the company in
2005.
We got the idea actually in
college back in 2004.
And so, was anybody using
the internet back in 2004?
Okay great.
So basically, I don't know
if
millennials use the internet
back then.
Sorry.
Okay, no more age jokes.
All right, here's the point.
So, back in 2004, you might
remember that there wasn't
a lot to do on the internet.
It was actually kind of
boring right?
This is before Facebook.
This is certainly before
Snapchat.
So not a lot of things that
you could go to,
you couldn't send people 15
second messages and
photos that disappeared,
cuz you didn't even have a
phone to send them photos.
So in the internet in 2004,
there wasn't a lot going on.
This was basically what the
internet looked like.
Sort of a barren, deserted
landscape and
this was the internet and
just to clarify,
the happy camel's Google and
the sad camel's Yahoo!
>> And that was effectively
the internet and
this is accurate, this is
the internet in 2004.
Yahoo has done a lot better
since then but,
but back in the middle 2000s
they were certainly trying
to find their way and
Google was sort of taking
over the world but
this was the entire, this
was the extent of the world.
So, what we noticed in 2004
in college was that it was,
for some reason, and this
isn't so
much the case today but
back in 2004 it was like,
really hard to share files.
And as simple of an idea as
that is now, you go back
ten years and it was either
really expensive or
it was really hard to
move data through different
corporate networks.
So I had an internship at
the time,
and in the internship, most
of my job using data was
actually just to copy
printed out pages and
then put them in cabinets.
That's what you do
as an intern if you're not a
computer science student.
So I was really, really good
at copying paper.
And unfortunately not a
skill that has
really been useful today.
But, it was really hard to
share files and
then in classroom
environments you
were constantly working with
lots of other people and
it was also hard to share
files.
I went to USC.
And USC gave you 50
megabytes of online storage
space in your email account.
50 megabytes.
So you can basically store
about one file and
then it would auto-delete
every six months.
I don't know who was running
IT at the time but
they certainly didn't buy
hard drives.
So, there was just really,
really hard to store and
share files.
And so we said, well,
why don't we make it really
easy to store and
share files from anywhere?
And so we got this idea for,
at the time it was called
box.net.
And what we noticed was
there were a bunch of
factors that had changed in
the software world.
The first was that the cost
of storage was sort of
dropping dramatically.
So, in our business,
basically every year or
two, you can double the
amount of data and
storage that goes in to a
hard drive.
So, what was uneconomical
two or three years ago,
all of the sudden becomes
feasible because the cost of
computing and the cost of
storage has dropped.
We had more powerful
browsers and networks so
Firefox was just emerging,
people were using the much
faster internet in both
their homes and
in the classroom.
And then people had more
locations that they
wanted to store and share
information from.
And so we had these sort of
three factors that all of
a sudden were emerging.
And I'm gonna sort of pull
these factors back
later when I give some sort
of tactical advice but
sort of the first point to
remember is, always look for
these changing technology
factors.
Cuz any market that has a
significant change in
the underlying, either raw
materials or
enabling factors is an
environment that's about to
change in a very significant
way.
And so we were very
fortunate that basically
the need for data in the
cloud was growing in
importance, and the cost and
the feasibility of doing it
was also improving rapidly.
And so we decided to put
together this really quick
version of Box, we launched
it as box.net, and
the idea was, let's make it
really easy to share files.
And it turned out that the
idea clicked.
We got angel funding from
this guy named Mark Cuban.
And this was before Shark
Tank, but
it was very similar.
And so, we got this funding,
and we decided that, okay.
This is gonna be super
exciting.
We are going to drop out of
college.
We're gonna move to the Bay
Area, and
it's gonna be totally
awesome.
And when you drop out of
college.
Anybody drop out of college
yet?
Okay, good, stay in school.
So when you drop out of
college, like everyone sort
of pictures it, it's just
gonna be, you know,
incredible, like Bill Gates
dropped out of college.
It will be like Bill Gates,
or
Michael Dell dropped out of
college and
it'll be super exciting like
Michael Dell, or
Steve Jobs dropped out of
college, so
this is what people imagine.
But nobody ever remembers
that this guy dropped out of
college also.
>> And, so it's not really a
guarantee obviously that
it's gonna be successful.
But, it's what you do, and
actually, funny,
I don't even know if this
guy dropped out of college.
>> It just sort of looks
like he had to.
>> I apologize if anyone's
related to him,
it's just a funny picture on
the internet.
So.
>> So basically we decided
we would drop out of
college.
We moved up to first Berkley
and
then we moved to Palo Alto a
little bit thereafter.
And we decided that we were
gonna open up the product
for free.
We got hundreds of thousands
of people that would sign up
for the product every single
month.
So, we had a free version of
the product called,
if you went to box.net, you
got a free one gigabyte of
file storage space, which
was,
again, quite a bit back in
2006 at this point.
But we were getting so many
users and
we were trying to figure out
what to do.
And what we ran into was a
common problem that really
any startup runs into but
was really pronounced by
our business model, which
was that for consumers, we
had built a very robust, a
very comprehensive product.
And for enterprises,
we had actually built too
insignificant of a product.
So, for consumers, what we
were running into was, we
had all these features that
you could pay for but a lot
of the consumers didn't need
all of those features.
And for enterprises,
we didn't really have
enough, security.
And we didn't have enough
capabilities around how
enterprises wanted to use
their data.
So we basically had more
functionality than what
a consumer wanted and less
than what enterprise wanted.
And so we found ourselves at
this juncture.
And we found ourselves
basically in this
period where it's very
difficult to figure out what
we wanted to go do with the
business, so
we had to make a choice,
right?
And so we were at this path
where basically,
we're at a juncture where we
had to
choose which path do go
down.
And this was back in early,
mid 2006, up to late 2006,
so I was, I think, 23 at the
time.
The co-founder was, was 22.
Our founding team was even
younger.
When we all dropped out of
college.
And so back in 2006, 2007,
we imagined these two
paths and the worlds were
very, very different.
Like when you do a consumer
start up,
it's basically just lots of
fun.
And, you know?
You have parties all the
time.
And it's just super
exciting.
And then the enterprise,
you basically are battling
these just large incumbents.
It's a fairly thankless, you
know?
Model because you know?
People just generally hate
enterprise software.
So that was sort of how we
imagined that the two
paths was, we had to choose,
you know,
one of these two worlds.
And so we looked at that and
we said okay, well consumer
looks really fun,
enterprise looks really hard
and,