https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQ7ZvO5DpIw
You mentioned that you're
taking longer then you'd like
to see growing and speak a
little bit about when,
how do you know whether or not
you should say and
how do you know when to give
up on also maybe with respect
to like your personalize life
and career goals.
How it fits in
>> So
the question is basically how
do you know when to pivot?
Part of the reason why having
investment thesis and
your confidence in your
being pretty clear on that is,
generally speaking,the answer
that I give people is
if you're confidence is
unmeasured for a fairly long
time or is decreasing, cause
time should be decreasing and
it's decreasing.
And then you go into intense
mode where you're trying to
figure out what kinds of
things you would do
that would increase your
confidence.
Right, and that's failing.
That's a seriously good time
to think about pivoting Right.
And you might have thesis on
can we raise money.
You might have thesis on will,
what's the pattern by
which the product distribution
and growth or, you know,
viral limitation or SEO or
anything else will work.
And just like, well, I tried
these things and
this fourth thing doesn't seem
as good as these three and
the next two things that I
think about.
So even worse that begins to
decrease your confidence and
that's when you should think
about pivoting.
A frequent mistake when it
comes to pivoting is
wait until you've essentially
been crashed into the wall and
everything is dead and you
can't make any and you can't
maneuver anymore and that's
you waited way too long.
Now, in terms of personal
career goals and so
forth, you know, part of the
thing that I
would say that is one of the
things that I meant to talk to
you during the slides that
since misread the time,
I rushed through it a little
bit.
One of the classic questions
is balance and
I actually think founders have
no balance.
Like one of the funniest
conversations I
ever had was with a governor
of Colorado who was
we're going to attract really
great entrepreneurs here
because we have this balanced
lifestyle.
Like, like literally if I ever
hear a founder talking about
oh this is how I have a
balanced life and so.
They're not committed to
winning, right?
And so the only really great
founders are like,
I am going to literally pour
everything into doing this.
Now, it only may be for a
couple years.
I may do this for a while,
then go do other things.
But while I'm doing this, I am
unbalanced at this thing.
It's not to say you don't take
breaks,
not to say that you don't, you
know, go on dates or
whatever else.
But you're super focused on
this,
because it's really hard, and
there's lots of ways to die.
And that's the reason why the
jumping off the cliff
metaphor is one of the ones
that I classically use.
>> So your definition of
sorry, depends on
the idea of identifying
uncertain opportunities which
others don't necessarily see.
Overall how efficient do you
think the startup ecosystem is
at identifying good
opportunities?
>> So how good is the startup
ecosystem at
identifying contrarian
opportunities?
Let's see.
That's kind of challenge.
Because the moment it
kind of actually becomes in
vogue it's less contrarian.
I'd say it's mixed.
Sometimes because part of what
makes a great investor is
an ability to go look I take
this radical shot and
I take this radical shot.
I take this radical shot and
there's enough people or
investors there's usually
someone, if you can find your
way to them, network finding
your way through the network.
Sometimes difficult, tons of
noise,
hard to get to the signal.
On the other hand there's
sometimes things that
are just kind of like, you
know, totally crazy.
Like one of the funniest
things is,
you know Benchmark was the
only one that would fund eBay.
You know, if you talk to most
of the people in
the Valley a year, 18 months
ago about BitCoin they
would've told you like what?
Bit what?
They have no idea what it is.
And by the way,
it's still unclear how BitCoin
will play out, although,
I think, the fact that there
will be a distributed
trust system on cryptocurrency
is I think almost certainly
going to exist in the world,
and the real question is,
is BitCoin the first or last
cryptocurrency.
First, there's new ones and
new features.
Last because it's the one that
has
network effects and is already
going.
And so.
I think it's pretty good with
it.
Frequently what happens is
people think
they're contrarian because
they're doing something they
think is a unique con-,
unique combination.
I'll give you two examples and
hopefully the,
the founders of these people
who sent me these cool,
I get about 30 pictures sent
to me a day.
That I don't basically don't
look at unless or
if something in the title
makes me laugh.
In which case I look at it
mostly as comedy.
And I'll share two comedy
ones.
One of them was wearable
diapers, which was the you
know, you, you have the
computer monitoring you know.
Whether or not the kid is you
know taking a pee or
a poop and it lets you know,
and you're like.
If you're that far away from
your child in this kind of
thing, it's probably a bad
sign of other things.
And then the other one was
kind of
a customized e-commerce bongs.
And your know like, oh, I've
got a contrarian idea.
Like, yes you do.
But not the right way.
Right?
So anyway.
So, you know, but, so I think
generally speaking,
the system's pretty good at
it.
In the back.
>> Do you find social net
ahead of time I guess.
How do you think about
creating markets versus.
>> Creating markets versus
discovering them?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
So this is actually, well,
it's a challenging question.
The, the the, the frequent,
like, and there's a,
and it's a good follow on the
contrarian thing,
like frequently there's this
classic thing of,
oh does the market exist yet?
Is that because it's going to
be huge or nonexistent?
The good news is, it's usually
one or the other.
Right?
And so that makes going after
something that most people
don't think is a market, but
you have a reason to believe
it,
is actually sometimes
frequently a good bet.
However it can freq,
it can sometimes completely
flame out.
And one of the things you're
doing when you're testing your
investment thesis is.
What would lead me to
think whether there was a
market there or not?
Because, you know,
at the beginning there are no
markets.
And so it is of course
conceptually possible to
create markets.
People think that there's a
new need for
this sort of thing.
On the other hand,
the problem is how do you get
fast adoption if people don't
even know that they want it as
a category.
Right?
So they say, well, but people,
they just realize, a classic
entrepreneurial misfire.
A classic one is if people
just realize once it
exists they'll realize they
really love it and
they'll, they'll line up in
droves for it.
Well, there's a few
entrepreneurs,
Steve Jobs one of them, who
can do that.
Most of the time it doesn't
work out that way, and so
you have to say in your
investment thesis why is
it that you think when you're
thinking about a market that
isn't already existent.
That, that you know that other
people don't know on
the countrian basis that leads
you to
think that market should
exist, right.
And so for example, a micro
one with LinkedIn was,
actually in fact the
classifieds means of
recruiting was in fact an
exercise of newspapers,
an exercise in information
age.
And actually, recruiting
direct to people is part of
what the networked age, and
the internet and
that's actually, in fact, how
recruiting should go.
Now, it was relatively easy to
validate that.
But, you know,
that's the kind of thing where
you think about,
there's potentially a new
market.
>> Last question, boss.
>> Yeah, last question.
>> When do you know you've
known someone long enough to
start a company in front of?
One of the things Stan told us
a in the first semester was
you someone you know for a but
when you guys started PayPal.
Like, for example, how long
did you,
it was a large group of people
so how do you know okay,
I trust the people enough to
start a company.
>> So the read I'm, I'm, I'm
repeating the question in
part because we're, this is
record, recorded and
everything else and I want to
make sure the people here it,
but the question basically is
how do you know that you
trust someone well enough to
be a cofounder.
There's a whole bunch of
different variables that go
into it and, look, it's one of
the risks that you take.
And you kind of get to a
thesis of do I think that I
know them well enough?
Now I'll parallel one thing
that I think
there's a parallel here that I
think is super useful.
So one of the things I tell my
portfolio company CEOs or
founders when there thinking
about hiring a CEO.
Is I think that the only way
to do this is,
when you get down to the
people that you thinking you
may hire as a CEO, you spend
20 plus hours which them.
Right, where you go into as
much depth in a conversation
about anything you think is a
possible difference.
Of opinion, belief, work
style, so
you've identified all this up
front so that you're, you're,
you're it's not that you have
a contract, it's not like,
oh signing a contract, this is
how we do it.
But we've established the
conversation.
We've, we've gone all the
parameters,
we've had a conversion about
what we might agree with or
disagree with.
One of the things that I
frequently think is
worth covering is almost like,
kind of, the divorce.
Like, wa, why would we want to
divorce?
Like, what would lead me to
say,
this isn't working, right?
And to cover that up front as
part of it.
Because then, at that point,
when you get into the field of
battle.
Which is hugely stressful,
you go through this valley
shadow of the moment.
You've at least got the basis
of we already conversed about
a wide variety of things we've
set up essentially some
expectations about what, you
know how we might be planning
together, and if it begins to
vary off that it's relatively
easy to bring it up in a way
that you're problem solving.
And that's the kind of thing
that I think you frequently,
you should be fairly confident
that you
have that level of trust.
For me, frequently,
it's to have a set of robust
conversations.
Such that, as like, like if
something comes up later,
it's like, well, we talked
about this inversion.
And we can, we can bring that
up, so.
Anyway, with that.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.