https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6fQHLK1aIBs
All of them will tell you no.
So you're never 100%,
but you definitely want to get
a close to that as you can.
Next complicated topic is
delegating.
So just like the other thing I
like about the metaphor of
editing is.
Writers do most of the work in
the world.
Editors are not actually
writing most of the content in
any publication.
So that's actually true of
your company.
You are not going to do most
of the work.
You shouldn't be doing most of
the work.
And the way you get out of
doing most of
the work is you actually
delegate.
Now the problem with
delegating is,
that actually you're
responsible for everything.
So as CEO founder there is no
excuse,
there's no like that's that
department over there,
this person over there screwed
up,
you're always responsible for
every single thing, especially
when things go wrong.
So how do you both delegate
but not abdicate.
It's pretty tricky challenge
and
both are sins, like if you
over delegate.
Or, and you advocate, or
you micro-manage, those are
both sins.
So I'm going to give you a
couple techniques for
solving this.
First, this actually comes
from high output management
and to grow, is what's known
as task-relevant maturity.
It's kind of a fancy phrase
for
basically, has this person
ever done this before?
It's really simple.
And how mature is this person
in doing something/ And
the more they've done the
exact same task before.
The more sort of rope you're
going to give them.
And the less, the more they're
trying something new,
the more you're going to
actually instruct them and
consistently, constantly
regularly monitor.
So that's kind of a basic
concept but
it's worth keeping in the back
of your brain.
The interesting implication,
and
this is pretty radical, is
that any executive,
any CEO should not have one
management style.
Your management style actually
needs to be dictated by
your employee.
So with one particular person,
you may be very much a micro
manager because they're quite
low on this scale.
And with another person you
may be delegating a lot
because they're actually quite
mature on this scale.
So it's actually a good thing
if you do reference checks on
somebody, and half the people
you call say they're a micro
manager, and the other half
say they actually give me
a lot of responsibility,
that's actually not a,
that's a, that's a feature not
a bug.
I didn't understand that at
first, at all, like I used to
be befuddled when people would
dereference checks on me, and
come back with this like,
complicated mosaic.
And that basically, finally
figured out that maybe I
was actually doing my job
correctly, and so
then of course,
thought other people that this
was the way to do it.
A more nuanced answer though,
that I've sort of came up
with, is how, how do you make
decisions?
And delegating versus doing it
yourself.
You don't want to do it
yourself too often.
So what I've basically
borrowed from Peter,
this is my first two by two
matrix ever in my life but he
taught me something at least
is you basically sort you,
your own level conviction
about a decision on a grid you
know, extremely high,
extremely low.
There's times when you know
something's a mistake, and
there's times where you
wouldn't do it that way, but
you have no real idea what
the, whether,
whether it's the right or
wrong answer.
And then there's a consequence
to mention, there are things
that if you make the wrong
decision are actually
catastrophic to your company
and you will fail.
There are things that are
pretty low impact,
that really at the end of the
day aren't going to
make a big difference, at
least initially.
So what I basically believe is
that where there's low
consequences, and
you have very a low confidence
in your own opinion, you
should absolutely delegate,
and delegate completely like
people make mistakes and
learn.
On the other side obviously,
where the consequences are
extremely dramatic and
you have extremely high
conviction that you're right,
you actually can't let your
junior colleague,
like, make a mistake.
You're ultimately responsible
for that mistake, and if
it's really important you just
can't allow that to happen.
Now the best way to do
that is to actually explain
your thinking, the why.
It's easy to shortcut when you
get busy,
explaining why's of the world,
but it's very important to try
when I was at LinkedIn I had a
colleague who's quite,
quite talented.
Both occasion we get annoyed
if, if I didn't exactly agree
with his opinion on something,
and so I'd
spent a lot of time trying to
persuade him why I was making
a decision a certain way.
And his wildcard, the card he
would ultimately call out if I
didn't quite persuade him,
he's like, okay you're the
boss, and that meant to
me like I was burning a lot of
social capital.
Every time he said that, I
knew I was like
really creating a thin line,
and that ultimately that was
going to backfire if I did
that too often, so
you want to track the times
that you're doing that.
Example of this is Squares,
one of my favorite people in
the world,
and my second hire, first
marketing hire had this
program he wanted to run
called Inner-Square,
which basically allowed people
to give out square merchants
to get out ten other squares
to their call.
Just imagine a food truck
outside,
put like ten squares on the
counter and
people could just grab them,
and Kyle had this great idea,
this would be this awesome
marketing program.
Squares would spread squares
to other people and, you know,
to some extent it was on
brand, so
it didn't have catastrophic
consequences.
Each of these ten squares
didn't cost that much money,
so financially we could afford
to do it.
But, at that time my ten years
of experience said
there's just no way this is
going to work in
a meaningful enough scale, to
move our metrics enough and
I actually would prefer we
don't, not do this.
But Kyle, so
excited about this that I
decided to just let him do it.
He learned that actually when
you
measure this thing it's not
massive.
It doesn't create a massive
value for the company.
It did require a fair amount
of operational complexity to
ship all these squares to
people and
figure out how to get them to
be squares etc.
But it allowed him to be
excited about his job and
to learn how to filter future
ideas, so it's totally worth
letting him make the quote
unquote mistake.
The next and most possibly
most important thing you do
is actually edit the team.
So these are the people that
you work with, and
nobody's going to have a
perfect team and
you're certainly not going to
start that way.
So would, I'm going to try to
do is
maximize the probability for
success in editing the team.
So I like this idea of Barrels
and Ammunition.
Most companies once they get
into hiring mode as
Sam pointed out you should
defer that for awhile, but
once you do they just hire a
lot of people.
And they're like, you expect,
and
you expected as you add people
your throughput,
your horsepower, or
your velocity of shipping
things is going to increase.
It turns out it doesn't work
that way.
Usually when you hire more
engineers you
actually don't get that much
more done,
you actually sometimes get
less done.
You hire more designers,
you definitely don't get more
done,
you get less done per day we
could talk about why.
But so the reason why is that
most people,
most great people even, are
actually ammunition.
But what you need in your
company are barrels, and
you can only shoot through the
number of
unique barrels you have.
So that's how the velocity of
your company improves is by
adding barrels, and then you
stock them with ammunition,
and then you can do a lot.
So if you go from a one barrel
company,
which is mostly how you start.
To two barrel companies
suddenly you get twice as many
things done per day, per week,
per quarter, and if you go to
three barrels, great, if you
go to four barrels, awesome.
Barrels are incredibly
difficult to find,
but when you have them, like
give them lots of equity,
promote them, take them to
dinner every week because it,
it, they're virtually it like
irreplaceable.
Because they're also very
culturally specific.
So a barrel at one company may
not be a barrel at
another company because one of
the ways in the definition of
a barrel is they can take an
idea from inception
all the way through shipping
and bring people with them.
And that's a very culturally
specific opportunity specific
skill set, rather.
So two questions probably are
occurring to you,
is how do you figure out who's
a barrel and who's not?
One is you start actually with
a very small set of
responsibilities.
It can be fairly trivial.
It can be something like, I
want to reward
the engineers that are in my
office at 9 o'clock at
night every night with an ice
cold fresh smoothie.
This is actually a real
example.
I was frustrated our engineers
were
working really hard at square.
And, you know,
maybe 20% to 30% would stay
very late into evening, and
I wanted to serve, we were
ready to serve them dinner but
I wanted to give them
something cool to reward them,
and you could think about
alcohol, but
that's a little complicated.
So smoothies were probably a
little bit
better than the pizza, which
drains you of energy.
But nobody could get smoothies
in my office to show up at 9
o'clock sharp that were cold,
that tasted good and delivered
in the right place that
engineers would find them.
You'd think this is simple,
but
in fact, it like, took months
to get this right.
So then we had an in, we had
an intern start, and
I think on his second day,
I was explaining this problem
and
he, he said, well, I'll do it,
and I was like looking at and
I'm like there's no way.
I've seen my office manager
fail, my assistant fail,
all who are actually pretty
good.
This just isn't going to
happen, and then long and
behold that night they show up
on time, cold, delivered to
the right place, and my first
instinct was great not,
not, nothing about the
smoothies.
But okay, now I can actually
give you something more
important and inconsequential
and complicated to do, and
that's what you actually want
to do with every
single employee every single
day is expand the scope of
their responsibilities until
it breaks and it will break.
Everybody like, I couldn't run
the world, like everybody has
like some level of complexity
that they can handle, and
what you want to do is keep
expanding it until you see
where it breaks and that's the
role that they should stay in,
that level of sophistication.
But some people will surprise
you,
there will be people who you
don't expect without,
with different backgrounds,
without a lot of experience
that just can handle
enormously complicated tasks,
and so keep testing that and
pushing the envelope.
The other signal to look for
is once you've hired someone
is this,
with an open office just watch
who goes up to other people's
desks, particularly people
that they don't report to.
If people start going to your
desk,
someone individual employee's
desk and
they don't report to them.
It's a sign that they believe
that,
that person can help them.
So if you see that
consistently,
those are your barrels.
Just promote them,
give them more opportunity as
fast as you can.
The other question everybody
asks about people is,
when do you hire somebody
above somebody?
And when do you sort of mentor
somebody or
when do you need to replace
somebody?
And the way, the way to think
about this is
every company has its own
growth rate and
every individual has its own
growth rate.
So some companies that are
very successful,
let's say LinkedIn.
LinkedIn was always a very
linear company,
it never went like this.
So for example I joined
LinkedIn 18 months after we
launched and we had only 1.5
million users which in
a social product is very small
in number and