https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uVhTvQXfibU
Like, that's just a done deal.
The second way to handle it,
which is,
and no companies do this.
Which is why I actually really
like this post that he wrote.
Like, you can say up front,
like,
you're guaranteed to get your
salary.
But for your stock to be
meaningful, like, this,
these are the things that have
to happen.
One, you've gotta vest.
Two, you have to stay until,
like, we get to an exit,
like the company makes it.
And or, like you've got to
have the money.
And like finally,
the company's like actually
got to be worth something.
because 10% of nothing is
nothing.
And look, the reason that we
set the policy this way is
like we really value people
who stay.
So don't join this company
like,
if you've got another, join
another one in 18 months.
because like, you're going to
get screwed.
And like, our policy like
guarantees you're going to get
screwed on that.
And so like, those are two
ways to handle it.
It really depends on like, you
and
how you want to run your
culture.
But again, with all these
things, it's just critical to
think it through from
everybody's perspective.
Because when push comes to
shove, that's going to matter.
It's going to change the
outcome of your company.
>> I'm actually revising my
recommendation slightly.
>> Let's hear it.
No, I just think there needs
to be more incentive to stay,
through the years.
But-
>> Right, so
you could add, you could add a
stay incentive.
>> But still like if someone
gets, if someone gets fired I
still think they get screwed a
lot of the time.
>> Well the other.
And the other thing that's
really important that Sam
pointed out it's like,
the distinction now is how
much money you have, right?
If you've got the money, you
don't get screwed.
You walk away with all, you
can buy your stock.
You do take some risk, but you
If you don't have the money,
you don't have the money.
Okay.
So, now, we're getting to the
person on my shirt, Toussaint.
He was the best at this.
And I want to take you through
some examples,
because they're very powerful.
Okay so, first of all, about
Toussaint.
He was born, the thing to
understand about him is he,
he was born a slave.
And but he wasn't just born a
slave, he was born a slave
in the most brutal place to be
a slave.
Which was in kind of the, then
the colony of Santo Domingo,
you know, now referred to as
Haiti.
But this was actually a much
more severe form of slavery,
as were, kind of,
all the sugar growing areas
than even US slavery.
Which is historically a very
brutal form of slavery.
And just to give you some
numbers on it, basically,
over the course of slavery,
the, something like 400 years,
a million slaves were brought
to the US.
And at the end of slavery
there were four million slaves
in the US.
In that same period,
to the sugar growing countries
in the Caribbean.
2 million slaves were brought
over.
And at the end of slavery,
there were 700,000 left.
So from just a quantitative
perspective,
like nearly ten times more
brutal.
And I'm going to read this to
you.
I don't know if I quite have
time, but I don't care.
>> So but, just to, to give
you an idea,
this isn't just like a
quantitative thing.
I'll read you sort of a,
a description of slavery in
Toussaint's area.
Whipping was interrupted in
order to pass a piece of hot
wood on the buttocks of the
victim.
Salt, pepper, citron, cinders,
aloes and
hot ashes were poured into
bleeding wounds.
It's not to heal them, this is
to make it worse.
Mutilations were common.
Limbs, ears, and sometimes
private parts, to deprive them
of the pleasures which they
could indulge without expense.
Their masters poured burning
wa, wax on their arms and
hands and shoulders.
Emptied the boiling cane sugar
over their heads,
burning them alive.
Roasted them on slow fires,
filled them with gunpowder and
blew them up with a match.
Buried them up to their necks
and
smeared their heads with
sugar,
that the flies might devour
them.
Fastened them to the nests of
ants or wasps.
And made them eat their
excrement, drink their urine,
lick saliva of other slaves.
One colonist was known in
moments of anger to throw
himself onto slaves, and stick
his teeth into their flesh.
So that's the slavery that he
grew up in.
And it's really important to
understand this.
Because to get out of that
perspective, was not easy.
But he had a vision and his
vision was kind of threefold.
One, he wanted to end slavery.
Two, he wanted to actually
take control of
the country and run the
country.
And thirdly, he wanted it to
be a first class,
world class country.
Not just like something that,
where he had freed the slaves,
but something that could
compete on a world wide basis.
And so that was his mindset
going in.
But that was the background
that he came from.
So example, management
example,
one conquering the enemy.
So, the kind of sequence of
battles that
occurred in Haiti.
Where first, you know, he had
to kind of defeat the locals.
But then, once he defeated the
locals, which is,
there were several countries
that were very,
very interested in taking
control of Haiti.
Principally Spain, England and
France.
So he had to defeat those
armies as well.
When he conquered them, he had
to decide what
to do with the kind of
conquered soldiers, and
the leaders on the other side.
And, to do this, he really
took into perspective kind of,
three different points of
view.
One, his soldier's point of
Two, the enemy's point of
view.
And finally, the point of view
of the resulting culture.
Like, what kind of country was
he building?
Because the army was going to
be the seed corn for
the culture of the whole
country.
So from the soldier's
perspective, I get this,
you know, do we get to
pillage?
Like, soldiers like to
pillage.
They get stuff, it's something
for their work.
And like, the second thing is,
they're trying to kill us,
so we should kill them.
Like, that's a basic
perspective of the people who
are fighting for 'em.
So, the most important people
to, to some.
Now, I put pillage up there
so, a couple things to note.
One, I didn't put rape up
there.
And very interestingly,
like not only did he not allow
rape among his army, but he
didn't even allow his officers
to cheat on their wives.
And if they did he'd get rid
of them.
Because he was so concerned
about the resulting culture.
What was it going to be?
Was it going to be productive?
Was it going to be best in
world?
Or was it going to be
something less than that?
And so that's, that was his
mindset going in.
His army was actually famous
for not pillaging.
So they were actually already
used to this,
they were famous for not
pillaging.
And this was a,
one of the most surprising
things to conquered people.
To the point where, in Haiti
he had a reputation when even
the white people were like,
very impressed with him.
Just because he would go in
and go into their city and
not pillage, even though he
would win.
But, again,
this is because he took a long
view of the culture.
So, and this is a kind of
important settle point,
which gets him to his
conclusion.
But he believed that the
culture of Haiti,
because it was a slave
culture,
sugar plantation culture, was
just pretty low
grade compared to what he had
experienced in Europe.
When he dealt with the
Europeans.
And then he thought that slave
culture was even more
broken than Haitian culture
because if you think about
slave culture it's like the
kind of culture where oh, you
don't do what I tell you, I'm
going to beat you to death.
I'm going to blow you up with
gunpowder.
If you think the kind of
behavior that,
that, then, that ensues from
that.
That was the culture he knew
he needed to replace.
He knew he needed to upgrade.
So his solution was, when he
conquered the British or
he conquered the Spanish or he
conquered the French.
He would take the very best
people from there.
And he would make them
generals in his army.
Okay, so, you probably didn't
expect that.
Like, so, here are the guys
trying to kill him.
He's leading a slave
revolution.
And he, when he conquers the
enemy,
he actually incorporates them
into his army, and
makes him part of that.
Because he wanted the
expertise, and he wanted the,
he wanted the culture to be at
a much higher level.
So the second question he had.
This is even more complicated.
What do you do with the slave
owners?
So you're leading a slave
revolution.
You take control of the
country.
What do you do with the slave
owners.
Three perspectives again.
So for the slaves, like, come
on, like if you're a slave and
you win the war against the
slave owners, like,
you want to kill them.
There is no question.
And not only do you want to
kill them,
but like that's your land now.
Like, we won.
Like F you.
From Toussaint's perspective,
it was more complicated
because he wanted Haiti to be
a first world country and
sugar was really important and
the whole slave economy was
the sugar economy.
Then, right, like, on the
other hand he was a slave and
he's got to be pretty upset,
particularly given the type of
slavery.
Then he had, but he had to
consider like,
he didn't know how to run a
sugar plantation.
And then like, he didn't have
any
business relationships on who
to trade the sugar with.
But on the other hand like,
like war,
like you win the war you get
the land.
Like, that's a pretty like
basic rule.
So what to do?
And then if you look at the
slave owner perspective, it's
pretty interesting because
they're coming at it from the,
and this is the point of
view that he actually had the
discipline to understand.
They were coming from a cost
structure that was
predicated on slave labor.
So, like,
their business didn't work
without slave labor.
Like, literally if they had to
pay people, like,
their cash flow wouldn't work.
They paid a lot of money for
the slaves up front.
And they paid a lot of money
for the land.
So in their mind, like, to run
it, like, that was, like,
that's how business worked.
Like, you can't just,
you can't just like change the
economics and
have it still work and then
they knew they had like
some power because of the
position they were in.
So what was the answer for the
slave owners?
So, one, so a solution was
like,
one, I'm going to end slavery,
two, I'm going to let slave
owners keep their land.
Three I'm going to make them
pay their workers.
So there are no more slave
labor.
You have paid workers.
But in order to fund that I'm
going to lower their taxes.
You guys ought to be kind of
impressed with that.
Like, lower the taxes of the
slave owners after you
defeat the slave owners and,
like, end slavery.
But he had a bigger goal.
He wanted a stronger culture.
The way he treated those slave
owners,
the, the need to keep the
economy going was important.
And then, like, let's look at
the results.
So, first of all, it is,
Toussaint's revolution is the
only successful slave rev,
revolution in the history of
mankind.
There's never been another
one.
There may never, hopefully.
We won't have slavery in a big
way, and
there won't be another one,
so, like, he's it.
Two you know, the plantation
owners kept their land.
Three, he defeated Napoleon.
He had a booming economy and a
world-class culture.
Under Toussaint, Haiti had
more exports,
export revenue than the United
States.
So that's how successful he
was in the revolution.
And this is the power of
looking at a situation not
just from your point of view,
but from the point of
view all the constituents,
even the people you hate.
Which is hard to do when
you're CEO, and
harder to do when you're
leading a revolution.
So just, look, in conclusion,
the most important thing that
you can learn as CEO, the, one
of the hardest things to
do is, you have to discipline
yourself to see your company
through the eyes of the people
that you're working through.
Through the eyes of the
employees,
through the eyes of your
partners.
Through the eyes of the people
who you're not talking to.
And who are not in the room.
Thank you.
Now for questions.
Yes, sir?
>> How do you communicate the
message to the rest of
the employees?
>> Right.
Right.
So this is a great question.
Yes.
So the question is,
so if you've gotta fire the
modern executive.
One, how do you have the
conversation.