https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAws7eXItMk
pursuing this gaming
broadcasting thing.
And, they talked a lot about
video stability.
Our service wasn't good in
Europe specifically but, but
just globally, video stability
is this huge,
huge issue for them.
And if you compare and
contrast actually, it was
really different.
Like, the things that people
who
didn't use our service said
about what they cared about,
was completely different from
the things that people who
were using the service cared
about.
And we focused on this stuff
because this was
the stuff where, it was so bad
that they
weren't even willing to use
our service because of it.
And most of
them actually had thought
about this because we were,
our user base happened to be a
very well educated user base
in the area who knew about all
their options for, for this.
And, they would, they
actually, you know,
reaching out to them meant
they could,
they probably already tried
all four services and
actually had an opinion.
It's great when you can users
who are that,
that informed and that,
that, they have understand the
space that well.
And and if you go to the.
I'm just going to go to the
next slide.
Yeah.
Here we go.
The other big thing we did
that I thought was
really important was we talked
to non-broadcasters.
so, we went up there and
we talked to all the people
who weren't using us
or competitors.
And in many ways,
those are the most important
people, right?
Talking to your competitor's,
that's your short term win,
right?
Someones using a competing,
piece of competing software
unless your piece of competing
software is something like
Google, which is a search
engine, which everyone uses,.
Okay.
Then,
there are no non-users to
convert.
But, in the case of gaming
broadcasting,
almost everyone's a non-user,
right?
The, the majority, this is
true for most new products.
The majority of people you're
computing with are non-users.
They are people who have never
used your service before.
And, what they say is actually
the most important.
What they say is, is the thing
that blocks you from expanding
from a, a, expanding the size
of
the market with your features,
right?
If you, all you do is look at
your competitors and
yourself, and all you do is
talk to your,
you know, your people who use
your competitors products.
People who use your products.
You can never expand.
Well, not never.
But, you're not learning the
things that help you
expand the size of the market.
You want to talk to people who
aren't even trying to use
one of these things, yet.
Who, who have thought about
it, maybe.
But, who aren't who aren't
into it.
So, what did they say?
My computer isn't fast enough.
I'm focused on training 12
hours a day for
the next tournament.
I like making the perfect
video, and like, editing it.
And so, I just upload things
to YouTube.
I don't do live streaming.
I don't, I, I, I have no
desire to,
to go into that space.
or, or this is actually,
particularly in Korea, this is
a big problem.
Once our strategy gets
broadcast in
a major tournament, we have to
start over.
We have to like, come up with
an entirely new strategy.
And so, the last thing we
ever'd want to do would be
broadcast our practice
sessions, are you crazy?
That's going to hurt us in the
next big tournament.
And so, this became,
this became a big outreach
program for
us, trying to figure out how
we can get people over this.
We bought people computers.
We ,.
We worked really closely with
gaming broadcast,
software companies to help,
the who,
who made the broadcasting
software to make that better.
We started building
broadcasting into games and
into platforms, like we built
broadcasting into the Xbox,
we built broadcasting into the
Playstation 4.
Because we wanted,
needed to overcome this issue
that, like,
it was too hard, broadcasting
wasn't, wasn't possible.
And so you sort of combine
these, for us, these
are three, three big groups we
looked at for broadcasting.
And you combine that feedback
and
what it tells you is not the
features to build.
Right?
Because the, the features they
asked for things like polls
things like
a you know, the ability to
have child account.
Like, child accounts in your
account.
We haven't built most of that
stuff.
But what was important were
the, were the, the issues,
like the goals they were
trying to accomplish there.
People wanted money.
People wanted stability and
quality.
People wanted universal access
for
viewers all around the world
to be able to watch them.
And so that became our focus,
actually.
And we dumped almost all of
our resources into things that
none, no one ever mentioned in
an interview.
But, those are the things that
actually address the problem.
And, and the way you could
tell that it worked is, was as
we, we would build these
things, and then we would go
back to this exact same people
we interviewed and say hey,
you told us you really cared a
lot about making money.
Well, we built you this
subscription program,
that will let you make money.
And, it, it, it's astonishing
because most people aren't,
have never had that
experience, actually.
They've never talked to
someone and
said it would be really great
if your product had feature X.
And then, and then, like, two
months later or
a month later, your product
actually has feature X.
Or at the very least,
a feature that addresses the
problem they brought up.
And so, it was actually, the,
the people we converted first
to our
product are the people that we
talk to about user research.
They are the ones who were
actually the most impressed,
which is kind of fun.
But it really worked, because
those,
we picked people who are
representative.
We picked big broadcasters,
small ones, medium ones.
And we, we made sure we were
addressing their concerns.
And that, that was completely
different from how we'd
approach the problem on
JustinTV.
Because in JustinTV, when we'd
try to do this,
we'd, we'd sat down.
We trolled through huge
amounts of data.
Like we, we spent tons of time
looking at Google Analytics.
Looking at mixed panel.
Looking at in-house analytics
tools.
Figuring out how people use
the service.
Looking at where our traffic
came from.
Completion rates on flows.
We spent all this time doing
that.
And that's good, I mean, you
can learn things from that.
I'm not telling you not to
look at your at your data.
But it doesn't tell you where
you need to go.
It doesn't tell you where,
what the problems are you need
to address.
And so we would just sort of
invent these ideas in
JustinTV.
And then, nine times out of
ten,
without talking to someone,
the idea turns out to be bad.
And that's just one of those
disappointing things about
doing user interviews and user
feedback.
It's why, I think, so many
people don't do it, which is,
you're going to get negative
news about your,
your favorite pet feature most
of the time.
Like, you're going to have
this great idea,
and you're going to talk to
the user, and it's going to
turn out that that nobody
actually wants that.
Like no, no one's actually,
they're actually completely
concerned about completely
different things and
they don't care about what you
thought was important at all.
And and that's a little bit
sad but just, just think about
how sad you'd be in four
months when you launched that
feature and it turns out no
one actually wants to use it.
So think that's about it for
my the lecture section of what
we're we're talking about.
I want to take some questions
from the audience.
>> What you see startups get
most wrong about?
I mean, most startups don't do
them at all, but
the ones that do what are the
most common mistakes?
>> I'd say, the most common
mistakes are,
showing people your product.
don't, don't show them you're
product.
It's, it's sort of like
telling them about a feature,
you want to learn about what's
already in their heads, your,
you want to avoid putting
things there.
The other thing is, asking
about your,
your pet feature direction, so
if you think you want to add,
add subscriptions to your
product.
Going and asking people would
you pay for a subscription.
Going and asking them, would
you use this feature.
And I'd say the the other big
mistake people make is
talking to who's available
rather than talking to
who they need to talk to.
There's certain users that are
really easy to get at,
because they are say, members
of your forum already.
Right?
You have some product forum,
and you talk to the users on
that forum because they're,
they're easier to get access
to.
we, we spent like weeks
digging for
identity information, and
figuring who these people
were.
So we could contact them, so
we could talk to them.
Because a lot of these people
weren't, it wasn't obvious.
They were just some user on a,
on a site.
And if that site didn't
support messaging, there was,
like, no obvious way to
interact with them.
And so we spent a bunch of
time trying to network, and
find those users, and bring
them on.
Because if you, if you just
talk to who's easy to talk to,
you're not really getting,
getting the best data.
The fortunate side there is
that almost everyone is
flattered to be asked what
they think.
And so most of them will
actually talk to you and
tell you things.
Yeah?
>> How hard is it to
get buy in from the rest of
your company?
I mean, like, you can go and
be like, whatever, I'm in
charge.
So you're doing what I say.
But it's probably not the best
way of doing it.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So how did you get them to?
>> That's a good question.
So the question is how hard is
it to get buy in
from the rest of the company
and how do you do it?
Getting buy in if you just go
to them and
say, I figured out, I talked
to the user,
I figured it out we have to
build this.
Is really hard.
Because people don't trust
you.
There's something magic about
showing them in
the interview though.
So I really recommend you
record interviews.
Recording interviews is like
magic.
A, it stops you from taking
notes in the middle.
And taking notes is a little
bit disruptive.
It makes it harder for you to
feel like you're actually
engaged in the conversation.
And b, you can then play that
recording for people.
So when, when they don't have
to be there for
the entirety of all of the
interviews.
But when you want to make a
point about what,
what we should be building and
why.
You just playback for the rest
of the company that interview
and it's it's like magic the
influence it has on people's
thoughts and what's what the
right thing to build is.