https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAws7eXItMk
And if you're talking to
college students,
as a consumer.
the, you're going to get a lot
out of students,
about, what their current note
taking habits are.
And, you know, what they would
be excited about.
One of the problems with
selling things to
college students, is that,
college students don't
actually spend very much
money.
it's, it's really hard to get
you guys to open your wallets.
Especially, if you want.
Them to pay for a
school-related thing.
And if you don't even want to
buy text books,
right, I think you probably,
probably all use or
that you know, borrow it from
your friend or whatever.
And so one of the like,
one of the things that I think
you'd be missing if you go
after just the students,
right, is you want to.
Figure out who,
who is the most important
person to this, to this app.
And if you're actually in a
note-taking app,
my guess is for colleges, the
people most likely to
actually buy a note-taking app
that you guys would used,
would be College IT.
Right, I mean, presumably for
most, for
the most part, if you want to
sell software to students,
like the people who have to
get
bought into that is usually
the school administrator.
So that would be one, that
would be one approach,
if you like thought that they
will.
You presumably go talk to the
College students and
you find out they don't
actually,
buy any note-taking software
right now at all.
I mean, likely.
It's possible they do in which
case I'm,
I'm complete wrong and this is
where you actually have to go
talk to the users but
you then have to try to maybe
try other, other groups right.
So I would talk to college,
I would talk to IT
administrators, as well.
Think that's another.
Area that's really promising.
You might lo, talk to parents.
Right?
Who, who,
who spends money on their
kids' Education and
is like willing to pull their
wallet out?
Like, the, you know, parents
of kids.
Parents of kids, who are
freshmen who are going off to
college for the first time.
You need this app to make your
kid productive so
that they don't fail out of
College.
and, and as I see a lot of
groups that are potential,
that aren't necessarily,
the obvious user, but who are
critical,
critical to your app's
success, potentially.
And when you, when you're at
the very beginning of
a startup like this, when
you're like,
you have this idea that you
think is awesome.
You want to have that broadest
group you possibly can.
You don't just want to talk to
one type of person and,
and, and learn that.
You want to get familiar with
the space.
the various kinds of
people who be contributing.
All right.
So lets lets have somebody
come up and we're going to,
we're going to pretend we're
going to the senior interview.
So we're going to talk to a
college student and
try to find out what we should
build.
You know, what we should get
into this note-taking app.
So, so, some, another
volunteer please for, for
running an interview.
Yes.
All right, so hello.
>> Hi, I'm Stephanie.
>> Hi, Stephanie.
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Welcome, thank you for
agreeing to do this user
interview with us.
So I, I wanted to, hear from
you about you know,
what are your note-taking
habits.
How do you take notes today?
>> Sure, so I take notes in a
variety of ways.
I like to now because of speed
and efficiency and
just to come back to it later,
it's easier for
me to just take notes on my
lap top.
And so a lot of those notes
will be primarily, text based.
But in certain classes.
So, for example,
if I'm taking a History class,
most of it will be in text.
But if I'm taking it, taking a
Physics class for
example they're going to be
more complex diagrams,
different angles that I have
to draw and
so that's little harder work,
harder for me to-
>> What's-
>> Get.
>> What software do you use
for this stuff today?
>> I just do pen and paper for
that.
>> You do pen and paper, so
you do a combination.
You take notes with pen and
paper, you take notes-
>> Exactly.
>> With your
computer sometimes.
>> Yeah.
>> And when you take notes
with when you take all these
notes, again it's like,
do you actually review them?
Like, do you, be honest, do
you actually go back and
actually ever look at these
notes?
>> The pen and paper not so
much.
But yes to the software-based,
because it's more easy to
access and it's easier for me
to, to share and collaborate
and maybe even merge notes
with classmates and friends.
>> So what do what do you
use to take notes today on
your computer?
Google Docs and Evernote.
>> Google Docs and Evernote?
>> Mm-hm.
>> And ,.
>> And.
>> Tell me more about
like why two things at the
same time.
>> So Evernote is easy, if I'm
trying to just collect it for
myself, I think.
And yes you can share, but I
think Google Docs for
me is easier to share and that
depends also if, you know,
a friend has already created a
folder.
For example on Google Docs and
I just have to add to that
folder if it's a group project
for example versus if it's for
my personal use I, I tend to
go more toward.
>> So it sounds like you do
a lot of note-taking
collaboration.
>> Yeah.
>> What-
>> I wish it was integrated
>> What tell me
more about that.
Like, like, do you take as,
do you want up taking most of
the notes, most of
the value of the notes out of
notes other people take?
Or is it mostly your own notes
you review at
the end of a semester?
How does that work?
>> It's mostly, mine because
I'm pretty picky about
the way I like things
organized.
like, design wise, or
formatting.
Even color, I'm really
particular with.
And, like, the font that we
use.
And that really affects the
way I study.
So, I tend to like, to like,
to like to personalize it,
even after I merge.
>> So, you, you pull in notes
from other people.
But then you merge them into,
into the main.
>> What works for me.
>> Right.
awesome.
And if you, if you have
Evernote notes and
you have Google Docs notes and
you have pen and paper notes.
>> Mm-hm,
>> Once the semester's over do
you ever go back to any of
that stuff or is it
like the quarter end, you guys
do have quarters here, right?
>> Yeah.
>> One the quarter's over
do you ever go back to any of
that stuff?
Do you ever?
>> For classes not so much but
if it's notes I've taken for
like talks like these, for
example, or
if it's like interview prep
that I'm doing.
I tend to go back because of
things that I like to kind of
keep fresh in my mind.
And to help me prep for, for
future things.
>> So that's interesting.
Tell more about that.
Like you take notes not just
in class?
>> Yeah, so I take notes to,
also to summarize main points.
So if it's like inspirational
quotes.
For example talks that I go to
like these.
And then like, maybe I'm going
to an event where I'm
actually going to meet someone
and it,
it helps to actually to think
about and
to remember and recall what we
shared at the time that,
you know, I attended the talk
or something.
>> Awesome.
All right.
Well, normally I'd
actually dig into a lot more
detail.
There's a huge amount of like,
open questions that
are still in my mind after
hearing that stuff.
Questions about, which people
do you collaborate with.
Questions about whether or
not you like, like what the
volume of notes are.
And like how, how long of, of
note-taking stuff.
Just sort of, digging in to
like what the current behavior
is.
But like in interest of time
and not like keeping everyone
here hearing about the
intricacies of one person's
note-taking habits forever
we're going to move on.
But thank you very much
Stephanie that was,
appreciate that.
So so that, that's like, that
kind of stuff,
you notice we're not talking
about the actual content of
the app at all.
Like, I'm not, I'm not,
I'm not really interested in
features.
I don't really want to know
about what they,
the specific feature set in
Google Docs and Evernote.
I might start digging in a
little bit more into,
which features actually get
used.
Like if she's actively
collaborating.
You know is, how does that
work?
I heard some interesting
things about oh,
we, we use folders.
That's interesting to me.
But the main thing you're
trying to do when you're
running these first set of
interviews is not necessarily
get, like, questions about
like user flows and
like optimizing that, or
questions about
like the specifics of of, of
any of that stuff.
kind of can be distracting
because users think they
know what they want.
But like you, you get the you
get
the horseless carriage effect,
where you're, you're you're,
you're getting asked for a
faster horse instead of
trying to design the actual
real solution to the problem.
If you start asking people
about features, so
you want to stay as far away
from features as
possible because the the
things they tell you.
Wind up feeling, almost
overwhelmingly real.
When you have a real user
asking you for
a feature, it's almost, it's
very hard to say no to them.
Because here's a real person
who really has this problem,
and they, they're saying build
me this feature.
But as you start to talk to
lots of people and
really get a sense for what,
what their problems are, you
figure out if this is actually
a promising area or not.
And like, based on what I
heard there, it's like.
Starting from that interview,
I'm not necessarily positive
there is a problem or
there's at least there's a,
there's a big enough problem
that it's worth building a
whole new product for.
Because I didn't hear a lot of
like things were were were.
There was a, a big blocker, or
there was something really
wrong with the way it, the way
it was working.
Unless I had some big idea I
would take that as,
you know, maybe a negative
sign.
But it doesn't necessarily
mean that you can't,
you can't move forward and
keep talking to more people.
Because just because you talk
to the first person and
you don't get anything out of
it,
doesn't mean there's not going
to be.
A ton more people, who
actually have a problem.
And you, once you talk to
about six, seven,
eight people you're usually
about done.
It's unlikely you're going to
discover a bunch of