https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EHzvmyMJEK4
people who understand what
they're getting into,
and understand what you're
getting into in terms of
future dilution.
>> Okay.
So you're raising money, you
understand what you're
selling, you figured out the
price,
you've got down the logistics
that Kirstie just described.
But what you may find is that
you don't understand some of
the terms and terminology that
your investors are using.
And this okay, but
you have a burden to go figure
that stuff out.
Don't assume that just because
you've agreed on the valuation
of the price that all the
other stuff doesn't matter,
because it does matter, and
you need to know how these
terms are going to impact your
company in the long run.
At Y Combinator Chris and
I hear founders say all the
time, I didn't know
what that was, I didn't know
what I was signing, you know?
I, I didn't know I agreed to
that.
So, really, the burden is on
you to figure this,
to figure this stuff out.
And we're going to go over
four common investor requests.
So, the first one is, board
seat.
Some investors will ask for
a seat on your company's board
of directors.
And the investor usually wants
to be a director,
either because he or
she really wants to keep tabs
on their money.
Or because he or
she really thinks they can
help you run your business.
And you have to be
really careful about adding an
investor to your board.
In most cases, you want to say
no.
Otherwise, make sure it's
a person who's really going to
add value.
Having money is very valuable,
but someone who really helps
with strategy and direction is
priceless, so choose wisely.
The other thing, is advisors.
There are so many people who
want to give advice to
startups, and so few people
who actually give good advice.
Once an investor has given
your company money,
that person should be a
defacto advisor.
But without any official
title, and
more importantly without the
company having to
give anything extra in return
for the advice.
So here's an example.
At Y Combinator we've noticed
that
whenever a startup manages to
garner a celebrity investor,
the celebrity almost always
asks to be an advisor.
We have a company that
provides on demand bodyguard
services, and an MBA
basketball player invested.
Ask to be an advisor, and then
asked to be given shares of
common stock in exchange for
the advisor services.
And the services that this
person had in mind,
this investor had in mind,
would be to introduce his
company around to all the
other professional basketball
players who might want to use
an on demand bodyguard.
But, this celebrity just made
a big investment.
Shouldn't he want to help the
company succeed anyway?
Why does he need something
extra?
All investors who can help,
should do so.
Asking for additional shares
is
just an investor looking for a
freebie.
Okay, next we're going to talk
about pro-rata rights.
What are pro-rata rights.
Some of you may have heard of
this before.
But, very simply its the right
to maintain your
percentage ownership in a
company by buying more shares
in the company in the future.
Pro-rata rights are a way to
avoid dilution, and
dilution in this context means
owning less and
less of the company each time
the company sells more stock
to other investors.
So, this is a really basic
example but,
say an early investor buys
shares of preferred stock and
ends up owning 3% of the
company once the financing
has closed.
And the company raises another
round of financing, and
the company will go to this
investor who negotiated and
got pro-rata rights and say,
hey, we're raising more money.
So you're welcome to buy,
you know, this many shares in
the new round to keep your
ownership at approximately 3%,
that is pro-rata rights at
their very most basic.
So pro-rata rights are a very
common request for,
from investors, and they are
not necessarily a bad thing.
But you absolutely as
a founder need to know how
pro-rata rights work.
Especially because, Kirstie
touched on this a little bit.
The corollary to an investor
having pro-rata
rights to avoid dilution,
is that the founders typically
suffer greater dilution.
The final thing is information
rights.
Investors almost always want
contractual information rights
about,
to get certain information
about your company.
Giving periodic information
and
status updates is not a bad
thing.
In fact at YC we encourage
companies to
give monthly updates to their
investors, because
it's a great opportunity to
ask for help for
your, from your investors,
like introductions or
help with hiring, that kind of
thing.
But you have to be really
careful about overreach.
And the investor who's saying
they want like a month budget,
or a weekly update, that's not
okay.
So the take-away here is that
just because
the type of financing and the
valuation has been negotiated,
doesn't mean that everything
else is unimportant.
You need to know everything
about your financing.
>> Okay, so then moving on to
after you've got that money.
You know, you've raised some
money the, the company bank
accounts probably showing more
zeros than at,
than you've ever seen in your
life.
So, so then what?
This is where
you actually start incurring
business expenses.
And business expenses are the
cost of carrying out
your business.
So things like paying
employees paying rent for
an office, hosting costs,
acquiring customers,
that kind of thing.
And business expenses are
important,
because they get deducted on
the company's tax return
to offset any revenues that
are made to
lower the taxes that the
company pays.
And on the flip side,
if it's a non-business expense
that the company incurs,
then that is not deductible on
the tax return, so
that can increase the profits
that the company then have to
pay tax on.
So, again, this is, this is a
separation issue.
The company will have its own
bank accounts, and
that's where the company's
expenses should be paid
out of.
again, you know, thinking
about this from a,
from a large company, if you
were working at Google,
you would not use a Google
credit card to buy
a toothbrush and toothpaste.
So the other thing to remember
is that, you know,
the investors gave you this
money.
They trusted you with all
these huge amounts of, of,
of money, and they want you to
use that money to make the
company a success.
It's not your money for you to
spend how you please.
And believe me, we've had some
horror stories of founders who
take that approach.
We had, we had one founder
that we knew of who took
investor money and went off to
Vegas.
And boy by his Facebook photos
did he have a good time.
Needless to say he's no longer
with the company.
But really this is, this is
stealing from the investors.
You know, think about it the,
the concept of business
expenses can get a little bit
blurry especially in
the early days when you're
working outside,
working in your apartment and
your working 24 hours a day.
But the way to think about it
is,
if an investor asked me what
I'd spent their money on, and
I have to give a line by line
breakdown of that,
would I be embarrassed about
telling any of the,
telling them what any of those
lines were?
And if you were, it's probably
not a business expense.
So, the other thing to bear in
mind is that, you know,
you're busy running your
company at 90 miles an hour,
just constant, constant.
So you don't have to
necessarily think about
the bookkeeping and accounting
at that point, but it's really
crucial that you do keep the
receipts, so that when you do
engage a bookkeeper or a CPA
to prepare your tax returns.
They can unpick all of this
and
they can figure out what are
business expenses and
what aren't business expenses.
But they're going to need your
help as a founder, because
they aren't going to know what
all these things are.
So, there is some involvement
from you and the way to
make the involvement the least
amount possible,
is to keep those documents in
a safe place,
so you can refer back to them.
So, if nothing else that you
remember do not go to
Vegas on investors money and
spend that money wisely.
>> Okay, so in this section
we're going to talk about just
doing business and, we're
going to hit a couple of
couple of topics in this
section.
So the first one is founder
employment.
Why are we talking about
founder employment?
Because, as we said a couple
times already,
the company is a separate
legal entity.
It exists completely separate
and apart from U.S.
founders, and so no matter how
prestigious we in
the valley think the title
founder is, you're
really just a company employee
and founders have to be paid.
Working for free is against
the law,
and founders should not let
their company take on
this liability.
You wouldn't work for
free anywhere else, so why is
your startup an exception?
And companies have to pay
payroll taxes.
We had a YC company that
completely blew
off their payroll taxes for
three years, it was a huge,
expensive disaster, and
in extreme cases, people can
actually go to jail for
that, fortunately not in this
case, but it's bad.
So the moral of this story is
setup a payroll service.
This is something that is
worth spending your money on.
But, and I actually I think,
I'm sure some of
the other lecturers have
touched on this points, and
actually Kirsty just mentioned
too.
Don't go overboard on lavish
salaries, minimum wage this is
still a startup and you have
to run lean.
So now I'm going to mention
founder break ups,
and first, well what is a
founder break up?
In this context I'm talking
about one found,
founder on the team being
asked to leave the company.
Which, because I've just said
founders are employees,
that means your cofounders are
firing you.
So why are we talking about
breakups in the context of
founder compensation, and it's
because, at YC we have seen
a ton of founder breakups and
we know that the breakups get
extra ugly when the founders
haven't paid themselves.
Why, how does it get ugly?
Unpaid wages become leverage
for
the fired founder to get
something he or she wants from
the company, and typically
that is vesting acceleration.
So the fired founder says,
hey,
my lawyer says you broke the
law by not paying me.
But if you pay me, and
you give me some shares that
I'm not actually entitled to,
I'll sign a release and make
all this ugliness go away, and
if you're the remaining
cofounders,
you're probably like, sounds
like a good deal.
And so now you have a
disgruntled person who
owns a piece of your company
and even worse in a sense,
the remaining founders are
kind of working for
that ex-founder, right?
Because they're building all
the value in the company and
the ex-founder who got fired
is just sitting there with
their shares going, that's
right, make it valuable.
So, what's the takeaway here?
Avoid problems by paying
yourself, paying your
payroll taxes, and thinking up
of your co-founder's wages
like a marital prenup.
>> And as well as the
founders,
you are going to need to hire
employees.
And again, a lot's been spoken
in previous,
in previous classes here about
how to find those people,
what makes a good fit,
how to make them really
productive employees.
But when you actually find
somebody, how,
how do you hire them?
You know, what's, what's
involved?
And employment is governed by
a huge raft of laws, and
therefore it's important to
get this right.
It's again the kind of
nitty-gritty stuff that as
long as you know the basics
you can probably keep yourself
out of most situations, but as
soon as things get complicated
you need to get yourself
involved with a specialist.
So the first thing you need to
do is figure out if
the employee or
if the person is really an
employee or a contractor, and
there are subtle differences
to this classification.
And this is important to get
right because the IRS
takes a big interest in this
and if they think you've got
it wrong they will come after
you and with fines.
Both an employee and a
contractor will sign documents
that assign any IP that they
create to the company, and
that's obviously really
important.
But the, the form of the
document is very different for
each, each type of person and
the method of payment's very
different.
So generally, a contractor
will be able to set their own
work hours, they'll be able to
set their own location.
They will be given a project
where there is an end result,
but how they actually get to
that and
the means they use will, will
not be set.
They'll be using their own
equipment, and