https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SHAh6WKBgiE
Okay, great.
So okay, great, thanks for
having me.
So, my name's Tyler I'm the
CEO of Clever and
what I want to talk today is
about sales.
And I've a little bit of
insight into this I graduated
college, I actually studied
math and
statistics, probably like some
of you here in this room.
And thought I was destined for
this world of, finance.
I was about to go start at a
hedge fund.
And at the last second, a
friend of mine roped me in to
join his startup, and asked me
to do sales there, which was
something that I knew nothing
about, and so, had to
figure out on the fly, and
spent a couple of years there,
figuring out sales for this
very early stage company.
And then, when it came to
start Clever, you know,
we started Clever, and I did
it with two co-founders who
are very technical, and one
very product-oriented, and
we wanted to build this
product for schools, and I
thought that experience would
have no relevancy whatsoever.
But it turns out that some of
the things that I picked up at
the, this previous job, where
it was figuring out sales,
have been huge parts of what's
made Clever grow so
quickly today.
Quick background on Clever, we
build software for schools.
We are an app platform used by
developers and
it's used today by about one
in five schools in America.
And we started it about two
years ago.
And so sales have been a be,
key piece of that, and
I want to use this time to
just share some of
the things that have worked
for me along the way.
Of course, there's a million
ways to do this,
so you'll find what works for
you.
So first I want to start about
how most,
how I used to perceive sales.
And a lot of people see sales
as having this, you know,
a lot of mystique around it.
You know, it's people who are
you know,
really articulate and
impossibly charming.
And they have these, you know,
killer closing lines that they
use.
And I think this is how I saw
sales, and I think this is
how a lot of founders I talked
to see sales, because they say
things to me like, you know,
we're just going to work on
the product and build a great
product, and then when it's
finally finished we're
going to hire the salespeople.
And what I've learned is that
hire the salespeople,
as a founder, the reality is
that's you.
And so you know, Paul Graham
likes to talk about how
there's two things you should
be doing at any point in
time when you're starting your
company.
You're either talking to your
users or
you're building your product.
And that talking to your users
part, that's selling.
And so.
You know, this is intimidating
to some people because
they're like, I've never done
sales, and I don't,
wouldn't even know where to
begin.
But it turns out that as a
founder,
you have some unique
advantages that make it,
possible for you to be really,
really good at sales.
And one of those is your
passion for
the product, and what you're
building.
And the second is your
industry knowledge of what
your, of the industry and the
problem that you're solving.
And those two things actually
totally trump sales experience
from what I've seen.
So, this is actually my
cofounder, doing sales.
This is what sales,
looks like in the very early
stage of a startup.
It's not Don Draper.
It's a lot of calls like
these.
But this is something that
even as
a founder who's never done it
before, it's very easy to do,
but you have to commit
yourself.
And what we did at Clever was
we dedicated one founder,
which was me, to peel off and
say,
okay, Tyler you're going to go
figure this out and and work
on this full time because it's
so important to our business.
So, couple things that I've
picked up about sales along
the way and in, in trying to
figure this out.
You know, the first thing that
everybody knows about sales is
they say, okay, it's a funnel.
And you have these different
stages of funnels and you, of,
of the funnel and you move
your customers through it.
Pretty common categories.
There's this prospecting
category where
you're trying to figure out
who's even interested.
Then you're having a lot of
conversations,
which is the second level of
the funnel.
Then you're finding out who's
really serious and
you want to close them and
sign the deal.
And then of course,
you're in the promised land
of, of revenue.
And what I thought would be
interesting would be to talk
about each of the stage, a
couple strategies that
we've used at Clever that
have, worked really well.
So that these aren't abstract
things but
things that, you know, you can
hopefully use at your startup.
So, prospecting.
So, prospecting is the process
of
figuring out who will even
take your call.
And you know, one of the
things that I
realized early on, so there's
this guy Everett Rogers who,
who's created this technology
life cycle adoption curve.
And he describes it as bell
curve where you've got you
know, your innovators and who
will try new things, and
you've got your early
adopters,
your mid-stage adopters, your
late adopters, your laggards.
And one of the things that was
really helpful for
me in understanding sales in
an early startup is he's
quantified the tail of this
bell curve and this part over
here, the innovators, those
are your potential customers.
And it might seem discouraging
that only 2.5% of companies
are your potential customers
that would even consider
buying from a startup that has
no users and no revenue.
But actually, I found just the
opposite.
I found it to be extremely
helpful to have this frame of
mind, because you realize,
when only 2.5% of companies
will even take your call or
consider using your product,
you realize what a numbers
game this becomes.
So if you want to reach that
2.5% and
you want to get some early
sales, you, you've,
if you're starting to do math,
you're hopefully starting to
realize you have to do a lot
of calling.
You have to do, talk to a lot
of people.
So early on in the early days
at Clever, this was my job.
You know, in the,
in the 2 months the first two
months of YC,
I reached out to over 400
companies trying to get them
to take a call and and talk to
us about what we're building.
There's, there's three ways
that I
have found most successful in,
in prospecting and
getting these people, one is
your personal network.
That's obvious.
I'm not going to spend any
time there.
Another one is conferences,
which is surprising to a lot
of people, and then the one
that people are most familiar
with is cold email.
And when I say conferences,
this is what people think.
They think I'm talking about
CES or, you know,
E3 or something.
And actually, the kind of
conferences where sales happen
look more like this.
And we've got, we would in the
early days would go to a lot
of these because you've got to
where your users are.
And if they're, if you're
selling to CIOs and there
happens to be a gathering of
them at a hotel in Milwaukee,
guess what, that's probably
where you should be.
So we go to conferences like
these.
We get the attendee lists in
advance.
We email every single person
in advance, and, and try and
set up meetings so that when
we get there,
every single minute of that
trip was, was well spent.
And this was huge in Clever's
early days.
These, this was where we met
all of our earliest customers.
The second thing I mentioned
is cold email.
A lot of people don't know how
to write cold emails.
It's actually really easy, and
the key is not to write a lot.
Should be really concise.
This is an email template that
I used early on and
you're welcome to copy it, but
it's really short.
Here's who I am, here's what
I'm building, and
I'd love to talk to you about
this.
Could we find time tomorrow?
It's really easy and, and you
can customize this and
find out for
every business you want to
sell to who's the right person
to send it to and you can send
out quite a few of these.
So all right, that's
prospecting.
And the reason this is so
important is because you've
gotta build that first layer
of the funnel.
Then you get them to take your
call.
And this is another place
where a lot of
founders I think just have a
lot of
questions about what to
actually do.
And the biggest thing to take
away,
in fact if you only take away
one thing from this
presentation today, the number
one thing you should remember
is when you get them on the
phone, remember to shut up.
And that's really surprising
to people.
So many founders, when I help
them with
their first sales pitch, they
finally get somebody on
the phone who wants to talk to
them about their product.
And they're so proud of this
thing they've been
building for the last three
months that all they want to
do is get on the phone and
talk about every feature and
talk about all the different
things they can do and
talk about why it's the
greatest thing in the world.
And I have that temptation
too.
It's just part of being really
proud of something.
But it turns out that if you
watch the best salespeople,
like the best salespeople in
the world, the top 1%.
And you have a chance to
listen in on a call with some
of those people, like I have,
the most surprising thing is
how little talking they do.
In fact, I've seen calls where
the,
where the salesperson told me
their goal was to
only spend 30% of the call
talking, and
have 70% of the call the other
person.
And they would ask a lot of
questions.
They'd say things like,
why did you even agree to take
my call today?
This problem that we're
talking about solving for you,
how do you solve it today?
You know, what would your
ideal solution look like?
And they're not, they're not
doing the talking.
They're finding, they're doing
everything they can to find
out what this person needs,
and hopefully understand their
problem even better than they
do.
That's what really great sales
is and in fact this is
something I, I, I, I drill
into everybody at Clever.
It's a really important part
of sales and
there's actually now if any of
you use Uber Conference,
they have this amazing feature
where when you hang up
a call it sends you an email
automatically and tells you
how much you talked versus how
much the other person talked.
And looking at one of those
emails you know,
if someone doing sales at
Clever, I get one of those
emails, I can tell immediately
how likely the sale is
based on how much talking we
were doing.
So, you got all these people,
now you got on the phone,
do a lot of listening, really
understand their problem.
And then the other part of
this stage that surprises
a lot of people is follow up.
So here's a lot of different
steps that you
can imagine going through.
You know, emailing somebody,
not getting a response, and
emailing them back.
Calling them, leaving a voice
mail, having a pricing call.
You know, there's probably
like you know,
60 things up here on this
slide that could be steps for
closing a deal.
These actually aren't just
random things,
this is one deal that,
this was the second deal
Clever ever signed.
These are all the different
steps that we had to in
order to get this done.
And you can see there's a lot
of really embarrassing things
up there like I emailed
somebody and they didn't
respond and I emailed them
again and they didn't respond.
And then I emailed them again
and
this is from somebody who
wanted to buy our product.
Isn't that crazy?
Ana that surprises a lot of
people.
I see so many founders today
have a great call with
someone, they send an email,
they dont hear back and
they say, oh that person might
not be interested.
well, guess what,
this is what it looks like in
the best case and.
And so you really have to have
kind of,
this unhuman, unreasonable
willingness to follow up, and
drive things to closure.
Now, qualify with that with
one thing.
Which is to say, when you're
starting a company,
your time is extremely
valuable.
because it's your only
resource.
And, and you couldn't possibly
do this for
every single person who might
buy your product.
So your goal should be to get
people to a yes or
a no, as quickly as you can.
Where you die is if you have a
thousand maybes.
And sometimes I talk to
founders who say oh, yeah,
I have this great pipeline of
you know, a hundred people who
are, who have expressed
interest in our product.