https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SHAh6WKBgiE
when I see companies come to
talk to me,
is that they don't know how to
simply explain what they do,
and then ask for money.
And that's basically what you
have to do as a founder.
So we're going to go over four
things.
The first is what your 30
second pitch is.
This you need to be armed with
constantly.
This is basically, how you
talk about your company.
This is magic.
Whether you're talking to
people who want to give you
money or don't want to give
you money.
You're talking to your
parents.
This is your go to.
The second is your two minute
pitch.
This is for people who are
more interested.
This is people who you might
want to raise money from.
Or people who you might want
to get to work for you, or
people you actually.
Kind need to get a little bit
deeper.
Notice that's where I stop.
A lot of people practice 10,
30 minute pitches,
hour pitches, I think that's
all garbage.
I think you can get everything
you need done in two minutes.
And one thing I like to tell
founders is the more you talk,
the more you have the
opportunity to
say something that people
don't like.
So just talk less and it'll
probably be better.
So, then I want to tell you
about when to fund raise,
because I think a lot of
companies get this a little
bit wrong.
And then, quickly, how to set
up investor meetings.
So, 30 second pitch, this is
so
simple, it's three sentences.
You can take your time, you
can breathe when you do this,
you don't have to get that
much information out.
The first is one sentence on
what does your company do.
Everyone I meet for the first
time screws this up.
You have to be able to do it
in a way that is simple and
straightforward, that requires
no pre-information on my part.
You have to assume I know
nothing, literally nothing,
about anything.
This is how you make it super
simple.
So you know, usually what we
tell people is apply the mom
test.
If in one sentence you cannot
tell your mom what you do,
then rework the sentence.
There is a one sentence
explanation that your mom, or
your dad is going to
understand.
So really, really start there,
and
it's okay if you use really
basic language.
It's okay if you're saying hey
we're Air B and B,
and we allow you to rent out
the extra room in your house.
That's simple, right?
You don't have to say we're
Air B and
B and we're a marketplace for
space.
I don't know what that is.
And it's going to require more
time.
So use simple language.
Very, very important.
The second is how big is your
market?
It makes sense to do a couple
hours of research.
Figure out what general
industry your product is in.
Figure out how big it is.
Investors like to
hear that you're in a
multibillion dollar market.
It's pretty simple to do this.
You know, Air B and
B might say, how big is the
hotel market?
How big is the vacation rental
market?
How big is the online hotel
booking market?
These are simple numbers to
look up on Google.
And it makes an investor
understand, oh wait,
if we're big, if we really
blow this company up,
it can be worth billions of
dollars.
Don't skip this step.
Second sentence, how big is
your market?
Third sentence, how much
traction do you have?
Ideally this sentence is
saying something on
the order of, we launched in
January and
we're growing 30% month over
month.
We have this number of sales,
this amount of revenue,
this number of users.
Very simple.
If you can't speak to traction
in terms of
pre-launch, you need to
convince the investor that
you're moving extremely
quickly.
So, the team started working
in January, by March,
we launched a beta, by April,
we launched our product.
Right?
Convince the investors that
you guys are moving fast.
That this isn't some long slog
that you guys aren't thinking
about this like a big
cooperation.
Your thinking about it
like a startup where you can
move fast and make mistakes.
That's all you have to do in
30 seconds.
Three sentences.
From that basis you should be
able to
start a conversation about
your company.
From that basis I understand
exactly what you do.
You have no unders, you have
no idea how valuable it is to
be able to explain to someone
what you do in 30 seconds,
so really internalize that.
Like if you take nothing else
away,
that's going to help you.
Okay.
Two minute pitch.
Now you've got someone you
actually have to
convince of something.
Maybe even someone you have to
ask for money.
So, I like to add four
additional components and
these also go by very quick.
The first is unique insight.
Now, if you talk to VCs
they'll say stuff like, what's
your secret sauce, what's your
competitive advantage,
what's your unique insight?
It's all the same thing.
When I think about unique
insight,
what I think about is here's
your opportunity to tell me
something that I don't know.
Here's your opportunity to
tell me
something that the biggest
players in the market you're
trying to enter don't
understand or don't do well.
This is the ah-ha moment.
And you'd better have it down
in two sentences.
The ah-ha moment.
So you've gotta crystallize
all of the reasons why you
guys are going to kill the
competitors, or the really
intelligent thought that got
this business started.
In two sentences, and I need
to ah-ha.
You can see whether it's
happening when you're saying
it.
That's why I like two
sentences, so
you get in and out fast.
So if I look at you and I'm
like huh.
Then it's okay, you've nailed
it.
If I look at you and
I'm like, I already knew that,
then you didn't nail it.
If I looked at you and
I just don't understand what
you're talking about,
you definitely didn't nail it.
So, practice that unique
insight.
In your two minute pitch,
that's all, you're only
going to get two sentences to
get that out there, so
it can't be complicated, and
that's basically the theme of
this whole thing right, it
cannot be complicated.
Next, how do you make money?
You know, your business model.
I see so many founders run
away from this question
because they think things
like, if I say advertising,
people are going to be like,
oh, that's stupid.
Just say it.
Don't run away.
If it's advertising, say
advertising.
Facebook's a massive
advertising business.
So is Google.
If it's direct sales, it's
direct sales.
If it's you know, a game and
you're selling in-app in-app
add ups, like that's fine.
Just say it.
Don't run away from this
sentence.
It only has to be one sentence
long.
Where founders get tricked on
how will you make money is,
they say, well, we're going to
run advertising, maybe some
virtual goods, we're going to
figure out how to do this, and
maybe this, and maybe this.
Well, now you're saying
nothing.
Now you've told me you have no
idea how you
want to monetize this.
This was a checkmark that I
just wanted to write, oh,
they know how they're going to
monetize.
Instead, I'm writing a big
question mark.
So, do the thing that everyone
else in your industry does
to monetize 95% of the time.
Say it and move on.
Like, it's totally okay,
no one's going to hold your
feet to the fire and
say three years later, you
didn't monetize this way.
But it's much better to be
clear and
concise than it is to start
spouting out every single way
your company can make money.
The next one is team.
I think that this answer is
actually really clear.
I think you're trying to do
two things.
If your team has done
something
particularly impressive, you
need to call that out.
We were the founders of
PayPal,
probably want to say that.
We were the founders of
Amazon, might,
probably want to say that.
So if you guys have done
something that has
made investors money, you want
to say that.
If not, then please don't go
on about the awards your team
has won, or the PhDs or the I
don't care, I don't care.
What we want to hear is how
many founders.
Hopefully between two and
four.
What we want to hear is how
many of them are technical.
How many engineers versus
business people?
Hopefully it's 50 50 or more
engineers.
We want to hear is that how
long have you
guys known each other.
We don't want to hear you guys
met at
a founders' dating event three
days ago.
ideally, you've known each
other either personally or
professionally for at least
six months.
We want to hear is that you're
all working full-time.
It's really helpful, we're all
committed to this business.
And what we want to hear is
how you met.
That's it.
You can get in and out of that
two sentences very easy.
Your only way to build
credentials is if
you've accomplished something.
And with an investor typically
it's if you've
accomplished something that's
made someone some money.
So don't try to overinflate
yourself if
you don't have that stat on
your resume, move on.
The more you talk about a bad
thing, the worse it looks.
So, the last one is the big
ask.
When it comes to this and you
have to figure out
whether this is a conversation
involves fundraising or not.
What I tell people is like
this is the time where
you kind of have to know what
you're talking about.
This is a time where you have
to know,
are you raising on a
convertible note?
Are you raising on a safe?
You have to know what the cap
of that safe is.
You have to know how much
money you're raising.
You have to know what the
minimum check size is.
These are things where if you
don't know these these things,
investors going to be like, oh
these guys aren't serious, or
they haven't done their
homework.
So whereas in the rest of
this whole thing you shouldn't
use any jargon.
In this part you shouldn't
just be like, oh,
we're just raising some money.
Like now it's time to
actually use a little bit of
that jargon.
If you don't know that jargon,
Google search it,
like, it's real simple.
You guys will learn it fast.
So, that's it by the way.
That's too, that's all your
pitch.
Done, like, game over.
Now you let them talk.
So, when to fundraise.
I think this is so important.
Right, you've got this little
Growth graph here.
Investors like to invest based
on traction.
And so literally it's always
better to raise money when
you've got more traction than
less.
Often times though,
you guys'll be in a situation
where you're just starting.
Or maybe you just launched.
So what you need to do is you
need to think about how do
you flip the equation?
Your entire mindset should be,
typically you are the ones
asking investors for
money and therefore they are
strong and you're weak.
How do you create a scenario,
where you are strong and they
are weak?
Right?
That's where you want to be
fundraising.
So first, how do you know that
you're strong?
If investors are asking you to
give you money, you're strong.
That might be a good time to
start fundraising.