https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=59ZQ-rf6iIc
so, 11 months after you
launch, or
first publicly talk about what
you're doing.
Is a good time to file
provisional patents.
We recommend people just file
All that does is just hold
your place in line at
the patent office and it gives
you another year to decide if
you want to patent something
or not.
It only costs about $1000.
It takes way less effort than
a full patent.
And most of the time you'll
know whether or
not you need full patent a
year later.
But if you just do this one
step,
you'll at least have the
option.
It's also a good time to file
trademarks for the U.S. and
major international markets.
again, if you don't do this at
this stage,
most people end up regretting
it.
And while you're at it, a good
time to grab all the domains.
FP&A, good time also I think
to
think about someone to start
doing FP&A.
I think most companies don't
end up realizing where
the knobs on their financial
model are until far too late.
And I think it turns out that
if you have
someone build a really great
model of the business.
And by really great,
apparently Roelof Botha,
who was the PayPal CFO and
built their FP&A model.
The top, the, like,
the top sheet of his
spreadsheet was 1,500 lines,
just as a level of the detail
people build these to.
But you can really optimize
the business and understand it
at a level that I think most
people totally miss.
Most people don't hire someone
like
this until they're many
hundreds of employees.
I think it's worth hiring
earlier.
Another thing that I think is
worth hiring earlier
that almost no one does is a
full time fundraiser.
Let's say you hire someone
like really, really great and
their full time job is to
raise money for the company.
You hire them after your b
round.
And you say, you know what,
by the time we raise our c
round we want the evaluation
to be double what it would
have been otherwise.
You almost certainly get
better results than if you
hire an investive banker or
someone else if it's just
someone internal to the
company and you end up paying
way less money, and take like
literally half the dilution.
So, I think this is one of
these like, slightly none
obvious optimizations that
people just failed to make.
Tax structuring, so, this is
another thing.
most, once things are working.
It would be worth you spending
a little bit of time thinking
about how you set up the tax
structure for the company.
I confess, I don't know a lot
about the details here
because I just find it
personally really boring.
But like somehow if you assign
all the IP to like some
corporation in Ireland that
licenses it back to the U.S.
corporation, you end up paying
like no tax, no corporate tax.
But I know you can only do
that like relatively early on.
And this ends up being a huge
issue for companies that
don't do it that compete with
companies that do do it.
You know once they're big,
public companies.
So that's worth doing.
A lot of people throughout the
class have talked about
your own psychology as a
founder.
Here's what they haven't said.
It gets worse, not better.
As the company grows, you
continue to oscillate.
The highs are better but the
lows keep getting worse.
And, you, you really want to
think about this early on and
just be aware this is going to
happen.
And try to try to manage your
own psychology through
the expanding swings that it's
going to go through.
Another thing that happens as
you begin to be successful.
As you go from being someone
that most people rooted for,
kind of the underdog,
to someone that a lot of
people start hating on.
And you know,
you see this first in internet
commenters who will be,
like, I can't believe this
**** company raised money.
It **** sucks, like, awful.
And it only bothers you a
little bit, but then, like,
journalists that you kind of
care about start writing this,
and it just goes on and on.
This also will go on and on as
you get more and
more successful, and
you just have to make peace
with this early.
But if you don't,
it will bother you all the way
through.
This is also a good time to
start thinking about
how long of a journey this is
going to be.
Very few founders think long
term.
Most founders think kind of a
year in advance.
And they think that you know
what
in three years I'm going to
sell my company and either I'm
going to become a VC or sit on
the beach or something.
Because so
few people make an actual long
term commitment to what
they're building, the ones
that do have a huge advantage.
They're, they're in a very
rarefied class, and so this is
a good time to like sit around
with your cofounders and
decide, you know what, we're
going to work on this for
a very long time.
And we're going to build a
strategy that assumes that
we're going to be doing this
for the next ten years.
Just thinking that way alone,
I think is probably,
a very high leverage thing you
can do for success.
Take vacation.
Another common thing that we
see is founders will run their
business for three or four
years, without ever taking,
you know, more than a day of
vacation.
And that works for like a
year, or two years, or
something like that.
It really leads to nasty
burnout if you don't do it.
Losing focus is another way
that founders get off track.
I actually think this is a
symptom of burnout.
When you get really burned out
on running the business,
you want to do easier things,
or
sort of more gratifying
things.
You want to go to conferences,
and
have people tell you how great
you are.
You know, you want to do all
these things that are not
actually building the
business.
And the most common post-YC
failure case for
the companies we fund is that
they're incredibly focused,
during YC, on their company,
and then after,
they start doing a lot of
other things.
You know, they, they advise
companies.
They go to conferences,
whatever.
Focus is what made you
successful in the first place.
There are a lot of reasons
people lose focus, but
fight against that really,
really hard.
This is a special case of
focus.
As you start to do well.
You will start to get a bunch
of potential acquires
sniffing around.
And it's very gratifying.
And you're like wow, I can be
so rich and that'd be so cool.
And negotiations feel really
fun.
This is one the biggest
killers of, of companies is
that they entertain
acquisition conversations.
You, you distract yourself.
You get demoralized if it
doesn't happen.
If an offer does come in and
it's really low,
you've already like mentally
thought that you're done, and
so you take the offer.
As a general rule, don't start
any acquisition conversation
unless you're willing to sell
for a pretty low number.
Don't ever just check it
hoping that
you're going to have the one
miracle high offer.
If that's going to happen
you'll know.
Because they'll just make you
a big offer before you can
meet them.
But this, this is a big
company killer.
And then just as a reminder to
everybody the thing that
kills startups at some level
is the founders giving up.
So sometimes you should quit.
But, if you mismanage your own
psychology and you quit when,
when you shouldn't, that, that
is what kills companies.
I mean that is, that is the
sort of final closet death
in most of these start ups.
And so if you can manage your
own psychology in a way that
you don't quit.
Dont go to place a where you
need to quit, or
give up on the startup.
You'll be in a far, far better
place.
So, marketing and PR is
something that
we tell companies to ignore
for a long time.
Everyone thinks in the early
days that the press is going
to be what saves them.
We tell them all the time it
doesn't work that way.
It's definitely true.
You know, press is not what's
going to save your startup.
But as you start to be
successful,
this is something that the
founders themselves need to
spend time on.
So, once your product is
working,
switch from not caring about
this,
to caring about it a little
bit.
And, the two most important
things for
the founder to do, the
founders to do.
Figure out the key messaging
yourselves.
Never outsource this to your
head of marketing or PR firm.
You, founders have to figure
out what the message of
the compay is going to be.
And once you set that, it
kind of sticks.
It's very hard to change this
once the press decides how
they're going to talk about
you.
The other thing is getting to
know key journalists yourself.
PR firms will always try to
prevent you from doing this,
because they need to have a
reason to exist.
And so they're like, well,
we're going to
handle the relationship with
the journalist.
We'll just bring you in for
interviews.
No journalist wants to talk to
a PR flack, ever.
They're so much more happy to
just hear from a founder.
I think the biggest PR hack
you can do,
is to not hire a PR firm.
Just pick three or four
journalists that
you develop really close
relationships with,
that like you, that understand
you, that you get.
And then you contact them
yourself.
They will cover every story
you ever give them,
and they'll actually pay
attention, get to know you and
care about the company.
This is so much better than
the normal strategy of having
a PR firm blast 200 contacts
that never read their e-mails,
with every piece of news.
so, this is something that I
think is important to start
doing.
This is also the time in
a company when business
development starts to matter.
And so, in the early days you
can
basically ignore anything that
would be like doing deals,
except maybe fund raising and
sales.
You know, this is the time
when they're important.
And everything, or many things
that you do,
like even fundraising, falls
under the,
the category of doing deals.
So there are,
here's my one-minute crash
course on this.
There are five points that I
think are important to
understand here.
We've talked about this a lot.
Nothing will serve,
nothing will matter if you
don't build a great product.
So assume that you've done
this before you go try and
get anyone to do anything with
you.
Developing a personal
connection with anyone
you're trying to do any sort
of big deal with,
is really important.
For whatever reason, most
founders fail to do this, or
many founders fail to do this.
But no one wants to feel like
they're this transactional
thing, that you're using them
to get distribution for
your product, or to raise
money, or whatever.
And, so figuring out some way
to actually care about
this person and care about
what you're doing with them.
And not view them, you have to
in your own mind not
just view them as a one off
transaction.
You have to actually care
about them and
what they're going to get out
of this.
Competitive dynamics,
so this is like basic
principle of negotiation.
Most funders learn this the
first time in fundraising but
it actually matters for
everything.
The way you get deals done,
and
the way you get good terms,
is to have a competitive
situation.
You know, if you don't do this
deal with party A,
you're going to do it with
party B.
It's not always an option, but
it usually is, and this is,
like, the single thing that
makes deals happen and
makes deals move.
Tyler talked about persistence
the last lecture so
I won't hit on that again too
much, other than to say,
you have to go beyond your
comfort point here,
most of the time as a founder.
And then, the fifth point is
you have to ask for
what you want.
This is another thing, I still
have trouble with this, and
certainly most of the founders
we do.
Have, you know,
if you want something to deal,
just ask for it.
Most of the time, you know,
you won't get laughed out of
the room and you might get it.
But you have to be like,
at some point you actually
have to say,
you know this is what I'd like
you to do.
Even if it feels aggressive or
an overreach, or whatever.
So I'm going to close,
this part of the talk with an
image.
One of the Airbnb founders
drew this on
like a business card or
something for another founder
that was starting a company.
And then I saw it once and
took a picture of it.
Because I thought it was such
a good summary.
And what he had tried to draw
here was the Ycombinator
process as he remembered it.
And I love it because it's
like so simple, and
it looks so do-able when it's
written on a business card.
But you're trying to find
product market fit.
You know, you're trying to
build a product, and
you're trying to close the gap
between those two gears.
The only way to do that is to
go off and meet the people.
You cannot do this without
getting really,
really close to your users.
And then he drew this graph
that,
sort of on a whiteboard at YC
and got in kind of,
like, one of the YC he writes
a passage, but that's
the graph of how adoption goes
for a new company.
So you launch in the press,
you get a huge spike.
It falls off to nothing.
At some point, at least one
point,
things look like they're
going to completely die and
kind of dip below the x-axis.
They recover a little bit.
You have this long, long,
long trough of sorrow before
things work.
In Airbnb's case,
it was 1,000 days before the
graph started ticking upward.