https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=59ZQ-rf6iIc
You have these wiggles of
false hope, and then finally,
finally, finally, things start
to grow.
Three years later.
So starting a startup ends up
being this very long process.
It is, you know, it can be
really rewarding.
It's definitely long, but it
is do-able.
And that's what I love about
that drawing.
So, with that, I think I have
about ten minutes left.
I can answer questions on
this, or
anything else in the course
that we've covered.
If anyone has some.
Yes.
>> You have that diversity
being important, but
an earlier speaker said
diversity wasn't important and
you should just hire people
that are very much like you,
and then you can cross.
>> So, here is the the
question is, how do you you
square the device of diversity
being important with earlier
speakers saying you want
people that are very similar.
the, the difference what you
want is you want diversity of
backgrounds, but you don't
want diversity of vision.
Like where companies get in
trouble is
when they have people think
very differently about what
the company should be doing,
or don't work well together.
You don't want that.
You do want to hire people
that you know, and
that you trust and that you
can work with.
But if everyone on the team
comes from exactly the same
background you end, you do end
up developing somewhat of
a mono-culture which often
causes problems down the road.
Not always.
Some companies have been
successful with that.
So what, what we tell people
is, hire people that you know
and that you've worked with
before.
But try to hi,
try to hire people that are
complementary and
align towards the same goal,
not people that are exactly
the same.
because you just get a, a
better skill set.
Yeah.
>> What are some examples of
ways to make a transition back
to a more personal level,
especially when you're really.
>>
>> How to keep track,
productivity systems.
So, the one I use, which
actually I think works really
well, is I keep one piece of
paper with my goals for
sort of a three to 12 month
time frame.
And I look at that every day.
And then separately I keep
one, one page for
every day of my short term
goals for that day.
And so if I need to do
something in like a week,
I just flip forward seven
pages and write it down, and
then I also keep a list of
every person and
what they're working on, and
what I need to tell them, and
what I need to talk to them
about,
what we talked about last
time.
So every time I sit down with
someone,
I kind of have the full
statement,
a list of things for that
person that works really well.
Yes.
>> So we talked about that
startup growing.
But most startups fail.
>> Yeah.
>> Any advice for
kind of fail gracefully.
>> Yeah.
>>
>> How to fail gracefully.
So, most startups fail,and
Silicon Valley almost goes
too far in how much it loves
failure.
Failure still sucks.
You should still try not to
fail.
And this whole, like, thing,
of like, failure's great, I, I
don't agree with.
But it will happen to most
people most of the time,
and it's a very forgiving
environment.
As long as you are upfront
about it, and
ethical, and don't let anyone
get into a bad situation.
So, if you're failing, first
of all,
you should tell your
investors.
And, second of all, you should
not totally run out of money.
What you don't want is a
blow-up with a bunch of, you
know, debts that the company
owe, and everyone, you know,
showing up to work, one day,
and the door being locked.
You'll know when you're
failing,
you'll know when the company
is,
things just aren't going to
work,
and you should just tell your
investors.
Like, hey, sorry, this isn't
going to work.
No one will be surprised.
Like, I expect to lose my, or
I'm willing to lose my money
on every investment I ever
make.
I know that happens most of
the time, and
the winners pay for it,
you know, still with a factor
of 100, so it's okay.
No one, people will be very
understanding and supportive.
But you want to tell people
early.
You don't want to surprise
them.
And you want, you don't
want to like
let your employees gets
shocked when they learn they
don't have a job.
you know, you, you,
you want to shut the company
down in a graceful way.
Help them find jobs.
Make sure you give them two or
four weeks of severance
payment, so that they're not
suffering a cash flow problem.
All that stuff is pretty
important.
Yes.
>> How many immigrant founders
have you seen in Y Combinator?
have we seen in Y Combinator?
In the last batch, I think it
probably went up for
this next batch, in the last
batch 41% of the founders we
funded were born outside the
US.
From 30 different countries.
So it's.
Yeah a pretty big percentage.
>> What do you think are other
good places to
start a start up?
>> Apart from the Valley where
do I
think are other good places to
start a start up?
Well I still think the Valley
is
the best by a very significant
margin.
But I think it's finally,
maybe beginning to weaken a
little bit.
Because the costs have just
gotten so out of control.
To be clear, if I
was going to start a company I
still wouldn't think about.
I would still pick Silicon
Valley.
And I think if you look at the
data of companies over
the last few years, Valley
still wins by a lot.
But Seattle, LA, lots of
places outside the U.S., I
think all of these make sense.
>> Like what places outside?
I hesitate to make
recommendations there
because I haven't spent enough
time in
this cities to really have an
intuitive feel.
but, like, I mean, you, you
know as well as
I do the common ones people
talk about, startup hubs,
and I just, I can't make a
personal recommendation there.
>> Hire a professional CEO or
like a senior.
>> When should the founders
think about
hiring a professional CEO?
Never.
you, if you look at the most
successful.
Companies in tech, they are
run by their founders for
a very long time, sometimes
forever.
And sometimes they even hire a
professional CEO and then
realize that that is not going
to like build a great company.
And so, like Larry Page came
back to CEO again.
I think, if you don't want to
be the long-term CEO of
a company, you probably
shouldn't start one.
I'm not totally sure about
that.
I think there are exceptions.
But generally, that,
the transition I talked about
today, if you go
from building a great product
to building a great company.
Being a founder, you know, for
nine of the ten years is going
to be about building that
great company.
And if you're, if you're not
excited about doing that I
think you should think hard
about, about it.
Yes?
>> What are some of the most
common and
most alarming warning signs
you should be looking for.
When you're trying to make
this shift from
building great products to
building great companies.
What are the, the most common
mistakes to make when
you're shifting towards
building your own company?
I think I went through most of
them here.
I tried to put everything in
here that I
see people mess up most of the
time.
Yes?
>> Is there a way to get
involved in the Y com,
community before getting
accepted?
Is there a way to get involved
with YC before getting funded?
No, and intentionally not.
Actually I'll say the one
thing you can do is if you
work at a YC company.
And then later apply I think
that probably like,
well not probably.
That definitely if you get a
good recommendation from
those founders will help with
YC.
So you know, working at a YC
company helps.
But there's not much you can
do to help and
that's intentional.
Like there is no pre start up
in a way that there's pre-med.
You should just focus on
whatever you're doing.
And when you start a start up,
there's things like YC and
others that are structured to
help you.
Most of the founders we fund,
we don't know at all before we
do it.
You know, you don't,
you really don't need to get
to know us or get involved.
We're, we're all good that
way.
Yes?
>> There's a statistic of
saying,
now harder to get into Y
company then getting,
getting into Harvard.
So I'm curious, the criteria
that are used,
think of start-up, does it
change over time, or?
>> The question is what,
what criteria do we use to
pick start-ups and
has it gotten harder?
Has it changed?
You know, we, the two things
that we need to see are,
are good founders and a good
idea.
And without both of those, we,
we won't fund a company.
But that hasn't changed.
That has, that has always been
the case.
The applicant pool to YC has
grown quite a bit.
But most of, or a lot of the
growth is, you know,
people that shouldn't be
starting start-ups anyway.
Probably, that are just doing
it
because it's sort of the cool
thing now.
So you know, if you're really
passionate about an idea.
And the idea is good.
And you're you know, smart and
get things done that you're
executing.
I still think you have a, a
very reasonable shot at YC,
even though the headline
number is bigger.
Yes.
>> The certain, certain market
that you're really excited
about but don't necessarily
know a lot about yet.
Is there a certain or ways to
,.
>> Sure.
If there's
a market that you're excited
about but
don't know a lot about yet,
what should you do?
Two schools of thought on
this.
One is to just jump right in.
Learn it as you go.
That's worked a lot of times.
The other is to go work at a
company in the space or
do something in, in the market
for,
you know, a year or two years.
I lean slightly towards the
second.
But as long as you're willing
to really learn and
really study and really get
uncomfortably close to your
users, either case will work.
And I don't think it's that
much of a disadvantage.
I, I think, all things being
equal,
I would go spend a couple
years learning about it
in detail, but I don't think
you have to.
Yes?
>> I have question related to
YC to.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah so,
I think that YC does fantastic
job in promoting partnership,
instead of combating.
In fact, as an institutional
investor I actually I
messed with a suite up at YC.
In past periods, the hardware
has things like you know, you
guys has 180 companies every
year jumping into the market.
And it looks like it's hard to
follow each of the YC
companies any more.
Do you think that this will
create some you know,
if some people will walk away
from YC.
Because they cannot follow
such a companies.
The company has to be very
polished and
the founder has to be thinking
over and over about ideas.
Easy to access the capital-
>> All right, so I think the
question is do I think
investors are going to fund
less YC companies as we grow?
no.
Definitely not.
Like certainly the trend in
this is the other way.
We have more and more
investors saying that,
you know, half their
portfolio's now YC companies.
And they're looking forward to
the day where it's
three-quarters.
No I don't think that's a
problem at all.
I think that is like so not on
my top 100 problem list.
The opposite of that maybe.
All right, one more question.
Yes.
>> When should a group of
founders raise a seed fund or
the first fund?
>> When should a group of
founders raise some seed
money?
This is a great question.
I think that, I think that in
general.
It's nice to wait until you
have the idea figured out and
initial signs of promise
before you raise money.
Raising money puts some
pressure on the company.
Some time pressure.
And once you've raised money
you can't be in
this exploratory phase
indefinitely.
you, and you end up having to
rush.
And so, like, if you haven't
raised money, and your idea's
not working, you can, you
know, like flail around and
pivot until you really hit on
the thing that's working.
But if you raise money and
your idea doesn't work,
you're in this like oh ****
moment, and you have to pivot.
And you pivot to
whatever the first vaguely
plausible idea is.
And that's bad.
So I think.
If you can wait to raise any
outside capital more than say,
like $100 or
$200,000 if you're necessary,
but ideally not even that.
Until things are working or,
or at least pointing in
the direction of working
you're way better off.
All right, thank you all very
much, this was fun.