https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ii1jcLg-eIQ
That short.
Like, long introductions are
no good.
Sam knows.
Alright, ready, everybody?
I'm not gonna ask if the mic
is working like in
every talk so far.
I'll just assume it's
working.
>> No!
>> No, fuck!
>> All right, well make it
work somebody.
>> It works, it works
>> All right, this is like
some kinda class tradition.
All right, all right.
I wrote out my talk and
afterwards in a couple days
I will like turn it
from a talk into an essay
and put it online.
So, you don't have to take
notes, just, just listen.
All right.
So, one of the advantages of
having kids is
that when you have to give
advice to people,
you can ask yourself, what
would I tell my own kids?
And actually, you find this
really focuses you.
So, even though my kids are
little.
My two year old today,
when I asked what he was
gonna be after two?
He said a bat.
The correct answer was
three.
But a bat is so much more
interesting.
So even though my kids are
little,
I already know what I would
tell them about startups if
they were in college.
And so that is what I am
gonna tell you.
So, you're literally getting
what I
would give my own kids,
since most of you are young
enough to be my own kids.
All right.
So,
startups are very
counterintuitive.
And I'm not sure exactly
why,
it could be simply because
knowledge about them has not
permeated our culture yet.
But, whatever the reason,
this is an area where you
cannot trust you're
intuitions all the time.
It's like skiing in that
way.
Any of you guys learn to ski
as adults?
You know, when you're
skiing,
when you first try skiing
and you want to slow down,
your first impulse is to
lean back,
just like in everything
else,
but lean back on skis and
you fly down the hill out of
control, so, as I learned.
So, part of learning to ski
is learning to
suppress that impulse.
Eventually, you get new
habits.
But in the beginning there's
this list of things you're
trying to remember as you
start down the hill.
You know, like alternate
feet, make s-turns,
do not drag the inside foot,
all this stuff.
Well, startups are as
unnatural as
skiing and there is a
similar list of stuff you
have to remember for
startups.
And what I’m gonna give you
today is the beginning of
the list.
The list of the
counterintuitive stuff you
have to remember to like
prevent your
existing instincts from
leading you astray.
The first thing on it, is
the fact that I just
mentioned that startups are
so weird that if you
follow your instincts they
will lead you astray.
If you remember nothing more
than that.
When you're about to make a
mistake,
you may at least pause
before making it.
When I was running Y
Combinator,
we used to joke that our
function was to tell
founders things they would
ignore.
And it's really true.
Batch after batch, the YC
partners warn founders about
mistakes they are about to
make.
And the founders ignore
them.
And they come back a year
later and
say, I wish we'd listened.
But, that dude is in their
cap table and
there's nothing they can do.
Why do founders persistently
ignore the partner's advice?
Well, that's the thing about
counterintuitive ideas, they
contradict your intuitions,
so they seem wrong.
So, of course you're first
impulse is to ignore them.
And in fact that is not just
the curse of Y Combinator,
but to some extent our You
don't need people to
give you advice that doesn't
surprise you, right?
If founder's existing
intuitions gave them
the right answers they
wouldn't need us.
That's why there are a lot
of ski instructors and
not a lot of running
instructors.
You don't see those two
words together,
running instructor, as much
as you see ski instructor.
It's because skiing is
counterintuitive.
So sorta, what YC is,
is like business ski
instructors, except for
going up the slopes instead
of down them.
Well, ideally,
you can however trust your
instincts about people.
You, your life so far hasn't
been much like
starting a startup, but all
the interactions you've had
with people are just like
with people in the business
world.
So, in fact one of
the big mistakes that
founders make is to not
trust their intuitions about
people enough.
They meet someone who seems
impressive, but
about whom they feel some
misgivings.
And then later, when things
blow up,
they tell themselves, they
say, you know,
I knew there was something
wrong about that guy, but
I ignored it because he
seemed so impressive.
And there's a specific
sub-case in business,
especially if you come from
an engineering background as
I believe you all do.
You think business is
supposed to be
this sorta slightly
distasteful thing.
And so when you meet people
who seem smart, but
somehow distasteful you
think well,
okay this must be normal for
business.
But it's not.
Just like pick people the
way you would pick people if
you were picking friends.
This is one of those rare
cases where it
works to be self indulgent.
Work with people you
genuinely like and respect
and that you have known long
enough to be sure.
Because there's a lot of
people who
are really good at seeming
likeable for a while.
Just wait till your
interests are opposed and
then you'll see.
All right.
The second counterintuitive
point is that, and this
will, might come as a little
bit of a disappointment.
But what you need to succeed
in a startup is
not expertise in startups.
That makes this class
different from most other
classes you take.
You take a French class at
the end of it you will
learn how to speak French if
you do the work.
You may not sound exactly
like a French person,
but pretty close, right?
This class can teach you
about startups but
that is not what you need to
know.
What you need to know
to suceed in a startup is not
expertise in startups,
what you need is expertise
in your own users.
Mark Zuckerberg did not
succeed in
Facebook because he was an
expert in startups.
He succeeded despite being a
complete noob at startups.
I mean, Facebook was
first incorporated as a
Florida LLC.
Even you guys know better
than that.
He succeeded despite being a
complete noob at startups
because he understood his
users very well.
Most of you don't know the
mechanics of
raising an Angel round.
Right, and if you feel bad
about that, don't, because I
can tell you Mark Zuckerberg
probably doesn't know
the mechanics of raising an
Angel round either.
If he was even paying
attention when Ron Conway
wrote him the big check,
he has probably forgotten
about it by now.
In fact, I worry, it's not
merely unnecessary for
people to learn in detail
about the mechanics of
starting a startup, but
possibly somewhat dangerous.
Because another of the
characteristic mistakes of
young founders starting
startups is to go through
the motions of starting a
startup.
They come up with some
plausible sounding idea.
They raise funding at a nice
valuation.
They rent a nice office in
Soma,
hire a bunch of their
friends.
And then the next step,
after rent a nice
office in Soma and hire a
bunch of their friends,
is gradually realize how
completely fucked they are.
Because while imitating all
the outward forms of
starting a startup,
they have neglected the one
thing that's actually
essential which is to make
something people want.
By the way, that's the only
use of that swear word
except for the initial one
that was involuntary.
And I did check with Sam
whether it would be okay.
He said he had done it
several times.
I mean, used the word.
>> We saw this happen so
often, No, I mean people
going through the motions of
starting a startup.
>> That we made up a name
for it.
Playing house.
Eventually, I realized why
it was happening.
The reason young founders go
through the motions of
starting a startup is
because that is what they
have been trained to do for
their whole lives up to this
point.
Think about what it takes to
get into college.
Extracurricular activities,
check.
Right?
Even in college classes,
most of the work you do is
as artificial as running
laps.
And I am not attacking the
educational system for
being this way.
Inevitably, the work that
you do to learn something is
gonna have some amount of
fakeness to it.
And if you measure people's
performance,
they will inevitably exploit
the difference.
To the degree that what
you're measuring is
largely an artifact of the
fakeness.
And I confess that I did
this myself in college.
In fact, here is a useful
tip on getting good grades.
I found that in a lot of
classes there might only be
20 or 30 ideas that
actually,
had the right shape to make
good exam questions.
And so the way I studied for
exams in these classes was
not to master the material
in the class.
But to try and
figure out what the exam
questions would be and
work out the answers in
advance.
Unlike, for me the test was
not like what my
answers would be on the
exam.
For me the test was.
Which of my exam questions
would turn up
on the exam, right?
So I would get my grade
instantly.
I would walk into the exam
and
look at the questions and
see how many I got right
essentially.
>> It works in a lot of
classes,
especially CS classes.
I remember Automata Theory,
there's only a few
things that make sense to
ask about Automata Theory.
So, it's not surprising that
after being effectively
trained for their whole
lives to play such games,
young founders first impulse
upon starting a startup is
to figure out what the
tricks are.
For this new game,
what are the extracurricular
activities of startups,
what are the things that I
have to do.
They always wanna know
since,
since apparently the measure
of success for
a startup is fundraisingn
another noob mistake.
They always wanna know, what
are the tricks for
convincing investors.
And we have to tell them,
the best way to convince
investors,
is to start a startup that's
actually doing well, meaning
growing fast, and then
simply tell investors so.
So then they ask, okay, what
are the tricks for
growing fast?
Alright?
And
this is exacerbated by the
existence of this term,
growth hacks.
Right?
Whenever you hear anybody
talk about growth hacks,
just mentally translate it
in your mind to bullshit.
Because what we tell them is
the way to make your startup
grow is to make something
that users really love.
Right, and then tell them
about it.
So that's what you have to
do.
That is growth hacks right
there.
So many of the conversations
the YC partners have with
the founders begin with the
founders saying a sentence
that begins with, how do I.
And the partner is answering
with a sentence that begins
with, just.
Right, why do they make
things so complicated?
The reason, I realized,
after years of being puzzled
by this,
is they're looking for the
trick,
they've been trained to look
for the trick.
So, this is the third thing.
The third counterintuitive
thing to
remember about startups.
Starting a startup is
where gaming the system
stops working.
Gaming the system may
continue to work if you go
to work for a big company.
Depending on how broken the
company is you may be able
to succeed by sucking up to
the right person.
Giving the impression of
productivity by sending
emails late at night.
Or if your smart enough,
changing the clock on your
computer,
cause whose going to check
the headers, right?
But, I like an audience I
tell jokes like that to and
they laugh.
Over in the business school,
headers, okay.
God this thing is being
recorded,
I just realized that.
All right, from now on,
we are sticking strictly to
the script.
>> All right.
But in startups, that does
not work.
There is no boss to trick.
There's no, how can you
trick people if
there's no one to trick?