https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yP176MBG9Tk
strategies to increase this
curve,
like keep making it go up
and up and
up, you want to basically
look at this analysis,
over time to see if that
strategy is working for you.
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, cool.
The second kind of growth is
viral growth and like sticky
growth you need to also
deliver a good experience.
But on top of that you need
to deliver a really,
really good experience,
like, what's going to make
these people shout out loud
on Twitter, on Facebook or
whatever and tell all their
friends and
email all their friends and
family members about you.
You have to really deliver a
good experience.
Combined with that is, u
need to have really good
mechanics for the referral
program itself, like,
you have a hundred customers
who really wanna talk
about you now, how are they
going to talk about you?
So, in that sense a viral
growth,
the viral growth strategy is
all really about one
building good experience,
but if you have that,
it's how do you build a good
referral program.
And so I've listed the three
main parts of that.
One is the customer touch
points, which is,
where are people,
learning that they can refer
other people.
So, that might be just,
after they book, or
after they sign up there is
a,
usually you see these like,
right after you sign up for,
for whatever reason most,
for whatever reason most
people just immediately tell
you to invite other friends,
even though you've never
used the product before.
And so, but that's a
customer touch point,
is just right after you sign
up.
A better one is after they
use the product after
a while, and you see that
they're highly engaged,
then to show them that link
and
get them to send it out to
everyone.
Another one is if
you're doing more of a
platform type play like, for
Homejoy we actually go
inside their homes.
So now, the customer touch
point is when the cleaning
professional is inside the
home,
they can have a leave
behind,
and, we can show them
something there too as well.
so, you wanna basically put
the customer touch points
and put the actual, link or
whatever it is, how they're
gonna refer all their
friends at a point in time
when they're highly engaged
and they're loving you.
Second is program mechanics.
And so that's where, like,
the most common thing that
I've seen is $10 for $10,
that is, you get $10 if you
invite your friend and they
use it and they get $10.
And so, you should try
different types of
mechanics in that sense and
try to optimize for whatever
works for you.
You know, it could be 25 for
25,
it could be ten for zero, it
could many of these things.
And lastly it's when the,
when your friend clicks on
the link, on your referral
link, when they come back to
the site, it's very
important to really optimize
that conversion flow of how
they're going to sign up.
And so sometimes you need to
just sell them in
a different manner, or
upsell that their friend has
suggested they use this and
so on and so forth.
So, all these combined, you
need to really play
around with these on
different dimensions and
come up with a good referral
program.
And, lastly, it's paid
growth, so,
examples of paid growth is
this right here.
And these are the most
obvious ones, but
I'm sure you guys can think
of more.
And paid growth is
basically,
you happen to have money,
you can spend.
You might have credit cards,
whatever, but
you can spend something to
get users.
So, the correct way to think
about pay to growth is that,
okay you're going to put
money.
You're gonna risk putting
money out there,
what are you gonna get in
return?
The simple way to think
about it is, is your CLV,
your customer lifetime, the
amount of money,
the net revenue, the amount
of money that people,
that your customer returns
back to you,
is it more than your CAC?
And your CAC is an
abbreviation for
customer acquisition cost.
So, an example is, you pay,
actually the slide
here has an example here, so
say you run a bunch of ads.
These are four ads.
Over 12 months,
the customer's worth $300 to
you.
Each one of these ads, when
you click on it,
the CPC costs different
types of money.
And then, when they click on
the ad, then they have to
come to your site and sign
up or buy something, and
the conversion rates are
different for all these ads.
And then, the CAC is
calculated simply by
the CPC divided by the
conversion.
And so, you see that there's
different acquisition costs
for different types of ads.
And to determine whether,
that is a good ad or
a bad ad, all you have to do
is, CLV minus CAC.
Is it more than zero?
If it's at zero then you've,
that's fine, but
hopefully it's actually more
than zero until you actually
are earning a profit on it.
So, we see that, despite the
sales remaining the same and
the conversions being higher
and lower,
there's sometimes, some ads
that might seem good,
actually don't seem so good
at the end of the day.
Now, the advanced way of
looking at it is you can
look at this for your whole
entire customer base for
aggregating all your
customers together.
But the better way of
looking at it is to break it
down by customer segments.
So, if you have for example,
if you're building
a marketplace, I don't know,
for country music,
the CLV's of someone in
Nashville Tennessee is going
to be much larger than the
CLV's and
latent value of someone in
Czechoslovakia.
So, or, I just assume that's
the case anyway.
So, you'll need to, you want
to make sure that when
you're buying ads for these
different types of cohorts,
or these types of customer
segments,
that you know what the
differences are.
You don't wanna mix like,
everything together.
So, the last one on payback
time is sustainability.
I think a lot of businesses
get in trouble, and
it turns into a bad business
when they start
spending beyond their means.
And it has a lot to do with
risk tolerance, or
how much risk you're willing
to take on.
So, when you look at CLV's
of these.
Let's just suppose you get a
customer a customer who's
worth $300 after 12 months,
that is,
in the first month they're
worth $100.
If you wait til the end of
the 12 month period,
then they give you the other
$200.
But if, in the first period
you're actually paying
$200 for them, then you're
in the whole for
$100 until the end of the 12
month period.
And that's when you start
getting into
potentially unsustainable
growth, which is
something could happen where
at the end of the 12 months,
you don't actually get the
$200 from the customer, and
you end up in a very bad
situation and
essentially just at the end
of the day,
you could be running out of
money.
And if you're doing this
with credit cards,
you will definitely find
that you're gonna have to,
you know, declare bankruptcy
very soon.
So again, payback time is
very important, a safe one
to go with is 3 months if
you have very high risk,
if you're very risk loving,
maybe 12 months is better.
Beyond 12 months is very
much an unsafe territory.
How much time do I have?
A minute, okay.
So, I'll just go into this,
the art of pivoting.
So a lot of people ask me,
Homejoy went through,
Homejoy in its current
concept is
literally the thirteenth
idea we fully built out and
try and execute on and try
to get customers for.
And so, a lot of the
questions I get
is how did you even, like,
get to that thirteenth idea?
And how'd you decide when to
move on.
And so the best guidance I
can give on that is,
to kind of look at these
three criteria, which is,
once you realize you can't
grow, or once you realize,
you are despite building out
all these great features and
talking to all these users.
None of them stick, or you
don't
have any good high retaining
users, or the economics of
the business just doesn't
make sense, then once you
make that realization, you
just need to move on.
And I think the trickiest
one is probably the growth
one, because there's so many
stories out there
where the founder stuck with
the idea, and then,
after three years, all of a
sudden it started growing.
So, the trick here is
basically,
what you really should do
is,
you should have a growth
plan when you start out,
which is you should ideally
just have, what is
an optimistic but realistic
way to grow this business?
And so, it might look
something like this.
And this is T and this is
number of users.
So, in week one you want,
you just want one user.
In week two you want maybe
two users and
so and so forth.
And you can keep doubling up
and up.
So, in week one you should
basically do
as much as possible,
build whatever you have to
build to get that one user.
And then in week two, so on,
so forth, you build whatever
you need to get two users,
four users, eight users.
In the beginning it should
be fairly, if you
have a product that people
actually wan,t you should be
able to maintain this growth
curve pretty easily just by
walking around and manually
finding people.
It's when you get to like,
you need 100 users a week,
or you need some of these
more,
you need the growth
strategies to start working.
And so, what I tell people
is usually if you're fully
executing on your product,
and you're really
working really, really hard,
then, if you go three or
four weeks in a row of no
growth, backwards growth,
then either, then it's time
to maybe consider a pivot,
in the sense that not
starting over, like,
completely come with a new
idea.
But you're probably
fundamentally doing
something wrong, because, in
that early stage of
a start up, you should
always be growing.
And, so, it's not.
And this is optimistically
what it looks like.
And this is like, kind of
the growth curve I set forth
and put out when I started
Home Joy.
But really what it looks
like is like this.
And so you wanna make sure
that when you're in
a low like over here, that
you don't just stop, right?
And that's why you should
wait two to three weeks,as
long as you keep working
hard, you'll eventually get
back here and you'll see a
trend like this over time.
Cool, so that's pivoting
and that's it.
I can take questions at this
point.
>> Answer one question.
>> Yeah.
One question?
>> So one question online
was, if your users have a
product that they're already
somewhat comfortable with,
how do you get them to
switch to your's?
>> Right so, there's a
switch over costs.
I'll tell you the example of
Homejoy.
So, Homejoy,
we actually were creating a
new market in the sense that
a lot of our initial users
never had cleaning before.
So, it was pretty simple to
get them on board.
And a lot of people who have
cleaners already,
really trust their cleaner
and they will.
To get them to come and use
something else is actually,
probably the most difficult
task in the world.
And so, when you're billing
things and trying to
get people to switch over to
you, what you really need to
do is find the moments where
your product or
what your offering is much
better or very
much differentiated from the
existing solution they have.
So, an example is someone
who had a regular cleaner
and maybe they had a party
one day and
they needed a cleaning
almost the next day.
And because Homejoy,
in most of the areas has
next day availability,
they would just come to
Homejoy and use it, because
they knew they couldn't get
their regular cleaner.
And once they start using
the product,
then that's when they start
realizing the advantage,
the little advantages of
using Homejoy which adds up
to a big advantage.
So, a lot of things are,
realizing that, leaving cash
out, or
leaving checks was really
annoying, and so billing
through online payments was
more convenient.
Being able to book, cancel,
and reschedule, according to
your own schedule was very
convenient and so
and so forth.
And so, it's just, it's
really hard to,
a lot of people when they
build the product,
they're like, and these 50
things are better than,
a little bit better than,
the existing solution.
It's really hard, even if
the benefits outweigh
the switch-over costs.
It's really hard to actually
tell that to a user and
try to get them to aggregate
all those benefits over many
little things.
It's better to just have one
or two things that clearly
differentiate yourself from
the product so.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Yeah.
>> That was awesome.
>> Yeah?
Okay.