https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5_0dVHMpJlo
need to always think through
and try to overcome.
And there is always this
question about
competition as a form of
validation.
Where we go for
things that lots of other
people are going for,
and it's not that there is
wisdom in crowds, it's
not when lots of people are
trying to do something that,
that's proof of it being
valuable.
I think it's when lots of
people are trying to do
something that is often
proof of insanity.
There are twenty thousand
people a year who move to
Los Angeles to become movie
stars,
about 20 of them make it.
I think the Olympics are a
little bit better,
because you can figure out
pretty quickly whether
you're good or not, so
there's a little bit less of
a dead weight loss to
society.
You know?
>> You the sort of
educational experience at
a place, the pre Stanford
educational experience.
There's always sort of
a non-competitive
characterization, where I
think most of the people in
this room had machine guns,
that were competing with
people with bows and arrows.
So it wasn't exactly a
parallel competition when
you were in junior high
school and high school.
There's always a question,
does the tournament make
sense as you keep going?
And there is always this
question if people go on to
grad school, or
post doctoral educations,
does the intensity of
the competition really make
sense?
There's the classic Henry
Kissinger line
describing his fellow
faculty at Harvard.
That the battles were so
ferocious, because the
stakes were so small.
Describing sort of academia.
And you start to think on
one level this is
a description of insanity.
Why would people fight like
crazy when the stakes are so
small?
But it's also,
I think simply a function of
the logic of the situation.
When it's really hard to
differentiate yourself from
other people.
When the differences are,
when
the objective differences
really are small.
Then you have to compete
ferociously to maintain
a difference of one sort or
another, that's often more
imaginary than real.
There's always a sort of a
personal version of
this that I tell where I was
sort of hyper tracked.
My 8th grade junior high
school yearbook,
one of my friends wrote in,
I know you'll get into
Stanford in four years
as a Sophomore, sort of when
it is going to Stanford four
years later, the end of high
school.
Went to Stanford Law School.
You know, ended up at a big
law firm in New York,
where from the outside
everybody wanted to get in.
On the inside everybody
wanted to leave.
>> And it was this very
strange dynamic, where after
I sort of realized that this
was not the best idea,
and left after seven months
and three days.
You know, one of the people
down the hall from me told
me, it's really reassuring
to see you leave, Peter.
I had no idea that it was
possible to
escape from Alcatraz.
Which of course, all you had
to do was go out the front
door and not come back.
But so much of people
identities got
wrapped in winning these
competitions,
that they somehow lost site
of what was important.
What was valuable.
And you know, competition
does make you better
at whatever it is you're
competing on.
Because when you're
competing,
you're comparing yourself
with the people around you.
You're figuring out,
how do I beat the people
next to me?
How do I do somewhat better
at whatever it
is they're doing.
And you will get better at
that thing.
I'm not questioning that,
I'm not denying that.
But, it often comes at this
tremendous price that you
stop asking some bigger
questions,
about what's truly important
and truly valuable.
And so I would say, don't
always go through the tiny
little door that everyone's
trying to rush through.
Maybe go around the corner,
and
go through the vast gate
that no one's taking.
Thank you very much.
I guess there's time for,
do you want to take a few
questions?
>> Sorry?
>> Oh yes, people want to
take,
I'll take a few questions
with few minutes time.
Yeah, go ahead.
>> Since, yeah, as you
mentioned,
you already mentioned
further competition often
look similar because the
narrative of
people tell our selves.
Do you have any ways to
easily determine the
difference when your
looking at an idea that is
better than your own idea?
>> Well I'd say the question
I always try to focus on is
what is the actual market?
So not what's the narrative
of the market,
because you can always tell
a fictional story about
a market that's much bigger
or much smaller.
But what is the real
objective market?
So, it's always, yeah, you
always try to figure it out.
And you realize people have
incentives to powerfully
distort these things.
Yeah?
>> Which of the aspects of
monopolies that you
mentioned would you say
>> Well
they have network effects
with the ad network.
They had proprietary
technology that gave them
the initial lead, because
they had the page
rank algorithm which was
sort of, an order of
magnitude better than any
other search engine.
You have economies of scale,
because of the need to store
all these different sites.
And at this point, you have
brand, so
Google has all four.
Maybe the proprietary
technology's somewhat
weaker at this point.
But, definitely, it had all
four, and
maybe three out of four now.
Yeah.
>> How does this apply to
and, second, what's it like.
The seconds what?
>> What's with the i-Phone?
>> That's
sort of a set of companies
that are doing
different copycat payment
systems on mobile phones.
There's Square, there's
PayPal.
They just have sort of
different shapes.
That's how they
differentiate themselves.
One is a triangle, one is a
square.
And so you know...
>> Maybe at some point the
apes weren't out of shape or
something like that.
But I think, pounds here we
started with focus on
the intelligence community
which is small sub-market,
you had a proprietary
technology that used
a very different approach.
Were it was focused on the
human
computer synthesis rather
than the substitution,
which I think is the
dominant paradigm.
So there's a whole set of
things I would say on
the market approach, and on
the proprietary technology.
Yes?
>> When you have design
thinking methodology in
a start-up thinking, which
is used to mitigate risk by
not creating things that
people don't want.
But I think young innovators
have inspiration create
complex systems that last's
through time.
>> Could you repeat the
question?
>> Yeah.
So the quest is what do I
think about lean start-up's,
iterative thinking,
where you get feedback from
people,
versus complexity that may
not work.
So, I am personally quite
skeptical of all the lean
start-up methodology.
I think the really great
companies did something that
was, sort of.
Somewhat more of a quantum
improvement that
really differentiated them
from everybody else.
They typically did not do
massive, you know,
customer surveys.
The people who ran these
companies sometimes,
not always, suffer from mild
forms of Aspberger's, so
they were not actually that
influenced,
not that easily deterred by
what other people thought or
told them to do.
So I do think we're way too
focused on iteration as
a modality, and not enough
on trying to have a virtual
esp link with the public and
figuring it out ourselves.
I would say that, the risk
question
is always a very tricky one
because there are, you know?
They're, they're, it's not,
it's often.
I think it's often the case
that you
don't have enough time to
really mitigate risk.
If, if you're gonna take
enough time to
figure out what people want.
You often will have missed
the boat by then.
and, and then, of course,
there's always the risk of,
of doing something that's,
that's not that,
significant or meaningful.
So, you know?
You could say a track in
law school is a low risk
track from one
perspective, it may still be
a very high risk track in
the sense that maybe your
not, have a high risk of
not doing something
meaningful with your life.
So, we have to think about
risk in these,
very complicated way.
I think risk is for a very
complicated concept.
Yes.
I was just checking for
the last advantage, but then
doesn't that
imply that there's already
competition to begin with
between the chess pieces on
the chess board?
>> Yeah, so, there's always
this terminology thing,
so I would say that there
are categories in
which people sort of are
bundled together.
I would say the monopoly
businesses were in effect
they really were a big first
mover in some sense.
You could say Google was not
the first search engine.
There were other search
engines before, but
on one dimension,
they were dramatically
better than everybody else,
they were the first one with
page rank,
with sort of an automated
approach.
Facebook was not the first
social networking site.
My friend, Reed Hoffman,
started one in 1997,
and they called it Social
Net.
So they already had the
name,
Social networking, in the
name of their company,
seven years before Facebook.
Their idea was that it was
gonna be this virtual
cyberspace, where I'd be a
dog and you'd be a cat.
And we'd have all these
different rules about how
we'd interact with each
other.
>> In this virtual alternate
reality.
Facebook was the first one
to get real identity.
So, it was, so I would say,
I hope Facebook will be the
last social networking site,
it was the first one in a
very important dimension.
People often would not think
of it as the first because
they, sort of, lump all
these things together.
>> I have one more question.
>> Okay, one question, let's
take one here.
>> If you're theoretically
someone who,
worked at Golden College and
left there after six months,
and is now going to do
science at Standford.
How would you recommend
rethinking
>> I don't have a great,
I'm not great at the
psychotherapy stuff so
I don't quite know how to
>> solve this.
There are these very odd
studies they've
done on people who go to
business school.
There's one they've done at
Harvard Business school
where it's sort of the
anti-Asperger, personality.
We have people who are super
extroverted,
generally have low
convictions, few ideas.
And you have sort of a
hothouse environment.
You put all these people in
for two years.
And at the end of it, they
systematically end up,
the largest cohort
systematically ends up
doing the wrong thing.
They tried to catch the last
wave.
You know in 1989 everyone in
Harvard tried to work for
Mike Milken, it was one or
two years before he went to
jail for
all the junk bond stuff.
They were never interested
in Silicon Valley or
tech, except for '99 and
2000 when they timed the dot
com bubble peaking
perfectly.
They did, and then '05 to
'07 was housing.
Private equity, stuff like
this.
I do think this tendency for
us to see competition as
validation is very deep.
I don't think there's any
sort of
easy psychological formula
to avoid it.
I don't know what sort of
therapy to recommend.
>> But my first.
My first starting point,
which is only like maybe ten
percent of the way,
is to never under estimate
how big a problem it is.
We always think this is
something that afflicts
other people.
It's easy for
me to point to people in
business schools or people
at Harvard or people on Wall
Street, I think it actually
does afflict all of us to a
very profound degree.
We always think of
advertising as
things that work on other
people.
How, who are all these
stupid people who fall for
all those ads on tv,
they obviously work to some
extent and
they work, to a disturbing
extant on all of us.
And it's something we, we
all should work to overcome.
Thank you very much.