https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n_yHZ_vKjno
Thank you for coming.
>> Move us all, thank you.
Cool, so you guys this is
awesome,
I've been watching the
lectures in this course,
isn't it absolutely amazing
the content?
And now you're stuck with me
today.
>> We'll, so how that goes.
Unlike Paul, when he was
talking in the Q and A,
and you guys asked him what
he would do if he was at
college today and
he said physics, I actually
indulged myself.
I went in, I went and did
physics,
did physics at Cambridge and
I think physics is
an amazing class to give you
transferable skills that
are really useful in other
areas.
But I guess that's not,
that's not why you're
listening to me today.
Like, physics isn't the
class, like, so I paid for
college doing online
marketing.
Direct sales marketing.
I started with SEO in the
1990s.
I created a paper airplane
site.
I had a monopoly.
In the small niche market of
paper airplanes globally
which you know,
when you want to start a
startup also see how big
the market could be in the
long term it wasn't great.
But what that taught me was
how to do SEO.
And back in those days it
was Altavista, and
the way to do SEO was to
have white text on
a white background five
pages below the fold.
And you would rank top of
Alta Vista if you just paper
airplanes 20 or 30 times in
that text.
And that was how you won at
SEO in the 1990s.
Like it was a really easy,
easy skill to learn.
When I went to college,
being a physicist,
I thought paper airplanes
would make me cool, and
I was actually the most
nerdy person in
the physics class, so I
created a cocktail site.
Which was how I learned to
program.
And that grew to be the
largest cocktail site in
the UK.
And that really got me into
SEO properly when
Google launched.
So with Google, you had to
worry about page rank, and
you had to worry about
getting links
back to your site.
Which basically, at that
stage,
meant one link from the
Yahoo directory.
Got you to the top listing
in Google if you had white
text, on a white background,
below the fold, as well.
When Google launched AdWords
that's when I
really started to learn how
to do all my marketing.
And that was buying paid
clicks from Google, and
reselling them to eBay for
a small margin of like 20%
using our affiliate program.
And that was what really
kicked me into overdrive
into doing what everyone
nowadays talks about is
growth, or growth hacking,
or growth marketing.
And in my mind it's just
internet marketing.
Using whatever channel you
can to get whatever output
you want.
And that's how I paid for
college and how I
ended up going from being a
physicist to a marketer and
transitioning to the dark
side of the force.
So what do you think matters
most for growth.
You've had loads of lectures
and
people have said it over and
over, so
what do you guys think
matters most for growth?
Someone give me an answer.
>> Great product.
I agree, great product.
What does great product lead
to?
>> Customers.
And what do you need those
customers to do?
>> Spread the word.
Someone said stay on your
site.
Someone said that.
That's it.
Retention.
Retention is the single most
important thing for growth.
Now we have an awesome
growth team at Facebook, and
I'm super proud to work on
it.
But the truth of
the matter is we have a
fantastic product.
But getting to work on
growth at Facebook is
a massive privilege, because
we're promoting something
that everyone in the world
really wants to use.
Which is absolutely
incredible.
If we can get people on, and
get them ramped up, they
stick on Facebook.
So many times I go advise
multiple startups,
my favorite was working with
Airbnb, but
I've worked with Coursera,
I've worked with
other ones that haven't done
as well as those guys.
But the one thing that is
true over, and over, and
over again is if you look at
this curve.
The sentiment, the active,
versus number of days from
acquisition.
If you end up with a
retention curve that
ascentotes to a line
parallel to the x axis.
You have a viable business,
and
you have product market fit
for some subset of market.
But most of the companies
that you see fly up,
we talk about growth hacking
and virality and
all of this other stuff.
I'm gonna try so hard not to
swear, but it'll happen.
Their attention curve slopes
down towards the X-axis, and
in the end intercepts the
X-axis.
Now when I show this chart
to
most people they say that's
all well and good.
You had a million people a
day in terms of
growth when you started the
growth team at Facebook, or
you were at 50 million
users.
You had a lot of people
joining the site so
you had a ton of data to do
this.
We used this same
methodology for
our B to B growth.
Getting people to sign up as
self-service advertisers,
we used this analysis to
understand how much
growth we were gonna have in
that market as well.
And in that place,
when I joined Facebook, the
product was three days old.
And within 90 days of the
product launching,
we were able to use this
technique to be able to
figure out what the one year
value of an advertiser was,
and we predicted it for the
first year to 97% of
what the number turned out
to be.
So I think it's very
important to look at
your attention curve, and
this is how we did it.
If you see here.
This red line is number of
users,
who have been on your
product for
a certain number of days.
So, a bunch of people, that
should say zero,
a bunch of people will have
been on your product,
all of your users will have
been on it at least one day.
But, if your product's been
around a year, or whatever,
you will have zero users
who've been on it 366 days.
Make sense?
The curves sensible?
Cool.
So what you then do is look
for all of your users,
who have been on your
product one day.
What percentage of them are
monthly active.
100% for the first 30 days
obviously,
because monthly active they
all signed up on one day.
But then you look at 31.
Every single user, on their
31st day after registration,
what percentage of them were
monthly active, 32nd day,
33rd day, 34th day?
And that allows you,
with only something like
10,000 customers or
whatever, to get a real idea
of what this curve is
gonna look like for your
product.
And you're gonna be able to
tell does it asymptote.
And it'll get noisy out
towards the right-hand side.
Like I'm not using real
data.
It'll get noisy out towards
the right hand side, but
you'll be able to get a
handle on,
does this curve flatten out
or does it not.
If it doesn't flatten out,
don't go and
do growth tactics, don't go
and
do virality, don't hire a
growth hacker.
Focus on getting product
market fit.
Because in the end,
as Sam said in the beginning
of this course,
idea, product, team,
execution.
If you don't have a great
product,
there's no point executing
well on growing it.
Because it won't grow.
Number one problem I've seen
inside Facebook for
new products, number one
problem I've seen for
startups I ever devised has
been, they don't actually
have product market fit when
they think they do.
So the next obvious question
that people ask over and
over and over again is okay,
so
what does good retention
look like?
Sure I can have five percent
retention but
I'm guessing that Facebook
had better than that, so
that's not gonna be a
successful business.
And I get really pissed off
when
people ask me that question.
Because I think you can
figure it out.
And I love this story, and
this is like my one
gratuitous story that I love
that I'm throwing in here,
so the rest of it may not be
as gratuitous.
But this is a picture that
was published in
Life magazine in 1950 of
one of the Trinity nuclear
bomb tests.
And there's a guy,
Geoffrey Taylor, who's heard
of Geoffrey Taylor.
Awesome.
Yes.
Someone's heard of him.
Geoffrey Taylor was a
British physicist,
who ended up actually
winning the Nobel Prize.
And he was able to figure
out from looking at
this picture, what the power
of the atomic bomb was,
the U.S. atomic bomb.
And Russian's were
publishing similar pictures,
just using dimensional
reasoning.
And dimensional reasoning is
I think,
one of the best skills that
I learned during my
time studying physics back
in the U.K..
And what dimensional
reasoning is, is you look at
the dimensions that are
involved in a problem.
So, you wanna figure out
energy?
Newtons, meters, newtons are
kilograms, meters are second
to the minus 2, so you've
got kilograms,
meters squared, seconds to
the minus 2,
and then you try and figure
out how you can get each of
those numbers from what data
you have.
So, the mass.
Is the volume of this
sphere.
So, that's a meter cubed you
throw in there.
So you've got meters the 5
over seconds the minus 2,
and he was able to use that
to just figure out
what the power of this
atomic bomb was,
what the ratios of the power
between the Russian and
US atomic bomb, and
essentially reveal one of
the top secrets that existed
in the world at that time.
That's a hard problem.
Figuring out what
Facebook's retention rate is
not a hard problem.
How many people are there on
the internet?
Give or take someone throw
something out.
>> 2.4 billion, 2.3 billion.
Something like that right?
Okay, Facebook's banned in
China.
So.
What now?
>> About a billion.
>> About 2 billion?
2 billion.
So
2 billion people on the
internet.
Facebook in their last
earnings call
said something around 1.3
billion in
terms of the number of
active users.
You can divide those numbers
by each other.
And yeah, that won't give
you the right answer.
Course it's not gonna give
But it's gonna give you
close enough to a ballpark
figure.
Of what the retention rate
looks like for Facebook.
If we signed everyone on the
internet up, and
then you will know it is
higher than that.
Similarly if you look at
Whats App, they've announced
six hundred million active
users.
How many people have smart
phones?
You can figure out that
number.
That number is out knocking
around.
It can give an idea of how
many users there are.
Amazon has had a pop at
signing up almost everyone
in the United States.
You know how many people are
online in the US, and
you've got a good idea of
how many
customers Amazon are from
the numbers they throw out.