https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sz_LgBAGYyo
All right.
So when I talk about making
products users love what I
mean specifically is like
how do we make things that
has a passionate user base
that our users
are unconditionally wanting
it to
be successful both on the
products that we build, but
also the companies behind
them.
We're gonna go over tons of
information.
Try not to take too many
notes,
mostly just try to listen.
I'll post the link to the
slides on my Twitter account
and on that link, there will
be a way for you to
annotate the slide and you
can ask me questions.
And so if we don't get to
them,
I'll answer them after the
talk.
So, you guys have been.
Listening to and
hearing a lot about growth
over the last several weeks,
and to me I feel like growth
is usually fairly simple.
It's the interaction between
two sort of concepts or
variables.
Conversion rate and churn.
Right?
And the gap between those
two things pretty
much indicate how fast
you're gonna grow.
And most people, especially
business type people,
tend to look at this
interaction in terms of
a very calculated in a
mathematical sort of way.
And today, I sort of want to
talk about these things at a
more human scale.
All right, cuz at start up
when you're interacting with
your users, you have a
fairly intimate
interaction that you have in
the early stages.
And so, I think there's a
different way of looking at
this stuff in terms of how
we build our products.
And we'll look at a lot of
different examples of that.
And how it's executed well.
My philosophy behind a lot
of things that I teach
startups is the best way to
sort of get to a billion
dollars is to focus on the
values that help you
get that first dollar, to
acquire that first user.
If you sort of get that
right everything else will
sort of take care of itself.
It's a sort of faith thing.
So I came to be a partner at
YC by way of being alumni.
I went to the program in
winter of 2006, so
it's the second ever program
and
I built a product called
Wufoo.
Wufoo's an online forum
builder.
It helps you create contact
forums and
online surveys and simple
payment forms.
It's basically a database
that looks like it's
designed by Fisher Price.
What's.
Interesting, though, is that
because it was fairly easy
to use, we're had customers
from every industry, market,
and vertical you can think
of, including a,
a majority of the Fortune
500 companies out there.
Ran the company for five
years, and
then we were acquired by
SurveyMonkey in 2013.
And at the time,
we were a very interesting
acquisition.
We were only a team of ten
people at the time.
And, while we acquired
funding out here in
Silicon Valley through Y
Combinator we actually ran
the company from Florida.
We had no office.
Everyone worked from home.
And we're an interesting
outlier.
So, each dot here represents
a start up that was,
that exited through IPO or
acquisition.
And we're this outlier to
the left.
The bottom is the funding
amount they took.
And the vertical axis is,
the valuation of the company
at the time.
To sum it up,
the average startup rates as
about $25 million.
And they return to their
investors about 676%.
Wufoo raised about $118
thousand total.
And our return to our
investors is about 29,000%.
>> So a lot of people were
very interested.
And are sort of like.
What makes.
Wufoo a little bit different
or
how do we run the company
very differently, and
a lot of it was focused on
product.
We weren't interested in
building software that,
I guess that just people
wanted to use.
Right.
That reminding you that you
worked in a cubicle,
cuz it was database app at
its sort of core.
We wanted a product that
people wanted to love.
That people wanted to have a
relationship with, and we
were actually very fanatical
about how we approached.
This idea.
At the point where it's
almost sort of
sort of sciency sort of way.
So what we said was like
Okay.
What's interesting about
start-ups in terms of
us wanting to create things
that people love is that,
love and unconditional sort
of feelings are things that
are difficult for us to do
in sort of real life.
And at start-ups we have to
do it sort of at scale.
So we've decided to do is
just start of by just
looking at, Okay,
how does real relationships
work in the real world, and
how can we apply them to
sort of how we
run our business and sort of
build our product that way.
So we'll go over basically
these two metaphors,
find new users as if we're
trying to date them and
existing users as if it were
a successful marriage.
So when it comes to dating,
lot of the stuff that
we uncovered had to do with
first impressions.
all, all of you often talk
about your relationships in
terms of the origin story.
If I asked you to tell me
about the first kiss,
how you sort of met, how you
proposed,
these are the things that we
say over and
over and over again.
They're basically the
word-of-mouth stories of our
relationships, and they're
the same kinds of
things that we do with
companies.
Human beings
are relationship
manufacturing creatures.
We cannot help, but create
and anthropomorphize
the things we interact with
over and over again.
So, whether it's the cars we
drive,
the clothes we wear, the
tools and software's we use,
we eventually prescribe
characteristics to it.
A personality.
And we expect it to behave a
certain way.
And that's how we sort of
interact with it.
Now first impressions are
important for
the starting of any
relationship,
because it's the one we tell
over and over again.
Right?
And there's something
special about how we
regard that origin story.
I'll give an example.
If you're on a first date
with somebody,
and you're having a nice
dinner, and
you catch them picking their
nose.
You are probably not gonna
have another date with them.
Right, but if you're married
to someone for
about 20 to 30 years,
and you catch on the Barca
Lounger digging for
gold right?
You don't immediately like
call your lawyer,
right, and then say like we
have a problem here.
I need to start drawing up
papers for divorce.
You shrug your shoulders and
say at least he has a heart
of gold.
So solving about.
First time interactions
means that the threshold is
so much lower in terms of
pass fail.
So, in software, and for
most products in internet
software that we use, like,
first impressions are pretty
obvious.
And they're the things that
you see a lot of
companies sort of pay
attention to in terms of
what they send their
marketing people to work on.
My argument for people who
are very good at product is
they discover so many other
first moments, and
they make those something
memorable.
Right, the first email you
ever get from a piece of
software.
What happens when you first
log in?
The links, the advertising,
the very first time you
interact with customer
support.
All of those are
opportunities to seduce.
So how did we think about.
Sort of like making first
moments on there,
and we actually took this
concept from the Japanese.
They actually have two words
for
how to describe things when
you're finished with them
in terms of saying like is
this a quality item.
And the two words of quality
are atarimae hinshitsu and
miryokuteki hinshitsu.
And the first one means,
taken for
granted quality, basically
functionality.
And the last one sort of
means,
enchanting quality, right?
Take for example a pen,
right?
Something has miryokuteki,
right, if the weight of
the pen, the way the ink
flows out of it, the way
it's viewed by the people
reading the handwriting from
the pen is pleasurable both
to the user of the pen and
the people who experience
the byproducts of it,
right, taking it to the sort
of next level.
Start with some examples.
So this is Wufoo's Login
link, and
it has a dinosaur on it,
which I think is awesome.
But if you hover over it,
the spec has the added
benefit of having a tool tip
that doesn't explain like
how to login or
what it does, but basically,
rawr.
And.
What we noticed about this,
like in early usability
studies as like this put a
smile on people's faces.
Like, hands down.
Right?
Universally.
And I think a lot of times
when we
are assessing products, we
never think about,
like, hey what is the
emotion on
the person's face when they
interact with this?
This is Vimeo's log in page
this is
actually a couple integr,
iterations ago.
It's one I find to be the
most beautiful, but.
It lets you know that when
you're starting out on
this journey with Vimeo,
that this is gonna be
something different.
They do this all over the
app.
If you search for the word
fart, as you scroll up and
down it makes fart noises as
you do this.
Right?
There's something different,
like this site interacts
with you.
>> Mm-hm.
>> It's a little bit
magical, it's a little bit
different.
And it's something that you
wanna talk about.
You don't have to always do
it with design.
This is a sign up form for
Cork which used to be a
social network for
people who loved to drink
wine.
On it, it says email
address,
it's also your sign-in and
has to be legit.
First name, what your mom
calls you, last name,
what your Army buddies call
you.
Password, something you'll
remember, but hard to guess,
password confirmation, think
it a, type it again.
Think of it as a test.
It's literally a poem as you
fill out the form.
Right?
And this is a kind of like
thing where you like,
oh, I like the people behind
this.
I, I, I'm gonna enjoy this
experience.
Now what does it say when
you fill out form like this?
Right.
On Yahoo, about what the
personality.
Of the site it's gonna be.
And what's disappointing to
me is like,
Yahoo forces every product
and
service under them to use
this exact same login form.
Flickr, I had thought,
had one of the best sort of
call to actions.
It was, get in there.
Right?
This is Heroku's.
Sign up page.
I think this is an older
version.
But, what's remarkable about
it is that, what you
start getting a feel for is
like, oh, scaling up.
My sort of server, and