https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQOC-qy-GDY
We launched in, you know,
less than an hour,
where we released a full
landing page.
And finally, it's okay to do
things that don't scale.
Doing things that don't
scale is one of your biggest
competitive advantages when
you're starting out.
And you can figure out how
to
scale once you have the
demand.
And, maybe once you've
scaled,
then you go get that ice
cream.
Thanks.
>> Sure.
>> How did your first
customer hear about you?
>> Yeah.
So the question was,
how did our first customer
hear about us?
Our very first one, I have
no idea.
We just launched
PaloAltodelivery.com.
We didn't do any marketing.
So I assume he just must
have
typed in Palo Alto delivery
into the web browser.
And then after that,
we didn't do, we did barely
any marketing.
I think I sent out like one
email to my dorm.
And that was about it.
It was all through word of
mouth and
that kind of just validates.
You know, just how strong of
a need you found.
You know, when people just
start talking about you and
they're willing to put up
with all this, you know,
terrible user experience,
terrible design, and
stuff like that.
>> When you started, it
seemed so obvious that you
were wondering why no one's
done this.
What's your answer now?
With that.
>> Yeah, I mean, looking
back, I think,
I think the biggest thing is
mobile.
The fact that now everyone
has one of
those in their pocket.
And we kinda saw that trend
and thought, you now,
what if you can design, you
know, a delivery system
that's entirely based off
mobile, where you don't have
to have any infrastructure
or delivery fleets.
Instead, you could, you
know,
instead of hiring drivers
full time,
purchasing vehicles, what if
you can tap into a more
on demand pool of
independent contractors, and
only send orders to them
when they have time.
So, that's kind of the, the
insight we had,
we, everything was done
through mobile.
Yeah.
>> Did you know you were
gonna be a startup, or
just making some money on a
website, at first?
>> Yeah, I mean, at the time
we just wanted, we're all
really passionate about
building technology for
small business owners.
And honestly, this delivery
things came out of
an experiment, right, with
the landing page.
Like it was literally an
experiment.
We didn't, we weren't
expecting anything and
it just took off, and we
went with it.
And logistics was always
something we were
really passionate about as
well.
You know like logistics,
transportation.
It was kind of the perfect
fusion of, you know,
how do you help small
business owners do delivery?
Back there.
>> Do you launch the mobile
app first or the website?
And how long did it take
from idea to
your first launch?
>> Yeah, we started with
this landing page right
here.
Took us an hour to launch.
>> How does DoorDash stand
out in
a space filled with and
other companies.
>> Yeah, the question was
how does DoorDash stand out
among a very competitive
space.
I mean, at the beginning, I
mean for us, consumer demand
has never been the problem,
even up until now.
So, for us it's just about,
you know, finding a need and
just focusing on serving
that demand.
So, in the beginning,
competition doesn't really
matter when you're getting
started.
>> Yeah, question was how
long it took for
us to incorporate into a
company?
When we went through YC.
So, we launched in January
2013, and
then we did YC that very
summer, and we, when we
decided to take this idea
through YC, we incorporated.
>> One more?
Yeah you.
>> What do
you plan to do next, or
where do you plan to go
with this besides like food
delivery?
>> Yeah I mean, the question
was where do we plan to
go beyond food delivery?
I mean for us, when we
started door dash it
was always like I said
about.
Helping small business
owners and
figuring out, how do you
service for
any local merchant, whether
you are a Macaron store or
a restaurant or a furniture
shop.
I mean, that's still our
focus,
that's like the long-term
vision.
For now we're just focused
on rush on
delivery as a way to scale,
but
ultimately that's where we
want it end up in.
>> Cool.
>> Thanks.
>> Okay, next is Walker
Williams from Teespring,
Teespring at the YC, you're
in Africa?
>> Yeah.
>> I almost rejected them.
Sounds like a dumb idea but
now they're doing hundreds
of millions of
dollars a year of revenue so
very lucky to have him.
And Walker's gonna talk also
about doing things
non-scale.
>> All right.
Thank you guys for having
me.
My name is Walker.
I'm the CEO and founder of
Teespring, for
those of you guys who don't
know what Teespring is.
We're an e-commerce platform
that allows entrepreneurs to
launch products and
apparel brands without
risks, costs or compromise.
Today the company is about
180 folks and
we ship tens of thousands of
products each day,
and I wanna talk to you
about one of the most
fundamental advantages you
have as a start-up and
that's you're able to do
things that don't scale, and
I define things that don't
scale as things that
are sort of fundamentally
unsustainable.
They will not last,
they will not bring in the
millionth user and
where they break, it's
usually time, but
it could be a number of
other things.
But it's really growth
strategies that won't take
you to a million users and
there's three real places I
wanna focus on today.
First one is finding your
first users.
The second one is turning
those users into champions,
and the third one is finding
your product and market fit.
So finding your first users,
the first thing you have to
understand is that there is
no silver bullet for
user acquisition.
Everybody and this includes
me when we got started,
you look for that, that
dream solution,
that pay-per-click campaign
that has tremendous ROI.
Some accelerating
partnership that's gonna
springboard you into the
stratosphere, an affiliate
agreement, something that
solves it for you.
But the reality is for
the vast majority of
companies and
in fact, for every company
that I've had the chance to
speak to CEO of, that's just
not possible.
Those are unicorns and
most of the companies that
from the outside look
like they've had this dream
growth curve.
The reality is that those
first users were impossibly
hard to get and let me tell
you about
the story of a ridiculously
unsustainable business.
So, this is teespring in
2012.
When we first got, when we
first launched the business
couldn't have looked worse
it took days of meetings.
We had to offer free design
and
days of revisions back and
forth.
We'd have to launch the
product ourselves.
We'd have to do the social
media.
All the sell like 50 shirts
for a local non-profit, and
generate $1,000 of revenue,
anybody looking in would
have said.
You guys need to give up,
this is a terrible idea.
But as time went on, those
users started to
add up and I think something
you have to
understand is that when you
first launch a company,
just by virtue of the fact
that it's a new product,
you're gonna be bad at
selling it, right?
You've got no idea what the
paying points of customers
really are.
You've never sold it before.
You don't have any success
stories to point to or
testimonials.
Those first users are always
going to be the hardest, and
so it's your responsibility
as a founder to do
whatever it takes to bring
in your first users and
it's gonna be different for
every company.
The common thread that I
hear is founders need to
spend personal time and
effort.
A lot of their personal time
and
effort to bring those users
in themselves,
it can mean a number of
thing.
Everything from sending 100
emails a day, getting on
the phone and just calling
as many people as you can,
going through a network,
if you have a network like
Standford or Y Combinator.
Anything you can do to get
that first user and I really
equate it to pushing a
boulder up a hill and
if you think of like a very
sort of smooth hill,
when you get started.
The incline is the steepest
in those first inches are
the hardest and over time as
you get farther and farther.
The incline stays out, it
gets easier and
hopefully, eventually you
reached a point where you're
at the top of the hill and
the boulder starts to
roll on its own, and so
those first users,
you just cannot focus on ROI
in the sense of time.
Do not expect to spend an
hour and
return thousands of dollars.
Maybe Stanley is one of
those unicorns that was
a pretty incredible story.
But for most of us those
first users
are going to take a lot of a
hand holding, a lot of
personal love and that's
okay, that's essential for
building a company, and the
one sort of caveat of that
is that I don't recommend
giving away your product for
free and there's plenty of
exceptions to this rule.
But in general cutting costs
or giving the product away
is an unsustainable strategy
I wouldn't recommend.
You need to make sure that
users value your product and
people have a different,
they treat products that
are free in a much different
way than a paid product and
often times it can give you
a false sense of security if
oh, we're getting all these
users surely we
can convert them over to
paid.
The second aspect is what
happens when you get those
users, how do you turn those
users into champions and
a champion is a user who
talks about and
advocates for your product.
And I'm a firm believer that
every company with a great
growth strategy has users
who are champions and so
really the easiest way to
build.
Turn a user in to a champion
is to delight them with
an experience their gonna
remember so
something that's unusual or
out of the ordinary an
exceptional experience and
the easiest way to do this
early and
again something that is
completely unsustainable,
it's not gonna scale forever
is to just talk to
those users and people will
say this all the time,
and you hear it.
It's one of the sort of core
tenants of why
combinators talk to users
but I cannot stress
how important it is that you
spend a large chunk of your
time talking to users, and
you should do it constantly,
every single day and as long
as possible.
Today at Teespring,
I'm still the catch all
email address, so
anytime somebody misspells
support or writes an email
address that doesn't exist,
I get that email, and so
I still do about 12 to 20
customer service tickets
every single day.