https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQOC-qy-GDY
I spend hours each night
reading every single tweet,
probably a little bit OCD,
but that's okay.
I read through all the
Teespring communities.
You're never gonna get a
better sense for
your product than actually
listening to real users, and
especially in the early
days, you're just,
the products you launch
with, and
the features set you launch
with, is almost certainly
not going to be the feature
set that you scale with and
the quicker you talk to
users and
learn what they actually
need,.
The faster you can get to
that point.
So there's three ways to
talk to your customers,
you can run customer service
yourself,
up until Teespring was doing
about $130-$140,000 a month
my co-founder Evan and
I did everything in customer
service.
This is one that there's
gonna be an instinct to
quickly pass off and that's
because it's painful.
Even today, when I open our
customer service
portal, I have like an
emotional reaction where my
stomach sinks because it
sucks talking to users
who have had a terrible
experience and it's painful.
It's something that you love
and you put so
much effort into and you've
gotten it wrong or
they've had a terrible
experience or
somebody didn't treat them
right.
But it's so important that
you go through that and
learn what you need to
build, what you need to fix.
The second step is to
proactively reach out
to current and churned
customers and
churned customers are
customers who have left, and
this is one that often falls
by the wayside in sort of.
The pursuit of new customers
but you wanna make sure that
your customers are having a
consistent, good experience.
You don't wanna just leave
those current users as
sort of, you don't want take
them for granted and
then when a user actually
leaves your service,.
You wanna reach out and
find out why both because
that personal outreach can
make the difference between
leaving and staying.
Sometimes people just need
to know that you care and
it's going to get better and
because even if you can't
bring them back
there's a chance that you
can learn from the mistake
that you made that caused
them to leave and fix it so
you don't churn users out
the same way in the future.
And the final one is, again,
the one that I'm probably
too OCD about, but
it's social media and
communities.
You need to know how
people are talking about
your brand.
You need to reach out and
make sure that,
when somebody does have a
bad experience and
they're talking about it,
that you make it right.
Problems are inevitable in
start-ups,
there's gonna be issues,
you're not gonna have the
perfect product,
things are gonna break,
things are gonna go wrong.
That's not important, what's
important is to
always make it right, to
always go the extra mile and
make that customer happy.
One detractor who has had a
terrible experience on your
platform is enough to
reverse the progress of
ten champions.
It's all it takes is one
person out there to say, no.
You shouldn't use those guys
for X, Y, and
Z reason, to ruin a ton of
momentum.
So even if it's there's
examples in the early
days where we would mess up
massive orders.
We would print the colors
slightly wrong,
it would be the wrong size
and
it would be like half of our
GMV for
that month and we would know
we got it wrong.
The customer would be
unhappy and
sort of this instinct is
well, it's only a little bit
off or it's not completely
wrong it'll be fine.
But the reality is you've
just got to bite the bullet
and make sure that's it
right, and those customers,
the customers that are often
originally the most
frustrated tend to turn into
the biggest champions and
the longest term users.
And the last one I
wanna talk about is finding
product and market fit and
what I mean that is that I
mentioned this earlier.
But the product you launch
with will almost certainly
not be the product that
takes you to scale and so
you're job in those early
moments or
those early days of a
start-up.
Is to progress and iterate
as fast as possible to reach
that product that does have
market fit and as engineers
you're instinct is gonna be
to build a platform with
beautiful clean code that
scales right?
You don't wanna write sort
of duct tape code that's
gonna pile on technical
debt.
But you need to optimize for
speed over scalability and
clean code and sort of an
example of this is,
in the early days,
we had a couple enterprise
customers come to us.
Sort of bigger non-profits
and
say, hey, we really like
your service but
you're missing these
fundamental things.
So we can't, we're not gonna
use it and we looked at sort
of what it would take to
build out those features and
we weren't sure they were
gonna work long-term, but
we wanted to try it.
And my co-founder Evan who
is our CTO and a million
times better developer than
I am, sort of run the map
and figured out that if we
did it the right way.
It was gonna take about a
month to build out
these features and
in a start-up, a month you
live in dog years.
A month is a year and that
just wasn't gonna do.
So he actually went out,
duplicated the code base,
duplicated the database and
was able to
basically build a completely
different product that he
didn't have to worry about
the existing users for,
to serve these enterprise
customers.
We gave them the tool,
they on-boarded, they
generate a lot of revenue.
Eventually, we learned what
features were core and
we integrated them into the
core product, but
what would have taken a
month,
we were able to do in three
to four days.
A great rule of thumb is to
only worry about the next
order of magnitude.
So when you have your tenth
user, you shouldn't be
wondering, well, how are we
gonna serve a million users.
You should be worried about
how are we gonna get to 100?
When you're at 100, you
should think about 1,000.
It's one of those things
where necessity is
the mother of invention of
all inventions.
So, when you hit that
breaking point, like
the Twitter Fail Whale is a
great example and Teespring.
There were months, month
stretches where
every single night, the site
would crash, every night and
during the day and every
single person on the team
would go to sleep with their
phone on loud under their
pillow so that inevitably,
when the buzzer went off,
we could quickly get up,
restart the servers and
go back to sleep and this
would happen daily.
But the reality is that it
was worth it and
you'll end up with these
huge pain points and
all this technical debt and
regret.
But it's worth it, just to
get to that end goal and
that product fit faster, you
will make it work,
you will survive that those
sort of bumps are just speed
bumps and speed is so, so
important early.
So, the lesson that I've
been learning lately is
you want to do these things
that don't scale as long
as possible.
There's not some magical
moment,
it's not the series A, it's
not when you hit a certain
revenue milestone that you
stop doing things that
don't scale.
This is one of your biggest
advantages as a company,
and the moment you give it
up.
You're giving your
competitors that are smaller
that can still do things,
that advantage over you.
So, as long as humanly
possible,
as long as it is a net
positive,
you need to be spending time
talking to your users.
You need to move fast in
development,
as fast as possible.
But don't give it up
willingly, it should be
ripped from you, and so sort
of trying to practice what I
preach I wanna give you guys
my email address.
If you guys have any
questions,
if you wanna learn about
Teespring,
if you wanna print some
t-shirts, fingers crossed,
just shoot me an email.
I'd love to help and I'd
love to speak to you.
And the last thing is we've
created an official how to
start a start up tee with
Sam.
And all proceeds are going
to Watsi.
I couldn't miss this
opportunity to sell.
So if you guys wanna grab
one of the official tees,
just go to
teespring.com/startup and
it's supporting a great
cause.
Thank you.
Sure.
Go ahead.
Yep.
The T-shirt printing
business, it seems like it
has a lot of So what made
you, what convinced you, to
think this is a viable
market even with all that's
going on in the world today?
Sure.
You know, so the question
was, the T-shirt printing
business has a lot of
competition.
What would convince us to
get into the market?
I think there's two factors
to it.
So first, I completely
agree.
From the outside, people
have been telling us
that this is a silly idea
since day one.
And sort of that every order
of magnitude we reach,
people will come and say
hey, that's a terrible,
terrible idea why are you
doing that?
But the reason that we
launched Teespring is
because we ran into a
personal pain point where we
had a need and we looked at
the current solutions.
I was a student at Brown,
and
I was trying to create a
remember the bar shirt for
a dive bar that got shut
down.
And I realized that nothing
needed,
nothing matched my needs.
And so, because I knew that
I had that pain point.
And I knew there was market
fit and
I had seen people adopt the
product.
I knew there was something
there and
it was also one of those
things where you,
you can sort of feel the,
you can sort of
feel the wind on your back
where people are adopting
the product quickly, the
pain point is clearly there.
It's not a met need.
So, I would say that
oftentimes great ideas start
by looking like silly ideas.
And then you can sort of
feel out whether or
not there's a scalable
business here by how people
are adopting it.
Is it possible to bring
customers aboard?
Sure.
Are non-profits your biggest
customer base, like?
No.
You know, today our
biggest customer base are
entrepreneurs who
are trying to build brands
and businesses.
You know, we have a little
over a 1,000 people that
make their full time living
on
Teespring today via brands
they've launched and
the other side is
influencers,
so YouTube stars, Reddit
communities, bloggers who
want to add product
merchandise as a way to sort
of create a brand and and
monetize that affinity.
So those are our two biggest
markets.
We still do work with a lot
of non-profits and
love working with them.
It's still a part of
our business just not the
majority.
Thank you.
Yeah.
All right, now we'll have
Justin talk.
Justin was the founder of
KeyCo, and then JustinTV,
which Twitch and is now and
he's going to talk about PR.
Cool.
Well, while I wait for
the slide to happen, I
started a bunch of startups
but I think you've heard a
lot of awesome, you know,
kind of how did I get
started stories.
So I'm gonna talk about
something very specific,
that people always have
questions with,
which is press and how do
you get it.