ERIKA NAGINSKI: So let's turn to Wittkower's analysis of Alberti, and on particular,
https://youtu.be/8EHkrqgkv4s
Alberti's relationship to antiquity.
What does it mean for a Renaissance architect
to look back to the classical past and deploy those forms in the context
of religious architecture?
If you think about it, this is not self-evident.
What does it mean to take classicism, which is a pagan idiom,
and introduce it to the context of Christian architecture?
This symbolic aspect is not so much Wittkower's problem.
He's after explaining how to match up one formal system against another.
He begins his inquiry with a problem, and that problem
is related to what we call a trabeated system or a post-and-lintel system,
which indicates classicism's reliance on horizontal beams or lintels
that are held up by columns or pillars.
Now, one of the curious aspects of Alberti's architectural theory
is the distinction he draws between a notion of an architecture of the wall,
on the one hand, which is a structural statement, and on the other hand,
the question of the column, which crucially for Alberti-- and this
may seem counter-intuitive-- belongs to the realm of ornament,
of the decorative.
And by relegating the column to the realm of the decorative, Alberti,
according to Wittkower, confronted one of the fundamental problems
of Renaissance architecture.
How do you define a wall?
So to explain this, Wittkower offers the diagram
that you see here with the following explanation.
These are his words.
"In his religious buildings.
Alberti consistently avoided the combination of arch and column."
That's what you see on the right-hand side of the diagram.
"When Alberti uses columns, he did, in fact, give them a straight entablature,
while when he introduced arches, he made them rest on pillars."
And that's what you see on the left-hand side of the diagram.
Sometimes these pillars had half columns adossed to them,
emphasizing their decorative role.
Wittkower continues,
"Whereas the first motif is Greek, the second is Roman."
The first motif is based on the functional meaning of the column.
It's supporting those arches.
The second is based on the cohesion and unity of the wall.
To explain the latter point, in the Coliseum,
the arch pillars may be interpreted as residues of a pierced wall
with half columns which carry the straight entablatures placed on them
entirely as ornament.
That's very explicitly carried out at the Coliseum.
Arches rest on pillars.
The column and the entablature are purely decorative.
Ultimately, Wittkower's argument will be that in the architecture of churches,
Alberti is going to reject the column entirely and turn
towards a pure expression of the wall, a kind of architecture of the wall.
And he's going to do this by examining four commissions.
The first is the Tempio Malatestiano in Rimini.
The second is Santa Maria Novella in Florence.
The third and fourth, both in Mantua, are San Sebastiano and Sant'Andrea.
What is convenient about these four commissions
is that they offer a neat chronology.
They offer a sequence in time, and Wittkower takes this chronology
to trace out the development of Alberti's thinking on architecture.
Buildings, in other words, become part of a single investigation
of classical modalities in the context of religious structures.