ERIKA NAGINSKI: Hãy chuyển sang những phân tích của Wittkower về Alberti,
https://youtu.be/8EHkrqgkv4s
đặc biệt là mối quan hệ của Alberti đối với quá khứ cổ xưa.
Điều đó có nghĩa là gì khi một kiến trúc sư thời phục hưng
nhìn lại quá khứ cổ điển và khai thác những hình thức này
trong bối cảnh kiến trúc tôn giáo?
Nếu suy nghĩ về điều đó thì đây không phải là hiển nhiên.
Điều dó có nghĩa là gì khi sử dụng chủ nghĩa cổ điển, một thành ngữ tà giáo,
và giới thiệu nó trong bối cảnh kiến trúc cơ đốc giáo?
Khía cạnh biểu tượng này không hẳn là vấn đề của Wittkower.
Ông làm thế nào để kết hợp một hệ thống chính thức với một hệ thống khác.
Ông bắt đầu cuộc điều tra của mình bằng một vấn đề
liên quan tới
Hệ thống này chỉ ra sự phụ thuộc của chủ nghĩa cổ diển vào những thanh xà
hay lanh tô ngang được đỡ bởi các cột trụ.
Một trong những khía cạnh gây tò mò nhất trong lý thuyết kiến trúc của Alberti
is the distinction he draws between a notion of an architecture of the wall,
on the one hand, which is a structural statement, and on the other hand,
the question of the column, which crucially for Alberti-- and this
may seem counter-intuitive-- belongs to the realm of ornament,
of the decorative.
And by relegating the column to the realm of the decorative, Alberti,
according to Wittkower, confronted one of the fundamental problems
of Renaissance architecture.
How do you define a wall?
So to explain this, Wittkower offers the diagram
that you see here with the following explanation.
These are his words.
"In his religious buildings.
Alberti consistently avoided the combination of arch and column."
That's what you see on the right-hand side of the diagram.
"When Alberti uses columns, he did, in fact, give them a straight entablature,
while when he introduced arches, he made them rest on pillars."
And that's what you see on the left-hand side of the diagram.
Sometimes these pillars had half columns adossed to them,
emphasizing their decorative role.
Wittkower continues,
"Whereas the first motif is Greek, the second is Roman."
The first motif is based on the functional meaning of the column.
It's supporting those arches.
The second is based on the cohesion and unity of the wall.
To explain the latter point, in the Coliseum,
the arch pillars may be interpreted as residues of a pierced wall
with half columns which carry the straight entablatures placed on them
entirely as ornament.
That's very explicitly carried out at the Coliseum.
Arches rest on pillars.
The column and the entablature are purely decorative.
Ultimately, Wittkower's argument will be that in the architecture of churches,
Alberti is going to reject the column entirely and turn
towards a pure expression of the wall, a kind of architecture of the wall.
And he's going to do this by examining four commissions.
The first is the Tempio Malatestiano in Rimini.
The second is Santa Maria Novella in Florence.
The third and fourth, both in Mantua, are San Sebastiano and Sant'Andrea.
What is convenient about these four commissions
is that they offer a neat chronology.
They offer a sequence in time, and Wittkower takes this chronology
to trace out the development of Alberti's thinking on architecture.
Buildings, in other words, become part of a single investigation
of classical modalities in the context of religious structures.