ERIKA NAGINSKI: Wittkower's first case study
https://youtu.be/8rZLI_9XWJ0
is what you see here. It's a small church in the city of Rimini
Italy on the Adriatic Coast. It was originally
a 13th century Gothic structure, so belonged to an entirely
different stylistic and cultural moment. The structure named
San Francesco, in other words, St. Francis, was run by the Franciscan Order,
and, since the 19th century, it's been known
as the Tempio Malatestiano, after the man you also see, Sigismondo Malatesta.
He was an extraordinary character.
This is a portrait by Piero della Francesca from about 1451.
Malatesta was a Renaissance nobleman who became Lord Rimini at the age of 14,
and became its sole ruler after abolishing
the authority of his brothers.
He was a notorious despot, and politically savvy vis-à-vis much more
powerful city-states.
And this earned him actually a temporary spot
as commander in chief of the nothing less than the papal armies.
Eventually, the Vatican was going to turn against him,
going so far as to condemn him to Hell for the rest of his lifetime.
This was obviously not commissioned at this moment.
The church was essentially a reconstruction
of the original structure, and it dates from about the time of Piero's portrait
from about 1450.
The archival evidence is scanty, which in many ways
makes this a perfect case study for Wittkower who's
less interested in those historical documents.
It's not clear, for example, when Alberti came on board,
nor what requirements there were for the design, what
they were meant to be like.
Was a dome part of the equation?
Or how the relationship played out between Alberti
as designer and his forceful patron, along with the builder in question,
Matteo de' Pasti.
What we do know is that in addition to making detailed drawings,
Alberti had a wooden model made--
this is lost today--
and a good part of the facade was up by 1454,
so work progressed rather quickly.
It's important to underscore that this was Alberti's very
first ecclesiastical commission. The patron's aim was
to turn the Church of St. Francis into a mausoleum for himself and his wife.
So it had a kind of personal commemorative function.
It's an unfinished project.
You can see this by the picture of the facade.
There was perhaps a projected dome, which was supposed to be hemispherical,
and it's a shape that was meant, therefore,
to mimic the Pantheon in Rome and, therefore,
allude to the classical past in a very grandiose way.
That dome was never built, and Alberti's facade was never finished.
This is, in large part, because of the question of the patron.
The patron's fortunes went awry.
He was actually excommunicated in 1460, so a mere six years after the facade
was, for the most part, erected, and he died in 1468.
Now, if you look at the facade, you'll see
that to either side of the entrance, there are two blind arcades.
We know that these were originally meant to house a sarcophagus for Malatesta
as well as another one for his wife, although there
is some disagreement about this.
But the idea adds consistency to the explanation
offered by Wittkower of a united whole, of a united
monumental and commemorative purpose for the whole.
What's interesting here is to do what Wittkower didn't
do, to think about the context of this.
For example, the pope at the time thought
this was a blasphemous structure, a blasphemous idea.
He decided that to plaster a classical facade on this church,
to turn it into an evocation of the Pantheon
was actually turning the church into something that was quote,
and this is the pope himself, "Full of pagan gods and profane things.
So full of pagan images that it seems like a temple
for the worshippers of demons."
This is obviously a conflicted commission.
Again, Wittkower's not interested in these issues.
What he sees in the Tempio is the first in a sequence
of four churches in which Alberti is carrying out
a systematic investigation of the fusion of classical system,
or classical principles in Christian buildings.
The building poses a problem, and he offers
a certain kind of answer or solution.
So problem one:
The Tempio, or how to impose a classical aspect
onto or over a preexisting medieval structure.
How do you do that?
Alberti's answer is to introduce to the facade
a variation on the Roman triumphal arch while reconsidering
the entire envelope of the building as an antique temple--
almost putting a classical box around the whole structure.
This is the first isolated church facade to do this in the Renaissance,
and this is why it's such an important example.
It started a trend, in other words.
And in Wittkower's words, Alberti was grafting the idea of the triumphal arch
right up onto the wall.
So given the patron's demands, this actually makes sense.
It's a clever response.
The idea of the triumph over death,
and you have a triple arch motif on the facade, with the central arch
over the door, and side arches for the sarcophagi.
You get a sense of what this Pantheon effect would have been like when
you look at the side of the church.
Both sides offered a deep arcade.
Think back to the Coliseum
here.
This deep arcade was based on a pillar and arch construction.
You have pillars and you have arches springing from them.
This is actually a form of construction that
stems from ancient Roman aqueducts.
Now, Malatesta planned to have the sarcophagi of this sort of illustrious men--
the poets, the artists, the scholars of his court--
inserted into the deep recesses offered by the arches.
Now, if you look at the plan, you'll notice that the original church,
conveniently, has a rectangular format.
It's a medieval church with a single nave and no side aisles,
extending into a large, semicircular apse.
Now, part of Alberti's plan was to transform
this basically simple and straight rectangle
by means of a large rotunda that would support a massive dome at the crossing.
The nave was meant to be covered over by a barrel vault made
of timber, and over this, a pitched roof over the side chapels and the nave.
One of the things you'll notice about the plan
is that the windows are actually unevenly distributed at the sides,
and Alberti screens this asymmetry, if you will, with the Roman arches
held up by piers, and the whole, as it were,
is elevated on a kind of antique-style podium.
He's, in other words, putting his own theory into practice.
If we turn to Alberti's own theoretical treatise in his Book
7 on Sacred Buildings, he writes, quote, "In my opinion,
the space taken up by the portico and indeed the whole temple
should be raised above the level of the city.
This will give it a greater air of dignity."
This idea of elevating the church and placing it on a podium, of making it
function as the sacred center of an urban context.
You see the podium effect here.
What remains of Alberti's design is most visible actually on the outside
rather than on the interior.
And you also can gather the repercussions
of what it means to impose a triumphal arch idea on a church facade.
The other important aspect of all of this
is that his classical source was local.
It's what you see:
The arch of the Roman emperor, Augustus.
What Alberti is doing here is that he's playing with classical motifs.
He's not copying them verbatim.
He keeps the roundels of the arch--
he transposes them onto the facade--
as well as the relation of the arch, the fluted
engaged columns, and the spandrel.
The spandrel is actually the space between a curved element
and a rectangular boundary.
And then he places a triangular pediment over the door, inside
of the arch on the facade rather than above it, as you see in the actual arch.
The capitals are in the spirit of anticomenia and in the playfulness
that we see with Wittkower, completely his invention.
Now for Wittkower, Alberti's approach to architecture
is to create a series of problems to solve.
The first challenge is that a triumphal arch is essentially
a one-story structure.
But when a church facade has to screen a very high central nave
between the chapels or lower aisles to either side,
the screen needs to be a two-story structure.
So how do you transform a triumphal arch,
which is a one-story structure, into a two-story structure
to mask the entirety of the church?
You're faced, as an architect, with the problem of extending a one-story system
to a two-story system.
There were Venetian precedents for this.
They were Byzantine and Gothic, such as Saint Mark's in Venice or the Frari.
So when Alberti tries to plaster a classical system on this,
what Wittkower does is to engage in a kind of game
to reconstruct what Alberti's intentions were.
He surmises the elements of the facade and the composition
of the facade that were never completed but must,
if you follow Wittkower's logic, have aimed
for unity in its classical scheme.
There's a key piece of evidence in the story.
It's a medal by a sculptor and medalist Matteo de' Pasti,
who collaborated with Alberti on the design
and the construction of the church.
That medal shows a huge hemispherical dome,
low curved walls placed above a heavily articulated entablature over the side
bays.
What the medal reveals is a fully elaborated second-story
arch over the central bay, above the entrance,
and it's clearly articulated as a small shrine, what we call an aedicula,
with a window divided into three parts sitting in the niche,
and the whole is crowned by a floral motif.
We see the legacy of this idea in Venice
in a monastery church of San Michele in Isola.
The evidence is that, in 1454, Alberti actually changed his mind
and switched the curved walls of the upper part
for straight sloping walls, decorated with large scrolls.
Still, ultimately, Alberti's scheme reveals
a classically derived system on the lower story,
and essentially a kind of medieval concept
above, despite the classical details.
By classicism, it's important to underscore
that I don't mean some generic notion of the classic,
but that we're referring very specifically to the Greco-Roman past
of Western civilization.
Now, for Italian Renaissance architects, this really
meant ancient Rome, not Greece.
Italian architects did not go to Ancient Greece.
They did not see the Acropolis firsthand,
but what they had around them, surrounding them in Florence, in Rome,
were the remnants of Republican and Imperial Rome:
the Pantheon, the Coliseum.
Problem number two:
How the entablature at the point at which it projects above each column
confounds the attempt to coordinate the lower story with the upper story.
And this is where the work of the diagram comes in.
When Wittkower has demonstrated in his schematization of the facade
is an attempt to resolve the contradiction of the lower
story with the upper story.
On the one hand, the composition as a whole
is rigorously faithful to Alberti's theory of architecture.
Remember that for him, columns were decorative,
and here, the columns remain, in principle,
the decoration of the facade, following his sense that the column needed
to be ornamental and not structural.
This is Alberti.
Quote: "The principal ornament in all architecture
certainly lies in the column."
While on the side of the building, as we saw,
the wall is aligned with a pillar arch construction.
He derives the design of the sides from the facade,
but strips the sides of the columns.
That's one side of the story.
On the other hand, there's what Wittkower is showing with his diagram,
with his lines, which actually have different weight if you look at them.
What his diagram foregrounds is actually a series
of disrupted rhythms, which come from his assessment
of the visual essence of the element.
The entablatures should, by a logic, create a horizontal barrier
between the lower register and above.
The interesting thing is that you also expect a vertical continuation,
and that's what you see in the central bay with the entrance
and that niche, or aedicula, above it.
This part accentuates the verticality of the building,
not the horizontality of the building.
What happens here is that fundamentally, we are left with a contradiction.
While the central vertical thrust remains apparent,
it is challenged, according to Wittkower,
by the high base, that podium on which all of the columns rest,
as well as the side bays, which emphasize
a horizontal aspect to the facade.
You can see him drawing the lines in bold
to emphasize this contradictory state to prove his point.
The result, for Wittkower, is that the outer bays
are closed off by the common base that links them, but left open at the top.
There's nothing above them.
There's nothing that closes them off.
And according to Wittkower, exactly the opposite happens in the central bay--
where there is no podium linking the two central columns, but their verticality
is emphasized.
Ultimately for Wittkower, these complicated rhythms
of the Tempio's facade leave its quote unquote "unity" completely unresolved.
And this is the point of the diagram, to show us, in the most distilled
way possible, that Alberti's daring, imaginative, but ultimately
failed project, was an attempt to resolve two incompatible systems.
What does it mean to put a classical envelope on a medieval structure?
What does it mean to impose a one-story logic taken from the Roman triumphal
arch, and impose it on a structure that required a two-story solution?
Ultimately, the diagram demonstrates Alberti's attempt
to capture an ideal formula.