ERIKA NAGINSKI: This brings us to the last two churches in the sequence.
https://youtu.be/vzHJXk5Kqjk
Churches whose designs are, in fact, ones
that foreground the fact that columns are now entirely absent.
Remember Alberti's distinction with which
we began between the notion of a wall architecture--
in other words, an architecture that affirms the idea of structure
as opposed to the column, which for him, remains in the realm of the decorative.
This distinction prompts Wittkower to claim
that the complete absence of columns in the two churches that you see here--
San Sebastiano in Mantua, begun in 1460, and Sant'Andrea, also in Mantua,
begun in 1462--
that in these churches where columns are absent
signifies a kind of decisive turning point in Alberti's project,
in his interpretation of architecture writ large.
With this idea, with these words, Wittkower's actually
bringing us back to the terrain of syntax, of ratio of architecture in relation
to objectivity.
Now, both churches were commissioned by the same patron,
the ruler of Mantua, Ludovico Gonzaga.
They are slightly different.
In fact, San Sabastiano is a central planned church.
It's a votive church which was never completed, and what we see today
is heavily restored.
Sant'Andrea, by contrast, is far more complete.
And in both cases, unlike the Tempio in Rimini
and Santa Maria Novella in Florence, Alberti
was not faced with the problem of adapting
his designs to a preexisting structure.
In other words, this idea of inventing the church whole cloth
means that Wittkower can analyze the facades as theoretical solutions
to an architectural problem.
For Wittkower, the two facades coincide as well as stand
as kind of polar opposites of each other.
On the one hand, if you look at them, the main proportions
are essentially the same.
Like Santa Maria Novella, the width corresponds
to the height from the level of the entrance to the apex of the pediment.
There's the enclosure within the square once more.
On the other hand, we have opposing conceptions of the facade here.
San Sebastiano underscores the presence of as much solid wall as possible.
It affirms the wall as principle, and this is the opposite of what we see
in Sant'Andrea where, besides the enormous and deeply recessed entrance,
the side bays have been broken up into three tiers of thresholds--
of doors, of niches, of windows.
Again, just as from the very beginning, the idea of the triumphal arch
motif as a solution to masking the two-story problem of a church
remains the reference here in these new churches,
remains the essential antique source for the facade,
as somehow the appropriate classical source for religious structure.
Now in his reconstruction of San Sebastiano,
Wittkower is going to emphasize the temple facade raised on its podium
again, just as we saw with the Tempio, and reached
by this broad monumental stair in the antique manner,
raising the church above the city fabric somehow, at least symbolically.
The facade is articulated by six equidistant pilasters,
and a broken entablature with an arched window behind it.
The source this time is another triumphal arch,
the Arch of Tiberius in Orange.
And what I've always found strange is that Wittkower
fails to mention that the arrangement of elements we see on the church
are actually coming from the east side of the arch, not the front.
Now with Sant'Andrea, there's another arch, the Arch of Trajan in Ancona.
This is what comes into play with one large passage and two narrower bays
that are also cut into three spaces.
The argument is that while the classical temple front,
with its columns and entablatures and pediment,
is a reference for both churches, this time he's pushed out the inner room
with its walls-- the so-called cella--
into the orders, abolishing any freestanding column and entablatures
and instead privileging the idea of the wall, of privileging,
ultimately, structure over ornament.
Here's Wittkower:
"The Tempio and Santa Maria Novella are connected in
so far as they show the compromise of wall and column, a compromise which
was later abandoned.
Here the compliance with the authority of classical motifs
was replaced by their interpretation in terms of a consistent wall
architecture."
Alberti, according to Wittkower, moved from columns and ornament
to the affirmation of the wall.
Where we had an exploration of the ornamental meaning of classicism,
now we have moved to a structural understanding of classical antiquity.
And this is what renders Alberti revolutionary in Wittkower's eyes.
So to conclude, let's think about Wittkower's Alberti.
For Wittkower, the four churches offer a coherent sequence.
From the very beginning, we are given a problem,
how to give a church, a religious edifice, a classical aspect.
How to find the sources that are going to solve
the problem of masking a two-story structure
and, ultimately, coming in the end at an aesthetic affirmation of the whole,
of some ideal principle of unity.
One of the dangers here, of course, is to confuse Wittkower with Alberti.
We want to make sure that we understand that Wittkower's approach, which
is about using diagrams to distill some kind of fundamental understanding
of architecture and its elements, is about schematizing buildings.
He is not going to want to address Alberti's exploration of vernacular
aesthetics that are part of a far more eclectic understanding
of religious architecture than Wittkower allows.
However, to think about Wittkower's reading of Alberti
is also to understand an approach that fundamentally
looks at the diagram as the revelatory tool for understanding
architecture and its development.
In this sense, by using the diagram, he's
actually turning to a mode of interpretation that
relies on the schema, and here we can recognize, actually,
an approach inspired by the philosopher Immanuel
Kant, who looks at the architectural imagination as the very thing that
schematizes the complexity of the world and transforms it
into an ideal that is presented as an objective principle
or axiom to the understanding.