[MUSIC PLAYING]
https://youtu.be/aI1R0ltbkiQ
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Wittkower's interpretation of the work of Alberti
and Argan's account of the work of Brunelleschi give us two examples
of Kant-inspired historians attributing to architecture the status
of an ongoing formal project--
a project of speculation and conjecture that takes
place in the architectural imagination.
We now look to put that idea into dialectical play with the movement
of architecture through history.
To return to history is to return this internal world constructed
by architecture, this world of aesthetic perfection,
to the more robust world in which we all reside.