K. MICHAEL HAYS: At the other end of history, architecture will find its primary form
https://youtu.be/3BCFmy5jJO0
in the interior.
So we move away from the object that marks and toward the interior.
This is the romantic stage of architecture,
and its paradigm is the Gothic cathedral.
Hegel conceptualized the Gothic cathedral
as an enormous interior landscape.
Think of all the activities that take place in a cathedral in medieval times.
There was bartering, there was trading, as well as worship.
There was a gathering, maybe even there were celebrations
of the community as a collective space.
It's a civic space.
It's almost like an urban interior.
And the great Gothic cathedrals, which Hegel knew, which he had visited,
were so large that they almost take on a kind of atmosphere.
They have a kind of interior atmosphere.
The stone of the cathedral, very unlike the stone of the pyramids,
is a stone that denies its own stone-ness.
It's been carved away.
It's been ornamented.
It's been decorated and refined until the stone seems to be
just vectors of energy surging upward.
And then there's the stained glass, of course,
modulates the light, modulates this atmosphere.
And the space takes on a kind of diaphanous quality,
a kind of lace-like quality.
It's important that it's collective.
It's important that it's dematerialized because here, the Spirit,
in the romantic period, is leaving the sensuous realm, is leaving nature,
is leaving the object realm, and becoming more conceptual,
becoming more self-conscious--
more self-conscious, more conceptual, and less material.