K. MICHAEL HAYS: The idea of Spirit appearing, of, sort of, shining forth
https://youtu.be/bAIiSEnRt4E
in objects of art is important,
and Hegel defends a kind of two-fold thesis about this.
For him, it is the sensuous material, everyday world that is the illusion
because it's not imbued enough with Spirit.
Art is showing-- is more real in a way, because it shows forth Spirit.
And Hegel uses the term "der Schein," which
literally means appearance, but also has an English cognate, which is, exactly,
"shining," a kind of shining forth.
So art shines forth in the sense that it transforms the sensuous world.
It transforms the material world into a representation of Spirit
through the work of the imagination.
Hegel believed that in the Romantic when art has moved,
is moving out of the material realm into the conceptual--
actually, was a prologue to the end of art.
Now, Hegel never said that art died.
He actually never said that art would end.
What he said was grand art, great art is past.
Even in his own time he believed that as spirit grew into self-identity,
that material forms, material objects were
no longer adequate to represent Spirit.
Interestingly, the other part of his model
is that as he moves from symbolic to classical to romantic,
even though each of those epochs have all
of the art medium represented in them, the paradigm of the symbolic
is architecture.
The real paradigm of the classical is sculpture,
because of this adequation of the human form to spiritual expression.
The real paradigm of the romantic is painting and music.
Why painting and music?
Painting is two-dimensional.
It starts to move out of the three-dimensional, physical, material
world into the realm of pure vision, a pure representation.
And music is even less material or more dematerialized.
The material of music is just time and rhythm.
And Hegel privileges music in the romantic.
Because he thought that the time and rhythm of music
was really representing or uniting with the time and rhythm of human
thought itself.
So music is the most conceptual art.
But then, finally, a Spirit achieves self-identity.
It moves away from art altogether.
And it moves toward philosophy and theology.
And these are the ultimate, in a way, representations of Spirit.
After that, Spirit no longer needs art to represent itself.
This is not to say that art doesn't continue.
This is not to say that art-- that humans still
produce art for other reasons.
But for Hegel it no longer produces art to represent Spirit.
So Hegel has it both ways.
He constructs an aesthetic whose very conception of possibility,
a very condition of possibility is that it moves through time, as it more
adequately represents Spirit.
And as the aesthetic moves through time it becomes less material.
It becomes more conceptual, until finally, it becomes thought itself.
And the adequate activity, the adequate process of Spirit
is no longer the materialization and the appearance through art,
but is actually thought itself.
So the aesthetic necessarily concludes at the end of history
by abolishing itself and becoming thought.
This doesn't mean that art will cease to exist.
Art practice will continue.
But it will find other opportunities, other cultural uses for its existence.
Hegel has a very beautiful quotation about philosophy--
"Philosophy always arrives too late.
As the thought of the world, it only makes its appearance
after actuality has finished its process of development and is over.
...Only in the maturation of actuality does the ideal appear to confront the real.
Then the ideal reconstructs this world for itself
in the form of an intellectual realm, comprehending in its substance.
When philosophy paints its grey on grey then the form of life has grown old,
and this grey on grey is not capable of rejuvenating it, merely of
understanding it.
The owl of Minerva only begins its flight when the twilight falls."