[MUSIC PLAYING]
https://youtu.be/yLSCG3DEoqI
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Scholars following Hegel often
insist that Hegel closed the door on art prematurely,
and it's rather that each epoch has to make its own decision as to what
the function of its art will be.
So let's say it's an open question whether art can continue,
in our own time, its vocation of giving appearance
to our distinctively human values.
In any case, what we want to keep from Hegel
is, first, that the importance of architecture
is not just its aesthetics but its deep historicity--
by that, I mean the felt fact of architecture existing in time as well
as in space.
And second is Hegel's placement of architecture at the center of human
existence, not as the work of isolated individuals--
though he knew they were architects, and he knew there were individual
builders--
but he placed the work of architecture at the center of existence
as a work of what he called the "Spirit," which, for us, means
of the community, of the collective.
Now, making much more modest claims, we want
to look at the work of a modern architect who
shares Hegel's understanding that architecture
is one of the fundamental postulates of our existence in the world,
of the way we are being in the world, and a central medium
of human thought and human memory.
For Aldo Rossi, architecture in our own time
must struggle with this lack of meaning, with this pastness
to which Hegel condemned architecture.
But in Rossi's work, there's also the suggestion
that the challenge of architecture's origin is not just behind us, that--
as Hegel insisted-- but that architecture
is finding its origin again and again, that it has to constantly
be re-enacted, that it has to constantly be reimagined,
and that architecture is constantly beginning again.