K. MICHAEL HAYS: I've mentioned the persistence of types, what
https://youtu.be/KFhooDK6UDA
Rossi calls "typological permanence."
But there's another dimension, another sort of temporality to type
that we might call the "anteriority of type,"
for it's not the case in Rossi's thinking
that the type just continues-- that once it emerges, once it's manifest,
that the type simply continues.
The type for Rossi is already there before the design effort,
before the actual construction, perhaps, even
before the architect's imagination of it--
that the type pre-exist the architectural act.
The best example of the anteriority of type
comes in Rossi's explanation of what he means by "the analogous city."
And to make this explanation, he asks us to look at a painting
by Canaletto of Venice.
If you look at this painting, you'll see a building to the left of the painting.
That's the corner of the Chiericati Palace of Andrea Palladio.
If you look in the very center of the painting,
is a project that Palladio made for the Rialto Bridge of Venice,
but never actually executed.
The Chiericati Palace is not in Venice;
it's in Vicenza, as is the very large building on the right, which
is Palladio's Basilica.
Now, these projects are important.
They have, already, various associations.
The Basilica, for example, was really just a kind of large classical wrapper
around an existing medieval building.
What Palladio did in the Basilica was sort of bring classicism
into an urban-- it's urban form, it's modern urban form.
And in the Chiericati Palace--
which is simply, in a way, a house--
he also used the classical language in the same way
to give the house a certain status, and all of these things
would have been important to Rossi.
I'll read Rossi's passage on this painting.
"To illustrate the concept of analogous city,
I give the example of Canaletto's fantasy view of Venice:
a Capriccio in which Palladio's projects for the Ponte di Rialto,
the Basilica of Venice, and the Palazzo Chiericati are set next to each other
and described as if the painter were rendering an urban scene
he had actually observed.
These three Palladian monuments, none of which are actually in Venice
and one of which is a project, nevertheless
constitute an analogous Venice--
formed of specific elements, associated it
with the history of both architecture and the city.
The geographical transposition of the monuments within the painting
constitutes a city that we recognize even
though it is a place of purely architectural references.
This example enabled me to demonstrate how a logical-formal operation could
be translated into (both) a design method and then
into a hypothesis for a theory of architectural design
in which the elements were preestablished and formally defined,
but where the significance that sprung forth at the end of the operation
was the authentic, unforeseen, and original meaning of the work."
There's an epistemological claim made in this passage, the claim
that architecture produces knowledge.
The type, though it's pre-theoretical and pre-conceptual,
nevertheless gives the form of social experience and collective
understanding.
The type sort of schematizes aesthetic experience, sensual
encounters, in such a way that it can be scanned
by the collective human understanding.
A city, of course, is a social and material object in its own right.
It's the most concrete of realities that architecture deals with.
But for Rossi, the city is also an invisible, abstract, virtual reality.
Every act of architecture can only come from the city, and every act
of architecture returns to the city.
We can imagine Rossi looking at this painting by Canaletto
and saying, "That is architecture"-- just as Loos looked at the mound
and said, "That is architecture."
But where is the "that"?
It seems that, for Rossi, architecture resides in a virtuality.
It's this virtuality that he calls the "analogous city."
So Rossi is making not only an epistemological claim--
that type produces social, experiential knowledge--
he's also making an ontological claim:
Architecture exists.
It exists as a virtuality that is manifest in the form of type.
You can imagine the ontological existing on a kind of vertical plane and history
unfolding through time, and it's at the intersection
of the ontological plane that this field of potential, this field of possibility
as it intersects historical time, we get the actualization of architecture
at that intersection.
But the ontological is folded into history from the start.