ANTOINE PICON: 1849 provided the incentive
https://youtu.be/uTba-dFC6Ao
for the organization of the Great Exhibition held
in London a couple of years later.
Indeed, Great Britain was, at the time, the most advanced country
technologically, but also in economic terms.
So how could it be that England had not organized an exhibition of this type?
The idea was actually taken by a small group
of people belonging to the Royal Society of Arts, a company that
had been created in the 18th century and had been revitalized
by the presence of Prince Albert, who had become president of the society.
Here we have a painting depicting the main protagonist of the organization
of the 1851 exhibition.
In the center, we have actually Prince Albert sitting
and the people pointing a finger towards the paper in front of the prince
is actually Joseph Paxton, of whom a bit later.
So...it's in the middle of the society that this idea
to organize something at a much larger scale than what
had been done before gradually emerged.
So first, one had to find a land where to hold the exhibition,
and Prince Albert actually secured the temporary loan of part of Hyde Park
as the place where the exhibition could take place.
Other members of the society were extremely active
securing promises of artifacts to be displayed.
The secretary of the society toured the United Kingdom,
visiting industrialists in order to obtain those promises.
What was gradually emerging was a very large project.
Overall, the estimation was that something like 800,000 square feet
would be necessary to host the entire exhibition.
Hence, the idea to call for a proposal for a very large building
in order to be able to shelter all the artifacts that would be displayed.
A committee was formed and asked for proposals to architects
all over Europe.
The call was issued in March 1850, and a couple of months
later some 230 proposals were received, most of them
from the United Kingdom and France.
Two proposals were especially noticed: the first one
by a French architect, Hector Horeau, a kind of gigantic
shed very much like a railway station; the second one
from Richard Turner, an engineer who had recently realized the Kew Garden
greenhouse.
Both proposals were admired for their qualities.
They were both, actually, proposing a single building, something that
would be retained by the committee.
In the case of Horeau, this inspiration
would later lead him to his utopian project for covering the Grands Boulevards
in Paris with iron sheds.
We can see there the genealogy between the world of the "passage,"
the Great Exhibition, and subsequent development in an urban iron
construction proposal.
The some 230 proposals for the Great Exhibition buildings
were exhibited in London in the Institute
of Civil Engineers in June 1850.
From those proposals, especially from the two most noticed ones--
the Hector Horeau and the Richard Turner ones--
the committee drew a number of conclusions.
The first one was that instead of conceiving
a series of separate buildings, it was probably
much better to imagine a single building which
would give more flexibility, a flexibility all the more needed
that the definitive organization of the exhibition
was not yet known, especially since all the loans had not yet been secured.
Another idea, related to the single building choice,
was to conceive it in a modular way.
And this is where the idea of a module of 24 feet
began to emerge as probably the most convenient choice.
The committee had a number of architects and engineers,
and since no proposals had been deemed completely satisfactory,
the architects and engineers of the committee
decided to design their own proposal following these general choices:
single building, a grid on a 24-feet module.
The result was actually a pretty horrendous proposal made of brick
with a giant dome that would have dwarfed the St. Peter's one, but which
proved not only ugly in the eyes of the public but also highly problematic
since it entailed a massive production of bricks
that would have then to be demolished.
At this stage, the organizers began to doubt that they would ever
be able to organize the exhibition.
Not only...was the scheme completely impractical, but the money to build it
seemed difficult to secure.
The public, in addition, was growing more
and more skeptical about the idea because of the images
that had been shown in the press, such as this one.
Prince Albert itself was beginning to despair.
This is where Joseph Paxton comes into play as, in some ways,
the savior, a kind of superhero like Superman,
who is going to really redeem the situation
and transform what was a path towards failure
into one of the greatest achievements of the early 1850s.