ANTOINE PICON: Joseph Paxton is a kind of quintessential British hero
https://youtu.be/qZg3_uXHey4
of those years insofar that he had no traditional training.
He was neither an engineer nor an architect, but actually
somebody who had risen pretty much by himself.
Queen Victoria was to call him a gardener
in a dismissive way in her memoirs.
Actually, Joseph Paxton was far more than a gardener;
he was somebody, indeed, interested in botany,
but somebody who had realized construction of all kinds, somebody
also who launched press enterprises.
He created a couple of journals.
And above all-- and that's true he was a gardener in that respect--
he had become the chief gardener of the Duke of Devonshire
and responsible for the management of the main estate
of the Duke in Chatsworth.
Chatsworth was a magnificent castle, but it was also...it
hosted a very large botanical collection.
The Duke himself commissioned expedition to bring tropical species
and acclimate them in Chatsworth.
If Chatsworth is mostly known today for its beautiful grounds,
it was also a highly experimental place where Paxton realized,
in particular, two experimental greenhouses,
which would play a role in the initial design of the Crystal Palace.
Paxton's main realization in Chatsworth was the Great Stove, a giant greenhouse
started in 1838 and completed in 1840.
It was, at the time, one of the largest greenhouses ever built.
The Great Stove was not only important because of its dimension,
but because also of a number of technological achievements, among which
the use of very large sheets of glass, very different from the smaller pieces
that had been used before Paxton.
Paxton worked actually in close relation with the Chance Brother
Company, a company who produced glass.
And actually, the Chance Brother Company will be working for the Crystal Palace.
The Great Stove has disappeared today, but it
was much admired by the contemporaries, among other things
not only because of the technology, but also its sheer size.
You have to imagine that it was as high as the vault of a Gothic church,
something quite impressive, which enabled the greenhouse
to host trees inside.
Here we have, for example, a drawing made by a German architect
while touring Chatsworth, which says a lot about the kind of European-wide reception
of Paxton's work.
So gardener, perhaps according to Queen Victoria, but a gardener
of a very special and elevated type.
Another key realization of Paxton at Chatsworth
was the 1850 lily house that he built to host the giant lily
plant called the Victoria regia.
This was actually a very rapidly growing plant,
which entailed actually rebuilding an entire greenhouse for it alone.
There, Paxton actually used a completely innovative roof principles,
using much longer sash bars supported by cast iron trusses, that would actually
be the very principle for the Crystal Palace roof techniques.
One of the key intuitions behind the lily house
was that a great resistance could be achieved by thinking of structure
not necessarily in terms of very large and massive structural members,
but through a more web or lattice-like way of thinking, something that
was inspired, allegedly to Paxton, by the very lily flower he
had to shelter in the lily house.
Here we have Paxton's daughter sitting on one
of the leaves of the Victoria regia.
And these leaves were rigidified through these kind of intricate webs, which
was a source of inspiration for Paxton.
And the whole lily house is actually a complex system
that functions a little bit like what we would call today
a kind of space structure.
As we can see here, they have relatively long sash bars, which
are supported by cast iron girders.
But the whole thing functions a little bit
like a web, which was one of the principles at work in the Crystal
Palace.
Here we have a more detailed view of the Paxton roofing principles,
which may look simple, but which is full of refinement.
For example, the wood beam are actually rigidified through iron cables
a little bit like a truss.
You may note also the grooves at the base of the wood beams.
They are actually meant to allow for the water produced
by condensation to be evacuated.
The genius of Paxton lies not only in the general conception of his building
but also in the very close attention paid to details.
And as we will see, details at the scale of the Crystal Palace
become no longer negligible.
I have insisted on the use of large sheets of glass by Paxton,
glass produced by the Chance Brother factory.
It's quite interesting that glass, which is, with iron, one
of the most emblematic materials of the Industrial Era,
remained relatively artisanal.
It was blown.
Typically, people blew cylinders that were then opened and flattened in order
to produce sheets of glass, while iron, of course,
knew very important transformation in terms of processing.
So we understand also that a process like the first Industrial Revolution
is actually a mix of very spectacular technological advances and more
incremental, more minute changes, like those
that characterize glass manufacturing.
So how did Paxton enter the story of the Great Exhibition?
Actually, through a series of serendipitous coincidences.
Paxton actually had begun sketching.
He was actually appalled by the official scheme of the committee in charge
of the exhibition.
And imagined that actually a greenhouse-like solution would actually
function much better at that scale, and especially
would be lighter and less expensive.
He had begun to sketch.
And here is one of the most famous sketches in which we find
the principle of the Crystal Palace.
It's a kind of cross-section,
and it's a kind of giant lily house with the same roof principles
but, of course, at a completely different scale.
Among the many interests of Paxton, one found railways.
Once again, he was a very special kind of gardener,
and he had become an expert in railways.
And he had traveled in order to participate to a discussion
at a trial regarding some kind of contentious issues on railway
construction and management.
And traveling back to London, he met with one
of the members of the committee, Robert Stephenson, the famous engineer, who
had been involved in a number of enterprises--
railway, but also bridges.
He's the author of the Britannia Tubular Bridge.
And Paxton showed his scheme to Stephenson,
who got completely enthusiastic and thought
that this could be the solution to the conundrum in which the committee found
themselves.
So Stephenson did encourage Paxton to actually submit
his proposal for the realization of the great building of the exhibition.
There was only one problem, which is that the call for proposals
were actually proposals to build the project elaborated by the committee.
Fortunately, in the contract, it was stipulated
that if the building companies had an alternative idea that was cheaper,
they could actually submit it in parallel with their proposal
to build the project of the committee.
So Paxton partnered with a firm called Fox and Henderson
and proposed his scheme as an alternative
to the construction of the committee.
Paxton's proposal was roughly 60% to 80% cheaper
than building the project with brick and mortar of the committee.
But it was not only cheaper.
It was actually much more seductive.
And the images published by the press immediately gathered
momentum around what appeared more and more as the solution
to the difficult problem of how to host the Great Exhibition.
Let's not forget that we're in something like in June 1850.
And they're barely one year and a half in order
to complete the construction to open the exhibition.
So actually, things were pretty much in rush.
This image, published in the press, is actually
the first version of Paxton's project.
As we can see, this is a very repetitive building
in which there is a certain indistinction
between the various parts of the buildings, something
that was wanted by Paxton.
In some ways, the Crystal Palace also marks the emergence
of a totally new idea in architecture, which
is the idea of flexibility, an idea that we, there again, become completely
accustomed to.
Flexibility seems a key notion when thinking
in terms of very large building.
But once again, this was the first time that such ideas ever emerged.
An odd thing to notice, there is no transept,
contrary to the final buildings in which we can see a transept with a barrel
vault in the middle of the building.
The transept was actually an idea that emerged
at the intersection of a couple of concerns.
One was that the ground on which the building was to be constructed
was actually leased.
But it had to be brought back in its initial shape.
And there were a number of trees on that ground,
and the British are very attached to trees, as we all know.
So trees have not to be destroyed.
So there was a problem on how actually to put the trees inside the building.
So the additional height provided by the barrel vault
was an elegant solution to that.
A second role played by the transept was actually
to improve a little bit the lateral bracing.
It did improve the bracing.
But one has to say that actually Paxton and Fox and Henderson, his builder,
were quite lucky because the bracing was still pretty imperfect.
And had a storm or something happened, the Crystal Palace
could have been in serious trouble.
This was a building very rapidly designed
and with a number of structural flaws that
have become evident to the eye of historians studying retrospectively
how it was designed.
I said that the building was enormous.
It covered on the ground something like 800,000 square feet,
something quite unheard of at that time.
In addition to that, a second floor brought some additional 200,000
square feet.
So in total, it was almost 1 million square feet,
something that enabled to display all the artifacts that
had been secured by the organization committee for the Great Exhibition,
but there again, something that one had never seen before that building.