ANTOINE PICON: The overall organization of the building is quite simple.
https://youtu.be/hOmCJWqsGS8
It is actually strangely reminiscent of the structure
of a church with a central nave, which is 72 feet large,
and rises at the height of 64 feet.
But which is actually four times longer than the greatest church
in the United Kingdom, St. Paul's.
And, of course, with a much thinner structure.
This made a very spectacular impression on all the visitors.
This is the Crystal Palace immediately after the end of the Great Exhibition.
And we can see this kind of impression of infinity.
It was, perhaps, the first time that a building
gave this impression of being infinite.
This repetitive, almost infinite space, in which the eye got almost lost.
I mentioned the trees.
Here, we have the transept of the Crystal Palace with one of the trees.
And we are, by the same token, introduced
to another theme that will play an important role throughout the Great
Exhibition, which is the juxtaposition of the natural and the artificial,
with the suggestion that human industry is actually
an extension of a kind of fecundity of nature itself.
The main entrance of the exhibition was through the transept.
And people immediately discovered the trees, but also fountains, colors.
I'll come back to the ambience of the Great Exhibition,
because this is also an important aspect that gave the building also
its mythical character.
Because of its scale, the building confronted its designers two completely
unexpected problems.
One was actually how to evacuate water, the rain that fell on the roof.
Because of the surface the building covered,
this problem of how to get rid of the water was actually pretty crucial.
The solution adopted, which Paxton had tested,
but at a much, much smaller scale in his lily house,
was actually to use hollow columns, in which the water would actually
be evacuated.
The new thing was actually that, at the bottom of the column,
you found pipes that were directly related to the sewers of the city.
So we understand another thing, which is that this is actually
the beginning of the merging between the buildings and infrastructure.
The building is so large that it becomes commensurable
with the urban infrastructure as a whole.
Since the construction of the Crystal Palace in 1851,
this potential blurring between architecture and the infrastructure
has been with us repeatedly.
This has been the case, for example, with the Kansai
Airport built by Renzo Piano in Japan,
which was, at the time of its completion,
one of the largest buildings in the world--
A few kilometers long.
It's quite revealing that, Ove Arup, in order
to give an idea of the scale of the building, actually used Hyde Park.
The very site where the Crystal Palace was constructed,
as if large large contemporary buildings, like the Kansai Airport terminal,
were actually the inheritor, and they are indeed,
of these kind of giant gigantism that was introduced
at the time of the Crystal Palace.
Another interesting aspect to note is actually
the double level of reading of a structure like this one.
Let pay attention, for example, to the node.
In order to additionally stabilize the structure,
you have these giant ties that intersect,
and there you have a node in the middle.
Look at the complexity of the node.
Of course, you don't discover it immediately.
But actually, iron construction will be marked
by this kind of tension between the overall appearance and the details
and the secret of complementarity between the two.
This is something to keep in mind is that, in iron,
because of the very repetitive nature, etc.,
details do matter.
"God is in the detail," as some famous architect would later say,
and Paxton is somebody who worked, one again, both
about the overall scheme, but also in these very minute details.
In order to understand that, you know, another building, built much later, actually,
the Eiffel Tower of 1889, the overall impression
is actually very much dependent of the type of node used.
Here, you have the typical node of the Eiffel Tower.
And again, there is this complementarity between the overall impression
and details that are kind of almost subliminal, but do play actually
quite an important role in the reading of the structure.
The famous art critic and theorist John Ruskin
had a very mixed feeling about the Crystal Palace,
because, of course, he was impressed by the performance as if, as he said,
"...the whole world had been encompassed by a single building."
But at the same time, and we'll return to that,
he was critical because iron was not his favorite material,
and he despised industrialization.
Nevertheless, saying that the whole world could now
be sheltered in a single building introduces
another very important dimension of this building, which
is a kind of environmental quality.
This is a building in which ventilation, the control of humidity,
all these questions that we think have arisen only recently
were already present.
You have to imagine millions of people sweating, etc.
You have to imagine the heat.
Even in London, sometimes, you can get sun
and the building can get pretty hot.
So the typical problem of a greenhouse,
but of course, it was a greenhouse not for tropical plants, but for people.
This is actually one of the louvers of Paxton.
And, actually, the building is inseparable from problems, complex problems,
of ventilation that, there again, we take for granted.
But where, for the first time, really addressed at such a scale
The Crystal Palace was mythical, not only
because of the very unique ambience it offered to its visitors,
but also because of the construction.
The construction is an integral part of the myth.
One could even say that it was the first time that construction was really
as much associated with the meaning of the building.
The contemporaries were completely struck
by how these standardized pieces arrived on site, were assembled.
This is the beginning, also, of the fascination for dry assemblage.
So nothing having to do with the wetness of mortar.
Nothing like, you know, all these traditional construction techniques,
but something like a magic dance of parts, pieces.
Not yet machines--
horses were still the main source of power on the construction.
In some ways, the Marxian notion of forces of production
was probably almost illustrated by such a ballet of industrial components.
Throughout the construction, Paxton was, of course, present,
and had multiple opportunities to show his ingeniosity.
For example, putting in place the barrel vault elements of the transept
was not such a simple process, as we can see on this engraving.
The barrel vault elements were actually in wood.
There again, we find this complexity, and this mix
of traditional and more modern elements.
The construction site was, by the way, really a spectacle.
And Fox and Henderson sold, actually, tickets
in order for the public to come and visit and see what was going on.
Speaking of ingeniosity, Paxton also designed a number
of machine [for raising, glazing], for all kinds
of purposes on the construction site.
Here we find also another interesting aspect
of what the Crystal Palace was about, which
is a kind of continuity between structural and mechanical engineering.
Something very specific to the British scene in many respects.
On the continent, engineers or builders did not always imagine machines.
Here, to design a machine and to design a building
are part of the same continuum.
And this is also a very important aspect,
an aspect that might explain, in some ways,
why the high-tech expression was a product of Great
Britain in the 20th century.
As if this legacy of articulation between machines and buildings had
remained an enduring tradition.
Putting in place the glass for the roof was also quite something.
An enormous enterprise in which, of course, risk was present.
The glass could break, could fall on the workers working below.
So special precautions had to be taken.
There again, innovative techniques were put into place.
For example, you have these little carriages
on rails that enabled, actually, to go a bit faster when
putting in place the large sheets of glass produced by the Chance Brothers
Factory.
Here on this vision, if you pay closer attention,
you will see actually the little carriages
circulating on top of the building on the rails, and putting in place
the glass.
While on the front of the picture, you have horses, which
are used to lift a girder of the nave.
So we can see there, again, this mix of innovation and tradition.
Mechanization would take over far later on construction sites.
The result was a completely strange space for the contemporaries,
something fascinating, but something that was not easy to categorize.
Was it architecture?
Was it something else?
I have mentioned the blurring between architecture and infrastructure.
In some ways, the Crystal Palace was sublime.
That's to say, something that escaped usual aesthetic categories.
And Paxton himself was never fully recognized as a fully-fledged designer.
It's quite revealing that, despite the spectacular achievement,
he was never awarded the Medal of the Royal Institute of British Architects.
As if the nature of what he had produced remained uncertain.
This strangely repetitive, fascinating space... but was it really an architectural creation?
And there, of course, we understand why John Ruskin was so reluctant.
Was it still art in the traditional sense?
Where was the hand of the craftsmen that Ruskin praised above everything?
All these traditional dimensions of art and architecture
had vanished in this enchantment of iron and glass
that would fascinate millions of people, but the status of which
remained very unclear in the eyes of the professional.
One can say that the Crystal Palace marks
the beginning of the split between the taste of the public at large
and what professionals, like architects, care about.
The Crystal Palace is sublime because it's spectacular in terms of size,
because of the emotion it gave to the people who practiced it.
But it's also something that doesn't have a clear status in terms
of architecture.
On this view, we can almost feel the sublimity
linked to the idea of infinity, of transparency.
And we can also understand why people who
appreciated Greek temples or Gothic churches could feel a bit ill at ease
in front of such a construction that did not
enter any clear category of the history of architecture.