K. MICHAEL HAYS: Khoảng giữa thế kỉ 19, có một xu hướng mạnh trong việc ứng dụng
https://youtu.be/-QDpnXyF9M4
sản xuất thiết kế nghệ thuật với các khu vực trong những khu công nghiệp lớn.
Một mặt, xu hướng này được thúc đẩy bởi sự ra đời của các loại vật liệu mới.
mặt khác, là do mong muốn hợp nhất khu liên hiệp các nhà máy
thành một khu vực, hoặc thậm chí là một khu đô thị
nhạy bén
Nó cũng được phát triển thành xu hướng bởi tầm quan trọng ngày càng tăng
của việc các công ti đã chi trả cho mong muốn có được hìn ảnh riêng cho công ti của mình.
Vì vậy kiến trúc ra đời khoảng cuối thế kỉ 19
và phát triển mạnh vào thế kỉ 20 đã bắt đầu được sử dụng cho mục đích thương mại
Phần lớn các nhà nghiên cứu đều đồng ý rằng các nhà máy tua-bin
Allgemeine Elektricitäts-Gesellschaft, hay công ti General Electric , ở Đức--
đều có trụ sở chính ở các khu đô thị nổi bật ở Berlin
đó là ví dụ cho việc kiến trúc thâm nhập vào .........
cũng như mong muốn sử dụng các vât liệu mớinhư thép và thủy tinh,
tuy nhiên nhấn mạnh rằng những vật liệu này được đưa vào
một loại biểu hiện nghệ thuật phù hợp với công ti đó
Năm 1907, Kiến trúc sư Peter Behrens được bổ nhiệm làm giám đốc nghệ thuật
chịu trách nhiệm việc sáng tạo toàn bộ hệ thống hình ảnh, hay các gói xây dựng thương hiệu
cho công ti quốc tế.
Ông thiết kế nhãn hiệu và chịu trách nhiệm về tất cả các ấn phẩm
cũng như việc thiết kế-- ít nhất là các kiểu dáng thẩm mỹ,
nếu không phải cac thiết kế kĩ thuât của các loại thiết bị gia dụng
như quạt, lò sưởi và đèn.
Ông cũng chịu trách nhiệm đối với tất cả các cơ sở bán lẻ và thậm chí là thiết kế các câu lạc bộ cho nhân viên,
cũng như các tòa nhà của nhà máy
Điều quan trọng là phải nhớ rằng các nhà máy ở thời điểm này
vẫn không được coi là kiến trúc loại "A". Các nhà máy bắt đầu
sử dụng vật liệu mới từ thép và thủy tinh, đặc biệt là để mở rộng các khu vực
mà thiết bị có thể được sản xuất và lưu trữ, nhưng các nhà máy bằng kính và thép
bị cho là một loại hình xây dựng chiếu lệ
Trách nhiệm của Behren là đưa ra các loại hình xây dựng  như loại hình công nghiệp hay chức năng
vào trạng thái kiến trúc nghệ thuật.
Behrens hoàn toàn rõ về ước mơ nâng cao kiến trúc nhà máy lên trạng thái
of serious, profound architecture.
The architecture that he desired, he himself called industrial neoclassicism.
It's a kind of reduced, abstracted classicism that would be a new-- that would also be a
new German architecture.
This last point is important because it expresses a desire not only
to represent the economic status and economic importance of the company,
but it was also an understanding of the company's role
as a primary force in the creation of state identity,
and even in social change.
In order to conceptualize this representational role
that this new architecture would play, which would be on the one hand
representing the commercial power of these great corporations,
these energy-producing corporations, but also to even participate
in creating a larger national identity.
In order to accomplish that, Behrens needed the help of architecture theory.
The theory that he turned to first was his own version
of Hegel's theory, which we've seen earlier in the beginning of this course.
It has to do with the way architecture appears in history as a representation
of a sort of cultural ethos, and that representational role, or representational
vocation of architecture, has to move and change through
time as culture itself changes, or as history itself moves
forward.
For example, in Greek times we know that the temple
is the primary architectural paradigm.
The temple for Behrens was the exquisite representation of the ethos of democracy, of intellectual
life, in the polis-- in the Greek polis.
Then we move into medieval times.
There it's the Christian church that is the dominant authority, that
is the dominant power, and the architecture is the cathedral.
The architectural paradigm is the cathedral that adequately represents that ethos.
With the secularization in the Renaissance, but also the move in power a little bit away
from the church and toward the aristocracy, then the palazzo
becomes the architectural type to represent that emerging and developing
aristocracy.
So, with this kind of Hegelian understanding of this teleological development of architecture
in relation to a social ethos, or a kind of cultural ethos,
he looked at his own time.
It was clear that in his work for the AEG, it was industrial capitalism which was the
new authority.
It was industrial capitalism that needed to assert itself
as I say both a power, a commercial power, but also even a cultural power in the creation
of a new kind of German identity.
What was then the architectural paradigm that would be adequate to this new ethos?
The factory.
Not just any factory, though.
The turbine factory.
The turbine factory which would house the construction, the manufacture,
of these giant steam turbines.
It was the biggest machine for producing electricity, for producing the power of Berlin, the power
of the whole of the country of Germany.
How do you represent that kind of production of power
adequately in a building?
For that he turned to another theorist.
The second theorist that Behrens turned to was the architect and historian Gottfried Semper.
He was a practicing architect, but also an architecture theorist
whose primary interest was in the very beginnings of architecture,
and how the beginnings of architecture could influence and help
structure and conceptualize architectural practice in the present.
To study those beginnings, he visited the Exhibition of 1851,
in London, housed by the Crystal Palace.
There, in one of the exhibitions, he saw a full-scale replica of a primitive hut
from the Caribbean islands.
And the sort of empirical fact of this primordial shelter
exhibited in what, at the time, was the most advanced building--
in the sense of new materials and industrialized production
of the architectural elements -- the contrast of the most advanced and the
most primitive sort of prompted Semper to turn to a kind of materialist
but also anthropological model of architecture's beginnings, and a
kind of model of how architecture could move from those
beginnings to the present.
The way he did this was to reduce the building down to four elements.
But each of those-- four sort of formal architectural elements.
But each of those elements would also have associated with it
a technique, a means of production.
A certain kind of material, but also a certain technical skill that
manipulates and forms that material.
The first element-- and he considered it first a social or cultural element--
which is fire, is the beginning, he thought, of society itself.
It's fire that provides both the formal centering device, but also the warmth,
the protection that the group can then gather around and form itself
as a tribe, as a group, as a community.
But the fire needs the help of architecture.
In order that the fire can be lifted up off the damp earth, lifted up
into the sort of vicinity of the group gathered around the fire,
another material in another form is required: something like a bowl, or a pot, or a hearth
that contains the fire.
And that container would, therefore, require the technique of ceramics.
Or perhaps later in history, it would require the techniques of metallurgy.
Now to hold that pot, that ceramic or metal pot, off the earth,
some kind of base is required.
And Semper theorized that the base would be made of masonry.
That the technique associated with the base that raises up
the hearth would be masonry.
Masonry has an inherent weight, a kind of inherent attachment to the earth,
because the bricks themselves are made out of the earth,
but they also bear on the earth with compressive forces.
Bricks are blocks that have to be put in a row and stacked,
and that cutting and stacking and the composition of solid, crystalline blocks is referred to
by the term stereotomy.
Stereotomy, in German, refers to the composition made of building up
with blocks, with chunks of materials.
It is almost naturally monumental.
It's almost naturally-- it also obviously deals with compression;
it deals with stacking; it's naturally related to the earth because of the weight of the blocks.
So stereotomy becomes a kind of automatic way
of producing monumentality.
But it's also associated with Semper with this idea of a base.
Now, in contrast to stereotomy, which is a kind
of-- also has a kind of inertness, also has a kind of idea of crystalline pieces-- opposed
to that is an architecture of an elastic frame.
Semper called this tectonics.
And this tectonic frame becomes the third element in this typology.
Semper deviated from the classical understanding of a trabeated system,
where the column and the entablature, or the column and the roof,
are two separate elements tied together at a joint.
He, rather, theorized a kind of tectonic assembly that would rise from this masonry base, where
the walls and the roof together made the tectonic system.
The other association or connotation of tectonic is that we're dealing with relatively small
elements that can operate not so much in a compressive way,
but that have tensile strength.
And these individual elements would be connected by a knot or a tying
together.
So this is what he called a tectonic system.
As the craft associated with stereotomy is masonry,
the craft associated with tectonics is carpentry.
So again, each part of the system has a technique associated with it.
Interestingly, too, it was in the knot, that the
joining together of two pieces of wood with a knot
that Semper saw the origin of architectural ornament.
The joint is the origin of ornament.
The final element in his system, the final typology,
is then the enclosing membrane that would wrap
this tectonic system of walls and roof.
Interestingly, again, Semper didn't imagine the enclosing membrane would be the same as
the stereotomic system of masonry.
Rather, he imagined that the enclosing membrane was a cloth or a tapestry
or some sort of woven material.
So the enclosing membrane, no matter how thick it was-- it could be thin and porous in some
climates, it could be thick and heavy and insulating
in other climates-- but in either case, that would be associated
with weaving.
The other interesting thing that Semper added to this
is that he knew that, as he had seen with the primitive hut in the Crystal
Palace, he knew that these architectural elements, formally,
would develop over time, but he also knew that, materially, they
would develop over time.
So what he theorized was, for example, if you
take the woven cladding, or the woven membrane, he knew that at some point that would become
made of brick.
But he imagined that the brick would carry some of the legacy of the weaving.
And maybe the way the mason would then use the brick in a more decorative way,
creating patterns, creating different textures, rather than just piling up in a straightforward
way, the legacy of the decorative surface of the carpet,
or the mat, or the cloth would continue into the masonry,
into the new material of masonry.
These four elements-- the fire, the base, the tectonic system that rests on the base,
and the cladding system or the membrane that then keeps out
the wind and the rain-- were Semper's four anthropological, materialist
types that are the very beginning of architecture.