K. MICHAEL HAYS: Peter Behrens's AEG turbine factory is a remarkable transcription of Gottfried
https://youtu.be/T89-68lxdp8
Semper's theory of the primitive hut into a monumental contemporary
building.
Like Semper, Behrens starts with what is really a kind of social but also technological device
that is at the heart of the architectural program.
Where Semper started with fire, Behrens starts with the turbine engine
itself, this giant steam turbine, which would become the central source,
the primary source of power.
That turbine has to be contained, has to be housed.
Like Semper, he starts with the base.
It's a remarkably high base that runs around the entire building.
You can see the scale of this, both the base and the overall building,
by looking at these figures in the foreground relative to that concrete pad, or that concrete
base.
On this giant masonry base, Behrens then constructs a tectonic system
made of steel, a system of arches, 28 all together, that span an area of 25
by 130 meters.
And the arches rise up, again according to Semper's dictum, constructing
a skeleton that holds up the walls and the roof together.
Now this is different from a stone system or a trabeated system
where column and beam are understood as separate elements.
Behrens has constructed a tectonic system that's a kind of singular net of small metal
systems welded or bolted together.
However, he deviates from Semper in an important way.
At the very top edge of the factory, of the building,
just before it springs into its roof, Behrens added a very heavy steel girder that goes
the entire length of the building.
Now, that girder is brought out from the glass wall of the building
and, thereby, creates a very heavy shadow.
The heavy shadow, together with the depth of the beam,
makes the beam seem much, much heavier, denser, and deeper than it actually is.
Now, there's a big distinction between the tectonic system,
in Semper's term, which is a system made up of separate elements joined together
that work together in this kind of tensile net.
There's a difference between that and a trabeated system,
which is a system of columns and beams understood as separate and load-bearing
through compression.
What Behrens has done is use a tectonic system according to Semper's theory,
and, yet, he's made it appear like a trabeated system
because it's the trabeated system that has the corporeality and the visual density that
he thinks is required for this monumental building.
Behrens thought that the trabeated system, or the appearance
of the trabeation, would resonate with classical architecture
more than a tensile system.
A tensile system would appear too flimsy, too lightweight.
So he's getting the power of a trabeated colonnade, which
resonates with the Greek temple itself, but he's building
that now out of steel and glass.
Behren's second focus was where this tectonic system springs from the base.
It springs from the base in this giant hinge.
Behrens focused a lot of his aesthetic compositional attention on that hinge.
The hinge is raised on the base.
It's almost as if it's a piece of sculpture on a podium.
The base comes almost to eye level, it's almost exactly at eye level.
So this giant hinge confronts you.
And the visual power of this metal hinge is almost
like an analog of the turbines inside.
Finally on this long facade is the glass.
Remember that Semper's theory is that the membrane, the wrapper,
would come from an idea of weaving.
This is where Behrens has used these enormous planes of glass.
And they're actually tilted slightly away from the base, tilted inward toward the building.
Part of this tilt then gives this visual weight to the column in the beam, but also it puts
the glass plane on display as a plane.
But the panes of glass here are very, very small,
and the mullions are very small, but they're very closely spaced.
The effect is that it looks like a weaving of glass and steel
according to Semper's dictum.
It's brittle, it has a tactility to it.
It has a kind of brittleness to the plane.
That tactility emphasizes again, the visual power of the glass.
As we move now to the front of the building, we see a slightly different aesthetic at work.
First of all, it's at the front of the building that we see the contours of this giant barrel
roof, or, actually, a kind of segmented barrel roof.
Now, that roof has a lot of volume.
That volume is not needed functionally.
That volume is not used by any of the equipment of the factory.
It's simply that Behrens wanted that contour, that silhouette
seen against the sky to convey this sort of representational power
of the building.
It's like a frontispiece.
It's like a temple front.
Structurally it works slightly differently.
We have these giant concrete piers now that at first gloss
are bearing the weight of this big sort of barrel roof.
But, in contrast to that, these giant concrete piers
are set back from the edge of the roof so that even though at first gloss, they appear
to be load-bearing, at second gloss, it almost looks as if the glass front itself is bearing
the weight.
And it's that contradiction or that dialectic or that tension that gives the kind of visual
power of this facade.
Once again, it's this tactile haptic plane of glass, a kind of plane that you almost
touch with your eyes as it were.
It has a tactility, a visual tactility that really makes the glass as material
important, almost more important structurally or visually
load-bearing than the concrete piers themselves.
Translating Semper's theory into an architecture of steel, glass, and concrete, Behrens is
able to bring the building of the industrial factory
into the realm of architecture, capital "A," and even to compare the factory building with
the monumental tradition that begins with the Greek temple.