K. MICHAEL HAYS: Glass became, for modern architects, the essential material of the future.
https://youtu.be/jf1LzUh-elQ
Glass was endowed not only with material visual qualities,
but also with spiritual qualities.
The German architect Mies van der Rohe would design buildings in America that would become
the epitome of glass and steel skyscrapers.
But Mies started his work in Germany.
In fact, Mies also worked in the office of Peter Behrens,
when the AEG factory was being designed.
And, yet, Mies was much more experimental than either Gropius or Behrens.
We have photographs of Mies in Behrens's office constructing models of glass skyscrapers and
then holding those models against the window in Behrens's office and twisting and turning
them to study and experiment with the reflective and refractive qualities of the tall glass
building-- kind of amazing moment in architecture.
Mies would continue these experiments in two projects for downtown Berlin-- one
on the Friedrichstrasse and the other on Alexanderplatz.
In both of these projects, Mies was looking to see how new building types could be derived
that would respond more adequately to the visual potentials of steel and glass and this
continuingly emergent technology of steel and glass.
But it wasn't until 1954 in New York in his project for the Seagram Building
where these experiments were first realized in a commercial office tower.
The Seagram Building was the administrative headquarters of the Canadian distillery Seagram's,
and it was located on Park Avenue in downtown New York.
Though the site of course is very, very different from the AEG factory, Mies-- like Behrens--
wanted very much for his building to engage the city
and even confront the city-- confront the city
with the representational power of architecture in the overall urban fabric.
Mies was not working on a corner as Behrens was in the AEG site.
He was working mid block.
So he confronted the city in a very different way.
He first sets the building back from the street line,
creating a fairly deep plaza in front of the building.
You don't actually see the Seagram Building as you're coming down Park Avenue.
You first see only the gap.
According to people that worked with Mies on the project,
that gap in the street line was very important for him.
It created a kind of anticipation, a kind of mystery.
But as soon as you enter that gap and turn 90 degrees,
the slab of the high-rise building confronts you
in a very, almost aggressively, frontal way.
The building appears now almost as a pure surface.
It's a pure network of steel and glass.
So let's look more closely at that surface.
The first thing we realize is that while most steel and glass
buildings of the time articulate the frame and use the glass as a kind of contrasting
transparency to the opacity of the steel frame, in the
Seagram's case, the glass is bronzed, and the steel is bronzed,
and the effect of that homogeneous treatment of the two materials actually bring the materials
closer together.
Of course, you can still see the articulation of the frame against the glass, but it brings
the materials a little bit closer together.
It gives the glass, at certain angles, also, a kind of opacity rather than a transparency.
The essential thing to be expressed by a high-rise building in steel and glass, for Mies, is
the idea of structure.
Of course, the structure of the Seagram Building is based on a steel frame.
The issue is that because of American building code,
the steel cannot be exposed.
It cannot even be made visible.
The reason is that a steel frame, in the case of an accidental fire-- exposed steel runs
the risk of softening and failing structurally.
So building codes require that the steel frame be clad in an insulating material, usually
concrete.
And that's the case at Seagram.
Even though it's actually made of a steel frame,
the entire steel frame is encased in concrete.
So how then do you make the essence of the building, which is structure,
how do you make that visible?
Mies's solution is to add an additional steel I-section.
We call it an I-section because if you cut through the steel member, its section is shaped
like an "I."
And that I-section is laid in a plane in front of the glass.
It actually has no structural function whatsoever.
It is an ornament.
It's an architectural ornament.
And, yet, as an ornament, as a non-functional element,
it represents the structure even more emphatically-- if you
will-- than the structure itself.
It's a more true representation of the structure than the structure itself.
And this is a very, very interesting development in the idea of architectural ornament.
We're a long way from Semper's knot, but what is similar to Semper's knot, or the ornament
of Semper's weaving, is its representational function for what
is, in fact, a constructional and structural vocation.
This I-section in front of the glass is playing the role
that in architectural terms, we call a mullion.
And the series of mullions in front of the glass--
because of that one flat plane of the I-section-- actually creates a virtual plane that is parallel
to, but in front of, the glass itself.
Visually, also, under the right lighting conditions, the mullions cast a shadow on the glass in
a very, very similar way-- but a much more delicate way-- than the columns
in Behrens's AEG factory cast a shadow on the glass.
In Mies's case, because of the delicacy of the fabric, the effect that this has
is to prevent us, in a away, from measuring-- from calibrating-- the distance from that
virtual plane to the actual plane of glass.
And the visual effect of that, under the right lighting conditions, is a kind of oscillation
of the surface.
It's as if the surface has a kind of optical depth and an optical movement
or a kind of shimmering that belies the simplicity of the actual architectural elements of the
surface.
Despite the large amount of glass in the Seagram Building
and the thinness of the material, the Seagram nevertheless
has a kind of corporeality and a presence that's actually very, very dense.
Now part of this is due to the proportions of the slab.
The sides of the slab have a sort of three to five ratio of width two frontality.
And that gives it a kind of chunkiness.
But, more important, the bronzing of the glass and the metal gives a totality to the surface
and a singularity to the surface that also contributes to the
visual weight.
The bronzing also does one more thing.
Bronze actually has a quality of aging.
And over time, rather than appearing more and more like a new building, the Seagram
has actually taken on an almost archaic quality.
Whereas Behrens used the resonance of his building with a Greek temple
to insert his building into a continuum of architecture as an art, Mies almost pushes
the associations back prior to Greece to some kind of ancient archaic slab that is older
than history itself, even as it's very much part of the present.
This haptic plane is completely abstract, but it still has a resonance with the architecture
of the past-- a grandeur in glass and steel, first begun by Peter Behrens.