K. MICHAEL HAYS: The Villa Stein-de-Monzie, usually called
https://youtu.be/oZFSKZTimzQ
simply by its location, Garches, is a very different kind
of translation of the Dom-ino system into a suburban house.
And here, we can see all the features of Dom-ino: the column
grid and its supporting horizontal slabs, its relationship to the earth,
the separation of the structural columns from the interior walls that
allows a free arrangement of the plan, the implication
now fulfilled of a non-load-bearing wall in front of the slab on the long side.
And the fact that it's a non-load-bearing
wall being indexed by windows that go across the entire width
of the facade, what Le Corbusier would call
ribbon windows or elongated windows.
And then, there's even a balcony that projects in front of the wall plane
that, in a way, further develops, or fulfills,
this implication of pulling the columns back
from that slightly cantilevered slab, that in front of that slab,
one is free to put a kind of wrapper, or a facade, of different types.
We will see again this idea of an itinerary of movement and stasis,
of frontality and rotation.
This time, however, that itinerary begins well beyond the house,
at the entrance to the entire site, that is marked by a little concierge
building with a find of skeletal canopy, or skeletal gate, through which you first
enter, and where we're initially fixed by the frontality
of this rectangular facade in the distance.
But we're fixed just off center, so that already the idea of frontality
and an implied need for rotation is introduced.
From that vantage, we can start to perceive, even if it's unconsciously,
what Le Corbusier called "regulating lines" of the facades.
For example, there are diagonals that go from the top corner
to the opposite bottom corner, and then other lines
that are developed off that diagonal, that are either parallel,
or perpendicular, to that diagonal.
And these give the facade a sensation of a very strict order.
But at the same time, it allows enormous variations of openings, and punctures,
and balconies, in the wall.
The wall envelope defines that all-important volumetric quality
that Le Corbusier sees as defining objet-type.
The column grid at Garches is not the square column grid of the Dom-ino plan.
It's rather a kind of geometric grid that
has a rhythm of base sizes, A, B, A, B, A. Or the proportion of the base
is 2 to 1, 2 to 1, and 2.
The English historian and critic, Colin Rowe,
compared this patterned geometric grid with Palladio's Villa Malcontenta,
that we saw earlier in this course.
Within that column grid, and free of the structuring function of that column
grid, are these curvilinear stairwells, and rooms
with curved partition, that are very, very similar
to the objet-type of Purist paintings.
And many critics have actually seen the villa as something
like a three-dimensional Purist painting.
Le Corbusier himself saw these curved shapes inside the column grid
as what he called "compressed organs" of the house.
And indeed, often the curves will indicate
spaces of intense bodily performance, for example like a stairwell.
Coming back to the front facade, the main entrance to the villa
is fitted with a big, cantilevered awning.
Located symmetrically to the main entrance
is another smaller service entrance.
But above the service entrance is placed a balcony.
So there's a kind of symmetry, or better, there's
a kind of balance to the two entries around the center of the facade.
But it's not an exact repetition.
It's not an exact symmetry.
The two large, elongated windows register the fact
that it is a non-load-bearing wall.
And the balcony that punctures through the surface at the very top, again,
starts a kind of plasticity.
It starts a kind of layering of the wall that will be carried out
on the interior of the house.
The first floor accommodates a large entry hall, as well as
a garage and various service spaces.
When we enter the entry hall, we come into contact
then with the freestanding columns, or what Le Corbusier
called the freestanding pilotis.
And here because the columns are freestanding apart from the wall,
they operate almost like a little framing device
that creates a moment of stasis, after the long movement through the side,
and through the front door into the entry.
At that moment of stasis, we confront a curved wall, symmetrically placed
within that frame, as well as a diagonal wall just to the left.
And the spatial forces of the curved wall and the diagonal wall
almost compel us to turn to the right to find the main stair that will take us
up to the primary second floor.
The second floor has the main living spaces, the dining room,
and the kitchen.
Given the elongated windows, we might expect
that the second floor would comprise a very large living
space that would run parallel to the front wall,
or parallel to the garden wall.
In fact, Le Corbusier has divided it up in exactly the opposite way.
The vertical surfaces that divide the space
are perpendicular to the two long outside walls.
The curvilinear wall of the dining room at once
makes an enclosing space for the dining room, that
has a view out the back to the garden.
But the curve also sets up an axis, which
defines the center of the living room on the opposite side.
At the front of the living room, is a gallery,
from which we can move out onto a sheltered terrace, which
can be seen from the living room and the dining room, but not accessed.
Once again, we have now a more complicated version
of rotation and frontality.
The whole weight, or energy, of the main floor plan
seems to be on the periphery.
There seems to be an energetic swirling of space around that central living
room.
And that swirling of space, which creates now a rotation, almost
virtual rotation, that parallels our bodily rotation through the spaces.
Against that are these vertical surfaces, often given
a kind of figuration, because of a certain kind of curve,
or a certain kind of opening, that creates moments of stasis,
within that peripheral swirl.
The third floor accommodates the bedrooms.
And then, finally, on the top floor, there's
an enormous terrace with a sauna.
And here, we can really get the sense of what Le Corbusier meant
when he talked about compressed organs.
The sauna is a very intense bodily space.
It's where the hot, wet air, and what, for Corbusier,
was an important hygienic function of the sauna, would be performed.
And he gives the sauna a little lozenge-ish shape,
again like a little organ placed on top of the roof terrace,
which itself then would provide dry air and sunlight,
again for a hygienic function.
The top terrace has often reminded commentators of
not just the hygienic health functions that Corbusier
wanted to be performed there, but also of an ocean liner,
the deck of an ocean liner.
Where beyond the function of, sort of a healthy space that's provided,
it was also an industrial space, a new kind
of space, on top of an ocean liner, which
along with automobiles and airplanes, were the objet-type that Corbusier
thought represented modern industry and modern spirit.