K. MICHAEL HAYS: After Le Corbusier had been able to develop and refine some of the attributes of the Dom-ino
https://youtu.be/TvXRdISin-g
system in the actual villas, he was ready to issue what, for him, was the first programmatic
manifesto of the "new architecture."
He called it "The Five Points of a New Architecture."
For polemical reasons, he suggested that "The Five Points of the New Architecture" would
be a universally applicable language of the new architecture.
And that it was the logical outcome and the correct use of both available technologies
of construction, like the concrete frame,
and, at the same time, a vocabulary that provided what he called the "spiritual needs," to supplement
those technical needs.
The manifesto "The Five Points of the New Architecture" was promotional.
It was intended to familiarize a lay public, an international public, with the ideas underlying
this new architecture.
The five points, or principles, they are at once technical and architectural.
And they are: the pilotis, the roof garden, the free plan, the ribbon window, and the
free facade.
The pilotis are the columns that derive from the columns in the Dom-ino system that support
the horizontal slabs and that raise the building above the ground.
By the time he's developed the pilotis in the villas, he's more and more interested
in using the pilotis to lift the building up off the ground.
The piloti, in that way, is a reversal of either of a classical podium, which anchors
the building to the earth.
But it's also the reversal of traditional domestic basements that were regarded by
Le Corbusier as dank and unhealthy.
At the same time the pilotis accepts the European convention of the "piano nobile," the noble
floor, the main floor.
The main floor which is one floor above the ground.
And then also the pilotis has implications for the sectional distribution of occupation,
even at the urban scale.
Corbusier imagined that, out of the house, is an idea of raising the spaces of occupation
above one floor.
And leaving the ground open for recreation, circulation, transportation, collectively
available.
That understood, urbanistically, this would actually imply a new, more democratic space.
An opening, an availability of the surface of the earth for spontaneous and varied uses.
In the same way, raising the building on pilotis replaces the basement.
The roof terrace, or the garden on the roof, replaces the pitched roof and the attic with
an open air room.
Reinforced concrete made each floor plate structurally homogeneous.
So that the top floor plate, the roof, was just as strong as the floors.
No single feature of Le Corbusier's work better summarizes his conviction about the healing quality of
the house itself than the roof garden.
On the roof garden, there was a regenerative inspiring forces and powers of this hygienic
exposure of the body to the sun.
The roof terrace recalls preindustrial life, which was lived more outside, and for Le Corbusier
would then be more healthy.
But it also suggests the hygienic pleasures of relaxation and traveling on the ocean liner,
itself one of modernism's object-type.
By freeing the columnar structure from the interior partitions which enclose the program,
Le Corbusier created the free plan.
The free plan is opposed by Corbusier to what he calls the "paralyzed plan."
The paralyzed plan is a plan of rooms:
each one discrete from the other, created by walls that are themselves load bearing.
Load bearing walls means that the rooms have to be of a certain size and a certain shape.
They have to be entered through doors and punctured by small windows.
The free plan allows a much more open arrangement and size of space and an interpenetration of
spaces one into the other.
The separation of space and structure, or structure and the partitions that enclose
space, also enabled an articulation of a vocabulary of formal plastic relationships.
These, what are called earlier, "pictorial elements" that animated visually as well as
spatially the open free plan.
This is the moment when the technical conditions of the Dom-ino diagram, which change a building's
structural solution and constructional methods, actually have an effect that is ultimately
not about technology at all,
but rather about new possibilities of space, new possibilities of form, that now can be
explored sculpturally, architecturally, as well as programmatically.
The fourth of the five points is the ribbon window, or elongated window.
The ribbon window is, in a way, a corollary of the free facade.
It's a window that can be cut into a wall, because the wall is not load bearing.
But it also, as a device, negates the aedicular window, the framing window, which is about
one individual positioning himself in a vertical rectangle.
The ribbon window is a collective window.
It's not an individual window, and it's also not a window that stabilizes at one point
perspective.
It's rather a window that produces a panorama.
It's almost like a cinematic version of a window, rather than a painterly version of
a window.
We can think of the ribbon window as being an analog of a tracking shot in a movie.
Le Corbusier insisted that, though it was developed for domestic use, it could become
a standardized, mechanized, mass-produced element for all types of buildings.
Finally, the fifth point, the free facade.
The free facade establishes the compositional pictorial availability of the surface wall--
even as it also allows the thinness of that wall to be more membrane-like:
a kind of thinner wrapper that encloses the building and emphasizes the volumetric qualities
that were so important for Le Corbusier over the static compression structural qualities.
The wall becomes a light membrane that allows the window to be extended without interruption.
But it also allows other kinds of openings to be much more varied and to be composed
geometrically and visually, rather than being determined constructionally or structurally.