[MUSIC PLAYING]
https://youtu.be/89SSB6U4yBc
ERIKA NAGINSKI: One of the central themes of architectural history is the way in which architecture relates
sự đại diện của chính nó, cho dù là qua vật liệu thông thường, các hiệp ước
chính tả, viễn cảnh, hay qua ngôn ngữ của nó
Hôm  nay tôi muốn tập trung vào thời kì ở cuối thế kỉ 18, và vào 1 nhóm kiến trúc sư
được gọi là những kiến trúc có tầm nhìn xa.
Có tầm nhìn xa không chỉ bở vì họ cân nhắc mối quan hệ của kiến trúc với sự thể hiện,
với ngôn từ hay với hình ảnh, mà còn vì họ batws đầu tạo ra sự không tưởng.
Chúng ta sẽ xem xét những tác phẩm của Ledoux, và, đặc biệt là của Étienne-Louis Boullée và
nhưng gì cuối cùng được gọi là "kiến trúc parlante" hay "kiến trúc biết nói"
Tôi muốn bắt đầu với 1 trong những kiến trúc sư tầm nhìn xa này với cái tên
Claude Nicolas Ledoux.
Anh ấy là người mà có thể coi là nổi tiếng nhất ngày nay vì đã xây dựng được nhà máy hiện đại đầu tiên.
Và nhà máy này đã được sử dụng dể sản xuất muối vào cuối thế kỉ 18.
Và tôi muốn bắt đầu từ đây là vì tôi muốn nhấn mạnh 1 điều về 1 trong số những
khía cạnh còn lạ kì hơn về kiến trúc thế kỉ 18
Ngày nay, khi chúng ta nghĩ về giai đoạn xây dựng, 1 kiến trúc sư có ý tưởng, họ thực hiện
nó trên giấy, họ xây dựng mô hình.
Họ tuần tự theo chuỗi trình bày có tính truyền thống cao:
kế hoạch, bản phác thảo, bản vẽ.
Đôi khi họ sẽ nảy ra những hình ảnh có nhiều triển vọng mà  gợi ra bằng cách nào đó
1 công trình thực sự thông qua hình ảnh.
Và cuối cùng, nếu họ may mắn, công trình đó sẽ được xây dựng.
1 trong số những điều kì lạ về gai đoạn cuối thể kỉ 18 rằng là bạn sẽ thấy các kiến trúc sư dảo ngược
quá trình này.
Họ sẽ nhìn lướt qua nhiệm vụ được giao.
Họ sẽ xây dựng công trình.
Và từ thực tế, họ sẽ tưởng tượng ra 1 kiến trúc giả tưởng.
Ví dụ, nếu chúng ta xem xét Saltworks mà ngày nay được ghi nhận là
1 di sản thế giới bởi UNESCO.
Nó tồn tại.
Nó đã được xây.
Nó được sử dụng làm nhà máy ở cuối thế kỉ 18 và trong thế kỉ 19.
Nhưng từ nhà máy đó Claude-Nicolas đã tưởng tượng ra 1 thành phố lý tưởng.
Anh ấy đã tưởng tượng 1 điều không tưởng mà anh gọi là thành phố Lý Tưởng của Chaux.
Vì vậy, tôi muốn đấu với ý tưởng này trong sự Giác Ngộ muộn.
Nhưng tôi muốn quay lại lịch sử và nhìn nhận đa dạng nhiều ví dụ.
Mà đó là truyền thống của thành phố lý tưởng.
vậy hãy bắt đầu với việc xem xét 1 cuốn sách khác, cuốn được Ledoux xuất bản năm 1804, về
sự chấm dứt của cuộc đời mình, như là 1 tác phẩm đối với thành quả đạt được của ông
ông đặt tên là " Kiến trúc trong mối quan hệ với nghệ thuật,  xã hội, và
pháp luật. "
Và, trong cuốn sách này, bạn sẽ tìm thấy một tấm bản đồ và tầm nhìn chiến lược của thành phố lý tưởng Chaux
điều mà ông đã rút ra được từ nhà máy sản xuất muối của ông.
Giờ đây là 2 chiến lược trực quan khác biệt.
Tấm bản đồ là về địa hình.
Cái thứ hai thực sự là cảnh quan từ trên cao, như thể chúng ta bay ngang qua khu phố và nhìn
nó mở ra khung cảnh thôn quê
Nếu chúng ta so sánh chúng, có những sự khác biệt khác làm ta bất ngờ.
Vì vậy khi bạn xem bản đồ, những gì bạn nhìn thấy là cấu trúc hình học phức tạp.
Thể hiện rõ ở bố cục bản đồ.
Và nơi sản xuất-- sản xuất muối-- đặt ở giữa đây
in a fully enclosed, heavily circumscribed oval.
Như thể khu phố thực sự kiên cố.
Và trên thực thế thì đúng là như vậy.
các thành lũy được thể hiện trong bản kế hoạch, và cả trong huyền thoại.
Chúng ta có thể thấy rằng xưởng muối được đặt ở trung tâm của thành phố.
Chúng ta thấy từ phần chú thích bên phải -- phần được thêm ở đây-- là 1 nhà thờ xứ
ở bên phải.
Ở bên trái, có 1 tòa án.
Bức tường chắn hình bầu dục bao quanh cao đến mức nó thực sự in bóng xuống khung cảnh.
It's a highly paranoid configuration, as though to get into the city is an act of enclosure.
So, we have only two roads to get in and out of town.
And the sense that these roads are highly sort of a diagrammatic.
We have one road running north to south from the forest to the river.
And then another running east to west.
These are the only points of access into the city of Chaux.
However, if you look at the perspectival view, the "Vue perspective de la ville de Chaux,"
you're going to see an entirely different kind of experience.
Here, the topography unveils and reveals mountains in the background.
You'll see that there's a far more open sense.
The ramparts are, in fact, gone.
And kind of integration of the landscape with the town.
So the kind of stifling geometric character of the map is replaced by a far more open
feel.
The semicircle, just like the map, is sort of fully elaborated into its elliptical form.
But there's a far more seamless movement between the center-- the focal point, the saltworks--
and the farms that dot the countryside.
Now what's clear in the view and less clear in the map is that Ledoux is actually working
out a design for public space, for "res publica,"
and trying to depict a harmonious living environment.
So we see troops gathering onto the esplanade.
We see the factory smoke rising out of the chimneys to sort of indicate that production
is happening.
In a sense, activities unfold here and emphasize that life thrives as a result of this ideal
city.
And, as a result, also, of the proper exploitation of nature's resources.
So when we look here, it's the buildings that speak, not the legend.
You have two large public squares, semi-circular.
You see that there's a church to the west, a market to the east.
If you look to the north, you will see on the one hand, public baths and a stock exchange.
And if you look below the church, there is a structure with a kind of semicircular auditorium.
This is actually part of the university that he is imagining here.
It's an auditorium for a medical school.
The other thing that's clear as you move out to the countryside, is that he's mixing old
and new structures, kind of Neo-Palladian villas and old farms, old churches.
What's happening here is that the saltworks-- the real saltworks-- have generated a vision
of an ideal society.
It's a utopian gesture.
Representation comes after the built structure to generate a perfect social world.
And here, the geometry is what's capturing us.
All of its variations-- the semicircle, the oval, the ellipse-- all of this becomes a
kind of formal metaphor for the harmony of human existence with nature.
You can even evoke the elliptical course of the planets, or think about the economic metaphor
of the circle of production.
This is utopia in Ledoux's terms.
And so let's just wrap this up by quoting Ledoux himself, and understanding the reason
for which he looks at the circular model to generate society.
This is Ledoux.
"Everything is circular in nature;
The stone that falls into the water propagates infinite circles;
centripetal force is incessantly countered by a rotary motion;
the air and the seas move in perpetual circles...
so the town of Chaux is an immense circle with a form as pure as that described by the sun...
The line intersecting the diameter of the salt works crosses the Loue river, immense
plains, the town, the forest, the Geneva canal, the Swiss pastures;
to the left lie [the great rivers], the port of Antwerp, and the North Seas carry the first
and much desired fruits of our labor, commerce and arts, to the very deserts of Siberia."
It's an extraordinary quote.
And what I find most moving in this is the dream of the global reach of this tiny little
utopia in the countryside, which is generated by a saltworks factory.
And in this language is this insistence on geometric forms, on nature, and on the rewriting
of society.
So what I am going to do now is discuss the repercussions of all of this.
But also its sources.
So I want to think about the roots of Ledoux's imagined society by actually turning back
the clock quite a bit, going back to the Renaissance, where we see the visual tradition of utopia
emerging in geometric terms, and also in literature.
And then I'll sit on the drawings of one of Ledoux's great contemporaries, the visionary
architect Étienne-Louis Boullée, who is most often used to represent architecture's relationship
to language.
In other words, what we call, "architecture parlante," or "speaking architecture."