ERIKA NAGINSKI: Now it would seem a given that architects would be interested in institutions and in
https://youtu.be/88sZOf9vwO4
studying their typologies and developing their typologies but one has to remember that this
institutionalism this imagining of public buildings was completely new in the Renaissance.
What's important for us is that this relation of the ideal city and inventing institutions
or public institutions anew with which to reorganize the social order really emerged
fully articulated only for the first time in the 18th century, so centuries later with
architects like Ledoux, who is looking at the factory as a kind of template for an ideal
society, and also with the works of the architect to whom I want now to turn, Étienne-Louis
Boullée, another one of these visionary architects whose "City of the Dead" I'm now going to
turn to.
This is a pen-and-ink drawing from the 1780s, so we're dealing with the decade before the
French Revolution broke out.
The French Revolution begins in 1789.
Boullée is an extraordinary character, historically, along these lines.
He's an academically trained architect.
His career spans the 18th century, this period we call the Enlightenment: the period that
saw the birth of social philosophy, of notions of democracy, of new forms of government that
would challenge royal authority, and by the end of the century, of course, with the American
Revolution and the French Revolution, we see society actually rewritten.
So it's no surprise that utopian schemes and the imagining of public buildings would occur
in this historical context.
But to go back to Boullée, this is an architect who was born in 1728, and he died in 1799,
the very year the French Revolution came to an end.
So he is, actually, a kind of perfect fit as a kind of architectural figura of the Enlightenment.
He's someone who was elected to France's official architectural institution: the Royal Academy
of Architecture.
He took himself to be a great proponent of classical ideas and of pure geometric forms
in architecture.
He, essentially, imagined a whole series of public buildings.
He fetishized the colossal in architecture, and most of all, most curiously, he built
relatively little.
His oeuvre is, essentially, found in drawings like this one of unbuildable projects, in
fact.
Yet, he emerged as one of the most influential theorists and teachers of his time.
And we can continue to feel his legacy in modern and contemporary architecture.
So how does he show us a "City of the Dead," a kind of urban fabrication that extends the
cemetery into an entire city fabric.
We have at the rear of the image a domed basilica, obviously a centralized structure, which is
elevated, and, if you notice, the curves and lines of its contours actually formalize the
silhouette of the mountain, the huge mountain that's rising behind it.
In other words, here architecture is not simply in symbiosis with nature; it's actually a
metaphor for it.
You sense the ghost of the ideal city in this so-called "City of the Dead," rendered as
eternal as nature itself.
And you're going to see in the drawings that we're going to look through Boullée, like
Ledoux, began to develop a whole typology of public buildings: churches, cemeteries,
libraries, schools, military forts; and, in this, of course, is inscribed a utopian aspiration,
a rewriting of society through architecture.
There's another aspect of Boullée's architecture that we need to address, however.
They are deeply engaged with the aesthetic philosophy of the period.
In particular, Boullée is looking to create a kind of equivalent, in architecture, to
what the philosophers who were his contemporaries called the sublime.
This is a concept that was developed in the 18th century; it was used to describe, imagine
the state of being awestruck, of being overwhelmed by the infinity of nature, by the infinity
of God-- in other words, by things that seem so incommensurable that we don't know how
to take account of them, that we actually don't know how to represent them.
In other words, the sublime corresponds to that which is immeasurable, unrepresentable,
inconceivable.
Boullée's writings and his images-- these pen-and-ink sketches-- sought to take those
kinds of qualities associated with the sublime, and they were conveniently typologized by
philosophers-- I'm thinking, in particular, of Edmund Burke or Immanuel Kant-- by the
end of the century, and these qualities can be identified as follows: obscurity, power,
vastness, infinity, magnificence, silence, suddenness, the intermittent sound or the
intermittent sight, and Boullée took these ideas and turned them into architecture.
What he was after, ultimately, was to make architecture somehow transcendent, to make
architecture reach a kind of philosophical condition.
And what it so interesting here is that, somehow, we're returning to the phenomenology of architecture.
In other words, how our bodies, how our senses react to the spaces around us, to the architectural
spaces around us.
So how does this work?
How does this work in terms of a paper architecture?
What I'm showing you here is what Boullée called "a funerary monument characterizing
the genre of a buried architecture."
What does this mean?
Well, first, it means that the image is, somehow, thematically tied to the sublime because the
subject or purpose of the building we see is, in fact, an architecture of death.
It is a kind of monumental gateway to a cemetery, if you will.
So it's representing the unrepresentable in architectural form.
This is quite a contradiction.
Second-- the title is a giveaway to this-- it characterizes what Boullée called a genre
or type.
This is an important word in the 18th century: type or typology.
It's a genre or type of architecture, and so, presumably, it typifies a set of characteristics
or properties.
These characteristics, or properties, are meant to have a certain effect or prompt a
certain kind of reaction on the viewer.
Third, that genre or type actually has a name.
Boullée calls it "buried architecture."
The idea here is that you, actually, bury a colossal structure so that architecture
itself becomes an analogy to the tomb.
Out of this typologizing, out of this searching for a typological formatting of public buildings,
Boullée developed what later would be called "architecture parlante," or "speaking architecture."
This is very much along the lines of what Ledoux was doing at the saltworks.
And the idea is that buildings somehow explain their function or explain their identity through
their formal attributes.
They speak their names.
The idea emerged in Boullée's collected writings and his drawings, which, essentially, span
this late 18th-century period from about 1778 into the French Revolution, into 1793.
And all of this manifested itself in utopian terms, in an architecture on paper that was
rendered monochromatically and that offered a kind of panoply of unbuildable edifices
presenting projects for public buildings moored to huge scale, to largeness of scale, and
highly formalized geometric vocabularies.
This is the rise of public building and public building typologies, and we understand that
when we go back the 18th century that this was a fundamentally utopian undertaking.
So what was this architectural language of utopia, if you will.
Well, it's based on regularized solids, gargantuan spheres, pyramids, huge quadrangles, with
each geometric form, somehow, thematizing a given purpose, a given use.
The result is that the symbolic aspect of architecture-- in other words, how you invoke
the character of a structure-- superseded all practical implications.
In other words, Boullée was absolutely not interested in whether these could be built
or not.
He was interested in their symbolic apparatus and their social utility.
So the example here is a military fort, and, for Boullée, military architecture needed
to suggest "the idea of force."
Accordingly, what you see in the drawing, or what you see in Boullée's imagining of
the fort, is that the actual techniques, the technologies of construction here, are pretty
much irrelevant.
He's not interested in mechanical problems, technical issues.
He actually dismissed Vitruvius for being too interested in engineering because this
was not what, for Boullée, the primary purpose of architecture.
The primary purpose of architecture was to imagine possibilities, for Boullée.
Instead, he was far more interested in how we, literally, read the identity of his structure,
which is a round central tower flanked by four square ones set on the diagonal.
In other words, this is an architecture of signs.
You have an absolutely massive shield-- it's, in fact, the shield of the great Greek warrior
Achilles-- plastered on the facade.
You have walls so massive that they give the idea of indestructibility, and the fact that
they actually couldn't be built was completely beside the point for Boullée.
You have piles of cannon balls and cannons set to each side of the flanking towers.
All of this is a kind of symbolic apparatus that produces signs so that we can read the
building, that the architecture, again, can speak its identity, speaks its character,
speaks its name.
Another example would be something like this, in this so-called geometrical elevation of
a chapel of the dead.
Again, we have the pyramidal shape, which we associate with the memorial, with commemoration,
with the end of life.
We're meant to understand this commemorative purpose through this visual illusion, if you
will, to the sublime, which Boullée actually stresses in his definition of architecture.
And when we turn to his writings, we can read into them his deliberate allusion to the philosophical
ideas that were circulating in the period.
Here is Boullée, "Architecture is the only art by which we can put Nature to work, and
this unique advantage makes manifest its Sublime aspect.
The means by which nature can be put to work, which belong to architecture, come from the
power to effect what poetry can only describe.
The art of moving us through the effects of light belongs to architecture.
For in all the monuments that are capable of stirring the soul and making us experience
the horrors of darkness, or, conversely, that create transportive sensations through brilliant
effects, the architect, who must know these means and master them, can dare to say: I
create light.
This is an extraordinarily ambitious definition of architecture, and there are several points
to retain.
First, that architecture is linked to nature.
Second, that the sublime character of architecture is based on that link to nature.
And third, Boullée's assumption that, somehow, the formal character of a building affects
our senses.
We feel horror at darkness.
We feel jubilation at light.
And, finally, the equation between architect and God: "I create light."
The assumption here is that there is a direct relationship between highly abstract forms
and human sensations, and that geometrical shapes can actually render architecture transcendent.
Drawings, in this sense, become a kind of template for the sublime and for inciting
a sublime reaction in their viewers.
Here's another one of these drawings; this one's a perspectival entrance to a cemetery
in which darkness and the pyramidal form evoke the end of life.
Over and over again, we see these mechanisms at work.
For example, in this project for a metropolitan church, where we can discern the regular succession
and uniformity of its kit of parts that, according to philosophers of the time, artificially
recreated the sense of infinity.
Listen to this account.
"Whenever we repeat any idea frequently, the mind by a sort of mechanism repeats it long
after...
Place a number of uniform and equidistant marks in regular sequence [such as a row of
columns] they will cause it to seem to extend to a length almost incredible and seem multiplied
without end...
[Likewise in a] rotunda you can nowhere fix a boundary; turn which way you will, the same
object still seems to continue, and the imagination has no rest.
But the parts must be uniform as well as circularly disposed, to give this figure its full force."
In this scheme of things, the architectural is actually created by the repetition of columns,
by placing uniform columnar screens on all sides.
And circularity is also crucial to the effect.
Here is shows up in this gargantuan dome, a dome technologically which could never have
been erected at the time because of its sheer size.
And, of course, to go back to the sublime; it is a rotunda that offers no boundaries
and no end points.
It is the architectural equivalent, if you will, of infinity.
And then there's the uniformity of the plan too, with four arms and entrances all exactly
alike, all the same, and, unlike Ledoux, completely devoid of program.
But now I want to return to where I began, and the idea that no mater how sublime Boullée's
projects seem, they were, nonetheless, very much tied to contemporaneous architectural
projects.
In other words, projects that were actually built.
What Boullée, in some cases, was doing was looking at the built, and then using the real
to create a fiction, to create a new typology.
So for the metropolitan church, all we need to do is to consider a church that was built
by the architect Soufflot, the Church of St. Genevieve, which is now the French Panthéon.
And if we compare the plans-- Boullée on the left, Soufflot on the right-- we can see
that, basically, what Boullée did was to take Soufflot's church and to turn it into
some kind of geometric giant.
Boullée's focus on vast dimensions, on a kind of formal purity, on a repetition is
inscribed in a sacred space that had a real precursor, a built expression in Soufflot's
church.
And what Boullée, essentially, did was to fantastically blow Soufflot's church out of
scale through representation, through drawing.
The idea, however, was already there in Soufflot's church.
This is typical of the visionary architect's translation of the real into the ideal, of
producing a fiction from the concrete.
So no matter how sublime Boullée's projects seem, they were nonetheless tied to contemporaneous
projects that were actually built.