[MUSIC PLAYING]
https://youtu.be/uwhQ4W0qXGc
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Just as the visionary architects of the Enlightenment
gave form to new subject positions and new social institutions
that arose from the developing economy in the 18th century,
so architects of the 20th century gave representation
to conditions of their context.
The late 20th century economy sponsored not only an industry
that produced machines like Behrens's turbine factory or Henry Ford's
assembly line, but also what philosophers
called the culture industry, which is akin to a factory,
but one that produces mass cultural goods--
music, movies, art, entertainment.
Just as the architecture of Ledoux, theatricalized the salt industry,
so would late modern architecture inevitably come
to be involved with its own new cultural ethos.