https://youtu.be/fl4wHx6vTi0
[MUSIC PLAYING]
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Today we'll look at the Centre Pompidou in the city of Paris.
It's a cultural and art center in the Marais district
on Place Beaubourg in Paris, designed by the team
of Renzo Piano and Richard Rogers.
The ultimate goal is to produce a reading of the center that
is ideological, to understand the architecture
as a mapping and a representation of a historical moment
and a political condition.
On the one hand, the center was inspired by post-1968 philosophies
of collectivity and community.
But on the other hand, the project was an interpretation
of new cybernetic theories of information and organization,
avant-garde theatrical principles, cutting-edge technology,
and a completely new attitude toward urbanism
and the practice of urban space.
The ultimate goal was a building that would support and represent
freedom and change in direct response to the desires of its users.
The concept of architectural imagination gives us
a way of articulating the relationship between everyday perceptual events,
perceptual habits and conventions, just the attitudes about being in the world,
and the relationship of that between the context, which is usually the city,
but also the social-historical context of those experiences.
So we can think about it as two levels.
The first level is existential and subject centered.
It's just how we as individuals, or as a collective,
are in the world in that existential being in the world.
The other, which is really history itself, is deep structural.
It concerns the objective conditions of possibility
for how we can be in the world.
In other words, different historical moments, different times,
different contexts allow ways of thinking in a certain way,
allow ways of behaving in a certain way.
But those ways are shifting through time.
If we can give an account of the context,
if we can construct the context with enough robustness,
with enough dynamism, then we can--
and if you think about and still continuing
to think about the idea of architectural imagination, we can see the building,
we can interpret the building as an active mediator between the context
and our individual experiences.
So a building, because it deals with space, it deals with material,
it even deals with uses and activities in time,
can be not just an inert object but an active mediator
between its historical context and our understanding of that context.
So what we want to do now is to think about the Pompidou
Center in the city of Paris at a particular moment in time
as a kind of representation, as a kind of registration,
and it's actually helping us produce an understanding
of a very particular moment in history.