K. MICHAEL HAYS: What's referred to as the events of May '68 were responsible for the program of
https://youtu.be/vt1DQpgbKfs
the Pompidou Center.
The events of May '68 in Paris involved a series of student demonstrations and student
occupation of certain sites.
There were times when the students would gather together with certain workers
and make a general strike.
It actually was happening across France, but it was most intense in Paris.
It sometimes involved violent confrontations, as the students demonstrated or the workers
demonstrated and came into conflict with police or the army.
But it also involved artistic ideas, ideas about how culture and cultural production
and artistic activity could actually bring about social and even political change.
One way of focusing it is to consider the activities of an avant-garde art group called
the Situationist International.
What the Situationists wanted was a way of practicing the city, a way of being in the
city which would divert and change the understanding of the city and of everyday life.
An example of some of their production includes a kind of what they call this a psychogeographic
map of Paris that would be a kind of instructional map of how to practice the city differently.
They took a map of Paris that everybody in Paris would have had, a way
to navigate the city.
It was called the "Paris Taride."
And they took certain places, very famous places or well-known places on the map and
would cut them out and then rearrange their relationship.
As you can see in the photograph here of the poster, they would then mark these connections,
reconnect the pieces with little red arrows that they call "plaque tournante."
A plaque tournante is like a rotating table or like a turntable that would reorient locomotives
and trains and things like this.
But the idea here is that through this new way of practicing the city, you would take
the different moods of different parts of the cities, the different atmospheres, the
different sort of attitudes that one experiences as you move through the city and you would
try to reconnect them and reorder them to detour them, to divert them and create new
attitudes, new experiences of the city.
The events of May '68, the student occupation, the student demonstrations were for, the Situationists
a kind of paradigm for a new kind of cultural production, for a new way of practicing urban
space, new alternatives of spatial practice.
And indeed, the stillness himself produced posters, slogans, new forms of art.
Here are some examples of the slogans.
This one, "Sous les pavés, la plage," that is "Underneath the pavement (underneath the paving
stones) is the beach."
And this was the idea that if you dug up the cobblestones, if you dug up the paving stones
of the street and threw them through the windows of the university, that eventually you would
uncover a new territory, you would uncover a beach in the very center of Paris.
So it has this idea of uncovering a new place for leisure or performance, but also a beach
from which could be launched a kind of new cultural attitude.
Or this one, "Il est interdit d'interdire de dire."
You can't do that in English.
Yeah, you could do it in English.
"It is forbidden to forbid bidding."
"It is forbidden to forbid speech..." would be another example.
And while Paris was the center of this kind of attitude, of course it
happened at other places.
In the United States, also around the summer of '68, the demonstrations against the Vietnam
War, the demonstrations for civil rights were very, very similar to the events of May '68
in Paris.
London sometimes felt left out as it looked to Paris.
The Rolling Stones were inspired to write a song about the events of May called
"Street Fighting Man," where they lament the fact that the Londoners weren't participating in
the way that people of Paris and maybe people in the States were.
But there was a general feeling of global change.
There was a feeling that, out of this moment was emerging what would be simply a different
way of life, and that cultural practices, art practices would have to reflect that.
The events of May '68 were a paradigm of what the Situationists were calling for, a new
way of practicing the city, a new spatial practice.
It was as if the posters made by the students would replace the sort of paintings that Whitney
would protect.
It was as if the slogans became the poetry of a whole new generation and the performances,
the demonstrations, even the violent ones, became a new kind of performing art, an urban
performance that would replace conventional theater.
So if the events were not a huge political success, they had, nevertheless, enormous
social and cultural impact.