https://youtu.be/FQrZnPaoiAE
K. MICHAEL HAYS: We can Baudrillard's analysis as helpful.
But I don't think we have to completely accept his cynicism.
Baudrillard finds the center duplicitous in a way,
because it invites us to come to an experience of art
or an experience of culture that no longer exists.
But his idea of art and culture is actually not
so different, it seems to me, than the conservative one expressed
at the Whitney.
Baudrillard expects art to be different from everyday life.
He expects, like Breuer, that art have a sincerity and a profundity
that he thinks is no longer possible in the third order of the simulacra.
But this is the depth model of art that it seems to me has been displaced.
What happens at the Centre Pompidou is more of a horizontal model of art.
It's where the center gathers up sites from different parts of the city,
makes those connection.
It's where it gathers up different kinds of events and activities
and brings them together on a horizontal plane
or expresses them in the surface of the facade.
The Place Bauberg is a counter-site.
It's a site of difference and alterity, where
an enormous amount of cultural power and energy is generated,
as if on a horizontal plane or as if on a surface
of networks of information and flow.
It's a place where different sites in the city, different spaces in the city
can be brought together, can be connected, can be examined, contested
but also represented.