[ÂM NHẠC]
Cả bài này nói về
học thuyết tiến hóa và
những quá trình cơ bản để
hình thành sự sống.
Chủ đề của chúng ta lúc này là Charles Darwin
ngoài biển khơi.
Charles Darwin được cho là đã
viết nên cuốn sách
với tầm quan trọng đứng thứ hai
trong lịch sử phương Tây, chỉ
đứng sau Kinh Thánh.
Vào năm 1859, ấn bản đầu tiên của
"Nguồn gốc các loài qua
con đường chọn lọc tự nhiên, hay
sự bảo tồn những chủng ưu thế
trong đấu tranh
sinh tồn" được xuất bản.
Ngày nay, ta chỉ nhắc đến nó bởi
cái tên "Nguồn gốc các loài", hay
thỉnh thoảng chỉ là "Nguồn gốc".
Vào thời điểm ông cho xuất bản "Nguồn gốc
các loài", ông vốn đã là một
nhà khoa học nổi tiếng lúc bấy giờ,
được biết đến bởi các thuyết
địa chất của mình, đặc biệt là cách hình thành
các đảo san hô và sự thật
là đất có thể dâng cao.
Nhưng vì "Nguồn gốc các loài",
ông đã phải suy nghĩ trong
suốt 20 năm, tìm kiếm
các ý tưởng, lo lắng phần nào
vì ý nghĩa
của những gì ông đang chứng tỏ.
Ông muốn chắc chắn rằng
ông có thể chứng minh điều đó.
Nhưng ông cũng lo lắng về
ý nghĩa đạo đức, thậm chí là tôn giáo
của những điều
ông đang nói.
Darwin không phải là người đầu tiên
mô tả rằng
giống loài có thể thay đổi.
Ông không phải người đầu tiên chứng minh
rằng chúng không được quyết định bởi
Chúa, bất biến hay không thay đổi.
Nhưng "Nguồn gốc các loài" là
một cuốn sách hoàn toàn khác.
Nó nắm bắt được trí tưởng tượng
phổ biến và thay đổi
cách ta hiểu về sự tiến hóa.
Cụ thể là, "Nguồn gốc
các loài" giới thiệu học thuyết của
Darwin về sự chọn lọc tự nhiên.
Sự chọn lọc tự nhiên là cách Darwin
giải thích như thế nào và tại sao
giống loài thay đổi theo thời gian.
Darwin was not an enthusiastic
rebel against the predominant
ideas of the day.
In fact he said, writing about
natural selection felt a bit
like confessing to a murder.
Darwin's start in life wasn't
terribly auspicious.
Ông là con trai của một bác sĩ và
cháu trai của một nhà tự nhiên học
nổi tiếng và một nhà thần học
tự nhiên.
He was sent off to Edinburgh
Medical School, the
fifth of six sons.
Ông đã được kì vọng sẽ tiếp nối
công việc của bố minh.
Nhưng ông có vẻ sợ phẫu thuật
và ông cũng không quá
giỏi trong việc học của mình.
Ông lại cảm thấy hứng thú hơn nhiều
đối với mùa gà
lôi và việc đi săn.
And so his father other kind of
pulled him out because he
didn't think his grades
were good enough.
His father decided to send him
off to Christ's College in
Cambridge, to turn his fifth of
six children into something
worthwhile.
He might be a parson,
a country parson.
Và Darwin cũng không quá hứng thú
đối với thần học,
nhưng ông thích
sưu tập ong, thứ vốn
là "mốt" lúc bấy giờ.
Thần học và sưu tập ong,
chúng có vẻ khác biệt hoàn toàn
nhưng thực tế, nhiều
nhà tự nhiên học thời đó
nghĩ rằng những gì họ đang
làm chính là nghiên cứu
công trình của Chúa.
Tự nhiên học cũng là một loại
thần học.
Khi Darwin về nhà cho kì nghỉ hè
năm 1831, ông
gần như đã sẵn sàng lấy súng của mình
và đi săn.
Trong khi thực tế, ông nhận được lời nhắn
từ một trong những giáo sư của mình,
người đã sắp xếp để ông
trở thành nhà tự nhiên học của đoàn tàu
HMS Beagle.
He would voyage on what was
planned to be a two or three
year voyage on the Beagle and
keep the captain, Captain
Fitzroy, company.
It was actually a pretty
important role because the
previous captain had gotten so
depressed that he had locked
himself in his cabin
and shot himself.
Darwin's primary duties would
be as a collector, as a
geologist, making
observations.
But he was really there as a
companion of the captain, who
couldn't be expected to
socialise with the crew, being
of such a higher class than
the members of the crew.
Although his father was not
happy about this either, he in
fact agreed to finance
the entire trip.
And Darwin went off.
The voyage in fact extended
to five years.
And during that time, Darwin
went from being interested in
geology, to becoming one of the
most prominent geologists,
even naturalists of his day.
The Beagle departed in
December of 1831.
And it began its journey,
sailing over to South America,
charting the coastlines
as it went.
Darwin turned out to be very
good at observations.
He wrote long journal entries
about the geology,
the things he saw.
He collected specimens of
animals and fossils.
Everywhere he went, he
accumulated more and more
information.
He observed coastlines
in Africa.
He went and looked at the
jungles in Brazil.
He lived through an earthquake
while he was in Chile, sailed
across the Pacific, where he
saw the Coral Islands, and
even made it to Australia.
Darwin didn't always realise
the importance
of what he was seeing.
For example, the crew ate the
turtles, that would prove to
be so important to his
evolutionary theory later on.
But he took a lot of notes and
he was sending specimens back
the entire time while
he travelled.
By the time he actually got back
to England in 1836, his
mentor had already started to
circulate some of his journals.
And he was excited to help
Darwin organise, to get the
naturalists, who would dissect
and classify and examine all
the specimens he had found.
Because he had brought back
specimens of extinct animals
from fossils.
He had brought back undiscovered
species.
There was a lot of excitement
around Darwin's voyage in
1836, by the time he got back.
The leading anatomists of the
day competed to analyse
Darwin's specimens.
And he started to put together
his own geological
observations in one of his first
papers, which describes
how he thought South America
was actually rising, the
continent was getting
taller, higher.
His travel memoir of his voyage
on the Beagle turned
out to be kind of
a best seller.
He was a bit of a sensation,
a kind of a gentleman,
naturalist scholar, elected into
the leading scientific
societies of the day,
particularly
for his work on geology.
But to truly understand Darwin's
importance, you have
to realise that it wasn't the
discoveries on the Beagle, it
wasn't what he found on the
voyage, it was what happened
after he came back, as
he sat and thought.
Darwin's great achievement
in a sense was his just
incredible imagination,
his big picture view.
As he started to put together
the details, he begin to see a
pattern emerging from what was
up to that time just kind of a
collection of different
species.
Darwin was the one who began
to see the relations among
these species.
For example, as Darwin was
voyaging, he took the first
volume of George Lyell's book,
Principles of Geology.
And Lyell had laid out a kind
of general understanding for
all of what you see
in geology.
He talked about the natural
forces that shaped continents,
erosion, upthrust, volcanic
processes.
As Darwin went along the
coastlines of South America,
he was very excited
to see some of
Lyell's theories proven.
And he wrote his first
papers using this
kind of frame of mind.
But what Darwin's achievement
was was to begin to take that
kind of understanding of the
world, that the world is
shaped by uniform processes,
natural laws that don't
change, and start to apply
it, not just to
geology, but to biology.
Lyell had pointed out that it
wasn't catastrophes, one-off
events that had shaped
the planet, but
slow and gradual processes.
If for example, geologists found
fossils of sea creatures
on the sides of mountains, as
they were in the Alps, then
they had to have somehow gotten
there by processes we
could still see today, slow
movement of the Earth.
When Darwin came back, he begin
to talk to the other
scientists of the day, the other
naturalists, not just
about geology, but also
about biology.
And he began to see a similar
sort of pattern, how gradual
change over long periods of
time could produce this
incredible variety of
species that we see.
But it took a while for him to
truly understand the scope of
what he was observing.
Instead of God creating each
species, separate in its
present form, he begin to see
how the species could change.
Darwin wasn't the first person
to argue that God hadn't
created every single species
independently,
in its current form.
But he was the first to pull
together all the evidence, to
give the big picture.
In the next topic, we're going
to talk about that big picture
and his theories of natural
selection and On the Origin.