[MUSIC PLAYING]
Darwin and the Origin
of the Origin.
In order to understand how
Darwin begin to think about
theory of natural selection we
have to realize that in 1838,
two years after he came back
from the voyage, he began to
read Thomas Malthus' "An Essay
on the Principle of
Population." In the essay
Malthus argues that population
has a kind of grim reality.
That it can increase
geometrically.
Offspring can double
every generation.
In the process, what Malthus
realised, and what Darwin
realised too, was that many
more animals could be born
than could possibly survive.
Some of these would never
make it into adulthood.
This was the grim reality
of population increase.
Darwin realised that species
don't struggle one species
against the other, foxes
against rabbits.
But what this meant was that
rabbits were struggling
amongst themselves to survive.
A species has a kind of internal
process of struggle.
He compared it to the selective
processes that
farmers use.
How they picked seeds to plant
the next season, or how they
bred pigeons for the qualities
they liked.
And that's why he referred to it
as "natural selection." He
saw it as similar to what humans
were doing, but on a
much larger scale.
By the end of the 1830s, and
all throughout the 1840s,
Darwin was really thinking
about natural selection.
He was publishing other books,
his books about his voyage,
his books on geology, but he
was stewing on these ideas,
and collecting more information
about different species.
He wrote a secret manuscript.
A 230 page book that he stored
securely, that would be
published if he were to happen
to die before he was able to
finish the project.
But he kept his ideas
mostly to himself.
He was troubled.
He wasn't just troubled by the
fact that he didn't feel like
he had enough information, he
was collecting more data.
But he was also just troubled by
the implications of what he
was saying.
His wife was very religious.
And he, too, had come from a
very religious background.
He was trying to sort of decide
what this all meant.
Darwin also struggled with
poor health, what we now,
probably, would call
psychological conditions.
His daughter passed away
and he had ill
health in the family.
But for 20 years he worked
on these ideas.
He didn't call evolution
at first.
He called it, in his notebooks,
transmutation of
species, or change of species.
He shared his ideas with his
colleagues in the learned
societies, but he didn't
make them public.
Finally in 1858, he was
rocked by a paper.
It was sent to him by a young
field researcher, Alfred
Russel Wallace.
Wallace, in 1858, in his paper
he sent to Darwin, who he
really admired, laid out what
was essentially Darwin's
theory, the theory he'd been
working on for 20 years.
Fortunately for Darwin, two of
his famous colleagues in the
Linnean Society talked Alfred
Russell Wallace into
presenting his ideas together
with Darwin at a meeting of
the Linnean Society of London.
Unfortunately for Darwin, he
was so distraught from the
death of another child that
in 1858, when the meeting
happened, Darwin didn't
even attend.
In the 1858 presentation,
Wallace read out part of his
paper, part of the letters that
Darwin had written to the
Linnean Society, but it
barely caused a stir.
The scientists who were gathered
there didn't really
see what was significant
about their
discussion of natural selection.
The 1858 presentation caused
scarcely a ripple.
That year in the annual report
the president of the Linnean
Society wrote, "The year which
has passed has not, indeed,
been marked by any of those
striking discoveries which at
once revolutionise, so to
speak, the department of
science on which they bear."
In other words, nothing
interesting happened
this year.
But then in 1859, Darwin
published On
the Origin of Species.
It was an instant best seller,
sold out completely.
It went through six
new additions,
just in Darwin's lifetime.
So what was the difference
between 1858 and 1859?
Why did it suddenly become
a best seller?
Well the first thing you have to
realise is that Darwin was
a brilliant writer.
All those years he had spent
stewing on the ideas, he had
built up example after example
of how you could see evolution
shaping the species
around you.
He had chosen examples from the
English countryside, from
hobbies like pigeon breeding,
that were popular in the day,
from cattle breeding, and all
the different examples that
readers would understand.
He had created a kind of
catalogue of life, in On the
Origin of Species.
And behind it, he showed how
evolution was working on
everything from orchids
to honeybees.
In Darwin's hands, biology
had become like
geology had under Lyell.
It was not just a catalogue of
diversity, but it was a system
that has certain underlying
principles that you could see
shaping each and
every species.
But it took a scholar with
Darwin's kind of encyclopaedic
knowledge of life, to
be able to do that.
The irony is that, we now look
back on Darwin as the father
of evolution.
He didn't even like the word.
He preferred descent
with modification.
He thought that evolution gave
the idea, too much, that there
was progress.
And in fact, his supporters,
even though they fought for
his ideas, really didn't focus
on what was the most important
contribution of his theory,
which was the theory of
natural selection itself.
They were with him on the idea
of species changed, that
wasn't his original idea.
But they didn't believe his
process was what was causing
the change.
But ultimately, I think one of
the reasons that On the Origin
of Species was so successful
is that Darwin shared one
trait with the natural
theologians.
They were able to see the
fingerprints of God in creation.
He was still able to feel that
awe, that wonder, and share
that kind of excitement,
but he saw the
effects of natural selection.
At the end of On the Origin he
shares this kind of amazing
vision that he has of nature.
"It is interesting to
contemplate a tangled bank,
clothed with many plants of many
kinds, with birds singing
on the bushes, with various
insects flitting about, with
worms crawling through
the damp earth.
And to reflect that these
elaborately constructed forms,
so different from each other,
and dependent upon each other
in so complex a manner, have
all been produced by laws
acting around us.
There is grandeur in this view
of life with its several
powers, having been originally
breathed by the creator into a
few forms or into one, and that,
whilst this planet has
gone circling on, according to
the fixed laws of gravity,
from so simple a beginning,
endless forms, most beautiful
and most wonderful, have been,
and are being evolved." In the
next topic, we're going to get
into Darwin's theory of
natural selection.