lyne5890
[Nhạc dạo]
Một trong những bằng chứng tiến hoá thuyết phục nhất
mà bạn có được
đều nằm ngay trong chính hệ mô và xương của mình.
Có thể đang phơi bày ngay trước mắt bạn
chính là đôi bàn tay.
Đôi tay không những rất đặc biệt
khi giúp ta viết chữ,
chơi đùa
Gíup ta chăm sóc,
bón cơm cho con trẻ ăn.
Thậm chí đánh nhau, hay giao tiếp tương tác với nhau
Mà khi ta nhìn ngược vào trong lớp da này
để nhìn vào cấu tạo bên trong đó,
ta sẽ thấy
cấu tạo đôi tay ra sao, hệ xương và cơ như thế nào
lại khá là giống với các loài động vật khác như vậy.
sự tương tự này không chỉ với loài khỉ hay tinh tinh,
mà còn tương tự với các động vật khác
mà ta không ngờ tới được.
Như là gấu, dơi, cá heo
thậm chí là ếch nhái.
Các nhà sinh vật học
gọi đây là
tính giải phẫu tương đồng
Sở dĩ có sự tương đồng này
là do các giống loài có chung một cội nguồn tổ tiên.
Rồi từ cội nguồn đó phân nhánh mà tiến hoá.
Một điều thú vị là, ta có thể thấy được
những điểm tương đồng này
khi nhìn qua lăng kính của cấu trúc giải phẫu,
cấu tạo cơ quan
hay cấu tạo liên kết hoá học
dưới những chức năng khác nhau.
Ví dụ, một cấu tạo tương tự
bên dưới một bàn tay người
và bàn tay thú vật,
hay bàn chân và vây cá
British anatomist Richard Owen,
the man who gave us the
term "dinosaur," or "terrible
lizard," also the man who
founded the British Museum of
Natural History, gave us the
terminology homology in 1843,
even before Darwin had
published "The Origin of
Species." Owen wrote that a
homology was the same organ in
different species under every
variety of form and
in function.
Anatomists of his day, even this
early, realised as they
peeled off the skin and
dissected different species,
that startlingly different
species had quite similar
anatomical structures.
The skeletons of a mouse and an
elephant sometimes matched
up almost bone for bone, even
though they look so strikingly
different from the outside.
For example, if you took the
tusks of an elephant, they
look extraordinary, but they
match up with the teeth of
other species.
To get a sense for how
homologies work, let's take a
look at a photo of my dog
Louie's front paw.
Now, you might not think from
looking at the photo that his
paw and your hand had
a lot in common.
Louie can't pick up things
with his paw.
He can't write.
He can't open a can of dog food
for himself with his paw.
He mostly just sort of runs
around on it and occasionally
uses it to scratch with.
But if you were to look at an
x-ray of his arm and his paw,
you would notice that
the bones match up
surprisingly well.
He has a humerus in his upper
arm, or in his upper leg, that
matches the humerus in your arm,
connected to his scapula.
He has a radius and ulna in the
middle part of his leg,
matching the two bones
in your forearm.
What's a little bit confusing
about Louie's leg is it looks
like he has an extra joint.
But that extra joint sort of
matches up to the metacarpals
in your hand.
His paw is actually using less
of his leg than your hand is
using of your arm.
And that fifth dew claw
is a vestigial organ.
It matches up to your thumb.
If we look closely at the
diagram of the bones, Louie's
leg kind of looks like a human
arm, but twisted in a fun
house mirror, or in Photoshop,
the same bones reconfigured
into new functions.
Even in a mammal with a
radically different looking
limb, like a horse, or an
elephant, and a dolphin, we
often find these bones match up
one for one in homologies.
And that's when it's most
impressive, I think.
When you see a limb with a
radically different function,
underlying it is the same-- or
a very similar structure,
because we've all descended
from common ancestors.
This, for example, is Jeffrey.
He's a pony that lives
on our farm.
At first glance, his leg may
not look like your arm, or
even a dog's leg.
But his leg is homologous
to your arm.
You have to realise that
Jeffrey's basically standing
on a single finger.
And his finger, or his hoof,
has less joints than your
finger does.
But Jeffrey's got a humerus, a
radius, and an ulna, just like
you do, in the whole section
of his leg leading down to
what looks like a knee.
In veterinary anatomy that's
called a horse's carpus.
The carpus has a seven-bone
structure.
It's homologous to our wrist.
And the lowest part of the
horse's leg, down at the
bottom, is called the cannon.
That last joint of his leg
is homologous with your
metacarpal, your middle
metacarpal, the third one, the
middle bone on your hand.
But like your tailbone, his
bones have fused together into
a single unit.
At the lowest point, what's
called the fetlock, he has a
single knuckle, a single joint
above what's essentially a
giant fingernail.
Now, what you have realise with
the bone structure of
Jeffrey's leg is it's severely
distorted compared to yours,
but the bones do match up,
because Jeffrey, unlike your
dog, has had to adapt in a
completely different direction.
If we compare these structures
to a dolphin's fin, or a
whale's fin, we see that, again,
the same underlying
structure, but distorted in a
completely different direction.
In the whale and the dolphin,
the radius and ulna and the
humerus are all compressed
and reinforced.
And in contrast, the phalanges,
the joints of the
fingers in our hands, are
multiplied to form the basis
of the fin.
Now, in contrast, the bat has
these extraordinary stretched
and elongated bones, that all
of the bones of the arm and
the digits are stretched out
so that the membrane of the
wing has a large surface area.
In all these cases, we see how
evolution has driven the same
structure into radically
different functions.
In the next topic, we're going
to keep talking about
homologies, but we're going to
talk about the direction in
that selection.