[PLAYING MUSIC]
In this topic, we're going to
look at the benefits of having
an immature brain and
some about tool use.
In our ancestors' tools, we
can really see how their
brains changed.
Up until about 1.8 million years
ago they had what we
call Olduwan tools
or pebble tools.
And they could have looked sort
of like river cobbles,
with one edge worked or knocked
off through some hard
hand percussion, that is
striking some stones together.
We can clearly see
how our ancestors
built a useful object.
But we're not really seeing
modern tools.
Oldulwan tools are so simple
that you'd be forgiven if you
just walked past one and you
didn't realise it was a tool.
Now about 1.8 million years ago,
things start to change.
Somebody, either Homo habilis
maybe or Homo erectus, starts
to build or make what we call
Acheulean or Acheulean tools.
Now, these are profoundly
different.
Acheulean tools, these are a
couple of replicas I have in
my hands, we start to see a
much more worked object,
symmetrical.
It's obviously made with
a model in mind.
It's not just a stone that's
picked up and made useful.
But it's a stone in which
somebody's image or idea of a
tool has been imposed.
We see the beginnings of design
and the ability to pass
on a model or a custom from
one group to another.
Perhaps the most amazing things
about Acheulean tools
is how long they last.
Some of these tools are
remarkably similar or
remarkably consistent across
a very long period of time.
With Acheulean tools, we see
the beginnings of design.
These two things are key,
regularity and the
imposition of design.
In one, we see our ancestors'
cognitive powers.
In the other, we see their
cognitive limitations.
That is, they were able to pass
on information with high
fidelity over generations.
But they weren't innovating
so much.
Creativity and innovation may
have taken bigger brains.
But remember, bigger alone
isn't necessarily better.
After all, Neanderthals, one
of our cousins that went
extinct about 30,000 years ago,
had bigger brands than
modern humans have, as
much as 20% larger.
In fact, over the last 80,000
years, our ancestors' brains
have actually become smaller.
Organisation of the brain
managed just as much as size,
as we mentioned in
the last topic.
As the brain grows in size,
certain parts of it grow
disproportionately, just
like our brain grows
disproportionately
to our body.
In particular, these midbrain
areas, the older automatic
functions, and the brain stem,
grow less that the cortex and
the extreme outside, the
neocortex of the brain.
The cortex and neocortex are
important, not only because
they allow us to pull together
different functions and
different ideas from different
parts of the brain, but
because the cortex and
neocortex allow us to
override, as we mentioned
in the last topic--
neocortex--
allow us to override some of the
things that are happening
under here, in the midbrain
and in the brain stem.
Overriding instincts may not
sound like a big deal.
But it creates a whole lot
of space for responding
creatively to stimuli.
For example, if every time
something made you upset, you
could only fight it or run from
it, well not only would
you be hard to live with, but
you'd have a hell time
learning things.
Every time you get frustrated,
you'd feel like running off or
attacking the person who
was teaching you.
The cortex and neocortex
don't make us human.
We share those traits, those
parts of the brain, with all
other mammals, more-so
with primates.
But the disproportionate growth
of the cortex and
neocortex means that the balance
of powers shift and
we're able to recruit these
parts of the brain into new
functions, into a new
structures, into new
behaviours.
Let's give you an example.
The visual parts of the brain
that respond to images that
appear on the retinas get
repurposed in the human brain
and used extensively in things
like visual imagination.
So you can use them for example
to envision what might
happen if you do an activity, to
test out and run scenarios
so hat your strategy gets more
sophisticated, or so that you
can imagine places
that don't exist,
events that never happened.
Our brains allow us to in a
sense run that visual area
top-down or backwards.
That is, not from the eyes to
the visual area to the parts
of our brains that are
conscious, but in reverse.
From consciousness, into the
visual areas, to create images
of the things we can imagine.
How did our brains our
brains get this way?
The key is changing the
developmental programmes of
our brains.
That is, you don't need new
parts to the brain.
You don't need necessarily
whole new genes.
What you need instead is
a slight change in the
trajectory of the way
our brains mature.
In most mammals, brain growth
is over relatively early in
their lives.
That is by the time they're
born, most of the building of
their brain is pretty
much done.
In humans, that's
not the case.
A human infant is immature for
a very long period of time.
We stay immature, which allows
our brain to grow faster,
longer, especially the last
parts of the brain that
developed, which are the cortex,
and the neocortex
especially.
In fact, if you compare a human
skull and a chimpanzees
skull, a human skull looks
a lot like an immature
chimpanzee skull.
If you were a chimp looking at
a human skull, you might be
like hey, where's
your fangs, man?
Why you haven't got
a snout yet?
When are you going to grow up?
From a chimpanzee's perspective,
a human preserves
infantile characteristics
into adulthood.
We call this prolongation, this
lengthening of immaturity
and the preservation of these
immature traits neoteny.
And we can see something similar
in domesticated dogs,
who seem to preserve
the traits of
immature wolves into adulthood.
Neoteny or the preservation of
immature traits isn't just
affecting human faces.
It's really affecting
our brains.
When we're born, we only
have 25% of our
eventual brain size.
In contrast, chimpanzees
have about 40%.
And macaques, who are pretty
brainy for mammals, have about
65% of their adult
brain capacity.
When we're born, we have about
the same encephalisation ratio
or brain size compared to
weight as chimpanzees.
But the difference is we
maintain that explosive,
immature growth rate
after we're born.
And so what we find is that
although humans and
chimpanzees track together
until birth,
afterwards things change.
This is especially important
because human brains are
maturing, not inside the womb,
where they're protected by the
mother's body from the
outside world.
Human brains are maturing at
this explosive immature rate
in the world, surrounded by
language, and tools, and
social interaction.
What it means is that when our
brains are most plastic, most
liable to be influenced by
things around us, well, we're
out in the world, learning.
So the next time somebody
tells you that you're
immature, well, you point out
to him, yup, that's kind of
what makes us human.
The next topic is the brain,
expensive tissue, or how we
pay for this thing.