leeminlinh_[âm nhạc]
Với chủ đề này, ta sẽ bàn tới lợi ích của việc sở hữu
một bộ não non nớt và việc sử dụng công cụ.
Nhìn vào công cụ của tổ tiên ta, ta có thể biết
bộ não của họ đã thay đổi thế nào.
Đến khoảng 1.8 triệu năm trước họ sở hữu
công cụ Olduwan hay công cụ đá cuội.
Chúng trông kiểu giống sỏi đá.
với một đầu gõ vào một
dụng cụ cầm tay cứng, đó là đập các miếng đá vào nhau.
Ta có thể rõ ràng thấy cách tổ tiên ta
tạo ra một đồ vật hữu ích.
Nhưng ta không thực sự thấy chúng giống công cụ hiện đại.
Công cụ Oldulwan đơn giản đến nỗi bạn có thể
đi qua nó mà không nhận ra đó là một công cụ.
Khoảng 1,8 triệu năm trước, mọi thứ bắt đầu thay đổi.
Người Homo habilis (người khéo léo) hoặc người Homo erectus (người đứng thẳng) bắt đầu
tạo ra công cụ Acheulean.
Giờ những công cụ này đã rất khác biệt.
Tôi đang cầm một cặp mô hình công cụ Acheulean
trong tay, ta bắt đầu tìm hiểu một đồ vật có công dụng hơn,
symmetrical.
Rõ ràng nó được làm từ một mô hình trong đầu.
Nó không chỉ là một viên đá được nhặt lên và biến thành có ích.
But it's a stone in which
somebody's image or idea of a
tool has been imposed.
Ta thấy những hình ảnh khởi đầu của thiết kế và khả năng truyền
một mô hình hoặc một phong tục từ nhóm này sang nhóm khác.
Có lẽ điều tuyệt vời nhất về công cụ Acheulean là
độ bền của chúng.
Vài công cụ như này vẫn còn như nguyên một cách đáng kinh ngạc
qua một thời gian rất dài.
Với công cụ Acheulean, ta thấy khởi đầu của thiết kế.
These two things are key,
regularity and the
imposition of design.
Một mặt ta thấy khả năng nhận thức của tổ tiên ta.
Mặt khác ta lại thấy hạn chế về mặt nhận thức của họ.
Đó là họ có thể truyền thông tin với
độ chính xác cao qua các thế hệ.
Nhưng họ lại chưa sáng tạo nhiều.
Sáng tạo và đổi mới cần bộ não lớn hơn.
Nhưng nhớ rằng, não chỉ lớn hơn thôi chưa hẳn là tốt hơn.
Vì là, người Neanderthal, một trong những anh em họ hàng của ta đã
tuyệt chủng khoảng 30 000 năm trước mà não họ lại to hơn
não chúng ta khoảng 20%.
Thực tế, qua 80 000 năm, não của tổ tiên ta
đã thực sự nhỏ đi.
Organisation of the brain
managed just as much as size,
as we mentioned in
the last topic.
As the brain grows in size,
certain parts of it grow
disproportionately, just
like our brain grows
disproportionately
to our body.
In particular, these midbrain
areas, the older automatic
functions, and the brain stem,
grow less that the cortex and
the extreme outside, the
neocortex of the brain.
The cortex and neocortex are
important, not only because
they allow us to pull together
different functions and
different ideas from different
parts of the brain, but
because the cortex and
neocortex allow us to
override, as we mentioned
in the last topic--
neocortex--
allow us to override some of the
things that are happening
under here, in the midbrain
and in the brain stem.
Overriding instincts may not
sound like a big deal.
But it creates a whole lot
of space for responding
creatively to stimuli.
For example, if every time
something made you upset, you
could only fight it or run from
it, well not only would
you be hard to live with, but
you'd have a hell time
learning things.
Every time you get frustrated,
you'd feel like running off or
attacking the person who
was teaching you.
The cortex and neocortex
don't make us human.
We share those traits, those
parts of the brain, with all
other mammals, more-so
with primates.
But the disproportionate growth
of the cortex and
neocortex means that the balance
of powers shift and
we're able to recruit these
parts of the brain into new
functions, into a new
structures, into new
behaviours.
Let's give you an example.
The visual parts of the brain
that respond to images that
appear on the retinas get
repurposed in the human brain
and used extensively in things
like visual imagination.
So you can use them for example
to envision what might
happen if you do an activity, to
test out and run scenarios
so hat your strategy gets more
sophisticated, or so that you
can imagine places
that don't exist,
events that never happened.
Our brains allow us to in a
sense run that visual area
top-down or backwards.
That is, not from the eyes to
the visual area to the parts
of our brains that are
conscious, but in reverse.
From consciousness, into the
visual areas, to create images
of the things we can imagine.
How did our brains our
brains get this way?
The key is changing the
developmental programmes of
our brains.
That is, you don't need new
parts to the brain.
You don't need necessarily
whole new genes.
What you need instead is
a slight change in the
trajectory of the way
our brains mature.
In most mammals, brain growth
is over relatively early in
their lives.
That is by the time they're
born, most of the building of
their brain is pretty
much done.
In humans, that's
not the case.
A human infant is immature for
a very long period of time.
We stay immature, which allows
our brain to grow faster,
longer, especially the last
parts of the brain that
developed, which are the cortex,
and the neocortex
especially.
In fact, if you compare a human
skull and a chimpanzees
skull, a human skull looks
a lot like an immature
chimpanzee skull.
If you were a chimp looking at
a human skull, you might be
like hey, where's
your fangs, man?
Why you haven't got
a snout yet?
When are you going to grow up?
From a chimpanzee's perspective,
a human preserves
infantile characteristics
into adulthood.
We call this prolongation, this
lengthening of immaturity
and the preservation of these
immature traits neoteny.
And we can see something similar
in domesticated dogs,
who seem to preserve
the traits of
immature wolves into adulthood.
Neoteny or the preservation of
immature traits isn't just
affecting human faces.
It's really affecting
our brains.
When we're born, we only
have 25% of our
eventual brain size.
In contrast, chimpanzees
have about 40%.
And macaques, who are pretty
brainy for mammals, have about
65% of their adult
brain capacity.
When we're born, we have about
the same encephalisation ratio
or brain size compared to
weight as chimpanzees.
But the difference is we
maintain that explosive,
immature growth rate
after we're born.
And so what we find is that
although humans and
chimpanzees track together
until birth,
afterwards things change.
This is especially important
because human brains are
maturing, not inside the womb,
where they're protected by the
mother's body from the
outside world.
Human brains are maturing at
this explosive immature rate
in the world, surrounded by
language, and tools, and
social interaction.
Điều đó có nghĩa là khi não ta non nớt nhất,
dễ chịu ảnh hưởng bởi những thứ quanh ta nhất, thì ta
out in the world, learning.
Vậy nếu lần sau có ai bảo bạn là
chưa trưởng thành thì hãy chỉ cho họ biết đó là điều
tạo ra con người.
Chủ đề tiếp theo là bộ não, một mô đắt giá hay cách ta
có được nó.