https://youtu.be/6cYCWkPrb-I
Trong suốt thế kỷ 20, Tokyo đã mở rộng theo rất nhiều hướng khác khác nhau.
Từ thời kì tiền chiến tranh, các khu ngoại ô mới được phát triển
và tăng về số lượng ở khu vực phía Tây và Nam thành phố
Sau chiến tranh, những tòa nhà cao tầng mới được xây dựng ở khu kinh doanh phía Nam
And after the 1980s, bay area, waterfront area
became the huge redevelopment area in Tokyo.
So to West or downtown South and to East, to the Tokyo Bay,
all of these directions was the process--
the process of the redevelopment process was
expanded all of these different directions.
And also, underground spaces were developed or redeveloped
in postwar era.
Vậy là Tokyo đã mở rộng trong các hướng khác nhau cả về mặt thể chất lẫn tinh thần
throughout postwar era.
But finally, there's another dimension in which the expansion of Tokyo
was performed.
It was media sphere, or the world of our imagination.
In television, or in film, or in photograph, or in many other media,
Tokyo was featured and documented and emerging
in very different way from these real redevelopment process.
So first, we are going to focus on TV commercial.
There are many very interesting and stimulating television commercials
throughout postwar era focusing on Tokyo.
Roughly speaking, the commercial, TV commercial in the 1950 and 1960s
symbolized Tokyo as the stage of modernism.
We will see the television commercial which focused on this dimension.
This commercial film especially emphasized
Tokyo as the symbolic stage on which the new modern style can
be expressed and realized.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In the television commercials in the 1950s and 1960s,
Tokyo was featured as the stage of the realization of modern style.
Modern lifestyle was dreamy image for ordinary people.
And all or many television commercial featured these kinds
of dreamy image of modern lifestyles.
And Tokyo was the center and at the same time
a stage of these realization-- of these realization of modern lifestyles.
But after the late 1970s, there appeared very different kind
of the television commercials which no longer featured Tokyo
as the real stage of modernism.
These new television commercial virtualized Tokyo itself.
Now, Tokyo became a kind of the virtual stage
of the image of new post-modernism.
Or in other words, Tokyo became the stage
of the future, unrealistic futuristic stage of consumer life.
We are going to see two different type of television commercial
which featured Tokyo but very different way from the television
commercial, which we already watched.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In the first television commercial, YMO, Yellow Magic Orchestra,
was a very popular techno music group in those days,
consists of Haruomi Hosono, Yukihiro Takahashi, and Ryuichi Sakamoto.
All of these musicians seemed very popular and influential
in progressive music in the world.
And this commercial film, they represented very post-modernistic image
of Tokyo.
All the images or all the scenes of Tokyo
were very much fragmented and virtualized.
For example, Tokyo Tower is real tower still exists,
but in this image of this film, Tokyo Tower was already virtualized,
like something different from the physical tower, which exists in Tokyo.
Và ngay cả khi họ mặc đồ như những nhà doanh nhân, và sau họ
they use the photographic image of Imperial Palace.
But the image is quite fictional and quite unrealistic.
So all the image of Imperial Palace or Tokyo Tower which
appear in this commercial are very much unrealistic.
On the other hand, second television commercial,
the scene was completely fragmented and connected.
The expression was quite post-modernistic.
On the one hand, the Western Shinjuku business
skyscraper, but on the other hand, the military weapon.
An encounter between these different items was quite fictional, unrealistic.
Vậy là trong tất cả các quảng cáo trên tivi những năm 1980
Tokyo was already very much virtualized in post-modern way.
I can show the transformation of Tokyo in this sense because until the 1960s,
Tokyo had been the stage of modernity.
Many different kinds of modern style was performed and staged in Tokyo.
Especially in Ginza and some of the other places.
But after the 1980s, Tokyo itself, or many image of the spaces in the city
were fragmented and virtualized, especially by the effect of media.
Chúng ta đã nói về nhiều về Tokyo hậu chiến tranh cho đến hiện nay
Nhưng sau chiến tranh, Tokyo đã thay dổi, đặc biệt là sau những năm 80
from the real stage to the virtual stage.