https://youtu.be/yR2feLYB8do
Hi.
So in our last topic, we
just touched on the basic HR
functions-- what those
core functions are.
And in this topic,
we'll be briefly looking
through the history of
how that function has
changed over the last century.
And the best way to
really explain that,
to go through that, is to
look at the four stages
that HR has developed
over the last century.
And you'll notice
there's a common theme,
and you'll see the direction
of where we're moving.
So really the first three stages
were quite the dominant stages
and these really what
were shaped and developed
the way that HR has
grown over time.
We'll also look
at the last stage,
which is more of
an emerging area.
Really hasn't
settled quite in yet.
But this is really where HR
is moving to in the future.
And as we go through
each stage, you'll
also find the
really common theme
there, it's really interesting,
is that we started off
with our first stage,
which is really concerned
about the needs of
the organization.
And as we move
through and progressed
to the fourth and
current stage, we
find that now the focus is more
on the needs of the people.
So over time,
research has really
shown us that if we consider
the needs of employees
and we meet those needs,
they'll in turn meet
the needs of the
organization, and that
will have the ultimate
impact on the organization's
productivity.
Let's look at the first stage.
So the first stage was really
took us up to the 1940s.
It was more so concerned
with just the welfare
and administration of staff.
So it was really at
a time in Australia
where it was mainly primary
production and manufacturing
in those days.
Owners of these factories were
really like father figures.
They were the ones responsible
for the hiring and firing
of staff.
And that was really the
type of relationship
that existed at that time.
And really, if you
get into stage one,
you'll find that
there weren't really
many people at that
time that took,
or many organizations that took,
a structured approach to HR.
It was really just
filling in a needs
and maintaining that
workforce to do whatever
the core businesses
of that organization.
As we progress to
stage two, we started
to see that shift
to the slightly more
strategic approach
to administering HR.
and this took us up
to the mid-1970s.
And you'll find that really
in this period of time
organizations were starting
to appoint personnel managers,
to deal with the day to
day needs of employees.
They started to appoint
industrial relations
personnel managers to deal with
issues that they were having
at the time with
unions and so on.
And you started to see that
a little bit more structure,
or more structured
approach, to HR.
There wasn't really
many organizations
at that point that had reached
the stage where they actually
had formal policies and
procedures and so on.
But leading the way at the
time, the David Jones department
store was one of the
first to really start
establishing formal employee
policies and procedures.
So they were quite
innovative at that time.
And if we think about
the type of industries
and how HR has impacted the
way that we manage people,
again you'll start
to see that pattern,
that pattern that the
needs of the employees
are the needs that we are
pushing closer towards,
and we're realizing have a
direct link on productivity.
Let's have a look
at the third stage.
So this is taking us up to
the 2000s, the early 2000s.
And here we really start
seeing a more concrete,
scientific approach
in application
of HR in organizations.
This is where we started
looking at strategy.
So we started looking at,
how do we plan for it?
How do we plan for the
organization's future
through our staff?
We look at things like
workforce planning,
and we started to look at things
like organizational change
and managing that change.
And again it was focused
on the employees,
more structured,
more formalized.
And that's where we get this
concept of strategic HRM.
And if we look at the
fourth stage, which
is really where we're at now.
This is the emerging stage.
We are really thinking about
sustainable HR management.
And what does that really mean?
What's sustainable HR?
It's really looking
at an approach
to HR that's concerned with the
future and future generations,
and how we can try and
effectively minimize
the negative impacts
that organizations
may have on their staff.
Also, we might look at
the negative impacts
that they may have on the
environment, on the communities
in which those
organizations exist amongst,
and really, how we can improve
and create a positive future
by minimizing the
negative impacts of HR
and maximizing the
potential to really build
on that human capital.
And we can see that if we
take care of our staff,
our productivity improves.
And we'll look a
little bit further
in the next topic about HR
practitioners and what they do.
And then we can see their role,
and how their role has also
changed through those
four stages over time.