https://youtu.be/6SUmhB4hGFk
Hi, Welcome back.
In our last topic, we
looked at a brief overview
of the four stages
of development of HR.
And in the same way HR
personnel or HR roles
have also evolved in
a similar fashion.
So we'll look at what
is it that HR people do.
And the role is quite
varied and there are so
many different things you
can do if you work in HR.
So we'll be looking at really
what that role involves.
We'll be looking at
some of the reasons
why people decide to
start a career in HR.
We'll also be looking at
different options that
may be available to you if
you're interested in entering
a career in HR and
really what avenues
are available to you
to educate yourself.
And as we mentioned
in previous topics,
HR is really a rapidly
changing and evolving area.
And more so than in
many other industries
it's so important
and so critical
that you're always really
on top of what's changing.
And so we'll also look at
professional development
as really a tool to help any
HR professional to maintain
current knowledge in an
industry of constant change.
And before we really
get into that we'll
have a look at some broad areas
of what the HR role can involve
and can include.
If we look at, firstly,
the HR function.
So there are various
roles that are just
about administering
the HR function.
And what we mean
by that is people
who are involved in recruitment.
People who are involved in pay.
People who are
involved in maintaining
work health and
safety compliance.
So these are generic
HR functions.
So there's a whole
variety of roles.
Just around those
specific functions.
Health and safety in
particular in Australia,
as with many other
countries, has
become quite a specialized
area in itself.
And there are now many
specialized HR roles
that are really just focused
on ensuring the health
and safety of
employees and ensuring
that the organization is
maintaining compliance
with the legislation.
We'll also look at
workforce planning.
So There's so many roles
just focused around
how we try and make sure that
our organization is prepared
from a human perspective or from
human resources perspective,
that we're prepared
for the next stage.
So as some of our
senior managers
move on and retire and so
on, do we have someone ready?
Do we have someone else
ready who's been trained
who is ready to jump
into that next stage.
And that's part of what
work force planning is about
and there are a whole
variety of roles
that are just focused on that.
And it really does
link up with what
we were saying in the
previous topic about how
we're more in a
stage of strategy
and HR really is about strategy.
And that's why there's
so many HR planning
roles at the moment.
We also have training
and development.
So again that's also
in line with the shift
and the change in
attitudes to HR.
Many organizations
really invest heavily
in training their staff,
in developing their staff.
And to ensure that they're
not just able to do their job,
because they've been
given adequate training,
but also to develop them
as people and their skills
and to help them develop
their own careers.
And it really
always comes back to
if we take care of our staff,
They'll take care of us
and that always
affects the bottom line
and improves our productivity.
So there's some
of the broad areas
of where you may find
different types of HR roles.
But again it's become
such a specialized area.
And it's constantly
changing and there's
a whole variety of
different things
you can do that fit
within this area.
The very interesting
thing is, is
when you look at
some of the research
to why people enter
a career into HR,
it's quite surprising
that the key reason why
they enter into that career
is really a humanistic reason.
So in a recent survey
of HR practitioners,
they found that 77% actually
entered into the field
simply to help other
people grow and develop.
And so it's a great and
rewarding career in that sense
because you can really have
an impact on other people's
lives and their development.
So at this point, you
might be thinking, yeah,
I might be interested
in a career in HR.
So what are some of
your options if you
want to start looking at
training or an education in HR.
There are really two pathways.
So you can either go down
the vocational education
and training pathway.
Or you go down the
higher education pathway,
which is universities.
Although there's really quite
a bit of a difference in both.
If you're looking
at qualifications
such as a certificate for
human resource management
or a diploma in human
resource management,
and to that
vocational education,
and training pathway,
it's really about skills.
So these qualifications
designed to really give you
the skills to do tasks within
various job roles in HR.
So for example, a
certificate four
will allow you or
provide you the skills
to undertake tasks that a
HR officer would undertake
or that a recruitment
officer would undertake.
And so it's really about skills.
Whereas when we go to
university or higher education,
it's more so about why
do we do these things.
VET tells us how to
do them, higher ed
tells us why we do them.
And so if you go into a
bachelor of business in HR
you really look at the strategy
behind why we do these things.
If you take that
step further and you
go into postgraduate
qualification in HR
you're really looking at,
well how can we change the way
we do these things.
And so you really have
quite a few options.
In module three
will also be looking
at training and
development in more detail.
So if you're interested, you'll
get a better understanding
in module three of why
we do these things.
So in our next topic, we'll be
looking at the HR implications
around email and internet
use in organization.
So stay tuned.