https://youtu.be/HxBhIlaB6Z8
Hi.
Welcome to topic four.
In this topic, we'll be
looking at email and internet
usage in an
organization, and what
the HR implications are of that.
Really since the mid-'90s,
there's been a huge impact
on the way we manage people
because of things like
the internet.
Internet and email are
obviously a critical part
of most organizations
and most job roles.
So we'll be looking at really
how the internet and how email
and how having access
to the internet
has really created a whole
set of new challenges
and new problems
for organizations.
It's great to have access
to all this information,
but the challenges
that come with that
also need to be managed.
And that's why, further
on in this topic,
we'll be looking at why and
how we need to make sure
that we have policies and
procedures in place to monitor
and maintain a good relationship
with the internet [INAUDIBLE]
for our staff.
Some of the key
legal issues we need
to consider when dealing with
the internet and email usage
really align to three
different points
or three different areas.
One, it's about our
IT infrastructure
and how we protect it.
So this is things like ensuring
that our systems are secure
and we don't have viruses being
contracted through emails,
or whatever.
The second area is
confidentiality.
So really we need to
consider the legal risks
of valuable
corporate information
and how that may be distributed
so easily through things
like email or even
through social networks.
And that's a really
critical legal aspect,
because we need to
ensure the security
of that kind of
valuable information.
The third area is
really about monitoring
staff's usage of the
internet and other aspects,
such as email and social media.
The reality is, although
they may have access
to a huge number of resources
that may better enable them
to do their job,
they also have access
to a lot of things that
are really time wasters.
And we'll be looking
at some of those
in more detail
throughout this topic.
So one of the
challenges that we have
with trying to monitor
internet usage in organizations
is people's access to things
like Facebook, shopping
websites, social
networking sites,
and even things like YouTube.
Although many organizations
have blocked it,
it's still often available.
And really how do we manage and
monitor that type of activity
and stop it from
affecting productivity.
Some of the other issues
are also around email.
And, in fact, email seems
to have greater challenges,
even more so than
internet usage,
because it has such an impact
in the way that we communicate.
So we can look at
some of the ways
that email can really
also be a big time waster.
And a recent survey showed
that 10% of all of our emails
that we receive at work are
completely unsolicited, so
essentially spam.
And just even those
minor challenges on a day
are really ways that
minimize our productivity
in the workplace.
But essentially, email can
become a real challenge,
because it's become a
primary way of communicating
between each other
in an organization.
So I may have someone sitting
one meter away from me.
I don't get up or I don't call
them, I send them an email.
And the potential
for misunderstanding
in that platform
of communication
or that form of communication
is just so high.
I'll give you an example.
In one organization
that I worked for,
there was an email
trail that went on
for approximately 25 emails.
And it was essentially over an
expense claim for biscuits--
for biscuits for
the office kitchen,
because they had guests.
The CEO of the
organization at the time
was actually included
in these emails.
So you can imagine
how many people
were involved in this back and
forth of emails about biscuits,
including the CEO, and how
much time that would've
wasted for all involved with
no real outcome and no impact
on productivity.
So we can see the
potential for email
to really be a big time waster.
The other issue with email
is it's not really as secure
as many of us think it is.
Email can be bugged.
Email can be tracked.
Email's very much
easily traceable,
as is a lot of your activity on
the internet, in the same way.
So this assumption that what
we say in an email is secure
is really incorrect.
The other problem with
email is, in many cases,
things we may not actually
say to someone face-to-face,
we find very
comfortable in an email.
And this is where, often, again,
other interpersonal problems
can be created in the
organization because
of the use of email.
This may potentially be a
good discussion point for you
in the discussion forum.
Think of circumstances
or times when
you may have emailed
someone about something
that you probably wouldn't have
said to them to their face.
And maybe just discuss
your experience
and what the challenges were
with that and potentially
how you may have overcome them.
So in looking at some of
the challenges and issues
with email and internet
use in organizations,
it really brings
home why we need
to have policies and procedures
to really manage these things.
And the two key
issues we're looking
at in any organizational policy
relating to internet usage
is really how we
protect the organization
from the business
and legal risks
that we discussed
earlier and also how
we limit the spread of
time wasting emails.
And they're really
the two key areas
we need to ensure are included
in an internet usage policy.
In our next topic, we'll be
looking at an emerging area--
workplace stress.
In many cases,
time wasting emails
could've been the source
of the workplace stress.
But we'll look at that shortly.