https://youtu.be/nf-x_JGHMH4
Hello, and welcome to CRIME101x, The Psychology of Criminal Justice. I’m Blake McKimmie,
and this is Mark Horswill and Barbara Masser. And we’re all academics at The University
of Queensland in Australia.
Now we don&#39;t want to spend a long time introducing the course, we&#39;d like to just jump straight
into it because there&#39;s lots we want to tell you about the psychology of criminal justice.
There are, however, a few things that we need to cover before we get started.
In a minute, Barbara will tell you a bit about the topics we’ll be covering, and Mark will
say a few words about research and the scientific method. In this course, we’ll be making
numerous claims about how things do and don&#39;t work, and these claims are based on the scientific
literature. Sometimes they might seem to be quite counter-intuitive. Mark will tell you
why we use the scientific method as a more reliable way of finding out how things work.
Let me first say a few things about assessment in this course. You will notice that we make
use of polls as well as a special type of quiz based on the principles of confidence-based
assessment. The idea with this is that we not only ask you to say what you think is
the correct answer, we will also get you to rate how confident you are in this answer.
By giving you immediate feedback about whether you were actually correct or not, we hope
to help you identify any confidently held, but incorrect, knowledge. This feedback should
help you better gauge the quality of your knowledge of the course content, and discourage
lucky guessing in quizzes.
Research suggests that people learn more effectively with this type of quiz, and we&#39;re hoping it
will help challenge some of the misconceptions that people have about the criminal justice system.
So why did we create this course? Well the three of us have been teaching courses related
to the psychology of criminal justice for well over a decade. We hoped to achieve two
things in creating this course.
The first was to reach out to all those people who were interested in learning about this
area who otherwise wouldn&#39;t have been in a position to take our course. We think this
is not only a very interesting area of study, but it&#39;s one that also has some really
important real world consequences.
The second was to completely overhaul how we taught our on campus course. This has been
a unique opportunity to devote a large amount of time and resources to rethinking how we taught
our on campus course. What you will see in the online version of this course is the
core of what we plan for the on campus course.
So now it&#39;s time to hand you over to Mark and Barbara, and I’ll see you in the weekly videos!