This is Peter.
He is a junior manager in the ACME organisation.
There has been much excitement among senior managers
since ACME secured a government contract three weeks ago.
The contract requires ACME to develop and implement
a new system to help school leavers
and young adults find employment in their community.
The current landscape consists of a number
of different community service providers
who have each implemented their own initiatives and systems
that seek to help young people transition from school
and into the workplace.
As these initiatives have not been coordinated, none of them
have been particularly successful.
It is the intention of the government to create improved
alignment by developing a centralised system that can be
used by community organisations.
It is expected that by the close of the projects in 12 months
time, employment of young people between the ages of 18 and 22
will increase by 40%.
If the system implementation is successful,
it will be used as a model in other similar projects
to help young people in other communities.
Peter is surprised when his boss taps him on the shoulder,
advising him that he has been nominated to lead this project.
Peter never thought of himself as a project manager,
and he was not included in the initial discussions
around the project.
Moreover, he was concerned that he still
had a full-time workload in his current position to deal with.
Peter has very little experience in working with young people
and community organisations.
Given the nature of the particular project,
he will be required to work closely with these two
groups together with secondary school teachers, parents,
and school principals.
The government grant is substantial,
and Peter has to ensure that the funds are adequately
deployed and managed.
He needs to ensure that the system enables community
organisations to create viable employment opportunities
for young people.
The development and implementation of the system
will require rigorous stakeholder engagement
and management at all levels throughout the process.
Peter has been advised by his more experienced colleagues
that he will need to carefully track system implementation
progress.
Sufficient time will need to be invested into the planning
activity, as Peter still needs to determine what
needs to be done by who, when, and how
to ensure the successful implementation
of the system and a positive outcome for young people.