Trong quá trình lên kế hoạch dự án,
các công tác ban đầu cần cân nhắc cẩn thận,
Đây là giai đoạn bạn thực sự áp dụng
không chỉ khả năng tư duy
mà còn cần kĩ năng cá nhân, kĩ năng làm việc,
để hiểu sâu hơn
nhận thức chi tiết hơn
về cách bạn định triển khai dự án.
Việc lên kế hoạch thực hiện theo nhiều cách.
Theo thời gian biểu.
Theo ngân sách.
Theo mô tả công việc.
Nếu chúng ta chỉ tập trung vào quy mô dự án,
thể hiện dưới hình thức chia nhỏ khối lượng công việc,
trong giai đoạn lên kế hoạch,
bạn sẽ có định nghĩa rõ ràng,
to be decomposed into workable elements-- elements that
can be executed and can be properly resourced.
And you time phase that, meaning that the work-- once it's
allocated into executable chunks is also
time phased to a schedule.
The other dimension to that is the resourcing,
ensuring that you have the right people to do the task,
and that that task is properly scoped so when
the resources are allocated, they're ready to go,
and they're set up for success right from the start.
That is very key for a project manager.
As it is with any activity, in any work or personal
endeavour-- is you want to set up people for success.
One thing I need to emphasise about planning
is a project plan, which sounds like it's obvious.
In my experience, there have been
projects where they have been poorly planned
and there's nothing documented.
Or if there is something documented, that it is not
an executable document.
So the project management plan is key to execution.
Some of the other aspects in the project management
plan-- it defines for all stakeholders,
and it's a point of reference as to what the project is about,
in terms of the mission, the vision
of the project, the objectives.
How the project is going to be executed,
the processes and procedures that will be applied.
How the project will be scheduled.
What is the budget.
Who are the resource allocations,
and how is the project going to be monitored and controlled,
which is like a feedback mechanism.