ROB LORENZUTTI: During project planning,
it takes the initiation to the next level of maturity.
And this is where you actually apply not only the sum
of your intellectual skills, but you also
draw on your personal skills, and working skills, and trying
to understand or better understand,
and to articulate in a more detailed way on how you intend
to execute the project.
The planning is manifested in different ways.
There's a schedule.
There's a budget.
There's the description of the work.
If we just focus on the scope, which
is articulated in the form of a work breakdown
structure-- in the planning stage,
you get clear definition of how the work is
to be decomposed into workable elements-- elements that
can be executed and can be properly resourced.
And you time phase that, meaning that the work-- once it's
allocated into executable chunks is also
time phased to a schedule.
The other dimension to that is the resourcing,
ensuring that you have the right people to do the task,
and that that task is properly scoped so when
the resources are allocated, they're ready to go,
and they're set up for success right from the start.
That is very key for a project manager.
As it is with any activity, in any work or personal
endeavour-- is you want to set up people for success.
One thing I need to emphasise about planning
is a project plan, which sounds like it's obvious.
In my experience, there have been
projects where they have been poorly planned
and there's nothing documented.
Or if there is something documented, that it is not
an executable document.
So the project management plan is key to execution.
Some of the other aspects in the project management
plan-- it defines for all stakeholders,
and it's a point of reference as to what the project is about,
in terms of the mission, the vision
of the project, the objectives.
How the project is going to be executed,
the processes and procedures that will be applied.
How the project will be scheduled.
What is the budget.
Who are the resource allocations,
and how is the project going to be monitored and controlled,
which is like a feedback mechanism.