JOHN SING: Ước định sự tiến triển của dự án của bạn
trong suốt giai đoạn thực thi là một phần
trách nhiệm của bạn trong vai trò là một nhà quản lý dự án
Tuy nhiên, điều này thường là phần bị quên lãng
trong việc quản lý dự án
Đối với những dự án nhỏ và đơn giản, điều này có thể thực hiện khá dễ dàng
Đặc biệt khi bạn có liên quan mật thiết
đến dự án
Ví dụ như, chúng ta hãy xem xét sự án về đám cưới của Anne
tương đối dễ để Anne có thể giám sát và đánh giá mức độ
tiến triển công việc với các bên có liên quan
trong việc hoàn tất chuẩn bị cho hôn lễ
Tuy nhiên, đối với những dự án lớn hơn, việc ước định tiến độ công việc
sẽ nhiều thử thách hơn  và có thể yêu cầu một phương pháp đã được thỏa thuận
Bạn làm thế nào để ước lượng mức độ thành công của một dự án?
Cách ước lượng và báo cáo về tiến độ dự án
bao gồm việc quyết định thông tin dự án và dữ liệu nào
cần được thu thập, và những thông tin trên nên được
phân tích và báo cáo theo cách nào.
những thông tin thu thập được thường sẽ
dựa trên những thứ đã được chọn làm mục tiêu quan trọng
để đo lường.
Ví dụ, bạn sẽ ghi nhớ lượng thời gian dành cho các hoạt động,
cách sử dụng các nguồn lực, các chi phí thực tế
nhờ đó có thể đem so sánh với lượng thời gian, nguồn lực
và ngân quỹ đã dự tính trước.
There is often a focus on cost and schedule.
And therefore, as a project manager,
you may need answers to the following questions.
What is the current schedule and cost status for your project?
How much will it cost to complete the project?
And when will the project be completed?
If there are schedule slippages and/or cost overruns,
what will be the forecast at completion?
Are there potential problems that need to be addressed?
The first step in answering those questions
would be to take your work breakdown structure information
and planned schedule, and then develop a base line plan.
Simply put, this is a plan that defines
what the project manager hopes the project will look like.
It includes cost, time and goal factors
using reasonable estimates.
The base line plan provides guidance
in all stages of the project.
Some call it a road map to our project success.
As information is collected it can then
be compared with this base line plan.
Because plans seldom eventuate as expected,
it becomes important to understand and investigate
any differences from the plan, and then decide
if any action is necessary.
The timing of this work is important
as there needs to be sufficient time
to allow for early detection of any inconsistencies
and correction of any causes.
If differences from the base line plan are significant,
correction action would be required in order
to bring the project back in line
with the original or revised plan.
In some cases, project scope may have
changed, which will result in a change in the base line plan.
Measuring and reporting progress is important
but requires you, the project manager,
to think through what it is you are going to measure,
the information required, and your ability
to access that information.