Chào Vsauce. Michael đây.
Khi nào bạn sẽ chết? Tôi không nói là chính bạn,
tôi đang nói đến tất cả các bạn-những người xem vsauce bình thường.
Dựa trên thống kê tuổi của Tổ Chức Sức Khỏe Thế Giới và thống kê của người xem vsauce trên Youtube,
ta có thể tính ra rằng
ngày trung bình mà tất cả những ai trên 15 tuổi
đang xem video này vào lúc này
sẽ chết lúc 8:42 sáng, ngày 28 tháng 11, 2059.
Mode la 2073.
Tệ hại thay, khoảng 340
trong những người đang xem video này trong tuần này sẽ không còn ở đây vào năm tới.
Những số liệu này là trung bình nhưng thú vị thay,
những người bình thường không cho rằng họ trung bình.
Những nghiên cứu đồng nhất cho thấy
một người bình thường cho rằng họ sẽ sống lâu hơn và khỏe mạnh hơn
trung bình. Ta đánh giá quá cao
khả năng những điều tồi tệ sẽ xảy ra với người khác và đánh giá thấp
tỉ lệ những điều đấy sẽ xảy ra với ta. Đó là tâm lý bình thường,
nhưng ta đánh giá rủi ro sai trong những cách rất thú vị.
K.C. Cole chỉ ra rằng ta phản ứng nhiều hơn với những sự đe dọa mang tính cá nhân,
hiếm có, thất thường, và kịch tính
so với những sự đe dọa có khả năng xảy ra cao hơn.
Tôi rất thích một ví dụ của cô ấy- hãy tưởng tượng một thế giới mà thuốc lá
là vô hại, nhưng một gói thuốc lá
trong 18750 gói chứa một điếu thuốc lá
làm từ thuốc nổ, và sẽ nổ khi được châm lửa,
nổ tung đầu người hút.
Thế giới sẽ ngập tràn những cái chết rất ồn ào
và hỗn độn mỗi ngày
nhưng trong cái vũ trụ tưởng tượng ấy, số người chết hàng ngày bằng với số người chết
vì thuốc lá
ở thực tại.
Kết quả sẽ gây sửng sốt hơn, tức thời hơn, và có khả năng gây ảnh hưởng đến hành động của ta hơn.
.
Tháng trước, tôi mà một vài Youtuber đã khác gặp
Tổng Thống Obama để nói về những quyết định
mà người Mỹ đưa ra để bảo vệ bản thân khỏi cái giá phải trả để khỏe mạnh.
Chỉ có khối u đo lường rủi ro mới có thể bì được với vấn đề về sức khỏe
đang xảy ra
trong suy nghĩ của ta.
Nào ta dùng nhieu sự thiên vị và đường tắt để tính toán xác suất
hơn để có thể nhồi vào một video được, nhưng một ví dụ điển hình
la availability heuristic. Ta có khuynh hướng suy nghĩ rằng một chuyện sẽ có khả năng xảy ra cao hơn
vì nó đã xảy ra gần đây hoặc là có nhiều ví dụ của việc đó xảy ra
trong trí nhớ ta, không phải vì nó thật sự có tỉ lệ xảy ra cao hơn.
Ta cũng phóng đại rủi ro ta không có kiểm soát
mặc dù gan dạ trước rủi ro tương đương
nhưng kiểm soát được. Nghiên cứu nổi tiếng vào năm 1969 của Chianti Stars về rủi ro
cho thấy mọi người chấp nhận rủi ro gấp 1000 lần
nếu họ có thể kiểm soát nó, ví dụ, lái xe so với rủi ro
không kiểm soát được, như, thảm họa hạt nhân.
Giờ ta sẽ nói về Abraham Wald.
Only so much extra armour can be added to
an airplane before it becomes too heavy to fly.
Now, during World War 2 the US military
noticed the planes returning
from enemy territory were usually damage
around the wings,
the body and the tail gunners.
So, they put more armour
on those areas. But it didn't make a
difference. The same number of planes
continued to be lost. So the military hired Wald
for his mathematical super powers.
He told them to put what little
armour they could on the parts of the planes that
weren't being hit. Why?
Well, because returning planes were survivors.
They took damage in areas where a plane
can take damage
and survive. Damage to other areas
caused the plane to
not return.
Wald was protecting them against
survivorship bias - only paying attention
to successes. A similar phenomenon is
partly responsible for why music
feels like it was just better back in
the day than it is now.
Is that really true or are we just remembering
the good stuff? Wald's work saved
thousands of lives and made flying safer
for many more. Tragically, a few years
later Wald and his wife
died in an airplane crash. You can't
predict how and when you will die, it's not that easy.
But a few risk scoring systems have been created
to make the discussion and comparison of
hazardous behaviors
clearer. The micromort was conceived by
Ronald A. Howard and is an amount of risk
equal to a one in 1,000,000 probability
of dying. John Green discussed Micromorts
in a fantastic mental floss video you
should watch, if you haven't already.
He points out that a single skydive
temporarily increases your
death risk by seven micromorts - a seven
in 1,000,000 chance of dying. That's the same
as smoking 5 cigarettes. It's been
estimated that you gain one micromort
for every half litre of wine you drink.
Every year you spend drinking Miami tap water, every 1,000 miles you fly in a jet plane,
every 230 miles you travel by car, every
20 miles you travel by bicycle
and every 6 miles you travel by motorcycle
or canoe. There is a happier
unit of risk - the microlife. Proposed by
David Spiegelhalter and Alejandro Leiva,
a microlife is gained by doing helpful
things. In small quantities their benefits are roughly
linear and one microlife is the equivalent of
30 extra minutes of life.
Twenty minutes of moderate exercise
gives you two more microlives.
Two hours of sedentary behavior
-1 microlives. Plenty of
non-scientific websites exist that allow
you to calculate when you will die
based on your life expectancy and habits.
PokeMyBirthday.com is the kind of goofy site
that takes a nonetheless interesting look
at not your death,
but your birth. Enter your birthday and
see when you were conceived,
when your mother probably first realized
she was pregnant with you
and the dates your parents created or
moved into position the two cells
that eventually became the thirty trillion cells
that are now watching this video. Every single person
who ever died, died right here on planet Earth.
Except for three.
The crew of Soyuz 11.
On June 30th, 1979, their cabin depressurized,
while returning to Earth, before they
crossed the agreed-upon boundary between
Earth and outer space. Far from
any populated area, a three-sided metallic columns
sits where they're craft landed in Kazakhstan.
It's a remote memorial to humankind's
remotest deaths. We haven't
all died here on Earth, but so far we have all been born
here. Thanks for being here.
Stay safe, and as always,
thanks for watching.