https://youtu.be/jC2JQtztWk0
STELLA BACHTIS: It is clear to see
that project management encompasses many areas
and industries.
Perhaps you have realised that you, in fact,
are a project manager in an activity you are already
involved in.
Over the next six weeks, we will be
working through the key areas of project management.
To illustrate and help you apply skills of project management,
we will be referring to and following three scenarios.
We'll use these scenarios to take you
through each phase of the project life cycle.
Our first scenario is based on Peter,
who was given an office-based project to manage
without having any previous knowledge or experience
in project management.
The second scenario is based on Janet, who is completing a DIY
project in her new home.
And the third scenario is based on an events planner called
Anne.
She runs a service-based business,
but all of her services require the same level of skills
and planning and execution.
You may see some similarities here
to situations you have been in or are now involved in.
As we work through the next few weeks,
we'll learn how each person can apply a project management
framework to deliver their individual projects
successfully.