https://youtu.be/zZriVGvk6_A
ANTHONY JOSEPH: So what is Apache Spark?
Apache Spark is all about scalable, efficient analysis
of Big Data.
In this lecture, we'll talk about the analysis and Big Data
parts of that statement.
In the next lecture, we'll talk about how
Spark achieves its scalable and efficient operation.
So let's start with Big Data.
Where does Big Data come from?
Well, it's all around us.
Everything that you do online, well, someone could record.
The clicks that you make, the ads that you see,
any billing events, when you're watching a video, if you fast
forward, or pause, or stop that video, every request that you
make to a server, or every transaction that you perform,
or every network message that you send or receive,
or any faults that occur in the network,
in applications that you use, or on devices--
all of this information could be recorded.
This represents just the tip of the iceberg
in terms of the data that could be collected and then analyzed.
Big Data also comes from user generated content.
And this can be on the web or on mobile applications.
So from Facebook, or Instagram, or Yelp, or Twitter,
or TripAdvisor, or YouTube-- all of these applications
have user generated content, like posts and videos,
and pictures.
Another source of Big Data is health
and scientific computing.
So in scientific computing, the large hadron collider
is generating petabytes of data.
Similarly, in protein applications,
we're generating gigabytes, terabytes, petabytes of data.
Genome X is generating many petabytes of data.
Graph data also is a source of Big Data.
And there's lots of interesting data
that has a graph structure.
So social networks, your friends relationships,
telecommunication networks, computer networks,
road networks, collaborations, and relationships.
Some of these graphs can be absolutely huge.
So think about the Facebook user graph--
all of those friends relationships
across billions of users.
Another source of Big Data is web servers.
An Apache web server log generates a record
every time you access something on that web server.
In this class, in the second lab,
you'll actually analyze an Apache web server
from a NASA web server.
Machines also generate lots of information.
Every interaction that you do with an application
on a machine generates a record in a file.
The internet of things is also a source of Big Data.
Here's a project that we're doing here at Berkeley where
we're measuring the humidity, temperature, and light levels
at different levels of a Redwood tree.
We have lots of Redwood trees here.
And they actually are so big that they
create their own microclimate.
And so this is an example of where
we use internet connected sensors to capture information
about what's happening over time at different levels of a tree
to measure this microclimate.
Another source is RFID tags.
So examples are here in California we
use RFID tags to pay our tolls.
It's the fast track electronic toll collection system.
We also use the data that's collected from the transponders
for traffic reporting.