https://youtu.be/Es6Q21iLNX4
SPEAKER: Hello.
This video will see how to reset our password
in case we forget it.
So we use community.cloud.databricks.com,
this URL, in order to come to the login form.
Obviously, we remember our email,
but we don't remember our password.
So all we have to do is to fill in our email
here and then click the Forgot Password link.
If our email is correct, we're going
to receive an email a few seconds later.
All we have to do then is just click on the link provided.
We will then see this form.
And we will have to fill in our password twice.
Then all you have to do is click Reset Password.
If all goes well, you will be back
in the Databricks Community Edition welcome screen.