http://youtu.be/L9uMIpP1g18
hello again and welcome back to operations management
we're continuing our sessions on
statistical process control
and this session we're going to be
talking about how we can create the
control limits for both
X bar and R charts if you recall
X bar and R chart always used
together they're used for variables
inspection and the X bar chart
indicate
changes in the mean which is the central
tendency of the process
whereas the R-chart tracks the range
within a sample so that monitors the
dispersion they're
always used together so we have a much
better view of the process
when we look at the X bar chart
we're going to create an upper
control limit by using
the mean plus three standard deviations
above the mean and for the lower control
limit it's gonna be
the mean minus three standard deviations now
you see I have Z here because sometimes
people use
number other than three standard
deviations although
3 is normal for this kind of
chart now when we do the standard
deviation
were actually using the standard error
which is the sampling distribution of
the mean standard deviation
and that's calculated by taking the
population standard deviation
and dividing it by the square root of
the sample size
so it's too an example here we have the
LRDR company
and produces a candy bar that has an
average weight of
10 ounces with the standard deviation of
.2  the company wants to monitor the
process that makes these bars
so they're going to collect data samples
they're going to use a sample sizes 16
and they want to create control limits
of three standard deviations
so we'll  calculate both the upper and lower
control limit
for this X-bar chart the average
weight
mean is 10 ounces the standard deviation
of the population is point
two ounces and we'reusing a sample sizes of 16
so to creat the upper and lower control limits
we're going to take the mean and add to
it three standard deviations above the
mean
but remember we have to calculate
standard deviation
by using the population standard
deviation of .2
and dividing it by the square root of
the sample size of
16 so we have 10 plus
3 times .2 divided by the square
root of 16
which is 10.15 the lower control limit
is calculated in a similar fashion
only was starting with the mean and
we're subtracting
the three standard deviations so that
gives us
9.85 so now you can imagine
a control chart that has a lower line
of 9.85
an upper line of 10.15 when we collect
data and we take the means of those samples
and we plotted on the chart
as long as those data points fall
between 9.85
and 10.15 everything looks fine but in
conjunction with the X bar chart we
have to take a look at the range
at the gate so we're going to calculate
the upper and lower control limits
of the range in a similar fashion to
the X bar chart
we're going to take the range means plus three
standard deviations at the range
standard deviation
so we have R bar plus
three times the standard deviation of  the
range and R bar
minus three times standard deviations of
the range
using the same process
now we know that the average weight
range of the candy bar
is .15 ounces with the standard
deviation of the range
being .03 ounces now the company is
monitoring this process for the range
ranging the same sample size of
16 and we're still going to use three
sigma control limits
so we're going to create the upper and
lower control limit
for the R chart the average weight
ranges .15 ounces and the standard
deviation
of that ranges point 03 and our sample
size
is 16 so we're going to creat upper
and lower control limits
so it's .15 plus 3 times
.03 which is 24 and a lower control
limit is .15
minus 3 times .03 which is .06
so again a margin to control chart
the lower line it's .06 the upper
line is
.24 as long as we calculate the ranges of
our samples
those data points fall between .06 and
.24
we say a our process is doing fine but
remember
X-bar or R-chart  always used in
conjunction
with each other so if there's even one
data point that falls
outside the control limits on either
chart
then the process is not considered in
control
we have to go look for a cause for that
variation
in our next session we're gonna be
taking a look
control charts for attributes which
would be the C chart
and the P chart. I'll see you then