http://youtu.be/FD9o2iz6gq0
hello again welcome back
operations management we're continuing
with statistical process control
and now we're going to be looking at how we
create control limits for P charts and
C charts if you recall P charts and
C charts
are used for attribute inspection in terms
up is there a defect is there not a
defect
a P chart is used to monitor the percent
or fraction
of defective units within a sample so
when you thinking about
P charts think percent defective we have
a total number
items in the sample and we're just counting how
many of them
are defective when we go to create
the upper and lower control limits just
like we've done before we're going to
take
the mean and we're going to add the number
of standard deviations
above the mean and then we're going to
take the mean and subtract the number
of standard deviations below the mean
for the lower control limit one thing to
remember with the P chart is we
actually have to calculate the standard
deviation of
3 and to do that we need the
mean percent deffective or the average
percent deffective
and we also need the mean sample size
so in this case it would be the square
root of p bar
times one minus p bar over in bar
now typically we use 3 for z
because we typically used three standard
deviations away from the mean
so here we have an example
the LRDR company is trying to monitor
the number of defective batteries that
they make
it's been determined that the average
percent deffective
in a sample of 50 is two percent so
we're gonna use 3 sigma control
limits and calculate and upper and lower
control limit for
a P chart so the first thing we need to do
is we need to calculate
that standard deviation of p we know that
the average percent deffective
is two percent which is .02
and our sample size was given is 50
so we make those substitutions p bar
.02
and n is 50 and we can calculate that
samples standard deviation for the
percent deffective
from there we can creat  upper and
lower control limits
p bar plus three times the standard
deviation
p bar minus three times the
standard deviation
and so our upper control limit is
.0398
and our lower control limit is
.0002
so when we have our control limits
and we have a control chart that lower
control limit is our lower line on the
chart
and the upper control limit is our upper
line on that chart
as long as our data points we're going to be
collecting samples
of data calculating the percentage
deffective in that sample
as long as that percent deffective falls
between these two limits
we consider the process in control if it
falls
outside the control limits we say it is
not in control
and we start looking for an assignable cause
a C chart is a little bit different
in stead of  like a percent deffective
we're actually looking
at the count of defects within a sample
which means there can be more than one
defect
in a particular product for example for
looking at a car there could be a flaw
in the paint there could be a flaw in the
windshield
there can be the flaw in a light
that would be three separate flaws and
each one of them
counts towards this C chart so there
can be more than one
defect on the unit so we calculate the
upper control limit by using c bar plus
z times square root of c bar and the
lower control limit
of c bar minus z times
square root c bar
and typically again z is three so we
have three standard deviations from the
mean
and c bar is the average number of defects
or the mean
so here we have another example this
one
is concerned with the number defects in
painted panels
and the average number of defects in a
sample of 100 is 2
the company wants to monitor the process
we're going to use
3 sigma control limits and now we're going to
calculate the upper and lower control
limits for C chart
we know the average number of defects
2 so that's c bar and then we simply create
the upper and lower control limits
by taking c bar plus three times the
square root of c bar
and c bar minus three times the square
root of c bar
are so we have 6.24
is our upper control  limit
and negative 2.24 is
lower and you can't have a negative
number of
defects so in this case we converted
that lower control limit
to 0 and in fact anytime we have a control
limit
where it's negative and it is possible to
have a negative number
we convert that to 0 that's all there
is to creating the
control limits for C chart and for R
charts
when we use them on a control chart the
upper control limit is the upper line the
lower control limit is the lower line
and then we just plotting the data in between
as long as that data points stays between
those lines our process is in control
if it falls outside we say it's not in
control
that's it for control charts have a good
day