http://youtu.be/hENmgX6bTvc
hello again and welcome back to operations
management in this session we're going
to talk about capacity analysis and I
have an additional problem for you
several people contacted me asking for
additional problems in different areas
and this is one of them so let's get
started in this problem we're dealing
with a group of people who are building
charity food boxes so they are a local
charity that makes up food boxes for the
elderly volunteers are only available
for five hours a day four days a week
but they want to make a hundred and
fifty boxes each week there are three
components to making a food box they
have to select the canned goods they
have to pack the good into the box and
seal and stack the box there are two
volunteers assigned to each task now you
can see the amount of time required for
each of these activities and now based
on this information
what is the process capacity per day can
they meet their target of a hundred
fifty boxes per week
what is the current bottleneck of this
operation and if you assume that every
volunteer is capable of doing every job
how would you reassign the volunteers and
what is your new process capacity
per day so what we're going to do is
walk through this problem and you can
see that these are the key pieces of
information they are available five
hours a day four days a week so this
helps us figure out our time available
our goal is a hundred and fifty boxes we
have the time required which is the
unit
load for each one of the resource pools
we have a resouce pool for selecting
the canned goods one for packing the goods
and one for sealing and stacking boxes and we
have how many resources that are
available in each poor there's two
volunteers for each task
so now we're going to put it into a grid
so that we can analyze the capacity so
we have a resource pools the unit load
an hour
the time available per person per day
which was given as five hours per day we
have two volunteers for each of the
resources and they work four days a week
so what we're going to be doing is going
to be calculating the total time
available per day then the effective
capacity per day and then the effective
capacity per week so when we look at the
total time per day we have 2 resources
2 volunteers working five hours a day
so there's ten hours available for each
of the resource pools so when we
calculate the effective capacity per day we
take the time available
divided by the time needed which is a
unit load and we can see that selecting
canned goods yield 28.57 boxes per day
83.33 for packing and 40 for sealing and
stacking but that's per day and we're
trying to meet a hundred and fifty in a
week and they work four days a week so
we're just going to multiply the effective
capacity per day by the four days a week
so we can see our smallest number of
boxes per week is in the selecting
canned goods we can only do
114.28 so that
is our bottleneck right there so answer
to her question based on this
information what is a process capacity
per day it's 28.57 boxes can they meet
their target of 150 cannot and our
current bottleneck is selected canned
goods now the last one was if we assume
that every volunteer is capable of doing
every job how'd you reassigned the
volunteers and what is your new process
capacity per day so let's take a look at
this
this we have excess capacity and that
excess capacity is in the area of
packing goods notice it more than double
our intended 150 because it's
over 300 so since we're over double
their what if we move one of the
resource units one volunteer from
packing goods and move it to selecting
canned good and when we do that and we
recalculated our effective capacity per
day and then our boxes per week we see
that now we can meet that hundred and
fifty requirement we have a hundred
seventy-one in selecting canned goods
166.67 in packing goods and our
sealing and stacking box
is a hundred and sixty now we look at
this we realize that our bottleneck has
now moved it's no longer selecting
canned goods it is now seal and stack
boxes so by moving one person from the
packing to the selecting we reduce the
excess capacity from packing and added
it to the bottleneck so that yielded an
overall effective capacity of 40 per day
because we have a new bottleneck in the
seal and stack and we have a weekly
capacity of 160 so one of the big things
about capacity analysis is once we
identify the bottleneck and see whether
we have excess capacity we can move that
excess capacity over to the bottleneck
to be able to increase their overall
throughput it'll be another operations
supplemental problem in capacity analysis and I
hope to see you for that one