https://youtu.be/FS-WZWUlPlM
so there's in operator
says, in operator says, hey
ask a question.
Is the string csev a current
key in the dictionary ccc.
key in the dictionary ccc,
and it says false.
So now we have
something that doesn't
give a trace back that
can tell us whether or not
the key is there.
So if you remember
the algorithm,
the first time you see
it you set them to one,
and every other time
you add one to them.
So this how we do
that in Python.
So here's how we
implement that program
that I just gave you in Python.
So here's our
names, it's shorter
so my slide works better.
Here's variable, our
iteration variable
it's going to go through all
five of these one at a time
and within the body of the
loop, we have an if statement.
If the name is not currently in
the counts dictionary counts is
the name of my dictionary,
if the name is not currently
in counts dictionary, I say
counts of name equals one.
Else, that must
mean it's already
there which means it's
OK to retrieve it,
counts sub name plus 1,
we're going to add a 1 to it
and stick it back in.
OK
And so when this finishes, it's
going to add entries and then
add one to entries today
that already exist,
and not trace back it all,
and when we print it out
we're going to see
accounts and literally this
could have gone a million
times and it would just be fun
and it would just
keep expanding.
OK?
So this pattern
of checking to see
if the key is in a dictionary,
setting it to some number,
or adding one to it, is a
really, really common pattern.
It's so common as
a matter of fact,
that there is a special thing
built into dictionaries,
that does this for us.
OK and there is this
method called get.
And so counts is the
name of the dictionary,
get is a built in
capability of dictionaries
and it takes two parameters.
The first parameter
is a key name,
like a string like
csev, cwen or marquard.
And then the second
parameter is a value
to give back if
this doesn't exist.
It's a default value if
the key does not exist
and there's no trace back.
So this way you can encapsulate
in effect if then else.
If the name parameters
is in the counts,
print the thing out,
otherwise print zero.
So this expression will
either get the number,
if it exists, or it
will give me back a zero
if it doesn't exist.
So this is really
valuable, right?
This is really valuable.
That's a pretty bad Smiley face.
So this is really
valuable because it-- once
we understand the idiom, It
really takes four lines of code
and turns it into
one line of code.
Because we're going to be doing
this if then else all the time.
Now we can reconstruct that
loop a lot easier and a lot more
cleanly using this idiom.
Right?
It's something that
looks kind of complex,
but you'll get used
to it really fast.
So we have everything
here is the same,
we create an empty dictionary we
have five names to go through,
we're going to write
a loop and it's
going to go through
each of those,
and then we're going
to say, counts of name
equals counts dot get
the value stored at name,
and if you don't find
it give me back a zero.
And then whatever comes
back either the old value
or the zero, add one to
that and then take that sum
and stick it in counts name.
So this is either
going to create,
or it's going to update.
If there is no entry, it's
going to create it and set it
to one, if there is an
entry it's going to add one
to the current entry.
OK so this is, this line
is kind of an idiom.
Read about it in the
book, figure it out,
get used to the notion
of what this is doing.
Understand what that is doing.
OK?
Because I'm going to start using
it as if you understand it.
So the next problem
is, a problem
of finding the most common word.
So finding the most
common the top five,
is often a trigger that
says use dictionaries,
because if you're going
to have to count things up
you don't know what the
most common thing is
at the beginning, first you
have to count everything up,
and dictionaries are
a great way to count.
So here's a little
problem and I would
like you to read
this text and find
me the most common
word in the text
and tell me what the
most common word is
and how many times it occurs.
Ready?
I'm going to give you a
thousandth of a second,
just like I would
give a computer.
I would expect that
they'll do this
in a thousandth of a second.
There you go.
OK I gave you five seconds,
times up, did you get it?
Or did you say to
yourself, you know
what I hate that,
it's no good, I
think I'll write a
Python program instead.
And you'll probably
show me a Python program
if I wait long enough.
So here's a slightly
easier problem,
from the first lecture.
Ready?
It's the same problem,
find the most common word
and how many times
the word occurs.
Did you get it?
I believe the answer is, and
I could look really dumb here,
the answer is, the and I
think it's seven times.
So that's the right answer.
OK.
Again things humans
are not so good at.
So here's a piece of
code that's starting
to combine some of
the things we've
been doing in the past
few chapters all together.
We are going to read a line
of text, split it into words,
count the occurrence, how
many times each word occurs
and then print out a map.
So, so here's what
we're going to do.
We're going to say OK start a
dictionary an empty dictionary.
Read a line of input.
Then split it, remember
the split takes a string
and produces a list.
So words is a list,
line is a string,
and then we'll print that out.
Then we're going to
write a for loop that's
going to go through
each of the words,
and then create, use this
idiom, counts of word
equals counts dot get
word comma 0 plus 1.
So this is going to
do exactly what we
talked about in the
previous couple slides back.
Either create the entries
or add to those entries.
OK and then we're going
to print them out.
So here's what that program
does, when it prints out.
Now this is actually
one long line
I'm just cutting it so
you can see it here's
this line we enter and the
words the they're seven of them,
then it takes this line
and splits it into a list
and there is the beginning
and end of the list.
The list maintains the
order, so the list simply
breaks all these words
into separate words
in a list of strings, from
one string too many strings.
This is many strings,
and so the and spaces
are gone and so
here's this list,
and then what we're
going to do is
we are going to run
through the list
and we are going to
keep running totals
of each of the words in
the list and then we're
done with a list, we're
going to print out
the contents of that dictionary
and we can inspect it,
go like let's look
for the biggest one,
it's kind of like looking for
the largest, like oh seven,
that's the largest and
the largest word is the.
OK so that's how
the program runs.
It reads a line, splits
it into a list of words,
and then accumulates a
running total for each word,
and then we hand inspect to see
what the most common word is.
OK
Oh no no, I don't
want that song again.
There we go.
And so here we have the, in
this kind of a smaller fashion,
we make a dictionary.
This entering a line of text
is here, it's all one line,
we do the split and then
we print the words out
and so that split creates a list
of strings from a single string
based on where the blanks are
at chop, chop, chop, chop,
and then here it
counting, we're going
to loop through each of
the words, one at a time
and use this idiom
counts of word
equals counts that get word
comma 0 plus 1, which is going
to create and/or update.
And then we print the counts
out and that comes up there.
OK so again, this is the
new thing we've done.
Everything else here
we've kind of seen before.
Now we can also loop through
dictionaries with for loops.
The for loop we've been put
all kinds of things over here,
we put strings over here, we
put listed numbers over here,
we put files over
here, and basically
what it really says is this
is a collection of things,