https://youtu.be/6KgArgGi6Mk
Hello, and welcome to chapter
five, loops and iteration.
As always, this lecture is
copyright Creative Commons
attribution, including
the audio, and the video,
and the slides,
and the book, even.
So now we're getting to
our fourth basic pattern.
We've talked about
sequential, where
steps happen one after another.
We've talked about conditional,
where steps may or may not
happen.
In chapter four, we talked about
the store and retrieve pattern,
and now we're going to talk
about the looping pattern.
And the looping pattern is the
last of our really foundational
ones.
And it potentially is
the most important one,
because it's the thing that
allows us to get computers
to do lots of things that,
say, humans might get tired of,
but computers don't tire of.
And so after this,
we'll start becoming
a little more skilled in the
basic language capabilities.
We'll talk about strings, and
then start talking about files,
and start doing some real work
after we get done with this.
So bear with us, it's
going to be a while,
but we'll get there.
So welcome to repeated steps.
This is the example that I had
in the first lecture, chapter
one.
And the basic idea,
just to review,
is that you have
this while keyword.
The while keyword functions
like an if in that it implicitly
has a decision
that's going to make.
And it's either going to do
the code in the indented block
or or skip it, basically.
So you either do
it, or you skip it.
The difference between
the while and the if
is that it's going to do it many
times as long as this question
that we have remains true.
And so in this case, n is 5.
While n greater than zero,
functions like an if.
So yes, it's going to run it.
Prints out 5, subtracts
one, so it's four.
Goes back up and asks
the question again.
Is n still greater than zero?
Well, since it's four,
yes, we'll continue on.
Out comes four, then
n gets subtracted.
Three, two.
And then we come
through, we print one.
We subtract n to zero.
We go back up.
n is now not greater
than zero, so we come up
and we execute outside the loop.
We leave the loop.
And that really means
in the Python code,
we skip to whatever's lined
up with the while statement.
The in same indent level
as the while statement.
And so that's how it works.
And I just print n at the
end here to remind ourselves
that n ended up at zero.
Not at one.
The last thing we printed
out in the loop was the one,
but n ended up at 0.
Because this loop was
going to run as long as n
was greater than zero, so it
had to be not greater than zero
to get out the loop.
So that's basically a
review of what we've done.
Now-- oh, wait, something else.
Iteration variables.
So the key to this is these
loops can't run forever.
We don't want them
to run forever.
We want them to run as long
as we want them to run,
they may run a very long
time, but not forever.
There's got to be a
way to get out of them,
otherwise we call them
infinite loops, which we'll
talk about in the next slide.
So the iteration
variable is generally
some variable that is changing
each time through the loop,
and we are changing it by
subtracting one from it.
And so this thing is
going to keep running,
and we can pretty
much see that, oh,
this is going to exit, right?
Whatever n is.
It could be a large
number, but eventually it's
going to get to zero.
So the iteration variable
controls how many times
the loop runs,
and it also allows
us to do something
different inside the loop.
And of course, this
is like a trivia loop,
where we're just printing
the iteration variable.
But it just means that this
loop is going to run five times,
and it's going to do something
potentially different
each time.
If you just ran the loop
that did the same thing over,
and over, and over again
with no data changing,
that's dull and pointless.
So just because you have
an iteration variable
doesn't mean that you've
properly constructed your loop.
It's a common problem, or
something we want to avoid,
is an infinite loop.
And here is a carefully
constructed loop.
We start n at five
at the beginning.
We have a good question at the
end, while n greater than zero,
it's going to run this as long
as n is greater than zero.
But the problem is, we don't
change in the little block,
we don't change the n.
Which means it's
going to come back,
and n is going to be five.
And that's going to run this,
and n's going to be five.
And it's going to run this,
and it's going to be five.
And so this an infinite
loop, which means this loop
will never exit.
It will never get out.
It's just going to
run forever in here,
because n's not changing.
Neither of these
statements change n.
So part of the
iteration variable
is there needs to
be something that
changes so that the loop
will ultimately make progress
to accomplish what it is
and know when to stop.
So this is an infinite loop.
And, of course, lather,
rinse, repeat is commonly
put on shampoo and conditioner.
And so you can next time
you're in the shower
take a look at your
shampoo and conditioner
and find the
infinite loop that's
on most bottles of
shampoo and conditioner.
Now here's another
loop just to emphasize
that it's possible to
structure these loops in a way
that they never run.
So this function is an if.
The while functions as an if.
And so when n is set to zero
and we ask the question,
it is literally going
to make the decision
based on n greater than zero.
Well, it is not
greater than zero,
so it's going to go
right by it over here.
It's going to come here
and go right to there,
and never run these
lines of code.
And we call this a zero
trip loop, and that's OK.
I mean, this is a
silly one, of course.
It just shows that the test,
the question that's being asked
is above the lines that make
up the body of the loop.
And if it's false,
the loop never runs.
So it's possible that these
loops have zero trips.
So that's a loop.
Now there are more than one way
to control the flow of a loop.
The basic flow of the loop is
when it gets to the bottom,
it goes back up to the
while and does the check.
This is a different way of
getting out of the loop,
or controlling the
execution of a loop.
There is a key word, or a
part of the Python language,
called-- what color do I got?
Nope, Green's over here.
Called break.
If you looked back
at reserved words,
break is one of
the reserved words.
Break says, hey, if I'm
in a loop, stop the loop.
Get out of this loop,
I'm done with this loop.
And so here's this loop.
Now the interesting
thing we've done
is I just got done talking
to you about infinite loops.
We have just constructed
an infinite loop.
Because the question is right
there, and the answer is yes,
true.
And that's a way to
construct an infinite loop.
We've done this because we have
a different way of getting out
of the loop.
So we've constructed loop
just on the face of it,
just looking at that line,
looks like an infinite loop.
So what this loop does is
it reads a line of input,
checks to see if it's the string
that we've entered as done.
And if it is, we're going
to skip out with this break
and get out of the loop.
Otherwise, we're
going to print it.
So at a high level, what
this loop is going to do
is prompt for strings of
characters until we enter done.
And that's exactly what it does.
It prompts, we say hello
there, it prints that out.
So we say finished,
it prints that out.