https://youtu.be/odIMpHInDbA
So at the end of this
bit of code right here,
we are going to have counts
with word count pairs.
OK.
So this is something
we've done before.
It's just dictionaries,
reading, splitting, and then
this pattern of how to
accumulate in a dictionary.
Then what we're going
to do is we're going
to make a new list called lst.
And now, we're doing this
key value in the item.
So this is going to go
through the key value
pairs in this list,
which is the key value
pairs from the dictionary.
Right.
But then we are going to create
this temporary list of tuples
that are val,key.
So val is like 20 the, 14 hello.
And that's what the list
is going to look like.
It's going to be tuples.
But it's going to be the
value, and then the key
rather than the
key and the value.
This one here is key,value.
This one here,
lst, is value key.
Now that we have a
list that's value,key,
we are just going to sort it.
Because now it's going to
sort based on the first thing
in that tuple.
And we're going to reverse it.
So the biggest values
are near the top.
And so when we're
all done, this is
going to be a list
except it's going to be
sorted based on the value.
So that's just one
step to sort it.
So this is a good example
of how we sort of go
through some work.
We get a data structure, a
list, the way we want it.
And now we can sort of
leverage the built-in sort.
We had to prepare a list, so
we could use the built-in sort.
We could do this by hand.
But it would be very
difficult. But it's easier
to say I think I'll make a
list, and then I'll sort it.
OK.
So I made two lists basically.
I made the original one.
Now I made this one just
for the purposes of sorting.
And now what I'm going to
do to print out the top 10
is I am going to write
a for loop, val key.
Remember this list,
lst, is value key.
And I'm going to say for val
key in list, using list slicing,
starting at 0, up
to but not including
10, which is indeed
the first 10 items.
Now, I'm going to
print out key value.
So it's going to be print
out the 22, Fred 16.
It's only going to
print the first 10.
So this list is
in val key order.
The tuples are val key order.
And so I'm going to
print it out in key val,
just so that I print out in a
way that makes the most sense.
And so this is a
simple way to do
a simple histogram of the
occurrence of words in a file.
So again, you should know this.
You should know every line.
Go back, review a couple times.
But you should know the
meaning of every line of this.
And if you do,
that's really good.
So as you become more powerful
and capable inside Python,
you will realize that there
are sometimes even shorter ways
of doing things.
Now what I'm showing
you here is not
that different than what
was on the previous page.
It's just really dense.
But you have to concentrate.
I want you understand what's
on that previous page.
If you don't understand
this, don't feel bad.
I'm going to explain it to you.
But don't feel bad
if you don't get, OK?
So I'm just going to explain it.
If it doesn't feel
right to you, go back
and look at the previous page.
OK.
So here we go.
I'm going to have a dictionary.
And then I'm going to print
in one line sorted by value.
So we'll start from
the inside out.
So this is a thing called
list comprehension.
It looks like a list
constant, because we
start with square brackets.
But this is a Python syntax
that says construct dynamically
a list of tuples v,k.
And I would like you to loop
through the items with k and v
taking on the successive values.
So this is creating
that reversed list
where value and
key are the order
of the items in each tuple.
And that's going to do that.
So it's going to expand.
It goes vazoo.
It expands this.
It makes a temporary
list right now.
Now if you look on
the previous slide,
we called that thing lst.
But here, we don't
even call it lst.
And then once we have the list
of tuples in value key order,
then we simply take and
pass that into sorted.
This is a function call,
the sorted function.
Now, I'm not reversing it.
But the print statement
prints out its ascending order
of the value, 1, 10, 22.
OK.
So you can make these
more dense once you're
a little more comfortable
with what's going on.
It's sometimes easier
to construct something
that seems to have steps, where
you can put a debug print here,
you can put debug print here,
you can put a debug print here.
And you kind of see
what's going on, right?
Whereas, once you
really understand this,
you can write some
more dense Python.
When you understand
this, it's OK, right?
So I'm not saying you're
supposed to understand this.
But I just want to
point out that it's
possible to do this
in a tighter fashion.
So tuples are like lists, except
that you can't change them.
You can't change lists.
And you can compare them.
You can sort them.
You can sort lists of tuples.
You can't sort within
the tuple itself.
The two values on the
left-hand side of an assignment
statement we can use sorted.
And we played the sorting
dictionaries by key and value.
So that's kind of the
end of this lecture.
And so at this
point, I just want
to congratulate you on making
it through the first 10
chapters of the book.
So I'll drink a
cup of tea to you.
Here's your cup of tea.
Here's my toast to you
in my Slytherin cup.
And so it's time for
a graduation ceremony.
So I'll give a little
graduation speech here
with my graduation hat on.
And this is my Slytherin wand.
And so the reason I'm
congratulating you
at the end of this chapter
is that at this point,
you kind have know all the
fundamentals of programming.
Programming really
comes down to what's
called algorithms
and data structures.
Sometimes we solve a problem
by a clever series of steps
that we put together.
And sometimes we solve a problem
by creating a clever data
structure.
And so the first few chapters
were about algorithm, steps,
loops, functions,
very procedural,
how you sort of create
these threads of stepping
and do things a bunch of times
or skip around or whatever.
And in the last three
chapters that we've covered,
we're talking about
data structures.
And programming power comes when
you combine algorithms and data
structures.
Now in the next
chapters, starting
with chapter 11,
Regular Expressions,
we're going to learn more clever
ways of doing the same thing.
So you kind of know how
to do a lot of stuff now.
From this point forward,
you'll say, oh boy,
that's more clever.
Or we'll use a database.
Oh, that's more clever.
But it's not
fundamentally different.
And so that's why it's
important for you,
before you leave this moment,
to understand everything
that we've covered so far,
loops, functions, strings,
files, tuples,
lists, dictionaries.
Because they're kind
of the foundation.
And everything else
will just kind of
be a subtle refinement
slash improvement.
So once you understand
that, you've kind of begun.
You become a basic programmer.
And I like, poof.
I magically [INAUDIBLE] you
and turn you a Pythoneo.
Something like that.
OK.
Enough with the Harry
Potter reference.
Thank you for spending
all this time with me.
If you've gotten this far,
I really appreciate it.
And of course, it's
really just the beginning.
But I hope that it has
been a good beginning.
Thank you.