https://youtu.be/L2IUSArpG98
So again, the second character
is up-to but not including.
And that's the kind
of weird thing there.
Of course, once you remember
that the first character is 0,
0 up-to but not including.
Nice.
If we leave off the first or the
last number, and both of them,
they mean the beginning and
end of the string respectively.
And so, up-to but
not including 2,
is M-O. 8 colon means starting
at 8 to the end of the string.
So that's "thon."
And then, that means the
beginning to the end.
And so, it's just the whole
string, "monty python."
Now, we've already played
with string concatenation.
Just the thing to emphasize here
is the concatenation operator
does not add a space.
If you want a space,
you explicitly add it.
So here, there's no space
in between the O and the T.
But here, there is a space
between the O and the T,
because we explicitly added it.
So you can concatenate
more than one thing.
And you add your
spaces as you want.
Another thing you can do
is you can ask questions
about a string.
It's sort of like doing a string
look up, using the In operator.
This a little different than how
we use it inside of a For loop.
This is a logical
operation asking
a question like less-than
or greater-than or whatever.
So here's an expression.
So fruit is banana as always.
Is N in fruit?
And the answer is, yes, it is.
True.
So this is a logical operation.
It's a question.
It's like True or False.
Is M in fruit?
No, False.
And this can be a string,
not just a single character.
Is N-A-N in fruit?
The answer is True.
And you can put parts of
Ifs, et cetera, et cetera.
So this is a logical expression
that can be on an If.
You can have a While,
et cetera, et cetera.
So it's a logical expression
and it returns True or False.
You can also do comparisons.
Now, the comparison operations--
Equals makes a lot of sense.
Less-than and Greater-than
depend on the language
that you're using, Python.
And so, if you're using a
Latin character set, then
alphabetical matters, the
way the Latin character set
would do.
But if you're in a
different character set,
Python is aware of
multiple character sets
and will sort strings based
on the sorting algorithm
of a particular character set.
So you can do comparisons
like Equality, Less-than,
and Greater-than.
And we've seen some things in
previous lectures actually.
We've had to use them.
So in addition to these
fundamental operations that we
can do on strings, there's
an extensive library
of built-in
capabilities in Python.
And so, the way we see these
built-in capabilities are
they're actually
built into strings.
So let's go real slow here.
Here, we have a
variable called "greet,"
and we're sticking the
string "Hello, Bob" into it.
Now Greet is of type
string, as a result of this.
And it contains Hello,
Bob as its value.
But we can actually
access capabilities inside
of this value.
So we can say Greet
dot lower parentheses.
This is calling something
that's part of Greet itself.
It's a part of all strings.
The fact that Greet
contains a string means
that we can ask
for, hey, give me
Greet, which just gives you
back what you're looking for.
Like here, print
Greet as Hello, Bob.
Or you could say,
give me Greet lower.
So this doesn't convert
it to lowercase.
It gives me a lowercase
copy of Hello, Bob.
So Zap is hello,
bob, all lowercase.
Now, it didn't change Greet.
Right?
And you could even put this Dot
Lower on the end of constants.
Why you'd do this, I don't know.
But Hi There, with H and
T capitalized, dot lower
comes out as hi there.
So this bit is part
of all strings.
Both variables and constants
have these string functions
built into them.
And every instance of
a string-- whether it
be a variable or a constant--
has these capabilities.
They don't modify it.
They just give you back a copy.
Now, it turns out there is a
command inside Python called
Dir to ask questions like, hey!
Well, here's stuff.
We got Hello, World.
We can say-- oh, I
want to redo this,
come here-- stuff as a string.
We can ask, hey, what are you?
I am a string.
Dir is another built in Python
that asks the question, hey,
what are all the things that
are built into this that I
can make use of?
And here they are.
That's kind of a
raw dump of them.
You can also go look at the
online documentation of Python.
And at the Python
website, you can see
a whole bunch of these things.
And they have the
calling sequence, what
the parameters are, et cetera.
So when you're looking
these things up,
you can go read about them.
Here's just a few
that I pulled out,
Capitalize-- which upper case
is the first characters--
Center, Endswith, Find.
There's Stripping.
So I'll look through a couple of
these, just the kind of things
to be looking for.
It would be a good
idea to take a look
and read through
some of the things.
Here's a couple that we'll
probably be using early on.
The Find function,
it's similar to In.
But it tells you where it finds
the particular thing that's
looking for.
And so, we'll put
fruit is banana.
And I'm going to
say, Pause-- which
is going to be integer
variable-- equals fruit
dot Find N-A. So
what it's saying is,
go look inside this
variable fruit.
Hunt until you find the first
occurrence of the string N-A.
Hunt-hunt-hunt-hunt, whoop!
Got it.
--and then, return it to me.
So that's going
to give me back 2.
2 is where it found it, right?
So where is it in the string?
That's what Find does.
And if you don't find anything--
like, you're looking for Z.
Nn-nn-nn-nn-na, I
didn't find a Z. Then,
it gives me back negative 1.
So again, this is just one
of many built-in functions
in string, the ability
to find a substring
or find a character or
string within another string.
There's a lowercase.
There's also an uppercase.
This might be better
named "Shouting."
Upper means, give
me an uppercase copy
of this variable.
So Hello Bob, becomes HELLO BOB!
And then lower is hello, bob.
Right?
So these are both
ways to get copies
of uppercase and
lowercase versions.
You might think these
are kind of silly.