https://youtu.be/Wdi6lhcrtBU
And if we say greet, Sally
it says hello, Sally.
And so it runs the code twice;
and the return function,
return value has been
put in here instead.
And so the hello came
there and hello came there.
So we get the two lines.
So return is a statement
that both terminates
the execution of the function
and defines the value of what
will be replaced when the
function call comes back
in the line that
function was called from.
So, here is a little smarter
version of our greet function.
It's very similar, it's
still called greet still.
It takes lang as a parameter.
And if the language
is the es then it
returns the string hola.
If the language is French
it returns bonjour.
Otherwise it returns hello.
So we're not actually
doing the print.
If you go back another
slides we are printing
but now we're just
returning a string.
OK so now I can call
print greet and pass
en in so then that runs the
code once with lang equal to en
and I get back hello
and then comma blank.
Then I call it again
and I pass es in,
and then that time it
returns the return value here
becomes hola, a string hola.
Hola, Sally.
And then Michael.
I pass in one more time.
Lang now is fr, the string
fr, and so it returns bonjour.
So the residual
is here is bonjour
and so out comes
bonjour, Michael.
There's a lot to this, right?
Passing stuff in , you have this
kind of placeholder variable,
and you have this return that
sort of appears where it was
called from.
It goes in, does its
work, it comes back,
and there's sort of this
residual value that sits here.
You don't have to have
a return in a function,
but if you want to do
something with a value
then you have to have a
return in the function.
We call the functions that
produce values fruitful,
and the other ones
are called void.
So that's a good name for them.
So, to review sort
of this arguments
parameters and
results, if we look
at max, the original
thing where it's
looking for the largest,
lexicographically
largest letter, it
looks: hello, world
is the argument
that's passed in.
We have this sort
of formal parameter
here called imp, which is
not really variable it just
happens to refer to whatever
is the first argument
in any particular call.
And that does it's little
thing and runs loops
and does all these things, and
at some point it returns w.
So that the thing that comes
out when the function quits
that becomes the
replacement value
here is a lowercase w string.
And then that is the
w goes over into big.
So the return is what
defines what comes back here.
Because you think of this
as; it's looking at this,
it suspends for the
moment, it runs this code,
its holding itself
here running this code
and then it comes back to here.
OK?
And the return value is
what defines coming back.
So, of course you can have
more than one parameter
and they are in order.
So here we have an a and a b.
The name of these things
doesn't really matter.
They're just relevant inside
of the function definition.
So we are going to add
two numbers together
by taking a plus b and
then returning the sum.
The added variable's just
kind of local to this function
and now we can say addtwo(3,5)
and then this will come back
as eight and then eight
will get assigned into x,
and so that'll print out eight.
And so you can have as
many of these as you want,
and the order
matters and there's
a one to one correspondence.
Three goes to a and five goes
to b when the thing is called,
and then the return
value again comes back.
OK?
So, that's sort of arguments.
And like I said,
not all functions
have to return values.
We call them void functions
when they don't return anything.
It's totally fine for
that to be the case.
So at this point you might be
thinking to yourself, OK great.
I still don't quite get
why to use functions.
In reality, in the
first 10, 11 chapters
of this book other than
using lots of functions,
we're not really going to spend
a lot of time making functions.
Because most of our programs are
going to kind of be that long.
And we're not going to do a
lot of reuse in the program.
And there'll be a time when your
programs become complex enough,
that you'll be like, oh
thank heaven for functions.
I think it's premature to
say you must use functions,
even though there are
some exercises that
just say hey do this
with a function,
just so you kind of get the
understanding of a function.
You will find soon enough,
as your programs grow,
you'll go like oh I keep
doing the same thing over
and over again.
Let me pull that
up into a function
and pass the parameter
in, have a return value,
and away you go.
Or you might find that you're
moving from one program
to another and you
have this common thing
that you want to do so you
make yourself a library
that you drag along.
And we will do
lots of libraries.
The book in the second half does
lots and lots of library stuff
doing things like parsing
XML, and this, that,
and the other thing.
So, don't feel like you
need to use functions
on every assignment because
they're a are natural thing
when the program
gets big enough.
So, just kind of understand
them on a mechanical level,
but it'll come to you
at the right time when
it's time to start building
your own functions.
So in this class we kind
of talked about functions.
Just got you started,
talked about parameters,
talked about built in functions,
talked about return values,
the store and reuse pattern.
So, the problems at the end
the chapter for this particular
chapter are relatively
straightforward in that --
like I said, we don't have
a real strong need to do
functions yet in this
class because the programs
aren't large enough, but
I just said OK take one
of your previous assignments
and refactor the code so that
at the top there's
a DEF, compute pay,
and you put like the if
and whatever in here.
And then later on
you do your code,
and then you call compute pay.
So you took code
that you already had,
you move it up into a
function, and make a function.
And I've also online got
sort of a sample of this,
because it's a little complex.
And so you should be able
to find on Python learn
or on the course site; should
be able to find a good example
because I really
want to get this.
Like I said, there
will come a time
when functions will make
the most sense to you.
But coming up
next, of course, is
chapter five and that's loops.
And loops are going
to rock the house.
So we really; that's our
fourth major pattern is loops.
And I'm looking forward to it.
So we'll see you at
the next lecture.