https://youtu.be/nO8eU3uts0o
and print the average.
So these two programs
are basically
equivalent-- the only time that
they might not be equivalent
was if there was
ten million numbers,
this would use up 40 megabytes
of your memory, which
is actually not a lot of
memory on some computers,
but if memory mattered this
does store all those numbers--
this one actually just
runs the calculation
so if there's a really
large number of numbers,
this would make a difference
because the list is growing
and keeping them all,
summing them all at the end,
this is actually storing
very little data.
But for reasonably sized
numbers like thousands or even
hundreds of
thousands of numbers,
these two approaches
are kind of equivalent
and then sometimes
you actually want
to accumulate something a
little more complex than this,
you want to sort them,
or look for the maximum
and look for something
else, who knows what.
But the notion of make a list
and then append something
to the list each time
through the iteration
and then do something
with a list at the end,
is a rather powerful pattern.
So this is also a
powerful pattern,
this is accumulator
pattern we just
have variables
accumulating in the loop,
this one is one where we
accumulate the data in the loop
and then do the
computations all at the end.
Certain situations will make use
of these different techniques.
OK so.
Connecting strings and lists.
So there's a method, a
capability of strings,
that is really powerful when
it comes to tearing data apart.
It's called the split.
So here is a string
with three words
and has blanks in between
here and abc.split
says parse this string,
look for the blanks,
break the string into
pieces, and give me
back a list with one item for
each of the words in the list
as defined by the spaces, OK?
So it breaks it
into three pieces
and gives us that back in the
list, it's very powerful, OK?
So we're going to split
it and we get back a list.
There are three words
and the first word,
stuff sub 0 is With.
So there's a lot of
parsing going on here.
We could do this with For
loops and a lot of other things
but there would be a lot
of work in the split.
Given that this is a
really common task,
it's really great that this has
been put into Python for us,
OK?
So split breaks a
string into parts
and produce a list of strings,
we think of these as words
and we can access
a particular word
or we can loop
through all the words.
So here we have
stuff again and now
we have a For loop that's going
to go through each of the three
words and then it's
going to run three times.
Now chances are good we're going
to do something different other
than just print
them out, but you
see how you quickly can take
us split followed by a For
and then write a loop that's
going to go through each
of the words without working
too hard to find the spaces,
you let Python do all the hard
work of finding the spaces, OK?
So let's take a look
at a couple of samples,
just a couple things to teach
you a little more about split.
Split looks at many spaces as
equal to one space so if you
split a lot of spaces,
it's still just
throws away all those spaces
and gives us four words.
One, two, three, four and
throws away all the spaces
because it assumes that's what
we want done, so that's nice.
You can also have split
on some other characters.
Sometimes you'll be
getting data and they'll
have used a
semicolon, or a comma,
or a colon, or a tab character,
who knows what they've used,
and your job is to
dig that data out.
So you can split based
on a different character.
Here, if we're
splitting normally,
this is a normal split, it's
not going to see the semicolons,
it's looking for
a space and so all
we get back is one item in
the string with a semicolon.
But if we switch and we pass
semicolon in as a parameter
to split, then it will know to
split it based on semicolons
and gives us first,
second and third back.
OK?
And then it gives
us three words.
So you can split
either on spaces
or you can split on a character
other than a space, OK?
So let's take a look at
how we might turn this
into some of our
common assignments
that we have this
chapter, we're going
to read some of
the mailbox data.
So here we go with
a little program.
First three lines,
we write these a lot.
Open the file, write
a For loop to loop
through each line in
the file, then we're
going to strip off the white
space at the end the line.
One, two, three, do
those all the time.
And we're looking for lines,
if you look at the whole file,
we're looking at
lines that start
with from followed by a space.
So if the line does
not start with from
followed by a space, that's a
space right there, continue.
So that's a way to skip all the
lines the don't look like this.
There are thousands
of lines in this file
and just a few that
look like this, OK?
And so we're going
to look and we're
going to try to find what
day of the week this thing
happened on.
So we're throwing
away all the lines
with this little bit of code.
Then what we do is we
take the line, which
is all of this text,
and then we split it.
And we know that the day
of the week is word sub 2.
So this is word sub
0, this is word sub 1,
and this is word sub 2.
So this is word sub
0, sub 1, and sub 2.
And so all we have to do
is print out the sub 2
and we throw away all the
lines except the from lines,
we split them and take the
third word or word sub 2,
and we can quickly
create something
that's extracting the
data week out of these.
OK?
So it's quick because
split does the tricky work.
If you go back to
the strings chapter,
you saw that we did a lot of
work to get this to happen.
So here's even another
tricky pattern.
So let's say we want to do what
we did at the end of chapter
six, the string chapter, let's
say we wanted to get back
this little bit of data, OK?
So we can look at
this and say, OK,
let's split this-- and this will
be 0, 1, and 2, and 3, and 4,
5, and 6.
We're splitting it
based on spaces then
that email address is
words sub 1, right?
So that email address
is this little bit
of stuff because it's in
between spaces, right?
So that's what we pull out, the
email address is words sub 1,
and we've got that.
So that's sitting in this
email address variable.
Then all we want, we don't
really want the whole thing,
we just want the
part after the @,
and we could do a
look up of the @,
but you can also do
a second split, OK?
So we're taking
this variable here,
email, which is merely this
little part right here,
and we are splitting it
again except this time
we're splitting it
based on an @ which
means it's going to
bust it right here
and find us two pieces.
So pieces now is a list where
the sub 0 item is the person's
name and the sub 1 item is the
host that their mail address is
held from, OK?
And so then, all
we need to know is
pieces sub 1 and pieces sub
1 is this guy right here.
So that's pieces sub 1
and so we pulled it out.
So if you go back to
how we did it before,
we were doing searching
and we were searching some
and then we're
taking slices-- this
is a little more elegant, OK?
Because really, we split
it and then we split it,
and we knew what piece
we were looking at.
So this is what I call
the double split pattern,
where you split a
string into a list,
then you take the
thing out and then
you split it again, depending
on what data you're looking for.
This is just a technique,
it's not the only technique.
OK so that's lists, we
talked about the concept
of a collection where lists
have multiple things in it,
indefinite loops, again
we've seen these things,
it looks a lot like
strings except the elements
are more powerful and
they're more mutable.
We still use the
bracket operator
and we re-did the
max, min and sum
except we did it in one line,
rather than a whole loop.
And something we're
going to play with a lot,
is using split to parse strings,
the single split and then
the double split is a natural
extension of the single split.
So, see you in the next
lecture, looking forward
to talking about dictionaries.