https://youtu.be/O0wE2M8-ois
inside of string because
line is a string,
if line starts with
from, print it out.
So this means it's going
to loop through all
of the lines of
the file and it's
going to print the
ones that start
with the string from colon.
OK again four lines
complete Python program
to read this file and
print the lines that
have a prefix of from.
So if you run this program,
and I suggest that you do,
this is what the output's
going to look like.
And it's like wait a second.
I'm seeing the lines, seeing
the lines, that have the froms
but then I get
these blank lines.
And why is that?
Why this blank lines there?
If I look at the program, I mean
I'm not printing blank lines,
I'm only printing lines
that start with from.
I'm not doing that, so why?
What do you think?
Give you a second.
I've certainly done enough
foreshadowing in this lecture.
Well it turns out these
new lines are the problem.
So it turns out that
the print, we've
been doing this all
along you just didn't, we
didn't make a fuss about it.
The print adds a new line
at the end of everything
that it prints.
So these yellow new
lines are coming
from the print statement.
But when we read the file,
each line ends in a new line.
So these green new lines
are actually from the file.
They're the ones from the file.
So what's happening is
we're seeing two lines,
and so that turns
into a blank line.
So how do we deal with that?
Well, we've got
a string function
that conveniently
solves that problem.
OK.
And that is we're going
to call our strip.
If you recall we had
strip, l strip and r strip
to strip white space on
one side, on the other side
or on both sides.
So in this one we're
going to use r strip.
We're going to say,
we're going to read
the line that this line is
going to have a new line in it.
Our strip says pull white space
and the new lines are also
comma'd as white space.
Blanks or new lines
are white space.
And then we're going to replace
this with no new line in it,
then we're going to ask
if it starts with a from
and then we're
going to print out.
And then we go and we're going
to see exactly what we're
looking for in this file.
And there's no new lines.
Now they're, so the new
line that's coming out here,
is the one from the print,
not the one from the file
because the one
from the file got
wiped out by that
particular line.
OK.
So another general pattern
of these file based loops
that we have done this,
is a skipping pattern.
Now you can do--
the non skipping
pattern is where
you're saying, I'm
going to look for lines
that start with from
and do something to them.
Sometimes you want to
do something to all,
you want to say here's a
bunch lines I'm going to skip,
and then I'm going
to do something.
So the skipping
pattern uses continue.
And so the first few
lines here are the same.
We open a file, we read
each line in the file
then we're going to strip
off the white space.
You're going to get tired
typing these three lines,
because you're going
to do it a lot.
Open the file, start
reading the file,
strip the white
space for each line.
And you can make it so that
you can look for some fact.
In this case, I'm going to say
if not line starts with from,
means this is true for all the
lines this don't start from,
continue.
If you remember
continue goes up.
So the continue says, I'm
done, it finishes the iteration
and it doesn't do
anything down here.
And so this is-- and
then we can do something.
So I've kind of
flipped this, where
I said, these are the
things I'm interested in,
that's lines that
start with from, so I'm
going to skip the lines
that don't, so I'm
going to use continue.
Either way you can do it,
depending on the complexity
or how much-- often when
you're-- this is a good pattern
when you have lots of
lines of code down here,
that you're going to do
a lot of cool stuff with.
You can also use things like
in, to select lines, right?
So I'm going to look
for lines that have
at uct dot ac dot za in them.
So again I'm going to
open it up, open these, go
through each line
in the file, I'm
going to strip their
white space out
and if not uct if this, if
this string is not in line,
then I'm going to continue.
So it's a way for me to
skip all of the lines that
don't have this string in it.
So these lines dupes,
that one has it too,
and then we're going
to print it out.
Then we'll print out the
ones that make it past here.
OK.
So, but in is another
way to do searching.
Like it starts with et cetera.
So one more thing that
you might want to try
is, so we can count right?
Now and this is a pattern for
prompting for a file name.
And so you'll get tired
of sort of changing
your code every time you want
to open a different file,
because you probably want to
run the program with mbox one,
sandbox short, because it
just, just so you can test it
with different things of data.
So here's just another pattern.
We add this line to say raw
input enter the file name,
and there you go, we'll
type in the file name,
and then the thing that we
open is whatever we entered
as the file name, and
then the rest of it
is pretty much yada yada.
So here I'm, reading
the whole file,
if the line starts with subject,
count equals count plus one,
and then there were 1797
subject lines in inbox dot txt.
There were 27 subject lines
and mbox short dot txt.
OK.
So that's prompting
for the file names.
Now open-- the open
statement fails
if the file name doesn't exist,
so you might want to add a try
and except around that.
If you want to, if you're
just writing code for yourself
and you it is OK, then you
don't have to write try except,
but if you want to catch it,
and catch a bad file name,
then you take the open and
turn into these four lines.
So this is the code that
we think might blow up
and it's going to blow up we
know it's going to blow up.
If they enter a bad file
name like nana booboo,
right, this is going to blow up.
So what do we do?
We use try and except.
We put try around that,
we're going to take out
some insurance on
that particular line,
and then if it fails we're
going to print this message
and then say exit, to get out.
So if you get a good file, if
you get a good file it works,
skips the except then runs the
thing, prints out the count.
That's what's happening here.
If on the other hand you
get a bad file, comes here,
open blows up, runs the except
prints this out and then quits.
So that's how this one
works with a bad file
and now no trace back.
Right.
So we are, it's kind
of a short lecture.
Were done with Chapter Seven .
We open a file,
we read the file,
we take out white space
at the end with r strip,
we used string functions.
So this is kind of
putting it all together
and it's kind of short little
programs now, so it's not--
and you know,
starting now, we're
going to start putting
these things together
and start actually
doing work because now
we have from the
first few chapters
we have basic
capabilities of Python,
now we have some
data to work with.
Going forward we're going to
do increasingly sophisticated
things with that data.
So I can't wait to see
you in the next lecture.