https://youtu.be/6KgArgGi6Mk
for ourselves at the end.
Finding the average of
a sequence of values
is the combination of the
two previous patterns.
This time, I'm going to use
more mnemonic variables.
Other variable called count,
everyone calls this count.
Sum, now, total would maybe
be a better word for this.
The running total.
And then the count and
the sum start out at zero.
And then each time
through the loop,
count equals count plus 1,
so we're adding one to count.
Sum equals sum plus
value, so we're
adding one to sum-- I
mean, adding the value.
Value, of course, being
9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15.
And then at the very end,
we can print out the number.
We have six things
with a total of 154,
and then we calculate
the average.
Of course, these
are integer numbers.
And so this is a
truncating division.
So 154 over 6 equals 25,
and not 25 point something.
If we were in Python 3000,
Python 3, it'd be better.
So the integer averages of the
numbers we just looked at it
is 25.
So sometimes we're
searching, like for a needle
in a haystack.
Looking for something.
And again, you have to
think of, like, your hand
is some amount of
data, and you've
got to hunt for something.
And there might be
a million things,
and you might only
want five of them.
And you can use
look by hand, or you
can write a loop that's got
an if statement that says
found it.
Maybe I found it at line
seven, or found it wherever.
So this is filtering, or
finding, or searching,
looking for a needle in
a haystack in a loop.
And so the idea basically
is that we have this loop.
It's going to go through all
the values, 9, 41, 12, 3, 74.
But we put in the loop,
we embed an if statement.
If the value we're looking
at is greater than 20,
print I found it.
So when value is nine, this
is going to do nothing.
And just go and
make value be 41.
And then value 41,
oh, yup, there we go.
Print large number,
so off this comes.
Then value becomes
12, nothing happens.
Value becomes three,
nothing happens.
Value becomes 74, oops, this
time it's going to happen.
So out comes large number 74.
Then value becomes
15, nothing happens.
And then value is all done.
And so it comes and finishes.
So this is the searching,
or filtering, or catching,
or whatever.
We can also, if we don't just
want to print everything out,
we want to say, is
something in there?
We'll look through
this million things
and tell me if blah exists.
And in this, we're
going introduce
the notion of Boolean variable.
Boolean is a true/false.
It only has two values,
and we've already
used it in the wild, true.
So that capital True,
that is a constant.
Just like seven, or
42, or 99, or Sam.
And so we're going to make
this variable called found.
Now found is mnemonic variable,
it's just a name I picked.
So found equals False.
This is going to be false until
we find what we're looking for,
and then it's going
to switch to true.
So it starts out
and it's false, then
we're going to run this
bit of code three times.
And if the value that we
are looking at is three,
then we're going to
set found to be true,
and we'll print found
value each time through.
So value's going to take
on 9, 41, 12, 3, 74,
so we get a line of
output for each one.
And the first time
through, it's not
yet found, because
we're looking at a nine.
Second time, we've
not yet found,
we looked at 41, still false.
So it can stay false
for a long time.
Oh, we found a true.
And then that means that this
code's going to run once.
And so you can think of this
found variable as sticky.
It's going to stay false,
and then the rest of the loop
it's going to stay true,
and at the end it is true.
Now the way we usually do
these kinds of things is we
don't bother with
this print statement,
so we wouldn't see
all this stuff.
All we see is before
false, after true.
And after it would just tell
us that, yeah, we found it.
There was a three somewhere
in that long list of numbers.
I'm just adding this print
statement so we can trace it.
But basically, this
loop from here to here
is asking the question, is there
the number three in the list
that we're about to go through?
Now I'll just give you a second
and ask you a quick question.
You can pause if you want.
How could you improve
this loop using the break?
Where might you put a break
to make this loop smarter?
It's OK if it didn't
jump out at you.
So if you think about
it, once you hit true,
there's really little point in
looking at the rest of them.
There just is no point.
So we could put a break right
here, inside this block.
You say, look, I'm
looking for a three.
All I care is whether
I found it or not.
If I find it, I mark it
to true that I found it,
and I get out of the loop.
Why bother?
Why do all these things?
Just get out.
So don't worry about it,
I'm just pointing that out
that that's one of the places
where break could be used.
The loop functions
either way, it just
looks through all the
rest of them as well.
OK.
So here's this largest
value one I've used before.
And away we go.
We have largest so
far, we check to see
if the one we're
looking at is better.
And if it is, we keep
it, and then away we go.
And then we find
the largest is 17.
What if, what would you
have to change in this code
to make this search for the
smallest of all the values?
Point where in the
screen, what would you
have to change to make
this look for the smallest
in the list of values?
What's making this
about being largest?
What would you have to change?
OK.
Pause if you like.
So here is some things
that you might do
to make it work about smallest.
So hey, one thing
we would do, let's
change the name of the variable.
We had a variable
named largest so far,
and now we'll change it to
be called smallest so far.
Changing the variable name
doesn't change the program
at all.
But it makes the program easier
to read if the program works.
So it's like smallest so far.
But that didn't make
it about being small.
The thing that made
about being small
is change this greater
than to a less than.
Because we're
thinking when we're
doing largest so far, if
the number we're looking at
is bigger than largest
so far, we keep it.
If the number looking
at in the smallest
is smaller than the smallest so
far, then we want to keep it.
So this is like keep.
This line here is
the keeping line.
And this is the when
line, when to keep.
We'll keep it if it's smaller.
So that's the key.
And so, yeah, so I name it
smallest so far, whoopdy doo.
That's good.
But the real thing that had this
being about largeness smallness
was whether this is less
than and greater than,
and this was the
repeated code that got
rechecked over and over again.
But this still has a bug in it.
So let's run this visually.
So now we've got a variable
called smallest so far.
We are going to check to
see if a series of numbers
that I'm about to show you
are smaller than the smallest
so far.
So the first number is 9.
Is that's smaller
than negative 1?