https://youtu.be/6KgArgGi6Mk
and handling all this,
and then we're done.
And so if you look at it, we
have an iteration variable,
but we didn't have
to increment it,
we didn't have to do anything.
Python took care of a
lot of things for us.
And so when we're looping
through known list of things,
or later when we
read a file, we're
going to loop through
the lines in the file.
And so the for loop is
a really nice, powerful,
and its syntactically cleaner.
It's really quite nice.
Now it's important to
realize that you don't have
to just loop through numbers.
I did that one with a set
of descending numbers,
so that was equivalent
to the while loop
that I started at beginning.
But this is a loop where what
it's going to loop through
is a list-- closed square
brackets are a list in Python.
This is a list of three strings,
Joseph, Glenn, and Sally.
They're string constants,
and then commas
are how we make lists.
And so friends is a
mnemonic variable.
Python doesn't know anything
about friends in particular,
but I've chosen this
variable name to be friends.
And it's a list of three
people, Joseph, Glenn and Sally.
And so I have an iteration
variable called friend,
and I'm going to loop
through this set of friends.
Now, Python doesn't know
anything about singular,
Python doesn't know
anything about plural.
I'm just choosing
these variable names
because it makes a lot of sense.
This is a set of friends,
because it has three of minute,
and this is a single friend.
What it's really
going to do is friend
is going to take on the
successive values Joseph, Glenn
and Sally, and this
little block of code
is going to run once for each
of those three items in the set.
And the variable
friend is going to take
on the successive
values of that set.
So out of this comes three lines
of print out, happy new year
Joseph, happy new year
Glenn, happy new year Sally.
Of course, this is the
i bit right over here.
But we just made it so,
hey Python, look, however
many friends there are, run
this code one time for each one.
Change this variable,
friend, to be each
of the success ones in order.
And then we print
that we're done.
OK.
So the for loop, we
go and try to make
a picture of the for loop.
The for loop's kind
of a powerful thing.
It does two things.
It decides if we're
done or not, how
do we keep going in the loop.
And as long as we
keep going, we're
going to advance the i value,
the iteration variable.
It takes care of the
responsibility of changing
the iteration variable, we do
not have to add lines of code
in that change the
iteration variable.
And so if we take a look,
we come in, are we done?
We're not done.
Set i to the right
thing, then print it.
Out comes 5, advanced
i, advance i.
Print it, advance it, print
it, advance it, print it.
Oh, now we're done.
i was not the thing that
decided when we were done.
The for loop just
keeps track internally
as i moves through these things
and goes, oh, I'm all done.
I'll take care of that.
You finished.
So there's no if in here.
It's not like, if
i equals 1, stop.
No, no.
It just says, you told
me to do five things,
I'm going to do five things,
and then we're going to stop.
And so again, the for loop
here has got two functions.
Decides how long the
loop's going to run,
and changes the
iteration variable
based on what you've told
it to in this in clause.
So I think in is a
real elegant construct.
It's just a key word, but
if you think about math,
if you're familiar
with sets, it's
like something inside
of a set of something.
I think it's a real pretty
way to think about it.
And you can think
of a little more
abstractly, that you
say, well, here's
a little indented block of code.
And I want it to run some number
of times, for each of the i
values in the set, five,
four, three, two, one.
That's how I think of it.
So I think this is a
real pretty syntax.
Different languages have
different looping syntax.
I think this is really a very
expressive, very pretty one.
So one way to think about this
picture is that the for loop
causes repeated execution, and
we're driving in this circle.
and then we stop.
The other way to
think about this
is to think about it a
little more abstractly.
To say, hm, at the end of
the day, all I'm really
telling Python is I want to
execute this block of code
five times, and I want
the variable i to change
to these three values.
So in a way, you
could think of this
as expanded is the for
loop sets it to five,
then runs your code.
The for loop then sets it
to four, runs your code.
The for loop sets it to
three, runs your code.
For loop sets it to two, runs
your code, sets it to one,
runs your code.
These two ways of looking
at it are the same
from your perspective,
because you're just
asking Python to do something.
Whether it does it this way or
whether it does it this way,
you hardly can tell
the difference.
It's probably going
to do it this way.
But logically it's
not that different.
It's not different
from doing it this way.
You're saying run
this block of, code
change i in the following way.
Cool.
It's like we don't
have to worry.
I mean, we can use mentally
either model of what's
going on inside, because
it doesn't matter,
because they're the same.
OK, so these definite
loops are really cool.
Starting in a
couple of chapters,
we'll mostly use definite
loops to go through lists,
or dictionaries, or
tuples, or files.
And so it's a finite
set of things.
It can be a large set
of things, but it's
a finite set of things.
OK.
So now I want to talk
about loop idioms.
Loop idioms are how
we construct loops.
And the loops have some
kind of a goal in mind.
Finding the largest,
we've played with that.
Finding the smallest,
counting the number of things.
Looking for lines that
start with pound signs,
something like that.
They have a high level view of
what they're supposed to do,
and then we have to build
a loop to accomplish that.
And and this goes back to how we
have to think like a computer.
We have to say, hey computer,
do this over, and over,
and over again,
and then I'll get
what I want when you've done
that over, and over again.
You have to do something
a million times.
I'm not going to
sit here and wait.
At the end, I'll
get what I want.
So I call these smart loops,
or how to build intelligence
into loops.
So for example, we want
the largest number.
But we have to
construct a loop that
will get us the largest number
thinking like a computer.
Thinking computationally
So idea is that we have
some kind of a loop,
and we're going to through
some list of things,
and this is going to
run a bunch of times.
But the way we're
going to do it is we're
going to set something up
before the loop starts,
we're going to do something
to each of the things that's
being looked at.
And at the end,
we're going to get
the result we're looking for.
And so in the
middle, it's working,
it's in the middle working.
And then here is the payoff.
The payoff is at the end when we
get the information that we're
interested in.
So I will use in the next few
examples this simple loop.
And right now, it
doesn't do much.
It does a print before, and it
has this variable thing that
goes through the successive
values of these numbers,
and it prints it out.