https://youtu.be/FS-WZWUlPlM
run this little
indented code once
for each item in the
collection and key
then becomes our
iteration variable,
and key is very mnemonic here.
It doesn't know
that they're keys.
And so keys, the key here,
is that there's a bit,
the important concept
here is that dictionaries
are key value pairs.
And so this is only
one variable and so
it actually decides
that they've decided
it goes through the keys,
which is actually quite useful.
So key is going to take
on the successive, values
of the labels, not the
successive values of the value
stored at the labels.
But it's really easy for
us to retrieve the contents
at that label, counts sub key.
So we're going to use the key
chuck, fred, jan to look up
the 140 to 100 and so it
prints out the key and then
the value added, the
key and the value added,
and the key and the value.
And so we're able to sort
of go through the dictionary
and look at all the
key value pairs, which
is the common thing that
you really want to do.
OK?
Now there's some methods
inside of dictionaries
that allow us to
convert dictionaries
into lists of things and so if
you simply take a dictionary,
so here's a little dictionary
with three items in it,
and we can say list sub and then
give a dictionary name, right
there, and then that
converts it into a list
but it's just a
list of the keys.
We can also say jjj dot keys,
kind of do the same thing,
say give me a list
consisting of the keys.
And then jjj dot values gives
you a list of the values.
142 and a 100.
Of course they're not
in the same order.
Now interestingly,
as long as you
don't modify the dictionary,
the order of these two things
corresponds, as long
as in between here
you're not changing it.
So the first jan maps to
100, chuck maps to one,
and fred maps to 42.
So the order, you
can't predict the order
they're going to come out but
these two things will come out
in the same order whatever
that order happens to be.
OK and so there's
one more thing.
So we got the keys,
we've got the values,
and we have a
thing called items.
Items also returns a list.
It's a list, but it's a list
of what Python calls, tuples.
That's what the next
chapter is about.
We'll talk more about
tuples in the next chapter.
A tuple is a key value pair.
So this list has
three things in it.
One, two, three.
The first one is
jan maps to a 100,
the second one is
chuck maps to one,
the third one is
fred maps to 42.
So just kind of bear
with me for a second,
we'll hit this a little
harder in the next chapter.
But the place that the city
and more this works really
beautifully is on a for loop.
Now for those of you who have
programmed in other languages,
this will be kind of weird.
Because other languages
have iterations.
But they don't have two
iteration variables.
Python has two
It can be used for
many things but one
of the things that
it's used for,
that's really quite nice is
we can have two iterations
variables, this jj items
returns pairs of things,
and then aaa and
bb are iteration
variables the sort of
move in, is synchronized,
are synchronized as
they move through.
So aaa takes on the value of
the key, bbb takes on the value.
And then the loop runs ones then
aaa is advance to the next key,
and bbb is advanced to the
next value simultaneously,
synchronized.
Then they print that
out then it advances
to the next one, and the next
one, and they print that out.
So they are moving in
a synchronized way.
Now again the order Jan,
Chuck, Fred is not the same,
but the correspondence
between Jan 100, Chuck one
and Fred, that's going to work.
And so basically
as these things go,
they work their way
through whatever order
they're stored in
the dictionary.
So this is quite nice.
Two iteration variables
going through key value.
Now if I was making
these names mnemonic,
and they made more
sense, I would
call this the key variable and
that be the value variable.
But for now, I'm just
using kind of silly names
to show you that key and
value are not special,
they're not Python
reserved words in any way,
they're just a good way to name
these things key value pairs.
OK.
OK, now we're going to
circle all the way back
to the beginning, all the way
back to the first lecture.
And I gave you this program,
I said don't worry about it,
will learn about it later.
Well now later.
At this point, you should
be able to understand
every line of this program.
This is the program
that's going to count
the most common word in a file.
So let's walk
through what it does
and hopefully by now this
will make a lot of sense.
OK
So we're going to
start out, we're
going to ask for file name.
You're going to open
that file for read,
then because we know it's
not a very large file, we're
going to read it all in one
go, so handle dot read says,
read the whole file new lines
and all, blanks, new lines,
whatever, and put it in
a variable called text.
Just mnemonic,
remember I'm starting,
this one I'm using
mnemonic variable names,
then go through that
whole string, which
was the whole file.
Go through and split it all.
New lines don't hurt it, new
lines are treated like blanks,
and it understands all that,
it throws the new lines away
and the blanks
away and splits it
into a beautiful list of
just words with no blanks.
In the list of the
words in that file
ends up in the variable words.
Words is a list, text is
a string, words is a list.
Then what I do is the pattern
of accumulating counters
in a dictionary.
I make an empty dictionary,
I have the word variable
goes to all the words, and
then I just say counts of word
equals counts word dot get.
Word comma 0 plus 1.
That, like we just
got done saying,
it both creates and or
increments the value
in the dictionary as needed.
So now at this point
in the program,
we have a full dictionary
with the word colon count.
OK, and there's many them.
All the words all the counts.
Not in any particular order.
So now what we're
going to do, is
we're going to write
a largest loop.
Find the largest, which is
another thing we've done.
So not only do I
not need know what
the largest count
I've seen so far,
I need to know
what word that is.
So I am going to set
the largest count we've
seen so far to none,
set the largest
word we've seen so far
to none, and then I'm
going to use this two
iteration variable
pattern to say go through
the key value pairs, word,
and count.
In counts item, so it's going
to just go through all of them
and then I'm going to ask,
if the largest number I've
seen so far is none, or
the current count that I'm
looking at, is greater
than the largest I've
seen so far, keep them.
Take the current word stick
it and biggest word so far,
take the current account stick
it in the biggest count so far.
So this is going to run through
all of the word count pairs,
word count key value pairs,
and then when it comes out,
it's going to print out the
word that's the most common
and how many times.
So if we feed in that context
it will run all this stuff
and print out, Oh the,
is the most common word
and appeared seven times.
Or if I print the stuff
that was two slides back,
words dot txt from
the actual textbook,
then it says the word
two is the most common
and happened 16 times.
So I could easily throw 10
million, 10 million words
through this thing and it
would just be totally happy.
Right?
And so this is not that
complex of a problem,
but it's using a whole bunch of
idioms that we've been using.
The splitting of
words, the accumulation
of multiple counter and a
dictionary, and so it's sort of
is, the beginning of doing
some kind of data analysis
that's hard for humans
to do, and error
prone for humans to do.
And so this is we're
reviewing collections,
we've introduced dictionaries.
We've done the most common
word pattern, talked
about that, a lack
of order, I get
that a bunch of times,
and we've looked ahead
at tuples, which is the next,
the third kind of collection
that we're going to
talk about and they're
actually in some ways a little
simpler than dictionaries,
and simpler than lists.
So see you in the next lecture.
Chapter 10, tuples.