https://youtu.be/6KgArgGi6Mk
So that middle part says,
run this six times, once
for each of those
values, and then after.
And so we will add some
intelligence at the beginning,
we'll add some
intelligence in the middle,
and we'll add some
intelligence at the end.
And then the whole thing
will accomplish what we want.
Right now this is
not that intelligent.
So now what I want to do is
I want to review the thing
we did, and I want you to
remember what the largest
number is, and I'm
going to show you
a sequence of numbers in order.
Ready?
I'll do it quickly because
you've seen this before.
So I'm only showing you
one number at a time,
so you want to tell me
what the largest number is,
so here we go.
The first number is 9.
The second number is 41.
The third number is 12.
The fourth number is 3.
The fifth number is 74.
And the six number is 15.
So what was the largest number?
Did you have to go back, or
did you remember how to do it?
Well, I will give you a clue.
It was 74.
That's because I know.
Now if you did that,
and you had to do
that for 20 or 30
numbers, you'd have
to create a mental
algorithm in your head
to approach it and
stay concentrated.
Focused.
So you would have create a
variable in your head called
largest so far.
I would show you the first
number, which would be nine.
And you would go, well, nine
is larger than negative one,
so I will keep that.
That's the new largest I've seen
so far, that's pretty awesome.
Because it's way better
than negative one.
41, I thought nine was good.
But 41, that is a lot better.
So I'm going to keep that one.
That's the best.
It's the largest
we've seen so far.
We've only seen two numbers,
but the best we've seen so far
is 41.
So 12.
That's not larger.
Who cares about that?
It's not as big as 41, so we'll
just go right on to the next.
On to the next.
Three.
That's lame when we're
looking for large numbers.
So we skip.
Whoa, 74.
That's a rockingly large number.
So that's actually the
largest we've seen so far.
Because it's bigger than 41,
and 41 was the former champion
largest we've seen so far.
And there's 74, so
we keep that one.
I don't know how many of these
things we're going to see.
We could see lots of them.
But the next one we see 15.
Well, that's no good.
We got 74 already, 74 is,
like, totally awesome.
So now, oh, we're done.
So hey, we're done.
And so 74 is the champion.
That is the largest.
It's not even the
largest so far anymore,
it's actually the largest.
It's the largest.
So again, we had this
thing at the top,
we had this loop in the middle.
At the bottom is where
you get the payoff.
And the payoff is
not in the middle.
While we're largest so far,
largest so far, largest so far.
But at the end, it
turned out once you've
looked at all the
variables, all the values,
the largest so far is,
indeed, the largest.
OK, so here's the
algorithm for this.
I have some variables.
And remember that
underscores are
valid characters in variables.
I'm being a little
over explicit in this.
So I have a variable
called largest so far.
And what I do is I set
it to negative one.
Then I print before, so
we can see that largest
so far is negative one.
Then we have a for loop, and my
iteration variable is the_num.
So that's going to
take on the successive
values 9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15, and
run this indented loop of code.
And so the_num will be
nine first time through.
If the_num, 9, is greater
than largest so far,
then grab the_num and assign
it into largest so far.
Then print at the end of
each loop largest so far
and the_num.
So in effect, the_num is nine.
We compare it to negative
1, and nine is higher.
So we make largest
so far be nine.
Next time through
the loop, num is 41.
So we compare largest
so far with 41,
and we like it, so we store it.
So we like it, we run
it, and we print out,
41 is the largest
we've seen so far.
Then we run again.
We come in, the_num
points to 12.
The_num, 12, is not greater
than 41, and so we skip.
So the largest so far
stays 41, and we see 12.
Similarly, the_num
advances to three.
We skip.
So we saw three, but the
largest so far is still 41.
Continuing, the_num is now 74.
It runs.
74 is greater than 41.
And so we run this code.
And so we say, 74 is
stuck in largest so far.
And indeed, then
we print it out.
And largest so far is now 74.
We continue on.
We go up more time.
the_nu, points to 15, but
15 is not larger than 74.
And so we skip, we print out 15
and 74, and then we come out.
And at the end, we get
the largest so far.
The name no longer-- I mean,
largest so far at the end
is the largest, but
the variable name.
OK.
Got it?
That's one idiom.
So let's just switch
to another idiom.
Now counting.
How many things are we
going to, how many times
is loop going to execute,
how many things are we
going to find in the loop?
It's all the same notion.
And the pattern
is really simple.
We start some variable, zork.
A better name for
this would be count,
but I want to call it zork.
And then we have a loop.
And then in the loop,
we just add one to zork.
And at the end,
zork-- that should
be light blue right there.
Zork should be the total count.
Now of course, we can look at
it and say it's going to be six.
But assume this loop is
looping through a million lines
in a file, or
something like that.
So it's cheating to look at
it and say, oh, it's six.
Because we want to
actually compute it.
So it's really simple.
Zork starts at zero.
It's going to run,
zork is one now,
and two, three, four,
five, six, and then
we've run out of stuff,
and then we print out six.
So that's the idiom.
Before, during, and after.
We do something before,
we do something during.
And in a sense,
this zork here is
the number we've seen so far.
And at the end, it
becomes the total number.
Summing in the
loop, very similar.
Again, you have to think
of this as, there's
a whole bunch of variables here.
We start a variable at zero.
Each time through the
loop, we add whatever
it is that we're seeing.
Instead of adding one, we're
adding 9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15.
And zork would be best
thought of as running total.
So zork is the running total.
And so if you look at the
numbers, running total's nine,
numbering total's 50, running
total's 62, 65, 130, and 154.
And then we skip
out, and at the end
the running total
becomes the total.
So that's another
of these patterns
that we do something
at the beginning,
we do something in the middle,
and we have something very nice