https://youtu.be/nO8eU3uts0o
Hello and welcome to
chapter eight, Python Lists.
So now we're sort of going to
start taking care of business.
We are going to make lists
and dictionaries and tuples
and really start
manipulating this data
and doing real data analysis--
laying the ground work
real data analysis.
As always, these lectures,
audio, video, slides,
and even book are copyright
Creative Commons attribution.
So lists, dictionaries
and tuples,
the next real three big
topics we're going talk about,
are collections.
And we've been doing
lists already, right?
We've been doing lists when
we were doing for loops.
A list in Python is something
that has square braces.
This is a constant list.
Now when I first talked
to you about variables,
I sort of oversimplified things.
I said if you put
x equals 2 and then
put x equals 4, the 2 and
the 4 override each other.
A collection is where you
can put a bunch of things
in the same variable.
Now I have to have a way
to find those things,
but it allows us to put more
than one thing in a variable.
And so here we have friends,
that has three strings, Joseph,
Glenn and Sally and
we have carryon,
it has socks, shirt and perfume.
So that's the basic idea.
So what's not a collection?
Well, simple variables.
Simple variables
are not collections.
Just like this example,
I say, x equals
2 x equals 4 and print
x and the 4 is in there
and the 2 is somehow gone.
It was there for a moment
and then it's gone.
And so that's a normal variable,
they're not collections,
you can't put more
than one thing in it.
But when you put more
than one thing in it,
then you have to
have a way to find
the things that are in there.
We'll get to that.
So we've been using
list constants
for the last couple
of chapters just
because we have to use
list constants, you know?
So we used it in the
For loop chapter,
we did list of numbers.
We have done lists
of strings, t that's
strings red, yellow and blue.
And you don't have
to necessarily have
to have things all
of the same type.
This is three item list
that has a string red,
the number integer
24 and 98.6 which
is a floating point number.
Here's an interesting
thing just as a side note,
this shows that floating
point numbers are not always
perfectly represented
inside of the computer,
it's sort of an artifact
of how they work.
And this is an example of
98.6 is really 98 point
na-na-na-na-na.
So when you see something
like that, don't freak out.
Floating point numbers are the
ones that show this behavior.
So interestingly,
you can always--
although we won't
put a lot of energy
into this-- you can also
have an element of a list,
be a list itself.
So this is a outer list that's
got three elements: 1, 7
and then a list that's 5 and 6.
So if you look at
the length of this,
there is three things in it.
Not four, three, because the
outer list has one, two, three,
things in it.
An empty list is
bracket, bracket, OK?
Like I said, we have been
going through lists all along,
we have iteration variables
For i in, this is a list,
we've been using it all along.
Similarly, we've
been using lists,
indefinite loops are a great way
to go through lists for friend
in friends, there we have goes
through three times, outcome
three lines with the
variable friend advancing
through the three
successive items in the list
and away we go.
So again, lists are not
completely foreign to us.
Now just like in
a string, we can
use the index operator, the
square bracket operator,
and we can look up items in
the list-- Sub 1, friend sub 1.
Not surprisingly, using
the European elevator rule,
the first item in
a list is sub 0.
The second item is sub 1,
and the third one is sub 2.
So here when I
print friend sub 1,
I get Glenn, which is
the second element.
Just like strings-- so once you
kind of know it for strings,
lists and the rest of these
things make a lot more sense.
Just remember that
we're in Europe,
and things start with 0.
Some things in these data
items that we work with
are not mutable, so
for example, strings:
When we ask for a lowercase
version of a string,
we're given a copy
of that string
and that's because
strings are not mutable.
And we can see this by doing
something like saying, fruits
sub 0 equals lowercase b.
Now you'd think
that, that would just
change this to be a lowercase
b but it doesn't, OK?
It says string object
does not support
item assignment, which
means that you're not
allowed to reassign.
You can make a new string
and put different things
in that string but once
the strings are made,
they're not changeable and
that's why we call fruit.lower,
we get a copy of
it in lowercase.
And so x is a copy of
the original string
but the original string,
once we assign it into fruit,
is unchanged-- can't be changed.
This on the other
hand, can be changed
and we can change
them in the middle.
This is one of the things
we like about them.
So here we have a list:
2, 14, 26, 41 and 63.
Then we say lotto
sub 2, of course
that is going to
be the third item,
lotto sub 2 is equal to 28.
Then we print it and we
see the new number there.
So all this is saying, is that
we can change them, right?
Strings no, and lists yes.
You can change lists but
you can't change strings.
So the lend function, we've
used it for several things--
we can say lend is
used for strings
and it's used for lists as well.
So the same function knows
when its parameter is a string
and when its
parameter is a string,
it gives us the number of
characters in the string
and when it is a list, it
gives us the number of elements
in the list.
And just because one
of them is a string,
it's still one element from
the point of view of this list
so it has one, two, three, four,
four items in the list, OK?
So the range function
is a special function,
it's probably about time to
talk about the range function.
The range function
is a function that
generates a list, that produces
a list and gives it back to us.
And so you give
the range function
a parameter, how
many items you want,
and the range function
creates and gives us
back a list that is four numbers
starting at 0, which is 0 up to
but not including, 3.
Sound familiar?
Yeah.
0 up to but not including 4.
And so the same
thing is true here.
So we can combine the
lend and the range
to say OK, we'll lend
friends, that's three items
and range lend
friends is 0, 1, 2.
And it also corresponds
exactly to these items.
So we can actually
use this to construct
loops to go through a list.
We already have a
basic For loop, right?
We basically have a For
loop for each friend
and friends and outcomes, Happy
New Year Glenn and Joseph.
If we also want to know
what position we're at
as the loop progresses,
we can rewrite
the exact same loop
a different way
and make i be our iteration
variable and say i in range
lend friends, that turns this
into 0, 1, 2, and then i goes
0, 1, 2, and then
we can in the loop,
look up the
particular friend that
is the particular one
we're interested in,
using the index
operator, friends sub i
and then print Happy New Year.
So these two loops
are equivalent.
This loop and this loop.
This loop is preferred unless
you happen to need this value
i, which tells you where you're
at, in case maybe you're going
to change something, you're
going to look through something
and then change it.
So for what I've written here,
they're exactly equivalent.
Prefer the simpler one unless
you need the more complex one,
they both produce the
same kind of output.
We can concatenate lists much
like we concatenate strings
with a plus.
And you can think of the Python
operators looking to its right
and to its left and saying,
oh, those are both lists,
I know what to do with lists,
I'm going to put those together
and so that produces a two,
three long lists become a six