https://youtu.be/Wdi6lhcrtBU
Now, this is not sort
of a profound reason
to use it in this.
I'm just trying to give
you the notion that there
is a way to store and
name code that then you
can retrieve later.
That's really what's
going on here.
So there's two kinds of
functions inside of Python.
And we've actually
been using them almost
from the very first lecture.
And that is, there
a built-in functions
that Python provides to us
like float, raw input, int,
those kinds of functions.
Those are just part of Python,
but we call them as functions.
The difference is
we don't write them.
And then, there's
user-defined functions,
functions that we
write, functions
to create functionality
that we want
to make use of like
encapsulating the ability
to compute pay for time
and a half for overtime.
And so we name these
things, and we treat them
as new reserved words
that we've created.
They're kind of an extension
to the language as it were.
So when we're coming
along, we define a function
with the def keyword.
The def keyword is
a reserved word.
It's one of the many reserved
words back in chapter one
that we talked about.
And it indicates to Python
the beginning of a function.
We define it.
And then when we call
it, it's called invoking.
It's like we're building
it and then we're invoking.
And you can build it
once and then invoke it
many, many times.
So for example, here's
a built-in function
called max that
finds the largest
character-- the sort
of lexigraphically
larger character-- in a string.
And so it's like, OK, tell
me the maximum character.
And so max is not some
code that we've written.
But we are invoking
a function here.
And we're passing in
an argument to that.
So the argument is the stuff
in between the parentheses.
So the max function
can find the maximum
of many different things.
At this moment,
we wanted to find
the maximum of that particular
string, the highest character
in that particular string.
So this is a right-hand side
of an assignment statement
too, so that has to be
evaluated to a value.
So it goes into the function,
does whatever it thinks
the function wants to do.
And then, the function
gives us back a value
that becomes the value for
max parentheses Hello world.
And that value, in this
case, is the letter w.
Because the letter w is decided
to be the highest letter,
and that's what
max gives us back.
And then, we're
done with that, then
that w ends up being assigned.
The assigned
statement completes.
And so you can think of
the function evaluation
as happening as part of the
right-hand side expression
calculation.
There could be a plus
here and other stuff.
And it's just at some
point a big expression.
And this one, it's a simple
expression with just one
function call.
Now, if we look at this,
there's some code somewhere.
Somebody wrote some code.
It's part of Python.
You didn't write it.
There's a max
function somewhere.
And you can think of a
function as having some input.
It's kind of like a program.
That's why some languages
call these things subprograms.
Because they have an input, they
do some kind of useful works--
whatever that useful
work happens to be.
And then, it produced
some kind of an output.
So Hello world is the input,
the string, the arguments,
the thing we're passing in.
Hello world is what's being
passed into the function.
The function is running.
And then, something comes
back and is sent back.
So it has input,
processing, and output.
So that's how a function,
some stored code--
whether we wrote it or
not-- they work the same
when we call functions.
So you could think of this as
somewhere inside of the Python
library is some code that maybe
has a little def in there.
And they named the function max.
And it takes a single parameter.
And it does some blah, blah,
blah, loopy, blah, blah, blah.
A lot of stuff.
Whatever max wants to do.
Whatever we need max to do
based on the specifications
that max is supposed to support.
But somewhere there is
code inside of Python
that actually represents
the function definition.
It's a built-in function,
because it comes with Python
and we didn't have to
do anything to add.
So some common
built-in functions
that we have been
using all along,
good examples are the float,
which takes as input anything
and returns you a floating
point number version of that;
type, which takes a parameter
of a variable or a constant
and says, what is the type of
this; float, again converting;
type, again; and float.
So these are all things that
we've been calling functions
all along.
And it passes the input
value into the function,
the function runs and
then gives us back
the return value,
which then participates
in the rest of the expression
on the right-hand side.
You can think of it's
pausing the calculation
on the right-hand side,
calling the function,
getting the result
of the function
back, and then
continuing the evaluation
on the right-hand side, then
coming up with whatever value,
and then printing
that value out.
Another thing that
we've done, is
we've done string conversions.
Right, so we've converted
in this case a string
to an integer.
And that's what type it is.
We've converted a
string to an integer.
So it converts its argument,
whatever that happens to be,
into an integer.
So that's just some of the
built in functions that we
have talked about so far.
Now this becomes
more interesting when
we can make our own functions.
There goes my tea bag.
Right in the middle
of the thing.
We take the tea bag out.
I think it's -- whoa.
I'll be right back.
OK, there's my tea.
So, we want to make
a new function.
As we said in the other
example, we use the Def keyword.
The Def keyword here, and then
we have some indented bit.
We create a name for it.
And then have some parentheses.
These parentheses will
later tell the inputs
that we're going to pass
in but this function has
no input so we just go
parentheses parentheses.
And then the all
important colon character,
which indicates the beginning
of an indented block of Python
that then is just the
text of the function.
So it's important to remember
that while this is executing,
when Python first
looks this it doesn't
run these lines of code.
It just remembers them and
names them print lyrics.
So it doesn't cause
any print out,