https://youtu.be/L2IUSArpG98
Hello and welcome to Chapter 6.
This chapter, we're going
to talk about strings.
And stuff is going to
start to get real now.
So as always, this material,
this video, these slides,
and what are copyright
Creative Commons attribution.
I want you to use
these materials.
I want to make more teachers.
So everyone can
teach this stuff.
Use it however you like.
OK, so we've been playing with
strings from the beginning.
I mean, literally, if we
didn't work with strings,
we could have never
printed "Hello, World."
And Lord knows we need
to print Hello, World
in a programming language.
And so, we've been using
them, especially constants.
Now in this chapter,
we're going to dig in.
Oops.
So a string is a
sequence of characters.
You can either use single quotes
or double quotes in Python
to delimit a string.
And so, here's two string
constants, hello and there,
and stuck into the variables
stir one and stir two.
We can concatenate them
together with a plus sign.
Python is smart enough to look
and say, oh, those are strings.
I know what to do with those.
And you'll notice that the plus
doesn't add any space here.
Because when we print
"Bob" out, hello and there
are right next to one another.
If for example, when
we're, like, reading
pay and rate and
hours and stuff,
we've done some conversions.
So this an example of a string
1-2-3, not 123, but the string,
quote, "123," quote.
And we can't add 1 to this.
We get a traceback.
We're kind of at this
point, as we expected.
And we would convert
that to an integer,
using the INT function
that's built in.
See how much Python
you already know?
I mean, this is awesome, right?
I can just say, oh, you
call the INT function,
and you know what that is.
Sorry, I'm just awesomed out.
So you convert
this to an integer.
And then, you add 1 to it.
And then, we get 124.
So there you go.
We've been doing strings
all along, had to.
I mean, literally,
strings and numeric data
are the two things that
programs deal with.
So we've been reading
and converting.
Again, this is a pattern from
some of the earlier programs
where we do a raw input.
And the raw input
just takes a string
and puts it in a variable.
So if I take "Chuck," then the
variable contains the string
C-H-U-C-K. Even if we type
numbers, that is a string.
Just because I put 1-0-0 in,
I still can't subtract 10.
We get a happy little traceback.
Oh, happy, little,
sad faced traceback.
But of course, if we convert
it INT or Float or something
like that, we can do
that and subtract 10.
And we can do that.
So we've been doing
this for a while.
We've been doing strings
and manipulating strings
and converting
strings all along.
So the thing we're
going to start doing now
is we're going to
dive into strings.
We realize that strings
are addressable at
a character-by-character basis.
And we can do all kind
of cool things with that.
And so, a string is a
sequence of characters.
And we can look inside them,
using what we call the index
operator, the square brackets.
And we've seen square
brackets in lists.
And you'll see that
they're similarities
between lists of numbers.
And in effect, a string
as a special kind of
list of characters.
So we take the string "banana."
The first character starts at 0.
So we call this operator, "sub."
So letter equals fruit sub 1.
And that is the
second character.
Now, this may seem
a little weird
that the first character is
a 0 and the second character
is a 1.
It actually is similar
to the old elevator thing
where, in Europe, the first
floor is zero, and then
negative one, and the
second floor is one.
All right.
It's kind of the same thing.
Actually, it turns out that
internally 0 is a better way
to start than 1.
You'll get used to it.
And then after a while, there's
some little cool advantages
to it.
But for now, just
beginning at 0.
It is the rule.
Just remember it.
OK, so the 0 is B,
the 1 is A, the 2
is N, et cetera, et cetera.
And we call this
syntax "fruit sub 1."
OK, so that is the sub
1 character of fruit.
And then, that is
an A. So that fruit
sub 1 says, look up in
banana, find the 1 position,
and give me what's
in that 1 position.
That's what the sub.
And what's inside these
brackets can be an expression.
So if we set N to 3, N minus
1, well, that'll compute to 2.
And then, fruit sub
2 is the letter N.
All right?
So that's fruit sub 2.
It's the third
character, fruit sub 2.
So the index starts at 0.
We read the brackets as sub,
fruit sub 1, fruit sub 2.
Now, Python will complain to
you if you use this sub operator
too far down the string.
Here is a character with
3, which is 0, 1, and 2.
And if we go to
sub 5, it blows up.
Now you know, by now, I hope
that you're not freaking out
about traceback errors.
Remember, traceback
errors are just
Python trying to inform you.
And if we just stop looking
at that as mean Python face
and instead look at that
as, oh, index error.
String index out of range.
Oh yeah, I stuck a 5 in there.
And there's only 3.
Ugh, my bad, thank you, Python.
Appreciate it.
Thanks for the help.
So think of this like--
it's not a smiley face.
But it's kind of like
a quizzical face.
Right, it's saying, eh, I
don't So Python is confused,
and it's trying to tell
you what is confused.
OK?
So don't look at
these as sad faces.
Python doesn't hate you.
Python loves you,
and loves me too.
So strings have
individual characters
that we can address
with the index operator.
They also have length.
And there is a built-in
function called Len
that we can call and pass in
as a parameter, the variable,
or a constant.
And it will tell us
how many characters.
Now, this banana has
six characters in it
that are 0 through 5.
So don't get a little confused.
The last character is sub 5, but
it's also the sixth character.
So the length is
really the length.
It's not length minus 1.
So Len is like a
built-in function.
It's not a function
we have to write.
As we talk about in
the functions chapter,
there are things that
are part of Python that
are just sitting there.