https://youtu.be/Wdi6lhcrtBU
it just causes Python
to remember them.
I've said that a
few too many times.
So here is a difficult
problem, I'll
let you think about
it for awhile.
I want you to kind of mentally
go through and execute
this code.
Ask what, ask yourself what
the output of this program
would produce.
How many lines?
How many lines of output
will this program produce?
So, how many of you said three?
How many of you said five?
Well, the right answer
is actually three.
You see five print statements
two, three, four, five.
But to of the print statements
are sitting inside of this.
And we never called, we never
invoked the function down here.
OK?
So this one --
let's clear this --
this one prints these
two get skipped,
this one prints and
this one prints.
So that's why there are
three statements that print.
There is, stored,
but we never used
a function called print lyrics.
And it's got two statements
in it, but we never used it.
So the output of this
is hello yo seven.
And that's because we
never actually invoked it.
We had to say print
lyrics parentheses
or whatever to cause
it to call this.
OK, that's just to emphasize
that as it looks at it,
it does not execute these lines.
So once we defined
a function, once we
have given it a name, given
it code that is part of it,
then we can invoke or call
it as many times as we like.
So now our little example works
a little better if we actually
call our function.
Python really doesn't care if
you don't call your functions.
Like, you told me to make one,
I made one, you didn't use it,
there you go.
But if you look at this one now.
So here we go.
X equals 5 print hello,
outcomes hello, define.
Nothing happens here.
Nothing happens here
it's just remembering.
OK then it says print go.
Then it calls the
function print lyrics,
which sort of stops us here.
Runs these two lines of code.
So out comes that and that.
Then it sort of finishes
this and it comes back,
x equals x plus 2.
Then it prints x.
That must mean x is 7,
and so out that comes.
And so, again it's on
the first time through --
go back go back go back --
on the first time through,
it doesn't print.
But then when it
hits this, it prints.
You could say print
lyrics several more times
and it would run this
as many times as it did,
and if it needed to as
many times as you want,
and it would make
output for you.
So you can invoke.
This is the definition
-- let's clear this --
this is the definition,
this is the call or invoke.
So we're invoking the function,
we're calling the function,
were causing the
function to execute.
Here we are just
causing the function
to be looked at and defined,
but not actually executed.
I hope that's clear.
Now, when we pass data into
a function, and functions
they don't take data are not
as useful as they could be.
There's plenty of
things that do,
times that you build a
function it doesn't take data.
But the most
interesting functions
are the ones that you could
hand them something to work on
and they can do their work and
then come back with whatever.
So this Max function is
a good example of this.
One that's taking an
argument, we call the things
in between the parentheses.
When we're invoking
the function,
we call the things in between
the parentheses arguments.
So that's passing
into the function,
feeding data into the function.
So we put arguments in between.
So for example here we
have a little program
that, it's a
function named greet.
And now we are going
to define this function
and we're going to
say, you know what?
I would like to
take a parameter.
Let's take a parameter.
Let's have one
parameter come in.
And we need kind of a
placeholder for that parameter
so within the function
we're going to use lang.
Now this isn't actually
a real variable.
It's kind of like a, it's
a placeholder variable.
So this first
parameter, whatever
it is, when it's called,
is going to be lang.
And so if that first
parameter is equal to es
we're going to print hola.
And if, else if it's equal
to fr we'll print bonjour.
And otherwise will print hello.
So there's apparently three
languages in the world;
Spanish, French, and English.
And if it's not Spanish or
French then it must be English.
But I have keep
this kind of small
so my screen
doesn't get too big.
So this is again
just the definition
and if you type this into
the interactive thing
it gives this dot
dot dot product.
And so we now have this
thing called greet.
And now we've extended Python to
add our own function to Python.
And now we can say greet en.
And so it runs this code,
except that en is lang.
And so that comes and
then it prints hello.
So out comes hello.
Now later we can say oh I
would like to do a greeting,
but this time I'm
going to pass es as it.
So lang becomes, for this
execution, es and then
it prints out hola.
And then the next
execution lang is fr.
So it executes this three
times, but lang is different
each time because we passed in
different parameters each time.
So that's how we can kind
of right general purpose
code inside the
function and then
reuse that general purpose
code in different ways.
A real powerful
powerful mechanism the
makes functions far more useful.
Now functions don't necessarily
just have to do stuff.
Real powerful
mechanism in a function
is what we call a return value.
So a function can
take its arguments,
do some work we've seen that.
And then, it can return a value.
And the key to the
return value is
when we call the function
like we were calling max,
it gives us back some
value like the little w.
So here we're going to
make a function called
greet that takes no parameters.
Don't take parameters.
But it has another keyword.
It's another reserved
word in Python
and whatever we put on
this return statement
shows up as the replacement
in this expression.
So whatever greet
is, it runs greet,
and then the return is
kind of a residual value.
So if we say print
greet, Glenn and it
says hello, Glenn
because the return
value for the greet function
is the string hello.