https://youtu.be/O0wE2M8-ois
Welcome to chapter 7, Python
for Informatics Exploring
Information.
I'm Charles Severance,
I'm the author
of the book and your host.
And as always this
is brought to you by,
no I'm sorry it is all creative
copyright Creative Commons
attribution, the audio, the
video, the slides, and even
the book.
So here we go, oh
and so frankly where
we've been working
all along, is we
have been writing code
and talking to the CPU,
hang on let me go get my CPU and
stuff hang on, be right back.
Ah.
OK here we go, here we go.
Here's all that stuff.
Remember that stuff
from the first lecture?
There we go with that.
Remember the mother board
from the first lecture?
This is kind of a
picture of what's
on the screen, the motherboard,
the CPU plugs in here,
memory plugs in here.
And remember how the CPU
is sort of the brains,
as much brains as there
is for the operation.
The CPU is asking what
next, the instructions
come in through
these little pins.
There's data inside
and it stores
sort of semi permanent data.
Variables are all stored
pretty much here in RAM.
And we write our programs,
and so your Python programs
they're sitting here
in this RAM in they're
being fed to this CPU,
through those chips,
through those pins
right the pins,
I mean it doesn't really
connect like that,
and so frankly up
to now everything
that we've been doing is
just the Python programming
language.
And so the only place we've
really been operating is here.
We have been putting
Python into the main memory
and-- the main memory, and we
have been effectively feeding
instructions to the CPU, the
central processing unit as it
needed them and the
program would stop.
And everything
we've done so far,
everything is just sort
of fiddling around here.
We have never escaped it.
So now we are finally
going to escape
from the central processing
unit and the memory.
We'll still write programs
and have variables in here,
but now we're going to use a
disk, the secondary storage,
the permanent media.
So if I go grab my Raspberry
Pi, that just goes right there,
here's my Raspberry Pi.
So here we've got
Raspberry Pi which
is the small version, which
of course has a CPU, memory.
and graphics processor all on
this little chip right here,
but the secondary
memory for the,
is this little SD card that
is the secondary memory
for Raspberry Pi.
So the structure
the Raspberry Pi
is exactly the same structure
any other personal computer,
it's just smaller
and less expensive.
And so in the
Raspberry Pi if you're
programming the
Raspberry Pi, you're
sort of finally escaping.
All your programs are in
here your CPU's in here,
and that's pretty much
how far you've got to run.
But now, of course when
you save your files you
save them to here.
But now we're going
to start looking
at data on the disk drive.
And so it's time to escape
to the secondary memory.
OK time to escape to
the secondary memory.
Oh Raspberry Pi you
can go right there.
OK?
So it's time to find
some data to mess with.
So a lot of what we've
been doing so far
is just kind of the pre
work to get to the point
where we can do this.
And in here we're going
to have data files.
Now we've been
making data files,
you've been writing-- every
Python program that you write
on your computer
gets saved as a file,
then Python reads
the file and runs it.
But, now we're actually going
to start messing with some data.
And so files are where we're
going to be working with.
And so, one of the things
about secondary memory,
is it's much larger.
And this main memory of
computer is pretty large,
it's just not large
enough to hold everything
that the computer is
capable of holding.
So the files that we're going to
work with, no we're not talking
about image files or
Quicktime movies or things
like that, we're going
to work with text files.
Because the theme of this
course is digging through text.
Sometimes we'll pull
it off the internet,
sometimes we'll
read files, but it's
digging through and using
all the things that we've
learned so far looping and
strings and all those things
to make sense of a
sequence of information.
OK?
Now to access file
information we
have to do this thing
called opening the file.
We can't just say,
yo the information
is just omnipresent,
because there
are so much data that you
can't have Python sort of know
all the data.
You literally have
hundreds of thousands
of files on your
computer's hard drive
and which one are
you going to read.
So there's a step
that you have to do,
but you call this built
in function, called open,
and say oh this is the
file I want to work with,
of the hundreds of
thousands, and then
once you do you've kind of got
this little connector into it.
And the open is a built
in function inside Python
so let's say goodbye to that.
The open function is built
in function in Python
and it takes two parameters.
The first parameter is the name
of the file, like M box dot txt
and then the second is how
you're going to read it.
Are you going to
read it are you going
to write it, et cetera,
now most the time we'll
be reading our files.
So we call the open
function, and pass it
in the name of the
file we want to open,
and then how we want to read it.
Now you can leave this
second parameter off
and it assumes that you're
going to want to read the file.
Now, when the open
is successful,
it doesn't actually
read all of the data,
because the memory is small,
small compared to a hard drive
so you have to sort of step
through the data you'll tell it
when to read it.
So the act of opening it is not
actually reading all the data
it is creating kind of like a
connection between the memory
and the data that's
on the hard drive,
right, it's connecting between--
that's going to fall down.
Are you going to
stand up that way?
Should come up with a
way to make that stand.
So it's a connection,
so that your programs
kind of running in here and the
file handle is just sort of a,
it's like a phone call between
your memory and your disk
drive.
It's not the actual
data, the actual data
is still sitting
on the disk drive.
OK, so a graphical way
to take a look at this,
is this file handle, the
thing that comes back
from the open request, the open
goes and finds the file out
on the disk drive
yada yada yada,
and then the handle
is something that
lives in the memory that is
sort of like the thing that
maintains its connection
to where all the data is
on the disk or on the
SD RAM that's in it.
So the handle is
not all the data,
but it is a mechanism that you
can use to get at the data.
So if you print
it out, it doesn't
have all the data from the file,
it says I am a file handle,
that's opened this file
and we're in read mode.
So it doesn't
actually have the data
even though this is the
data that's in the file.
And then we have
operations that we
do to the handle like open
it, close it, read it, write
it, so we do things to those.
So the handle, and then
through the handle,
it actually changes
what's on the disk
or reads what's on the
disk, so the handle
is kind of a thing
that's not there.
If you attempt to open a file,
and the name of the file--
now the way we're
going to do these
is, these need to be in the
same folder on your computer
as your Python code.
Now there are trickier
ways to do it,
but we're going
to keep it simple.
This is the name of a
file in the same folder,
as the Python code
that you're running.