https://youtu.be/Wdi6lhcrtBU
Hello, and welcome to Chapter
4, Functions, in my book Python
for Informatics.
As always, these slides and
this audio and this video
are copyright Creative
Commons attribution.
Now, we are to the point--
you know, in Chapter 4,
we're sort of well
into the class--
so I figure I should
introduce myself a little bit,
let you know a little bit.
As I said before, I
think in the beginning
I'm taping this in
a wonderful building
at the University of
Michigan called North Quad.
It's a relatively new building.
It's got some
residential sections
and some academic sections
and some classrooms.
And one of the classrooms
that I typically teach in
is actually 2255 North Quad.
It's a really beautiful
room with great ways
for people to interact.
And so sometimes I'm teaching,
you know, little tiny Dr. Chuck
down here, with a
smile on the face.
And sometimes, my students are
taking my classes on campus.
And sometimes, students are
watching me through a lecture.
And so this building
is really beautiful.
And if you ever get a
chance to come to Ann Arbor
and take a look at it,
maybe walk through it,
it's really quite nice.
One of the things
I like about it
is that I think
it's really highly
inspired by Harry Potter.
Of course, Oxford and Cambridge
are the real inspiration
for Harry Potter.
But our cafeteria, for
example, it kind of
looks like the four
tables in Hogwarts.
And you can kind of imagine
a snowy owl flying around
and a Sorting Hat at the
front sorting people.
And so the nickname
for the place
is Quad-warts, because
it's North Quad.
Quad-warts, that's like
Hogwarts and North Quad kind of
jammed together.
And of course, given that we
sort of think of ourselves
a little bit as Harry Potter,
people when they first
come in September, often sort
of decide to sort themselves.
And a few years back, when we
first started the building,
the students decided that I did
not get to be in Gryffindor.
As a matter of fact,
it's probably time for me
to show you who I am and
who I've been sorted to be.
So the students decided that
I couldn't be in Gryffindor,
but I had to be in Slytherin.
And that's because of my
name, Charles Severance,
and Severus Snape.
What's even cooler, of course,
is given that I teach Python,
Slytherin's House is a snake.
So it makes a lot of sense.
They even have this really
fancy Slytherin teacup
that I use to drink
tea during lectures.
Sometimes, I drink coffee.
Sometimes, I drink tea.
Wow.
This thing itches.
So let me just get rid of it.
If I had any hair, that
would mess my hair up.
So let me get rid of this
for the rest of the lecture.
So there I am.
OK.
Enough of that.
Back to Dr. Chuck.
So with that sort
of brief interlude,
the actual topic of this
lecture is functions.
And so storing and
reusing is basically
an idea that we will often
have a series of steps
that we will want to use
over and over in a program,
increasingly complex.
The things we'll
use in this lecture
are kind of silly,
because I have
to keep them short so the
slides don't get too long.
But a good example
of the kind of work
is maybe I'm going to use
Google's geocoding service.
And I'm going to send some
unstructured data back and get
a GPS coordinate back.
And that's a service
that I want to call.
And it would maybe be about
this many lines of code.
And I'm going to want to
that all over the place.
So do I want to put
this many lines of code
40 places in my program?
Or do I want to put
it one place and then
call it in the various
places that I need it?
And so that's why I call it the
store and the reuse function.
So if we take a look at
the simple syntax here,
these things are
called functions.
In some languages, they're
called subprograms.
But we call them
functions in Python.
And the keyword that we're
really going to focus on
is def, which stands for define.
And what happens here is when
Python sees this def keyword,
it actually doesn't
run the code.
It says, oh, you're
going to make a function.
And you're going to
turn on a recorder
and start recording this code.
So it has a colon
at the end of it.
So it has an indented
block afterwards.
And so the indented
block becomes recorded.
So instead of running
the code, like if we just
put print "Hello" and print
find: Fun," it would run it.
But instead says, hey,
don't run it right now.
Name it, "hello."
We give it a name.
It's kind like a variable.
We choose the name.
We've chosen hello
as the name of this.
Define it as hello.
Have it have these two
lines of Python in it.
And we'll use it later.
And so that's the
function definition.
That's the store phase.
It's sort of like it doesn't
really run those lines.
It sort of makes
a variable called
hello that actually
contains Python code rather
than containing 12 or
a string or something
like that we've
worked with before.
So this is the store part.
And then, the reuse part is
we then have extended Python.
We now can call our bit of code.
So we say, hello--
hello name is what
we came up with-- parentheses.
And then, that says--
remember that code
that I put in there
under the name hello?
Run it now.
And so if I start
looking at that and then
it just continues.
So let me clear this
and start over again.
And so if I watch what Python
does from the beginning
as it reads here
and goes, oh, you're
defining a function named hello.
Great.
I will remember, remember.
I've got that
remembered for you.
Let's continue on.
Oh, hello.
You want me to run that
stuff that you just got done
storing under the name hello.
So then, it kind of
goes and runs it.
And out comes Hello, Fun.
Then after that, it
runs to this print,
and then out comes print Zip.
Then, we say, you know what,
I want to reuse that again.
I stored it once.
I can resue it as
many times as I want.
And now, hello.
And then, these two lines
of code run a second time.
So we stored once,
gave them a name,
and then ran them
twice in the context
of wherever it is we wanted.