https://youtu.be/RvnzLwDluaM
The games in this course are designed to enable
you to experience specific kinds of unknowns
in environments where you can have some fun
and also learn about how to make choices in
situations where you don't have full information.
In the Gem Mining game you're down in a  mine
drilling for gems. You can choose between
two sites in which to drill, where gems clearly
are visible through the rock-face. However,
these sites may not be equally likely to yield
gems.
Let's take a look at the game itself, and
I'll give you a couple of tips about how to
play it.
Here we are, down in the mine.
You orient the drill with your mouse. It points
toward your cursor.
You move the drill with the four arrow keys
on your keyboard. They give you eight directions
in which to move the drill.
When you place the drill's tip over a gem,
you get it to drill by left-clicking your
mouse. Like this.
You'll see a shower of sparks and you'll hear
a drilling noise.
You'll also see the scoreboard recording the
number of drilling attempts at the site you've
chosen, and the number of hits of gems
that you've scored, in dollar amounts. You can see I've
scored five hits of Rubies out of twelve attempts.
You can choose to drill in two sites.
One of them, the Opal site, produces Opals
or nothing. But the Ruby site produces either
Rubies, or Quartz, or nothing.
Quartz doesn't have value, so although you
can see the number of times drilling yields
quartz, it doesn't add anything to your total
score. Only Opals and Rubies count towards
your score.
The game ends after you've made 300 drilling
attempts.
Well, that's all there is to the Gem Mining
game. It's really very simple. See if you
can figure out the best way to play this game.
Good luck.