https://youtu.be/hbaKJYFTVxM
In his review of Sarah Palin's book, "Going
Rogue", Jonathan Raban described it as a "four-hundred-page
paean to virtuous ignorance." What did he
mean by this phrase? Raban was referring to
the kind of homespun philosophy that is exemplified
by expressions such as "I don't know much
about art, but I know what I like." He characterized
it as a "commonsense conservatism" whereby
morally upright laypeople are better able
than experts to judge the merits of, say,
American foreign policy, because too much
expertise clouds judgment. Some commentators
opined that "virtuous ignorance" is just another
way of saying "anti-intellectual." But we'll
soon see that's an over-simplification. Once
we know what to look for, virtuous ignorance
turns up in lots of places, and not just among
right-wing politicians or, for that matter,
anti-intellectuals.
Here's an example that isn't attributable
to conservative politicians or anti-intellectuals.
In fact, it involves highly educated people.
Back in the 1970's I took a PhD in sociology.
My then fellow sociology graduate students
and I hadn't read any psychology beyond a
few works by Freud, but we all knew we hated
psychology, with the possible exception of
Freud. More than that, some of us also knew
that psychology was full of reductionist,
positivist, medical-model-following reactionaries
who were blind instruments of capitalism.
Eventually, however, my curiosity was piqued.
What was so evil about psychology? I decided
to find out. When I revealed to my peers and
professors that I had started taking a class
in psychology, my status immediately plummeted.
For them, not studying psychology indicated
superiority of intellect. True cognoscenti
would know better than to waste their time
learning about such an obviously reprehensible
discipline.
Years later, I ran across anecdotal evidence
that this view was not confined to students.
A psychologist colleague attended a seminar
by a very prominent sociologist, and was inspired
by the sociologist's portrayal of a revolutionary
future for the social sciences. However, he
was puzzled that no mention was made of psychology
or psychologists. Afterward, he approached
the professor and asked him how psychology
would fit into his vision of the future. The
sociologist replied that he had once, long
ago, taken a class in psychology but tried
not to think about that unfortunate lapse
in judgment. These days, I work in a psychology
department. Clearly, I have gone over to the
Dark Side.
I'm not picking on sociologists. Plenty of
examples are available in other disciplines.
Another psychologist colleague, very well
educated and highly intelligent, once confessed
to me that she was proud that she knew nothing
about economics. In these examples, ignorance
is made virtuous by converting it into a kind
of status marker. Professing ignorance of
the right things can be an indicator of high
status. In many societies, class and/or caste
distinctions have been partly based on this.
Not so long ago in English society, knowledge
of a mere craft or trade (versus an art or
discipline) was considered beneath nobility.
So the issue isn't in the decision or preference
not to know X, it's the moral judgments about
those who do or don't know X. This is the
key to the fascinating realm of virtuous ignorance.
At first, the very phrase may seem almost
oxymoronic. However, it isn't too difficult
to find cases of virtuous ignorance with serious
moral purposes underpinning them.
But first, can people think that ignorance
is virtuous in other ways than conferring
status on the ignoramus? In his 1991 book,
"Strange Weather", in the Acknowledgements
page, the self-appointed critic of science
Andrew Ross declared "This book is dedicated
to all the science teachers I never had. It
could only have been written without them."
Taken literally, the second sentence seems
unexceptional. I think we would all grant
that had he even a bare-bones scientific education,
Ross could not have written the book that
he did. But some of those rebutting Ross'
work, such as biologist Paul Gross and mathematician
Norman Levitt, interpreted his declaration
as a hubristic boast.
Why would Gross and Levitt think this dedication
was a boast, and what could Ross have been
boasting about? A clear hint comes in the
Introduction on page 8, where he says "As
I lacked the training of a scientific intellectual
and the accompanying faith, however vestigial
or self-critical, in the certainties of the
scientific method... My position, then, became
that of a cultural critic". There we have
it: Ross is claiming not only that scientists
are indoctrinated into a faith, but also anyone
undergoing scientific training becomes contaminated
by this faith and, worse still, cannot be
rid of it even through self-criticism. It's
like the stain of Original Sin. Therefore,
contamination can be avoided and purity maintained
only by not studying science.
It isn't a big leap from the idea that knowledge
might be a contaminant to the concept of taboos
against knowledge. We encountered taboos in
my taxonomy of ignorance, under the branch
called "ignoring". Where do knowledge taboos
come from? What creates and sustains them?
The anthropologist Mary Douglas wrote a classic
book "Purity and Danger", with an intriguing
first approximation to a general theory of
taboos. She claimed that there are two kinds
of proscription in taboos: One against threats
or dangers, and another against pollution
or contamination.
So, let's try this out on knowledge. First,
some information could be declared off-limits
because knowing it would pose a danger, either
to oneself or to others, or both. Or perhaps
the process of acquiring the information would
incur dangers. What kinds of dangers lurk
here? Perhaps the most obvious examples are
knowledge that can be used against other people,
such as knowing how to remotely take over
people's computers or how to make weapons.
As for acquiring knowledge, the dangers could
range from physical (as in experimenting with
explosives) to social (as in committing illegal
acts in the pursuit of knowledge).
Now, consider the second kind of taboo, pollution
or contamination. "Innocence", when it refers
to a kind of saintly naivety, is a familiar
but interesting kind of virtuous ignorance.
In Christian traditions it is associated with
the tree of knowledge, forbidden fruit, and
the events that got humanity kicked out of
the Garden of Eden. Those who have lost their
innocence or known sin are "tainted". Mary
Douglas defined pollution as dirt in the wrong
place. Translated into the realm of knowledge
and ignorance, the crucial idea is that information
can be in a wrong place. For instance, some
kinds of knowledge, such as how to have sex,
may be considered appropriate for adults but
not for children. One of the most intriguing
aspects of innocence is the notion that its
maintenance often requires the protection
of innocents by more knowledgeable (and therefore
unclean) guardians.
At first glance, proscriptions against knowledge
raise familiar images of censorship, oppression,
and domination: Book burning, bans against
certain teachings. This sort of thing is fair enough; examples
abound of ignorance imposed by powerful agents
on those who are powerless. Nevertheless,
virtuous ignorance also can be found at the
base of benign or even benevolent arrangements
agreed to by society as a whole.
We've already encountered examples of such
arrangements. We've seen that privacy amounts
to a multilateral ignorance arrangement, whereby
we agree that certain kinds of information
about ourselves will not be available to others
without our consent. Respecting others' privacy
is virtuous behavior, thus, virtuous ignorance.
People who violate privacy norms pose a threat
to the person(s) about whom they have obtained
private information. A right to privacy amounts
to a right to at least some control over who
knows what about you. Virtuous people do not
poke their noses into matters that are none
of their business. In fact, privacy is a close
cousin to censorship, especially when censorship
is agreed to by those in power and the public
on whom it is imposed.
We've also seen that social relations based
on trust and friendship operate in a similar
manner. Trust is not about concealing information,
but trust relationships do require observance
of an interesting kind of privacy. If one
person is monitoring another or insisting
that they fully account for their actions,
the person under surveillance will conclude
that the monitor does not trust them. Trust,
therefore, is both an example of a social
relation that requires tolerance of undesired
uncertainty (the risk of being exploited)
in favor of desired uncertainty (freedom to
seize opportunities for new relations) and,
of course, virtuous behavior.
And so, we have arrived at examples of virtuous
ignorance that are socially mandated and underpin
some important forms of social capital: Privacy,
trust, and friendship. We can add politeness
and civility to this list. Moreover, an organizational
culture favoring creativity, initiative, and
entrepreneurship requires the toleration of
at least some ignorance.
Finally, let's take a look at an example of
ignorance that is considered virtuous by some
but not by others: Ignorance generated by
tax evasion. Tax evasion via the so-called
"shadow economy" is widely tolerated and facilitated
by citizens in many countries, and in those
countries the shadow economy can account for
a large portion of total economic output.
A 2010 International Monetary Fund report
estimated that from 2002 to 2007 in half of
the G20 countries, the size of the shadow
economy equated to at least 20% of the official
gross domestic product. For many people, tax
evasion is motivated by pragmatic self-interest,
but for some it actually represents what they
consider to be a justified protest against
their government's policies on taxation and
related matters.
As a result, official economic indicators
such as inflation rates, employment rates,
and gross domestic product are substantially
inaccurate. Governing the economy becomes
almost impossible, and the small tax base
severely limits what governments can provide
for health, education, welfare, or infrastructure.
But the governments in these countries face
a very awkward tradeoff: They are missing
out on large sources of revenue if they ignore
or tolerate the shadow economy, but cracking
down on the shadow economy could cause the
entire economy to crash.
In this lecture we've investigated the concept
of virtuous ignorance, and we've found not
only that it exists, but it's also quite pervasive
and underpins some important forms of taboo
and social relations. Beliefs that certain
kinds of ignorance are morally justified and
that undoing them would be immoral are hard
to change, especially if they are embedded
in the dominant culture. The next lecture
will focus on a type of ignorance that is
even more difficult to change, namely the
kind that accumulates as a byproduct of cognitive
and social processes that are largely unconscious.