KH - Vân Bùi (2/11)
Trong bài bình luận cuốn "Going Rogue" của
Sarah Palin, Jonathann Raban đã ví nó như một "bài ca ngợi
400 trang về mặt tốt của việc thiếu kiến thức." Ông có ý
gì? Ông đang nhắc đến
triết học đơn giản ví dụ như
"Tôi không biết nhiều
về nghệ thuật, nhưng tôi biết mình thích gì." Ông gọi nó là
"chủ nghĩa bảo thủ thông thường"
khi người bình thường còn
tốt hơn các chuyên gia trong việc đánh giá, ví dụ như
chính sách ngoại giao Mỹ, bởi quá nhiều
chuyên gia ảnh hưởng xấu đến phán xét. Vài bình luận
cho rằng đây chỉ là cách nói khác của
việc chống lại kiến thức chuyên sâu. Nhưng ta sẽ
thấy đây chỉ là sự đơn giản hóa thái quá. Khi
ta biết cần tìm gì, nó sẽ xuất hiện
không chỉ ở các chính trị gia cánh phải hoặc
phản lý tính luận
Ví dụ sau không liên quan đến
chính trị hay phản lý tính luận mà
là về những người có học thức.
Những năm 1970, tôi học tiến sỹ xã hội học.
Tôi và những bạn học của tôi
chưa hề đọc tâm lý học ngoại trừ
các tác phẩm của Freud, nhưng chúng tôi biết mình ghét
tâm lý học, trừ Freud ra.
Một vài người trong chúng tôi còn biết
tâm lý học toàn là chủ nghĩa cá nhân,
thực chứng, những kẻ phản động tuân theo khuôn mẫu
trở thành công cụ của tư bản.
Tuy nhiên, cuối cùng tôi vẫn rất tò mò.
Tâm lý học có gì xấu xa? Tôi quyết định
tìm ra. Khi tôi cho các bạn và giáo sư
biết việc tôi đăng ký một lớp
tâm lý học, địa vị của tôi giảm tức thì.
Họ cho rằng không học tâm lý học thể hiện
đẳng cấp học thuật. Một chuyên gia chân chính
không phí thời gian
học những quy tắc
không chính xác.
Vài năm sau, tôi có nghe một câu chuyện có thể chứng minh
rằng quan điểm này không chỉ có ở sinh viên.
Một đồng nghiệp tâm lý học tham dự một se-mi-na
của một nhà xã hội học có tiếng và đã được viễn cảnh
tương lai tân tiến cho khoa học xã hội mà ông này vẽ ra
truyền cảm hứng. Tuy nhiên, anh ta
lại thắc mắc tại sao không thấy nhắc đến tâm lý học
Sau đó, anh ta đến gặp
vị giáo sư nọ và hỏi viễn cảnh ngành tâm lý học
tương lai như thế nào. Nhà xã hội học
trả lời rằng ông đã từng
học nhưng cố gắng
không nghĩ về những điều
tiêu cực. Tôi thuộc khoa tâm lý học.
Tôi đã trải  qua những
mặt xấu.
Tôi không chỉ trích xã hội học. Một vài
ví dụ ở các quy luật khác.
Một đồng nghiệp khác, rất có học
và sáng dạ, từng tự hào kể rằng
bà không biết ti gì về
kinh tế. Ở đây, sự thiếu hiểu biết
đã được đâọ đức hóa bằng cách biến thành
sự thể hiện địa vị. Sự thiếu hiểu biết đúng chỗ
có thể là dấu hiệu của địa vị cao.
Trong nhiều xã hội, sự phân biệt tầng lớp
ít nhiều cũng dựa trên điều này.
Trong xã hội Anh trước đậy, kiến thức
thủ công hoặc thương nghiệp (so với nghệ thuật hoặc
quy tắc) bị coi là phi quí tộc.
Vấn đề không phải ở việc chọn không
không biết X, mà ở việc ai biết
hoặc không biết X. Đây là
lý do cho sự nổi lên của sự thiếu hiểu biết có đạo đức.
Có thể bản thân cụm từ này dường như hơi mâu thuẫn
Tuy nhiên. không quá  khó
để tìm ra những tình huống với
mục đích đạo đức đằng sau.
Tuy nhiên, liệu con người có nghĩ rằng sự thiếu hiểu biết
có thể mang tính đạo đức khác với sự áp đặt
địa vị cho sự thiếu hiểu biết? Trong cuốn sách
"Thời tiết kỳ lạ" của ông, phần lời cảm ơn,
người tự nhận là ghét khoa học,
Andrew Ros tuyên bố "Cuốn sách này xin gửi đến
tất cả những giáo viên khoa học tôi từng học. Nó
đã không thể ra đời nếu thiếu họ."
Câu thứ hai có vẻ cũng không phải
ngoại lệ. Tôi nghĩ ta đều đồng ý
rằng ông, kể cả giáo dục khoa học cơ bản,
Ross khó mà viết cuốn sách đó.
Nhưng một vài chỉ trích,
như nhà sinh học Paul Gross và nhà toán học
Norman Levitt, coi tuyên bố của ông
là sự khoe khoang.
Tại sao họ lại nghĩ vậy?
Ross đang khoe những gì?
Gợi ý ở trong lời mở đầu
trang 8, ông viết "Vì tôi không
được đào tạo về khoa học
và niềm tin vào nó, nên dù phương pháp
khoa học còn hạn chế và cá nhân
quan niệm của tôi cũng có mang
bản chất văn hóa."
Ross cho rằng không chỉ những nhà khoa học
bị thấm nhuần một tư tưởng mà còn
hoàn toàn trở thành chúng và
tệ hơn là không thể
thoát khỏi chúng dù có tự đấu tranh. Nó như
một con dấu tội lỗi. Vì vậy
việc này chỉ có thể bị ngăn chặn bằng
cách từ bỏ giáo dục khoa học.
Tư tưởng kiến thức là vật lây nhiễm hoặc
những lời đồn chống lại kiến thức
không phải là mới. Ta đã nhắc đến chúng trong
phân loại sự thiếu kiến thức, mục ignoring.
Những kiến thức cần tránh đến từ đâu?
Cái gì sáng tạo ra và duy trì chúng?
The anthropologist Mary Douglas wrote a classic
book "Purity and Danger", with an intriguing
first approximation to a general theory of
taboos. She claimed that there are two kinds
of proscription in taboos: One against threats
or dangers, and another against pollution
or contamination.
So, let's try this out on knowledge. First,
some information could be declared off-limits
because knowing it would pose a danger, either
to oneself or to others, or both. Or perhaps
the process of acquiring the information would
incur dangers. What kinds of dangers lurk
here? Perhaps the most obvious examples are
knowledge that can be used against other people,
such as knowing how to remotely take over
people's computers or how to make weapons.
As for acquiring knowledge, the dangers could
range from physical (as in experimenting with
explosives) to social (as in committing illegal
acts in the pursuit of knowledge).
Now, consider the second kind of taboo, pollution
or contamination. "Innocence", when it refers
to a kind of saintly naivety, is a familiar
but interesting kind of virtuous ignorance.
In Christian traditions it is associated with
the tree of knowledge, forbidden fruit, and
the events that got humanity kicked out of
the Garden of Eden. Those who have lost their
innocence or known sin are "tainted". Mary
Douglas defined pollution as dirt in the wrong
place. Translated into the realm of knowledge
and ignorance, the crucial idea is that information
can be in a wrong place. For instance, some
kinds of knowledge, such as how to have sex,
may be considered appropriate for adults but
not for children. One of the most intriguing
aspects of innocence is the notion that its
maintenance often requires the protection
of innocents by more knowledgeable (and therefore
unclean) guardians.
At first glance, proscriptions against knowledge
raise familiar images of censorship, oppression,
and domination: Book burning, bans against
certain teachings. This sort of thing is fair enough; examples
abound of ignorance imposed by powerful agents
on those who are powerless. Nevertheless,
virtuous ignorance also can be found at the
base of benign or even benevolent arrangements
agreed to by society as a whole.
We've already encountered examples of such
arrangements. We've seen that privacy amounts
to a multilateral ignorance arrangement, whereby
we agree that certain kinds of information
about ourselves will not be available to others
without our consent. Respecting others' privacy
is virtuous behavior, thus, virtuous ignorance.
People who violate privacy norms pose a threat
to the person(s) about whom they have obtained
private information. A right to privacy amounts
to a right to at least some control over who
knows what about you. Virtuous people do not
poke their noses into matters that are none
of their business. In fact, privacy is a close
cousin to censorship, especially when censorship
is agreed to by those in power and the public
on whom it is imposed.
We've also seen that social relations based
on trust and friendship operate in a similar
manner. Trust is not about concealing information,
but trust relationships do require observance
of an interesting kind of privacy. If one
person is monitoring another or insisting
that they fully account for their actions,
the person under surveillance will conclude
that the monitor does not trust them. Trust,
therefore, is both an example of a social
relation that requires tolerance of undesired
uncertainty (the risk of being exploited)
in favor of desired uncertainty (freedom to
seize opportunities for new relations) and,
of course, virtuous behavior.
And so, we have arrived at examples of virtuous
ignorance that are socially mandated and underpin
some important forms of social capital: Privacy,
trust, and friendship. We can add politeness
and civility to this list. Moreover, an organizational
culture favoring creativity, initiative, and
entrepreneurship requires the toleration of
at least some ignorance.
Finally, let's take a look at an example of
ignorance that is considered virtuous by some
but not by others: Ignorance generated by
tax evasion. Tax evasion via the so-called
"shadow economy" is widely tolerated and facilitated
by citizens in many countries, and in those
countries the shadow economy can account for
a large portion of total economic output.
A 2010 International Monetary Fund report
estimated that from 2002 to 2007 in half of
the G20 countries, the size of the shadow
economy equated to at least 20% of the official
gross domestic product. For many people, tax
evasion is motivated by pragmatic self-interest,
but for some it actually represents what they
consider to be a justified protest against
their government's policies on taxation and
related matters.
As a result, official economic indicators
such as inflation rates, employment rates,
and gross domestic product are substantially
inaccurate. Governing the economy becomes
almost impossible, and the small tax base
severely limits what governments can provide
for health, education, welfare, or infrastructure.
But the governments in these countries face
a very awkward tradeoff: They are missing
out on large sources of revenue if they ignore
or tolerate the shadow economy, but cracking
down on the shadow economy could cause the
entire economy to crash.
In this lecture we've investigated the concept
of virtuous ignorance, and we've found not
only that it exists, but it's also quite pervasive
and underpins some important forms of taboo
and social relations. Beliefs that certain
kinds of ignorance are morally justified and
that undoing them would be immoral are hard
to change, especially if they are embedded
in the dominant culture. The next lecture
will focus on a type of ignorance that is
even more difficult to change, namely the
kind that accumulates as a byproduct of cognitive
and social processes that are largely unconscious.