http://youtu.be/r-bNPLRdAqk
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: Hi.
In this video, let me show you
another finite state machine.
We're going to build
a line tracking robot.
And this is going to be a
Moore finite state machine.
Let's begin with the inputs and outputs.
This line tracking robot has two motors,
one on the left and one on the right.
And it has two sensors to tell
whether we're on the line.
The goal of this system
is to make an autonomous
robot which drives along this track.
OK, so I'm going to track this line.
The two motors, if I drive both motors,
both the left and the right motor,
they will go straight.
If I drive just the right motor here
and not the left, it'll turn left.
And another way around if I drive just
the left motor and not the right motor,
it'll turn right.
OK.
So those are my outputs
to the two motors.
Let's look at the inputs.
The inputs are infrared sensors.
And these infrared sensors
will tell me yes or no
whether or not the two sensors you
see positioned here in the front
are on the line or not on the line.
So in this configuration here,
if both sensors show one,
that means that both sensors
are on the line, which
means the robot is down
the middle of the track.
However, if I'm off to the left you
see that the left sensor will go dark
and the sensor signal will be 0.
But I'm off just a
little bit to the left,
so the right sensor's still on the line.
So the right shows a
1, the left shows a 0,
and that means the robot
is off to the left.
If the sensors are reversed, in other
words, if the right sensor is dark
and the left sensor sees the
line, I'm going to have a 0, 1.
So again, the sensors allow me to see
the situation of where the robot is.
I have one more case that I don't
know quite how to handle yet
and that is if I'm lost.
And that is both sensors go dark.
I'm either off to the left
or the right, I don't know.
And this is where the finite
state machine will help us.
If you wanted to build it,
here are two motor drivers.
The output of PF2 is going to drive this
transistor, driving this right motor.
And the output of PF1 is
going to drive this transistor
and drive the left motor.
Again, both motors on go straight.
1, 0 turns left and
0, 1 will turn right.
And here's the sensor interface.
This is a QRB 1134, an infrared
sensor with a focal length
of about five millimeters.
This infrared diode
emits infrared light.
That light will either reflect
or not reflect off the line.
And then that reflected light
will either turn on or turn off
this transistor.
This is a thresholding circuit
such that this signal here on PF4
will tell me whether
or not there's a line.
1 means I see a line.
A logic 0 means I don't see a line.
And I have a second
one for the other side.
OK, let's begin with a strategy.
Here I have my robots on the line.
Both sensors show line.
And then the color means
here that this dark blue
means these motors are active.
And so both the left and
right motors are spinning.
So as it spins forward, we see that
the robot goes in a straight line.
But then the robot goes in a
straight line, but the line moved.
And now we have something
that went wrong.
The left sensor went dark, went 0.
That means I'm off to the left.
So what am I going to do?
My strategy is if I'm off to
the left, I want to turn right.
And we saw how to turn right is
to slow down the right wheel.
So if I slow down the right
wheel and drive the left wheel,
it will turn back towards the line.
So we see that the robot will turn.
The right wheel isn't stopped,
it's just running at a slower rate.
And it turns and moves
until it's back on the line.
Again, both sensors see the
line, both wheels are active,
and so now it's going to move forward
again until the line goes away.
The right sensor went
dark, left sensor's on.
So what am I going to do?
I'm going to slow down
the left wheel, which
will cause it to rotate to turn left.
This line turned a little faster,
so it took a couple of times for it
to turn and move until it sees.
So now that once both
sensors are activated again,
I'm going to go back to the steady
state, which is to drive both wheels so
the robot goes straight.
That's my strategy.
If I'm off to the left, I'm going to
turn right and if I'm off to the right,
I'm going to turn right.
And if I'm on the line,
I'm going to go straight.
So now what we're going to do is capture
that strategy into the state graph.
So we've got to define some states.
So states, if you remember,
are what do we know?
What do we believe to be true?
So if I'm on the line, if I'm
in the center of the road,
then what I'm going
to do is go straight.
And that's what this says.
If I'm in the center, go straight.
If I'm off to the left
then I want to turn right.
And if I'm off to the right,
I'm going to turn left.
So this is the essence
of how I'm going to use
my outputs to build this state graph.
I'm going to use the outputs,
which are a function of the state.
So if I'm off to the left, I'm going to
turn right, and if I'm off the right,
I'm going to turn left.
Now, I could've added a lost state.
But we'll see what happens if I
get lost when I build the machine.
So now let's build the
state transition table.
The state transition table
is built in this way.
Down this axis are the state names.
It's a Moore machine.
So every state has a unique output,
or every state has an output.
It doesn't have to be unique,
but every state has an output.
So that's what I put here.
Now in this state transition table, I
need a column for every possible input.
And then what I place in the table is
what do I do if I'm in the center state
and if the input is a 1, 1.
The question now
becomes what to do next.
And that's what I place in the state.
So let's do a few.
I'm in the center
state and I see a 1, 1.
I'm still on the line.
I'm going to remain in the center state.
I've also started to
build the graph down here.
And I've also started to build
the data structure here just
to show you this one to one mapping.
This entry in the table
matches this arrow
in the graph, which matches
this entry in the software.
If I'm off to the left, and now I see
the line, that means I'm on the line.
So I'll go to the center spot.
If I'm off to the right, and now I
see the line, both beautiful lines,
I'm going to go to the center state.
So in this state graph,
whenever I see the line
I'm going to see both lines are going
to be next into the center state.
That was an easy one.
Let's do a harder one.
What do I do if I'm off to the left?
In other words, the input is at 0, 1.
I'm off to the left.
If I'm in the center state and
I just went off to the left,
I'm going to go to the left state.
The other thing I'm going to do,
if I'm already in the left state,
I know I'm in the left, and I'm still
in the left, what I'm going to do
is actually oscillate here
between left and center.
So again, if I'm off to the
left I'm going to turn right.
This is where the finite state
machine really helps us out.
And that is, what if I go off the track?
Now, what's important to know
about a finite state machine
is we know not only
what the input is now,
but we know where it was previously.
So what this is telling me is I used
to be just a little bit off the left,
and now I'm way off to the left.
You see that?
I used to be just a little
bit off, and now I'm way off.
And if so, I'm going to
stay in the left state.
So in this mode, I'll stop one
motor, drive just the other motor,
and make a hard turn back to the right.
Again, the whole thing is symmetric.
What happened on the left
happens on the right.
So this is where I used to be on the
line and now I missed the right sensor,
right sensor just went dark, so I'm
just a little bit off to the right,
so I'll go to the right state.
And then what will happen is this will
oscillate between these two states
while I'm a little bit off to
the right, which will again
make a toggling on the left motor and
make a soft left turn back to the line.
So off to the right,
I'm going to turn left.
So the red entry in the
table matches this arrow,
matches that spot in the software.
This purple entry matches
this arrow and that thing.
So again, all three are connected.
Just like going way off to the left,
I could go way off to the right.
And you see now the sensor shows
0, 0, but I knew previously
I used to be off to the right.
And so this arrow here will
keep me into the right.
So I used to be just a
little bit off to the right.
Now I'm way off to right.
And so I'm going to do a
complete stop on the left motor,
making a sharp left turn to go back on.
I got a couple of more entries
that don't make any sense,
but I've got to put something in there.
This one is weird.
This is telling me I used to
be a little bit off to the left
and somehow I jumped to be a
little bit off to the right.
That can't happen
unless your robot skips.
But I got to put something in there.
Similarly, this one says
I used to be off the right
and now I'm off to the left.
I don't know how it happened, but
I'm going to put something in here.
This one's a little more plausible.
This one happens if the robot
is actually running completely
perpendicular to the track, where
it goes from both sensors totally
on to both sensors totally off.
And so in this mode,
I'm just going to guess.
I'm just going to pick one and
hopefully it was off to the right.
Let's put it all together.
Here's the entire state graph.
Again, one to one mapping between
the table, the graph, and the data
structure.
That means no more, no less.
Let's talk about time.
Motors typically run at
about a tenth of a second.
So we're going to run
our finite state machine
about 10 times faster than that.
So each of my states is going to
have a delay of 10 milliseconds.
All right, so now let's do the software.
There's my structure from before.
There's my state and index.
This index is going to be 0 for center,
1 and 2 for the other two states.
I'm going to add some debugging
variables, input and output.
Input's obviously going to be the input.
Output's going to be the output.
I'll initialize my GPIO
ports, my PLL and SysTick,
and then set the state to
assume I'm in the center.
It's a more machine,
so what do I do first?
I do the output.
Of course, this is not the output.
This is just reading the
output out of the variable
and storing it into
this debugging variable.
The actual output occurs
when I do the output
to the motor, when I write to
port F. And so this variable here
is going to be either a 3, a 2,
or a 1 depending upon whether I'm
in the center of the
left or right state.
As I mentioned before, each
state will wait 10 milliseconds.
So this one is captured
out of the structure.
And then I'll wait 10 milliseconds
to slow down this driver.
Then I produce my input, which is
going to read from the two sensors.
And then it's a Moore
machine, so the next state
is a function of the
current state and the input.
So I'm going to go to
the next state and then
I'll repeat this over and over again.
Let's show you this in the software.
Here I have the solution to that.
And so let's debug it, I'm
running it in the simulator.
So my port F, there's my sensors.
These two bits are my output
and I got the Logic Analyzer up,
and so we hit the Go button.
And again, this state here tells
me I'm in the center state.
And my two inputs are high,
my two outputs are high,
the motor's going straight.
If one of the sensors goes on,
we see that when I turn right,
when I'm off to the left, it will turn
right by toggling the other motor.
If I get back on the line,
I'm going straight again.
If the other sensor's on,
I'll toggle the other motor.
So again, I have my
inputs and my outputs
and I can see them here in the debugger.
So in summary, what do we have?
This is a Moore finite state machine.
We produce an output, which
is a function of the state.
We look at our inputs.
And those inputs tell us
what the next state will be.
And the idea is to develop
a strategy and build
that strategy in to what
should the outputs be
and what should the next states be.
All right, you try.