http://youtu.be/fWgV7fFLJ3k
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So to
demonstrate our communication
using serial UART we're going
to develop up a chat tool.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
So we can talk together?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
we can talk to each other.
And in any communication, to start
with we have to define our protocol.
So the protocol we are going
to use for our communication
is described visually here.
So we're going to have
two microcontrollers.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Do I get one?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yes.
This is a microcontroller which
is the microcontroller for me.
And this is another microcontroller.
And we're going to
connect them as we saw
using the serial
communication, which means
that the transmit line(TxD) on mine
will be connected to receive line(RxD)
on this interface, on
this microcontroller.
And the receive line(RxD here will be
connected to the transmit line(TxD)
here.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: What about ground?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And there will
be the common ground as a reference.
So I'm not going to show that because
we have already demonstrated that.
So, in addition what we're going
to do is both of these machines
will have an interface.
One is a button which will
allow us to choose a message.
So this is a Chooser.
And another button
which is a Send button.
So the same thing is
going to be here as well.
So the Chooser will allow us to
choose one of these messages.
And the idea is that there
is the on board LED here.
Let's say this is my LED.
The on board LED is picked.
For example, if I pick the LED
to be red, by using the Chooser,
then this is the message I want to
send which says "Are you there".
And in response, so there's
an LED here as well,
I could use the Chooser on the
receiver side, pick an answer.
And answers are here in my color wheel.
And the questions are on the side.
So I could pick an answer.
I would say, "Yes".
So that's my white, and I choose my
white, and it's going to transmit.
Now what's going to have
to happen in this process
is, this protocol,
which is human readable
will have to be converted
to some binary message.
And my binary message
for the transmitter
when Jon chooses that question red
is going to be the message that he's
going to send is going to
be a 0x30 that he transmits.
And I will send a response.
And that's going to be a
response back saying "Yes".
And that will be a 0x36.
So the encoding of the messages
can be seen on the color wheel
as starting from 0x30, 0x31,
that's hex 31, hex 32, hex 33.
hex 34, 35, 36, and 37.
So we'll show you how the code
for the sender and the receiver
is going to look like.
They're going to be uniform code that's
running on board the microcontrollers.
And we'll show you the
configuration of the UART
and also show you
sending of the messages.