http://youtu.be/CoM92k3nGhQ
DR JONATHAN VALVANO: So as
we saw from last chapter,
the Logic Analyzer is a non-intrusive
hardware debugging instrument.
And I've connected the Logic
Analyzer to the UART system,
connecting one wire, channel
zero, from the signal from A to B,
and channel one from the transmit line
from B to A. And we're going to see,
that if I select a pattern-- like
if I want to send the color Red--
I will then push the send button.
And over here on the
Logic Analyzer, we see
that this is the UART
pattern which was sent
from B to A. Let's
send a different color.
Let's send Green.
And there is the Green pattern.
The signal is transmitted in serial.
And we have the start bit, bit zero,
bit one, bit two, bit three, bit four,
five, six, and seven.
And right here is the stop bit.
So we can see voltage versus time
as our signal is transmitted.
And I have it triggered
on the falling edge, which
is the idle to start the transition.
So if I send a Blue, we can
see that the pattern changes.
Now if I switch the Logic
Analyzer to trigger on the falling
edge of the other one, so now we
have the falling edge of the A to B.
And over here, if I send a Red, we see
that the A to B signal has the pattern.
Green, Blue.
And I can use the Logic
Analyzer to test to make
sure the baud-rate is
correct by measuring
the time between these pulses,
and make sure my pattern is right
as I push the values.
So in summary, the Logic
Analyzer is a hardware device
that allows us to measure
multiple digital signals
in their amplitude versus time behavior.