http://youtu.be/kbKg-QGoHDE
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Next we'll show you
the software needed for the Chat tool.
We're going to add one more
driver function, one more
input function, which is
going to be non-blocking.
Non-blocking means that if
the receive FIFO is empty
that means it has no data.
And so rather than waiting, like
a busy-wait what will happen is
we will simply return a zero.
And that will mean
that there is no data.
If the receive FIFO empty flag is
zero, that means there is data,
and so we will input the
data and return the data.
This will allow the
main program to check
to see whether it has received any
input from the other microcontroller
and processes it.
But if there is no data,
it doesn't have to wait.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So this
is different from the InChar
we wrote earlier which was a
blocking I/O. The difference is
that the blocking I/O would have
sat in a loop waiting for the input
to be available.
And once it's available, it's
going to return the data it reads.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, so what's next?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: This is the
main program of our Chat tool.
We will initialize the
PLL at 80 megahertz,
we'll use SysTick down here for
wait, we'll initialization our UART,
and we'll initialize the
port F buttons and LEDs.
The main body of the Chat tool, you
can see, is a great big while loop.
The first thing we're going to do is
check to see if switch one is pressed.
It switch one(SW1) is pressed,
that means it's a zero,
we are going to select the
next color in the wheel.
And you can see that is done
with this line of code here,
which will add one to the color and then
mask it with a seven so at all times
the value color goes to zero,
one, two, all the way up to seven.
If the switch is not pressed,
then we will go to the next step.
And we will check to see if
switch two (SW2) is pressed.
If switch two is pressed,
its time to send the message.
And so what will happen is we will
encode the message and send it.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
switch one is our Chooser
and switch two is our Send button.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: The
last thing we're going to do,
and if it's not pressed, we'll
go to our third step, which
is to check to see whether we
have any received messages.
And that was our input, non-blocking
from the previous slide.
We saw with the non-blocking input we
had two choices, either we had no input
or we did have input.
If we have input we're
going to decode that input.
In our case the encoding
and decoding is very simple.
To encode the message, we took
the number zero through seven
and added 30 to it to get
the ASCII zero through seven.
To decode the message we're
going to mask off the 30,
so again we have a number
between zero and seven.
And we will set the color
to that input value.
The fourth step is to output
to the LED either the value
that we've selected with the
press switch or the value
that we've read from the input.
And so if we don't have an
input, we're going go here.
We're going to add a fifth step,
and that is a 20 millisecond wait.
And this will remove the
bounce of the switch.
And so these steps, one,
two, three, four, and five
are repeated over and over
again in the While loop.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So John,
I understand the flowchart.
But I see that you have this
variable called previous prevSW1
and prevSW2, what are those used for?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: They are used
to make sure when I touch the switch,
it increments the color just once.
And the way I'm going to do it
is in this if statement here.
I'm going to look for the touch,
or the falling edge of switch one.
So the switch one will be touched
when the switch one is zero.
But the previous value of switch
one through the loop was a one.
So if the switch one is not
pressed it goes through the loop
and there's a one in this variable.
And if I'm going around the
loop, and I touch the switch,
it will become a zero.
So if switch one is a zero, and the
previous time through the loop it's
a one, I've detected
the first touch event.
So the color number is
just increment once.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So otherwise
the switch one would be zero
and the previous value
of the switch would also
be a zero, that tells me that it's
been pressed but not released yet.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
And we do the same thing for
switch two and it's previous two.
Because when I push the button,
I only want to send one message.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, and the input that we
are talking about reading is
from the UART in this picture,
in the flow chart, that's
coming from the UART
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, so let's play.