http://youtu.be/g3V4KnWxdMo
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: We've set
up our chat tool in our offices,
and we're going to
use it to communicate.
I wonder if Professor
Yerraballi is in his office.
In order to use it, I will
push the Select button
until I get the message
that I want to send.
Red means "Are you in
your office", and I
push this button to send that message.
Sent the message.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Oh,
I see a message from Jon.
He's asking me if I'm in my office.
I will send a response back,
"Yes", I am in my office.
I send a White saying,
yes, I'm in my office.
I wonder if he wants
to go out for coffee.
Let me send a message back.
I pick a color, I pick
the color Blue, and I
send it to see if he
wants to have coffee.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh, I see a Blue.
I'm not thirsty so let's
select a response, not thirsty.
OK.
Push the Select button until it
goes black-- Black means "No" --
and I will send the Black message out.
So I've sent the black message
saying I'm not thirsty,
but I am hungry, always hungry,
so I was ask him if he's hungry.
So I will select the Green light,
which means "Are you hungry",
shall we go out.
And send the Green message.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Oh, I see
he's not thirsty, but he's hungry.
I'm hungry too.
Let's meet for lunch, but let me
first tell him, "Yes" I am hungry.
And maybe I should come over to his
office so that we can go from there.
And make a message,
that's my message, which
is a Cyan, asking him if
he wants me to come over.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh, I see he sent
a Cyan that says, do you want to meet.
And so I will say, Yes,
come up to the office.
So I select the White, which
means yes, come up to the office.
So in summary, what we have
are two microcontrollers
connected by this long cable.
We can transmit data from
my computer to his computer,
out this transmitter into that receiver.
And then he can select his response by
sending data to in the other direction.
And, as you can see, every time we hit
the Send, we send one 8-bit packet.
I wonder if he's coming to my office.
There he is.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Hey, John.
You ready to go?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's go out for lunch.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's do it.