http://youtu.be/zF1swxwoPq8
Dr. Jon Valvano: Next we will
look at number conversions.
And there are four big
ideas in this section.
The first is Device Driver.
The second is Successive Refinement.
The third is number conversion itself.
And the last is we will
see two types of loops.
So a device driver, as we saw,
is a set of software programs
to facilitate using
I/O. And so what we're
going to do is create one
of those driver functions.
And so we're going to
take a number and we're
going to convert it to an
ASCII string and output
that ASCII string to the device.
Successive refinement is a
software development technique
which allows us to go from the
big idea into the fine details.
And so it is a software
development process.
And we'll use it to solve this problem.
And then we will see two types of loops.
We will see where in
the first loop we will
see when we don't know how
many steps it is, it is unknown
how many times through
the loop we will run.
And in that case, we're
going to use a While loop.
And in the second method, we will know
exactly how many times and we'll use a
For loop.
So what are we going to do in this lab?
We're going to take a
number like the integer 123
and we're going to convert it
to a set of ASCII characters.
'1', that's the ASCII code
for 1, the ASCII code for 2,
and the ASCII code for 3, and we're
going to output these three ASCII
values to the device.
So what the human will see is 123.
So we're converting what the computer
sees into what the human sees.
For instance, if the computer
has the number 65432,
then the output is going to
be hex 36, 35, 34, 33, and 32.
And we see one of the problems is at
the time I'm writing this program,
I don't know whether I'm going
to output three characters
or whether I'm going to output
four or five or six or seven.
This is what is unknown
at the time of execution.
Whenever we write software, there are
three questions that we wish to ask.
First is where do we start?
What's the starting point?
Where do we begin?
That's always a very troublesome thing.
The second is how do we make progress?
So if we make progress in the correct
direction, we'll eventually finish.
And the last is the ending
point, or when are we done?
So in this case here, we see
that what we're going to do
is we're going to have the number 123.
And so we begin with where do we start?
Do we start with the biggest digit or
do we start with the smallest digit?
Where do we start?
And we'll look at that when
we get to the next one.
And then the progress is we're
going to create one digit of output.
But the trick is after I
create one digit of output,
I need to create a simpler problem.
It needs to get simpler.
So for instance, if I tried to pick
off the most significant digit,
then naturally the one
that I think I should get.
Then the question for
this is, I would need
to pick out the one,
the hundredths digit.
But for this number,
I'd have to pick out
the six, which is the
ten thousandth's digit.
And so we see it's difficult
to pick off the first one.
Conversely, if I start
with the ones digit,
start with the other end of the number,
we see in all cases the first digit,
the ones digit it is easy to get.
Because I can just take the
number and find the modulo of 10.
The number modulo of 10
will be the ones digit.
And that will be easy to do.
Similarly, if I adjust the number
in this way after I get that digit,
I can simplify my problem.
And I'm going to simplify my
problem such that this divided by 10
is going to produce a 123 down
to the 12 and the 65432 will
be reduced to a simpler problem of 6543.
And then the ending point will
be when this number n eventually
goes to 0 I'll be done.
So this is my strategy.
So let me show you the method
of software development called
Successive refinement.
Successive refinement is to go from the
big picture down into the fine details.
So first, I'm going to think
of my program in three steps.
I'm going to initialize some things.
I'm going to create some digits.
And third, I'm going
output those digits.
Because we saw in my method I created
the digits in the opposite order.
I created them from the
least significant digit
to the most significant.
But I want to output them
in the other direction.
So my big picture will be to
create a storage of the digits
and then output them in the other order.
That's my big picture.
I can refine that by thinking about how
it is I'm going to create the digits,
right?
I'm going to create a digit.
And we saw we're going to create a digit
using this digit equals n modulo 10.
And we're going to simplify by
using this n equals n divided by 10.
That's how I'm going
to create the digits.
And then I'm going to repeat
until n is equal to 0.
And next I'm going to output the digits.
But I've got to output
them in the other order.
So when I refine this some more, I
think about what do I need to know?
You remember, what we do
is we place our knowledge.
Our knowledge have to go into variables.
And so I'm going to create--
we saw we had the parameter n.
That was an obvious one.
And we saw we had the digit
d, which is an obvious one.
We're going to need another one.
We're going to need some sort of
count which we'll initialize to 0.
And this count will tell
me how many characters.
And the other thing I'm going
to need is some sort of buffer
to store the data into.
So as I create the characters,
I will store them in the buffer.
In this count, as I go through the
buffer, can index into this array.
All right, so that's my initialization
step is to set the counter equal to 0.
And the counter will tell me how
many elements are in the buffer.
So as we saw, we're going to
create the number this way.
We're going to create
the digit this way.
We're going to create the
digit by taking n in modulo 10.
That's the remainder of the
division of n divided by 10.
And then we'll reduce the
simplicity of the problem,
reduce this complexity of the
problem, by dividing by 10.
Now the numbers are getting smaller.
And if I take any number and divide
it by 10, it'll eventually hit 0.
I have to place this number somewhere.
So I'm going to store it in the buffer.
I'm going to store the
digit into the buffer.
And increment my count.
And you can see I'm getting
pretty close to writing C code.
So my last flowchart is going
to be easy to translate.
And now I will test to see if I'm done.
If the number n is not 0,
that means I have more digits.
If the number is 0, then I'm done.
Let's start with the example 123.
The first time through, I'm going to get
a d equals 3 and then this will be a 12
and then I'm going to
store the 3 right here.
Increment this to a 1.
Keep repeating.
The second time through,
I'm going to get the 2.
And I divide, this will be the 1, I'll
store the 2 here, this goes to a 2.
Third time through, I'm going
to get the hundredths digit.
This will become 0.
I will store the 1.
And now count is equal to 3,
telling me I have 3 elements.
But now I'll drop out of the loop.
That was this part of the flow chart.
Now let's finish the second
half of the flow chart.
I know that there is a counter which
tells me how many digits I have.
And I know I have a
buffer which contains
the digit in the opposite order.
And so if counter equals 3, I know
the first digit that I actually
want to output is a
2, at the index of 2.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to get the digit back
from the buffer at counter minus 1.
And that will give me the
most significant digit.
I will create an ASCII character out
of it by adding a 0x30 and that will
convert the 0 to 9 into an
ASCII character, '0' to '9'.
And then I'll output this
number to the device.
In our case here, we're going
to output it to the UART.
And then we will repeat this loop.
I know exactly how many
times to go through the loop
because I have an initial
value for counter.
And then I'll decrement the counter.
Counter minus minus.
And then if the counter-- I want to
output, as we can see from the things,
I want to output the
2, the 1, and the 0.
And so I'm going to quit as long as
counter is greater than or equal to 0.
I will go back.
But if it is equal to
minus 1, then I'm done.
So we saw the process of a successive
refinement is to take the big picture
and add details to it.
And there were three
fundamental things you
should remember when we write
software is where to start,
how to make progress, and how to end.
And so in this case here, we
started with the ones digit.
We made progress by taking
the remainder and simplifying.
And we got done when n is equal to 0.
Let's look at the other example, 65432.
This buffer, again, would have had the
numbers in the opposite order, 2, 3, 4,
5, and 6.
Count would have been equal to a
5 because there are five digits.
And then we would have wanted
to output them in this order.
6 and then a 5 and then a 4
and then a 3 and then a 2.
And this loop here would have reversed
the order from 2 to 6 to 6 to 2.