http://youtu.be/KIOJTpdS4d8
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right,
let's put the pieces together.
This is the startup.s.
There's the Reset Handler, which is
where it begins when you hit the reset.
Down here we see that
SysTick_Handler, which we'll do next.
But the one we're doing
today is the PortF_Handler.
So when we touch the
switch, this location
will specify what
software gets executed.
That is our vector.
All right, let's look
at the initialization.
We're going to activate the
clock, clear our counter.
The direction register is equal
to a 0 because it's an input.
We're going to enable the
pin for digital signals.
We don't care about the alternate
function or PCTL, or the analog mux.
We do have to have a
pull up because this
is PortF bit 4 on the LaunchPad,
which requires a pull up.
And here are the four bits
that we saw in the last video.
IS equals 0.
IBE equals 0.
IEV equals 0.
And to arm it, we're going to set
the IM, or the arm bit equal to a 1.
When we write to the ICR,
it will clear the flag.
This is the code which
sets the priority 7
register to set the
priority for this interrupt.
And then we're going to set
bit 30 of the enable register
to enable the PortF edge trigger.
And lastly, we're going to enable
all interrupts by clearing the I bit.
Here's our interrupt service routine.
On the trigger, which is
the falling of the switch,
we're going to first acknowledge
by clearing the trigger
flag by writing a 1 to the IC register.
And then we're going to
increment the counter, which
will count the number of
times a switch is pressed.
And then we'll return from
interrupt by just simply returning.
The main program doesn't do much.
It initializes the system and
then waits in this wait loop.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Now let's run it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah.
All right, to run it, we'll download it.
And we're going to run debugger.
This is the real board.
We're going to set up a watch down here
so that we count the number of edges.
And then we're going to
hit the Go button up here.
And we're going to see down here
in this window how many times we
pressed the button.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Now I'm going
to press the button and release it.
So that's the touch
caused an increment by 1.
I'm going to press and
release a second increment.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: It works.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And press
and release the third increment.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
So in summary, we've seen that important
events are set to trigger an interrupt.
We'll set the priority
of that interrupt.
We'll set its vector
so we know where to go.
We will arm it to say we're
interested in interrupts.
We'll enable it in the nested
vector interrupt controller.
And we'll clear the I bit so
all interrupts can happen.
And when the trigger
event occurs, we will
perform the action
required by that interrupt,
and then acknowledge the interrupt,
which is clearing the trigger flag.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So next, let's take
a look at another interrupt, a
commonly used interrupt, which
is the periodic SysTick interrupt.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's.