http://youtu.be/PCfkXtJ549s
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: There
are two interrupt service
routines to run on a robot.
The first is a periodic
interrupt called SysTick,
and it will generate the pulse
width modulated output on PA5.
So we are going to see PA5 look like
this, where the time when it's high
is an H and the time
when it's low is an L.
The bus clock is
running at 80 megahertz.
And this time here is going
to be one millisecond.
And so these H plus L,
which we saw was a constant,
is going to have to be 80,000 to get
the period to be one millisecond.
So what I'm going to do
in my SysTick interrupt
is I'm going to look
and see what happens.
So in other words, if PA5
is already equal to a 1,
I'm going to set PA5 equal to a 0.
Then if PA5 is equal to a 0,
I will set PA5 equal to a 1.
That will cause the output
to toggle on every interrupt.
And we're going to get an
interrupt on each of these times.
The interrupt's not
entirely regular, but we're
going to get an interrupt
on each of those times.
And the way I'm going to make this
work is if the output is a low,
I'm going to set the reload
value equal to L minus 1.
And if the output is a high, I'll set
the reload value equal to H minus 1.
And the minus 1 is because, as
you know, it counts down to 0.
And that is my flow
chart for the output.
And this will generate a
pulse-width modulated signal on PA5.
I'm going to use the two
switches on the LaunchPad,
switch 1 and switch 2,
to allow the operator
to select how much power
is delivered to the motor.
And I'm going to create an
edge-triggered interrupt such
that I get an interrupt on the falling
edge of either of these two buttons.
And in order to communicate between
this interrupt service routine, which
is edge-triggered, to this
one, which is periodic,
I'm going to pass data through global
variables H and L. And so if switch 2
has been pressed-- and I will
look at its raw interrupt status
to see if that one caused the interrupt.
So what I'm going to do is speed
it up by subtracting 8,000 from L.
That's going to change it by 10%.
Down here there will be a calculation
of H which is equal to 80,000 minus L.
But in order to make sure
it doesn't wrap around,
I'll make sure L is larger
than 8,000, in order
to test so it doesn't
go all the way to 0.
If it's not switch 2,
we'll look at switch 1.
And if its raw interrupt
status is set, that
means I got it
edge-triggered on switch 1.
And if its H is small enough, then
I will add 8,000 to the L value.
So again, we'll look at the value
of L. And if it's small enough,
then we will add 8,000-- which if I
add 8,000 to L and then I calculate H,
this will slow it down
or supply less power.
And there's one last thing I have
to do is acknowledge the interrupt.
And I acknowledge the interrupt by
setting the interrupt clear register
and then return.
So this is a flow chart of the system.
The SysTick will produce the
pulse-width modulated output,
And then the edge-triggered interrupt,
the falling edge on either switch
1 or switch 2 will cause
the power to the motor
to either be increased or decreased.
All right.
Let's look at the software.