http://youtu.be/p4QevDMCuKo
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Next we're
going to test the robot car.
Similar to a logic
analyzer, an oscilloscope
is a non-intrusive hardware
debugging instrument
that allows us to observe signals in
their amplitude versus time behavior.
I have connected up to channel
0 one end of the motor.
So we see when the output is a 0
to the motor, power is applied.
On channel two we have the output
of the microcontroller, which
is the PWM, or Pulse Width
Modulated Signal here at 10%.
So over here we've got a
measurement going, 10%,
and now we're going
to push some buttons.
And now we're going to 20%.
You see the motor has started.
30%.
Faster.
40%.
50%.
60%.
70%.
80%.
90%.
And the motor is now spinning very fast.
So in summary, the microcontroller
adjusts the power to the motor
by adjusting the duty cycle.
And we see for each of the patterns,
the period was exactly a millisecond,
but we adjusted the duty cycle.
And this measurement was
obtained with an oscilloscope.