http://youtu.be/uRbhW-gimZI
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I'm Jon Valvano.
In this video we will use
edge triggered interrupts
to solve a real time problem.
The problem we're
going to solve is we're
going to have a switch attached to
PF4, and when we touch the switch,
there will be a falling edge on PF4.
The action I wish to perform
is to increment a counter.
This is a software action,
and so the interrupt
is going to trigger a software action.
And the time between the hardware
event and the software action
is called latency.
This is a time delay between
a desire and an action.
And if this latency is less
than a bound, in other words
it's always less than
some number, then we
will classify this system as real time.
In order to make this real time,
we're going to use the interrupts.
The interrupt is going to cause a
trigger on the falling edge of PF4.
We'll acknowledge the interrupt,
which is to clear the trigger,
and then we'll increment the variable.
After incrementing the variable, we'll
return back to where we came from.
Next we'll show you the steps
involved in initializing
the edge triggered interrupts.