http://youtu.be/3727LI4TIeE
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Professor Yerraballi,
what are we going to learn today?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Today, we're going
to look at an important
topic, interrupts.
Interrupts are what make embedded
systems truly responsive and ready
for real time.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Interrupts
are my favorite topic,
and they allow the computer to work
on multiple tasks just like humans do.
When the phone rings, we answer it.
And when the alarm goes off, we wake up.
And when I'm hungry, I eat.
So just like humans, some tasks
can be scheduled in advance.
But there are other tasks that we
just respond to when they happen.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So if everything was
done using busy-wait
synchronization, that
would look like me staring at
the phone for it to ring instead
of just picking it up when it rings.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Yes, interrupts allow
the system to make efficient
use of processor time
so that we can perform other tasks while
we're waiting for the I/O to complete.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Of
course, for interrupts to work,
we need support from both the processor
and the device that it interfaces.
Devices can be internal,
like the SysTick counter,
or they could be external
like switches and UART.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: From a programmer
standpoint, we will do three things.
First, we must initialize the interrupt.
And second, we'll have to write
an interrupt service routine which
processes or services that interrupt.
And third, we're going to need a way
for the interrupt service routine
to communicate with the main thread.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And
from a processor standpoint,
we will look at what happens behind
the scenes when an interrupt occurs.
That is we look at what transpires
upon a context switch-- that
is from the background thread
to the foreground thread
or the foreground thread
to the background thread.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes,
but Professor Yerraballi,
you know I like to build things.
What are we going to build?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: We're
going to build something fun.
In fact, we're going to build a
robot car using DC motors that
will control the duty
cycle of the DC motor
by using interrupts to
control precise timing.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: But
I don't like to go slow,
and this car will go really fast.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Yes, so let's build it.