http://youtu.be/S9Jay8ib9yc
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO:
All right, let's look
at the software used
to control the motor.
Let's begin with the initializations.
We're going to use
port A for the output.
So I'll activate its clock.
We have two global
variables, H and L. And they
are going to be
initialized to some value.
This value doesn't matter.
But they're initialized.
We're going to turn on port A bit 5 in
the usual way-- no analog, direction
registers, and output.
I am going to set the 8
milliamp output current
because this has to drive
the base of the TIP120.
So I'll enable 8 milliamps out of PA5.
And I'll enable it, and
then initially make PA5 low.
I want to run SysTick.
So I'm going to set the
reload value equal to L,
and so it will run for
this initial value 8,000.
And writing a 0 to the current
will cause the counter to clear.
In order to use interrupts,
I need to set the priority.
And so in priority 3 register,
these eight bits, or specifically
the top three bits of
this register, will
specify the priority of the SysTick
interrupt, which I'm going to set to 2.
This is interesting,
because priority matters
because I have to interrupts running.
But I'm going to set it equal to 2.
And then to turn on
SysTick interrupts, I'm
going to set the interrupt enable
bit, at the clock source bit to 1,
and the turn on the SysTick to 1.
That's a 7 in the control register.
So now my system is initialized.
Next, let's initialize the two buttons,
switch 1 and switch 2, in port F.
Again, we're going to turn
on the clock for port F
and wait for the clock to stabilize.
Since we're using PF0,
we have to unlock it.
So we write this value
to the lock register.
And then we can commit and
allow us to write to those bits.
This stuff in the middle
is the usual stuff
we've been doing over and over again.
PF4 and 0 are inputs.
They're configured as general
purpose I/O, no analog.
They do have a pull-up, because
there's no pull-up on the board,
so we have software pull-ups or
internal pull-ups in the chip.
Now comes the interesting part.
And that is to set up an
edge trigger interrupt,
we need to specify it's edge-sensitive
as opposed to level-sensitive.
And that's by clearing the
bits in the IS register.
So it's edge-sensitive and not level.
We have to specify the edge by
setting these two registers.
IBE is not both, but it is falling edge.
So we're going to zero the corresponding
bits, bit 4 and bit 0, for all three
of these.
So it will be falling edge
edge-triggered interrupt on port F.
I like to clear the flags in the ritual.
So the first interrupt
occurs after I'm all done.
So when you write to the IC
register, that'll clear the flags.
They probably weren't set,
but I'm a little worried
about that sort of thing.
We do want to arm it.
And again, all of these bits
could've caused an interrupt.
But in this case, we're only going
to interrupt on bits 4 and bit 0
from the two switches.
I mentioned priority with SysTick.
I'm going to mention priority
again and set the edge trigger
to interrupt on port
F, also to priority 2.
Because I'm going to share
to global variables, H and L,
I need to make sure that they're
always in a consistent state.
So if this interrupt is priority
2 and the other one's interrupt
is priority 2, those two interrupts
will never suspend each other.
They're equal brothers
in the priority scheme.
So one will not interrupt the other.
So H and L will always be consistent.
Now, the edge trigger interrupt
is an external device.
So we need to enable it in the
nested vector interrupt controller.
That's here in register EN0.
This bit is interrupt 30, which is that
edge-triggered interrupt on port F.
You notice I have not
enabled interrupts yet.
Where do I do that?
Let's look in the main program.
One of the good design practices is to
go through the initialization process
with interrupts disabled.
That means no interrupts can happen.
Set the bus clock to 80.
Set the SysTick interrupts to be on.
Output enable PA5.
Arm and enable the PF4 and
PF0 falling edge interrupts.
And then after the entire
system is completely enabled,
initialized, then I
will enable interrupts.
So the first interrupt has to occur
after all the initializations.
So I'm not getting interrupts
before I initialized.
The other interesting thing to
observe in the main program,
and that is this entire robot controller
is going to occur in the background.
So all the software to control the robot
occurred in the two interrupt service
routines, which we'll
look at in a moment.
But the main program is
free to do other things.
And as grandma said, when you leave
the room, turn off the lights.
So if there's nothing else
to do, this will actually
enter a low-power wait state
for those interrupts to occur.
All right, let's look at the interrupts.
Let's look at the SysTick
interrupt service routine.
Again, this occurs
twice every millisecond.
If the signal on PA5 is equal
to a 1, this will be true,
and we will then set it equal to a 0.
We'll clear PA5.
And then we're going to run, for
the following L minus 1 cycles,
with PA5 low by setting the
reload value to L minus 1.
Well, if PA5 wasn't equal to a 1,
it had to have been equal to a 0.
That's the else.
And so in that case, what
we'll do is we'll turn PA5 on.
And then we will leave PA5
on for H minus 1 bus cycles.
So in this way, we have PA5, which is
high for H cycles and low for L cycles.
And this whole time here is
going to be one millisecond.
All right, let's look at the
other interrupt service routine.
OK, let's look at the
interrupt service routine.
We saw that this could occur on
the falling edge of either switch 1
or switch 2.
And the raw interrupt status register
will let me know which one occurred.
So if the raw interrupt
status bit 0 is set,
we know that switch 2 was
the one it was touched.
And so what we're going to do is, if
there's room, if the L is big enough,
we will then decrease L. Decreasing
L will cause it to speed up.
And then after we looked at
switch 2, we'll look at switch 1.
Again, the raw interrupt status bit 4
will tell us if switch 1 was pressed.
And if switch 1 is pressed and if L
is small enough, we'll make L bigger.
Making L bigger, as we saw,
will cause it to slow down.
And then in all cases, we will force
H plus L to be equal to 80,000.