http://youtu.be/sTxtG1UX1_0
JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's look at the steps
involved in configuring an
edge triggered interrupt.
The hardware step is to
connect PF4 to the switch.
That's the one on our LaunchPad.
The software steps are to make it an
input, to not do alternative function,
not do analog, to not do PCTL,
so all these bits will be zero.
The interesting step is the
set up for the edge trigger.
We have the direction bit, the input
sense bit, we have this IBE bit,
we have this IEV bit,
and we have this IME bit.
And these are the bits that we will set
to specify the mode for edge trigger.
In all of the modes, we're going to
set the direction register to a zero.
And in our case, we're
interested in edges
so we were going to set the IS bit
equal to zero and that means edge.
The next is we're going to clear the
both bit because we don't want both
but we do want the rising
edge or the falling edge.
So the IEV bit zero means it's
a falling edge, edge triggered.
The IEV bit equal 1
would be a rising edge.
And the last mode we could look at, or
use potentially, is the both mode equal
to a one.
Doesn't matter what this
one is, and in that mode
we're going to get both interrupts,
both edges will cause an interrupt.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So if I was
pressing a switch then Jon,
it would interrupt on the
touch and the release?
JONATHAN VALVANO: That's
what this mode would do.
But the mode we're going
to use is this mode here,
because we want just a
touch to cause an interrupt.
This last bit will be
a one and that says,
once you see the interrupt-- once you
see the trigger-- cause an interrupt.
So the idea of an arm, is the
trigger will cause an interrupt.
So the mode we're going to
use, is this mode right here.
Next, let's look at some
other things we have to do.
Interrupts use vectors.
Vectors are addresses
which tell the system
where to get the software to execute.
And so there are lots of
vectors in the system.
The particular vector that
we're going to be using
is the one here located
at address 0x000000B8
and this is going to be the port
F interrupt service routine.
This vector table are 32-bit addresses,
and they begin at location zero.
So at location zero is
the initial stack pointer,
at location four is the initial program
counter, somewhere in the middle
will be our SysTick vector, and
the one that we're interested in
is the port F, the port
F interrupt service
routine which is located
down here in ROM location B8.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So for each interrupt
that is available on the LaunchPad,
there's a corresponding
entry in the interrupt vector
table that tells the system
what interrupt service
routine to run when that
particular interrupt occurs.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Exactly.
And there are hundreds of them.
The one we're interested
is this one right here,
the port F interrupt service routine.
Next let's talk about priority.
Priority is like you'd imagine.
Priority means if two things happen at
the same time, which one goes first?
Which is most important?
And there's a register on the
system called priority seven.
And it turns out that bits 23,
22, and 21 of this register
will specify a number
between zero to seven
and set the priority for
the port F interrupt.
Each interrupt that's
possible has a three bit
location in one of these priority
registers to specify it's priority.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
priority does not just
pertain to two things
happening at the same time.
But if one priority-- one interrupt
service routine is currently running,
and if another interrupt
were to occur, the question
of whether this interrupt
continues or is suspended
and this new interrupt that
occurs, gets processed.
The priority answers that question.
If a higher priority
interrupt were to occur,
then the current interrupt
service routine is suspended.
The new interrupt service
routine runs, and then
control returns to the interrupt
service routine that was suspended.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Exactly.
So a high priority
interrupt service routine--
let's say this one is a priority
one, and this one is a priority
two-- a high priority interrupt can
preempt a low priority interrupt
service routine.
In this example, we're going to set
the priority for this interrupt to two.
Which means a zero or one could preempt,
but a two through seven would not.
So we saw the vector and the priority.
Next we're going to have to look
at an enable for this interrupt.
There are two enables.
There's one specific enable in the
nested vectored interrupt controller,
enable register zero.
And it turns out that bit 30
will have to be set at one
to enable the port F interrupts.
And the second, is a global
interrupt enable for all interrupts.
And that exists in the PRIMASK
register, which exists in the processor.
And that's the I bit.
And the I bit has to be zero to enable.
And if it happened to be a
one that would mean disable.
All right, next let's
look inside at the port F.
There are three registers in
the port F edge triggered mode.
Each of the bits in port
F could be edge triggered.
And the one we're interested
in, is port F, bit four.
So we're interested in bit
four of these registers.
And the IM is the arm bit which we will
set one, once in the initialization
such that we want port F to have
an edge triggered interrupt.
The actual trigger bit is right here.
There's the trigger bit.
And we can look at if you want to.
The trigger bit here is in the RIS--
raw interrupt status register--
and there's the trigger bit.
And we have one more bit, bit four
of the interrupt clear register.
If we write a one to this bit that
will acknowledge or clear the trigger.
In summary, the hardware-- which
is the falling edge of PF4--
will set the trigger, and the
software will acknowledge the trigger
by writing a one to the
interrupt clear register.