http://youtu.be/sNhlNi0zL2A
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
This is Ramesh Yerraballi.
Let's take a look at another interrupt,
which is the SysTick interrupt.
The SysTick interrupt is used
to generate periodic events.
That's one of its uses.
So we'll see an example where we want
to produce a wave, a square wave if you
will, where on port F, bit 2, we
will produce a square wave like this.
It's going to be on and off for one
millisecond, on one millisecond, off,
and repeats this process.
So that's our problem.
So the way we're going
to solve this problem
is we will periodically interrupt.
And every time we
interrupt, we will toggle.
The software action will be toggled PF2.
So this is our trigger and
the action is toggle PF2.
So let's take a look at the
components of our program.
The initialization involves our SysTick
registers, the control register,
the reload register, and
the current register.
So we will set our control register
to 0, disable during set-up.
We will set our reload value
to a calculated period.
This period corresponds
to our 1 millisecond.
And the calculation is that
our clock is at 16 megahertz.
And at 16 megahertz, 1
millisecond is 16,000 times
62.5, which is 1 millisecond.
So our count is going to be 16,000.
So that's what we call it.
And as Jon indicated in the previous
program, we need to set the priority.
The priority for the
SysTick interrupt is
in a different register, which is the
priority three register of the Nested
Vectored Interrupt Control.
And we are setting the priority to
be equal to 2 by this statement here.
And the last thing we will
do is we will enable SysTick
because we finished the initialization.
And then we will enable interrupts
by setting the I to be equal to 0.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Professor
Yerraballi, this 7 is new.
Last time, we wrote a
different number to it.
Last time, we wrote a 5.
Why is it a 7 now?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
that's a good question,
because previously when we enabled
SysTick, we wrote a value of 5 here,
which was a 101.
Now we have a different value,
which is 111 instead of a 101
which corresponds to a 7.
So this bit here is
to enable interrupts.
That is, we're saying that when
SysTick crosses the boundary where
it goes from 1 to a 0 transition,
we want an interrupt to be flagged.
And that's a bit to say that.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
So let's take a look at
how the code is set up.
So first, we initialize
the SysTick interrupt
by calling the SysTick_Init
with this value, 16,000,
which corresponds to 1 millisecond.
We enable interrupts.
And our while loop is just sitting
there waiting for the SysTick
to be fired off every time
it crosses the 1 0 boundary.
And this is just a wait for interrupts
so that we are in a power saving mode.
So now when the interrupt trigger does
occur, we execute the SysTick_Handler.
And within the SysTick_Handler, we
perform a toggle on port F, bit 2.
And we're also incrementing a counter
to keep track of how many times
we did this flipping of the bit PF2.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
how are we going to test it?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's test
this by running it in our simulation.
So we're going to make sure
we're in simulation mode.
So we go to our debug.
It's in the simulator mode, OK.
And I'm going to go ahead and--
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Build it.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: --build it.
And I'm going to run it.
And we have already set
it up so that the Logic
Analyzer is monitoring port F, bit 2.
And we also have a
viewer here that shows
us our SysTick timer, the registers
corresponding to SysTick timer.
And this is on PF2 which
we can look at here
or we can look at in the Logic Analyzer.
So let's go ahead and run it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ooh.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And we see
the SysTick causing interrupts.
And we can measure the time
between our two interrupts.
And that's 5.6 to 5.690, so that's
pretty close to 1 millisecond.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Works.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: It works.
And we can also see
the LED here, but this
is a visual that doesn't
tell us whether it's actually
going on and at 1 millisecond.
So we looked at how the SysTick can
be used to generate a square wave.
But maybe there's some
interesting applications for this.
Jon, what do you think?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah.
We can use this type of
wave to control our motor.
So we're going to build a robot and
use this SysTick wave to apply power
to the wheels.
Should we build it?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's do it.