http://youtu.be/vjboJ9rDEJM
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's
take a look at communication.
I'm going to call those the
inter-thread communication.
Remember that we talked about how
we have our main program, which
is running some code repeatedly,
and we have our background threads.
So background thread is some interrupt
service routine that's being triggered.
That's triggered.
It performs some task, and it
returns from the interrupt.
And there could be a
second one and so on.
So the question is, how
does information get
passed between the main thread
and the background thread?
So first, we might think that well,
we could use something like variable,
a local variable if you will,
or a register to put things in.
And we will realize that when we do a
context which all that information is
lost because we have a new context.
So what can we use to
communicate between the two?
So the part that is accessible to
both the main and the background
is memory, so the global memory.
So let's see how this will work.
We will look at it in three examples.
The first example we will
look at is communicating
between the background and
foreground using a simple flag.
A flag like this could involve the
main program is waiting for some event
to occur, and the background
thread will allow the main program
to know that this event has
occurred by raising a flag.
The second one is a
little more substantial.
That is, we will
communicate back and forth
using what I call the
concept of a mailbox.
A mailbox involves actual data that
is being communicated and a status.
So we have data and status.
So we'll use two global
variables for this.
The third one is what
good real time systems
should use because they allow for
good asynchronous communication.
These are buffers.
And specifically, we'll
use a First in First Out
queue (FIFO), which allows us to buffer.
So the background thread, if it wants
to communicate to the main thread,
adds to a buffer.
And the main program is going
to consume from this buffer.
So this will be the
third one we'll look at.
So let's look at the first example.
The first example involves
where the main program
wants to know whether
an event has occurred.
And the occurrence of this event is
through an interrupt service routine.
So the occurrence of the event will
be indicated by the interrupt service
routine by setting a flag-- which
is a global variable-- to 1.
It sets that and it quits.
Now, the main program which was doing
its work-- whatever that work was it.
This is the work of the main
program, the task, the main task.
It was performing that task, but
it periodically-- actually every so
often-- it'll check this flag.
And if the flag is set to
1, then it does some work.
So it'll do some work
associated with that event.
And then it goes back and
does its other calculations.
On the other hand, if
the flag is not set,
then it'll just go back and do
what it was normally meant to do,
which is repeat the core work
that it was meant to design for.
And one thing we have
to be sure is that when
we have in fact done the work associated
to the event, we will disable the flag.
We'll set it to 0.
This way, when I come back
to check the flag again,
I'm not finding the flag to be on
simply because I did not turn it off.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: We can
extend this idea of a flag
to incorporate passing of
data through a mailbox.
The mailbox has two components.
It has the flag, just
like the previous example,
but we're going to add a data field.
In this particular example
of a mailbox, the purpose
will be to pass data from the interrupt
service routine into the main program.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
For example, the UART
could have been triggered by
the arrival of a data packet.
And so the data that is
being read from the UART
could be put into this data
buffer, if you will, a mailbox.
And the flag is raised to
indicate to the main program
that there is fresh data.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So in
the interrupt service routine,
we will read the data
from the input, and we
will write it to a global variable.
And then we will set the flag to a 1.
Now, the main program, which looks a
lot like this, is checking the flag.
If the flag is 0, that
means there is no data.
Then it will do something else.
But if the flag is a 1, there is data.
Then, we can process or observe
or look at or enjoy this data.
It's called consuming the data.
We will use it up.
Whatever we're supposed to do
with that data, we will do.
And then just like we did with
the flag, we will clear the flag.
And so we notice that there is a clear
definition of what this mailbox is.
If the flag is equal to 0, that means
there is no data and the main program
is waiting.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Doing other things.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: But if the
flag is 1, that means there is data,
and the main program, if it
notices it, can take the data.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
this is a classic paradigm
called producer consumer paradigm.
The background thread is
going to produce data.
And the foreground thread, which
is our main thread, consumes data.
So Jon, can we also have
the other way around?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
The main program could be the producer.
And what it would do is it would write
into data and it would set the flag.
And the interrupt service
routine could be the consumer
and it would check the
flag and then use the data.
So data could flow in the
other direction in a mailbox.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
this allows for communication
between any threads in any direction.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
Let's look at the third
way to communicate,
and that's called a FIFO, or
a First In, First Out buffer.
If we're passing data from
the interrupt service routine,
this means this is
probably an input device.
If we're passing data, we are
going to put that data into a FIFO.
This is a buffer which
will store this data.
When we put, we're going
to put it into this FIFO.
It's a buffer that contains data.
The main program, when it
wants data, it will call Get.
So there are two functions with a FIFO.
And then it will consume
that data or use it up.
And so the data flows from the producer,
which is, in this case, the interrupt,
through the FIFO into the main
program, which is the consumer.
There are two functions, Put,
which stores data in, and Get,
which stores it out.
So the FIFO has a number
of properties, one of which
is it is order preserving,
which means the order in which I
put it will match the
order in which I get it.
So data is streamed from
one thread to another.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the FIFO
is extending the idea of a mailbox.
A mailbox is just one data item.
But now we've expanded it so that we
can have n data items, many data items.