http://youtu.be/8gEZlEu5GxY
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: This is the
robot car with two DC motors--
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Operated by these two switches.
The switch-- one will reduce the speed,
the other will increase the speed.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's go faster.
Here we go.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So this is a high duty
cycle, which you already know about.
And we'll see whether the car--
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's go.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: --moves fast.
So here's the car moving really fast.
Good catch.
Let's see what's the maximum
speed we can operate it at.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah, faster!
Do it again.
Come on, let's go!
[LAUGHTER]
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And you
could operate it at a low speed.
This is a 10% duty cycle.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Car won't move.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Not enough umph.
This is a joyride.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I think it needs
sensors to tell where it's going.
Don't you?