http://youtu.be/O33fg9621QI
JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's look
at how the DC motor works.
We have a north magnet,
and a south magnet.
And this will produce a B field, and
this will create a magnetic field from
north to south.
Next we're going to have a wire.
This is a course on robots and embedded
systems, so we're going to have wires.
And through this wire, a
current is going to flow.
So if current flows through
this wire, and this wire
is perpendicular to the
magnet, then what will happen
is a force will be induced on the
wire such that the magnetic field--
the electrical current and the force--
are all orthogonal to each other.
The actual interface to create
these magnets, these electromagnets,
will be to have a winding-- and
we saw that in our stepper motor--
such that if I were to drive
current through this circular path,
that will create a magnetic
field in this direction.
From an electrical standpoint, we
will see the motor has three parts.
The resistance of the windings, the
inductance of the coil, and then we're
going to have this magic
electromotive force.
Interestingly enough, this
conversion is two directional.
So mechanical force can be
converted to electrical energy,
and electrical energy can be
converted to mechanical energy.
So the micro-controller, in order
to generate electrical energy,
has to produce current through the coil.
And this current, times the voltage
across the coil, as you know is power.
And if we take power and we do
it for a certain amount of time,
we're going to have energy.
So this is the essential conversion
here, that occurs in the interface.
So let's look at this interface.
We're going to have an output
port of the microcontroller.
This will be a digital output
as you know, zero or 3.3 volts.
And it's going to go
through a 1K resistor.
The currents through these
motors are quite large.
The one on our stepper motor car
will vary from either 100 milliamps
all the way up to one amp depending
upon how much load there is.
And these currents are way too large
to connect to a microcontroller.
So we're going to use a current
amplifier, or transistor.
And so this is the coil, which as you
saw contains some R some L and EMF.
And to prevent things from exploding,
I'm going add a snubber diode.
Right there, that's a 1N914.
And because this is a
one AMP motor, I'm going
to use a transistor which can
drive lots more than one amp.
I'm going to use a TIP120.
This is an NPN Darlington which
essentially amplifies current.
And so I'm going to have current on
the order of milliamps driving out
of the microcontroller, into
the base, down to the emitter.
And this current is going
to be amplified such
that I can have up to an amp of
current flowing out of my battery,
across the motor, across the
collector, down to the emitter,
and down to ground.
Here's our circuit again.
Let me remind you how to connect
it up to the microcontroller,
without exploding the microcontroller.
Because now we have lots
and lots of current.
The battery here, it's
going to control the robot.
And it's is important to
connect the battery such
that the current flow comes out
of the battery, across the motor,
and it will flow across the
collector of this transistor,
and back to the battery.
And the current-- this
one amp of current
is not going to flow into
the micro-controller.
Now we are going to need to
power the microcontroller.
So we're going to take
this 8.4 into a regulator--
just like we did with the stepper
motor car-- to get a 5 volt output,
and tie this into VBUS.
But these currents here are very tiny.
So the microcontroller
current, the lower current--
which is on the order
of 10 to 50 milliamps--
to control the board, that's going
to flow through this direction
and back to the battery.
And so we see we've got
two separate current paths.
One for the motor, and
one to drive the board.
And so we have our LaunchPad
powered in this way.
OK, now it's time to
write some software.
We saw that the energy applied to the
motor is a function of the voltage.
Which in our case, is
fixed at 8.4 volts.
The current, which is also
fixed, from 100 milliamps to one
amp depending upon the load and time.
And it's the time parameter
that we're going to control.
So I'm going to connect
the circuit to PA5.
I could've used any output pin.
And I'm going to create what's called
a pulse width modulated signal.
Basically I'm going to
adjust the parameter time.
And the way I'm going
to do a pulse width
modulated signal is going
to create a pattern, such
that the period-- or the
frequency of this wave-- is fixed.
But the duty cycle is going to vary.
So if I labeled this time H for
high, and this time L for low,
that's the time.
And there's an H and
there's an L and there's
an H. I'm going to fix the period by
forcing H plus L to be a constant.
And I'm going to control the duty
cycle, by having H over H plus L vary.
And so the microcontroller
can make the motor spin faster
by increasing the duty cycle.
Or even-- or even faster.
And we can see here that the period of
each of these waves, which is H plus L,
is fixed.
But the duty cycle will vary.