http://youtu.be/pStlJQ4WiRc
PROFESSOR JONATHAN
VALVANO: In this video,
let's look up how to
connect the audio jack.
Now, there's lots of audio jacks
out there, but this one is typical.
Let's look and see if we
can find how to connect it.
So down here, it tells us that
there are terminals, and the three
terminals that most of the
jacks have is this one here,
which is the sleeve,
which will be our ground.
And most of them have a
seven, which is the tip,
and we'll have a six
here, which is the ring.
Hey Justin, which is which?
What's the ring and tip?
JUSTIN: The tip is the left channel
and the ring is the right channel.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
So Justin tells us that
the tip is the left channel
and the ring is the right channel.
To see it as a circuit,
we can scroll down
and see that the equivalent
circuit for this jack.
again, is the sleeve and
the tip and the ring.
So we're going to connect our output
across the sleeve and either the ring
or the tip to make our sound.