http://youtu.be/V7mA-2kw_ys
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's talk about sound.
We're going to see sound
from two perspectives.
We're going to see some
from the generation.
How do we generate sound?
And then we're going to look at
sound and how we perceive it,
and how the perception happens.
Our micro controller
is going to control.
It will use our DAC to
convert the digital to analog.
And then we'll use a speaker
to generate the sound.
The sound is a air pressure.
And so we're going to have pieces
of air at high pressure followed
by pieces at low pressure.
High pressure, low pressure,
high pressure, low pressure.
And this sound is going
to-- this pressure
wave is going to traverse the air.
And our ears are going to perceive it.
The ear drum will oscillate, and
we'll touch the nerves in our ear
and our brain will perceive the sound.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So some
perceived this way, visualize this way,
is change in air pressure.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
And if we look at this air
pressure, we can visualize it
as an oscillation of pressure.
And so, we can see
that at any given spot,
the air pressure is going to
oscillate with respect to time.
The other way that we can perceive
sound, or understand sound,
is the fact that this pressure
wave actually travels.
And so this pressure is
also oscillates in space.
So the wave actually propagates away
from the generator to the perceiver.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So now that
we've looked at what sound is,
let's look at the properties of sound.
First, we know that sound
can be visualized as a wave.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And so
there are properties of this wave.
One of the obvious properties
is the period of this wave.
And one over this
period is the frequency.
And when we talk about sound,
we define this frequency
as the pitch, high pitch or low pitch.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: The second
property of sound, or in a wave,
is the amplitude.
In the context of sound,
we call this loudness.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So if the sound
is much louder, it will be bigger.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
So, let's take a simple note, a
sound that all of us can relate to,
an A-note on a piano or a keyboard.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
This A note is going
to oscillate and 440 cycles per
second, so we'll call it 440 Hertz.
If we were to go down an octave to the
octave below, we get another A note,
and it oscillates at one half
that frequency, or 220 Hertz.
If we go 1 octave up, then it'll
oscillate twice that, or 880 Hertz.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we can
have notes in between things.
Let's look at some notes that
are useful and make a nice sound.
The note G which is at 392 Hertz,
the note E, which is 329.6 Hertz,
and the note C which is 261.6 hertz.
You will see that these numbers
have a relationship when
you do the lab for this
class, this particular module.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Yeah, in the lab, where
it's going to use these four
notes to generate a piano.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, we saw sound
can be described by three properties-
the frequency of sound, the
amplitude, or the loudness of sound,
and there's a third property,
which is the shape of sound.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So if you
wanted to listen to a trumpet,
you would see that the trumpet wave
looks different than the sine wave
that we drew in the last picture.
The shape of this sound is different.
It still oscillates, but it's
not as regular as the pure tone
that we did in the last slide.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's
put all of these things together.
We're going to build a system
that will produce sound
by converting digital
signal to an analog sample.
We'll hook up a speaker that'll
produce sound that we can listen to.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
All right let's go.