http://youtu.be/FTOcCjC5gbU
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's look at the software
needed to create the sound wave.
We saw the wave is periodic.
And we're going to use a
data structure which contains
the numbers 4, 5, 6, 7, 7, 7,
6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 2, 3.
This data structure,
this array, is going
to contain the numbers which
represent the shape of my wave.
We'll have an index which varies from
0 to 15 as we index into this array.
And the output is going to be the
DAC, as a function of this index,
is going to represent the shape.
4, 5, 6, 7, 7, 7, 6, 5,
4, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 2, 3.
And then what will happen is the
wave will repeat over and over again,
4, 5, 6, 7, 7, 7, 7.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, so let's take a look
at the initialization of this DAC.
First, we'll look at
the port initialization.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And
so the DAC initialization
will produce 3-bit output
on port PB2, PB1, PB0.
And these three bits are connected to
our DAC that we saw in the last video.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
And now we will look at the
initialization for the SysTick
periodic interrupt.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
We've used SysTick before.
The important thing for us to
remember is this reload value
here will specify the rate
at which SysTick interrupts.
And this will be an important
design parameter for our system.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Next, let's
look at the interrupt service routine.
So the SysTick handler is the
interrupt service routine,
which gets executed every time
the SysTick interrupt occurs.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So recall
that what we want to create
is this wave, 4, 5, 6, 7, 7, 7,
6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 2, 3.
And then it will repeat
over and over again.
This is our DAC output.
But now what we're going to do
is change this access to time.
And we're going to do that by
generating a SysTick interrupt.
And in the SysTick interrupt, I
am going to do one DAC output.
And if I do exactly one DAC
output, if I write to port B
exactly once per
interrupt, what'll happen
is the time between these
two numbers is going
to be a function of the period
of the SysTick interrupts.
And so we can see that
every 16 SysTick interrupts,
we're going to have one
cycle of our sound wave.
We've got to finish and
update our Index so that we're
pointing to the next entry of the table.
And then we quit.
So right here, we see we're
going to increment the Index.
And when it gets to 16,
we'll roll it back over.
So the Index goes 0,
1, 2, 3, up to 14, 15.
next time, it'll be 0 again.
So in summary, we're going to produce
one output to the DAC every interrupt.
And we're going to control the
frequency, the pitch, of this sound
by adjusting the rate at which
we SysTick our interrupts.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So what
about a plan for testing this, Jon?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Real important.
We're going to do two types of tests.
The first is a heartbeat.
And a heartbeat is a minimally-intrusive
debugging instrument.
Every time we're going
to get an interrupt,
we're going to toggle port F, bit 3.
And so if we looked along this curve,
we're going to see port F, bit 3
toggle every time there's an interrupt.
So in this way, we can see whether
our software is living, or is it dead.
The second instrument
is a non-intrusive.
We're going to use the oscilloscope
and actually look at the DAC wave,
and see if we get this picture.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
let's look at the main, then.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: The main
program initializes our devices.
And if the switch is
pressed, what we'll do
is enable interrupts and
set up the SysTick so
that it generates a periodic interrupt.
And if the switch is not
pressed, we'll disable
interrupts, which will stop the sound.
Let's see how we calculate
this number 50,000.
We know we want 100 Hertz sine wave.
And we know that there
are exactly 16 outputs
of the DAC per one cycle of
the sine wave, the output wave.
And we know we have an 80 Megahertz
bus clock that's controlling SysTick.
And if we perform this
calculation, we will
get the 50,000 used in this program.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK,
so we've designed everything.
So let's build the system.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All
right, let's build it.