http://youtu.be/BHLSiifPEes
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's build a system.
We'll use our life
cycle, which means we'll
begin with the design of the system.
We'll develop a prototype.
We'll test to make sure it works, and
then we'll deploy the embedded system.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
system we are going to build
is controlled by a switch, and it's
going to produce a sound, a 100 Hertz
sound, which is our sound
that we are going to look at.
And we will design both the software
and hardware that goes into it.
And we will use systick
interrupts in the software,
and we will design a DAC
as part of the hardware.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
Show me the DAC.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we will take
a different approach to the DAC here.
We've seen two designs for
the DAC that are possible.
One, which is a binary-weighted design.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And that's
the one you're going to use in lab.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And now we
look at a different design, which
is called an R-2R ladder design, which
is a design that a lot of the chips
have in them that produce sound.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
how does the R-2R work?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's take
a look at this R-2R ladder circuit.
As described, it's going
to be a bunch of resistors
that are hooked up this way, which is--
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Don't
talk while you're erasing.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
-that are hooked this way.
We have our three signals,
and we have our resistors.
And this is where we're going to
connect our headphones or our speakers.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So why
is it called an R-2R ladder?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the resistors
that we use will be in the ratio R-2R.
So there's an R here to our 2R.
This will be a 2R.
And this is a 2R, and this is a 2R also.
And so if, let's say, we
picked our R to be 11k.
And that's a good choice because
of the way our voltages work.
And so the 2R is going
to be simply a 22k.
So the way we are going to connect
this to our microcontroller
is we have our three bits.
This is bit 2, bit 1, bit 0.
And we connect this to our bit 0.
We connect this to our bit 1,
and we connect this to our bit 2.
And we connect this to the ground.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So the lowest bit
is furthest away from the headphones--
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: -physically.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And we'll see why that's
the case once we do our computation.
Now, the analysis of this is done easily
using the Principle of Superposition.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
So what does that mean?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's take
a look at how superposition works.