http://youtu.be/5LveKTMGuEM
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Hey, Ramesh.
Let's build something.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, so let's build a DAC.
Remember what a DAC does.
A DAC is a digital to
analog converter, which
means when I have my microcontroller
produce a digital value,
we write to the DAC and the
DAC produces an analog value.
So maybe it produces one
particular value on a signal.
Some signal.
So, we want to see how to do this.
And we will do this by
using this circuit for it.
There are two designs that we
can do for the analog circuit.
One is a binary-weighted circuit.
The other, which is more popular in
systems, is an R-2R ladder circuit.
The binary weighted design is
intuitive, so we will do this first.
So our goal is to produce
a signal, so we've said.
Let's say we're working
with a three bit DAC, which
means that I have eight levels.
So our precision-- so
we have a three bit DAC.
We have eight levels, and the eight
levels are from zero to the seven.
And we are going to write that down
here- 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
And we want to produce a voltage.
And let's assume our voltages
are between 0 and 3.3 volts.
So we want to use an analog
value-- this is our digital--
and we want to produce
an analog value, Vout,
which ranges between 0 and 3.3 volts.
Well, each of these then
will be a fraction of that.
So this will have a value
of the 3.3 times 1 over 7.
This will be 3.3 times
2 over 7, and so on.
So when we get here, it'll
be 3.3 times 7 over 7.
That will be my voltage.
So that's my behavior
that I want to get.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So what's
the resolution of this DAC?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, as we see
the smallest change we can capture
is a difference between consecutive
values, which in our case
is 3.3 divided by 7.
So our resolution delta
And our precision, again, is eight.
So that's the design we're looking for.
So let's design this.
So again, here is our
schematic, microcontroller.
And we're going to use
three bits for now.
It doesn't matter.
I'm going to call them bit
two, bit one, bit zero.
So this is our bit two,
bit one, and bit zero.
So, we're going to use
the three bits, and we're
going to produce our output,
which is going to be our Vout.
And the way we're going to do that
is we're going to connect resistors.
And we make an observation that
each of these bits-- this bit
has a position of one, this
bit has a position of two,
and this bit has a place
significance, or place value of four.
So when we choose our
resistors, we will choose them
in that ratio, which
is 4 is to 2 is to 1.
So we will use the-- bit two will
have 11 K, we'll have 22 K here,
and this will be a 44 K
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So which one
is twice as much as the other one?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So bit zero is-- remember
that bit zero has a place value of one.
So the resistance, that is, whatever
signal comes out of here for a one
has half the significance as bit one.
So in order to do that, we
subject it to a higher resistance.
And so the lower the significance,
the higher the resistance.
So bit two has the highest significance,
so it has the least resistance, which
is 11 K. And notice the ratio
between these three is 11 is to 22
is to 44, which is 1 is to 2 is to
4, which is exactly what we want.
So let's analyze this circuit
to see how it behaves.
So let's take our table again.
This is our N. This is the bit values.
And I'm going to represent
them by Q2, Q1, and Q0,
which is basically what I see here.
Q2, Q1, and Q0.
So, if I have zero, this is a
0, 0, 0, and this is my Vout.
Now if I have an N value of
one, then what I have is 0,
0, 1, which makes this
a 0, this a 0, and this
is a 3.3 volts-- I'm going to
make because I have a one here.
And similarly, I have a
two, which is a 0, 1, 0,
so that's 3.3, and 0, and three
which is 0, 3.3, and 3.3, and so on.
And I'm just going to write one more.
Four, which is 3.3, 0, and 0.
And so on, all the way up to
seven, which is all three bits
are on- 3.3, 3.3, and 3.3.
So we'll calculate how our Vout is.
So first, I'm going to do an
analysis for one of these.
So let's do an analysis of our four.
So the circuit for this situation is
we have a 3.3 here, a 0 here, and a 0
here, which gives us a
equivalent circuit-- I'm
going to draw the equivalent circuit
here, which is our 11K with a 3.3.
And we have these two,
which are in parallel,
and they connect to our zero volts.
And we want to find out what Vout is.
And Vout is with respect to zero,
so we want to find out this voltage.
So if I were to convert this--
and remember these are 22 K,
and this is a 44 K. So if
I were to convert this,
the equivalent circuit looks like
this, where I have 22 times 44.
Remember these are in
parallel by 22 plus 44, which
gives me a value of 44 by three kilohms.
OK, so I have 44 by 3
here, and I have 11 K
they are in series, and what
I have is a voltage divider.
So I know that Vout is going
to be given by a value, which
is 44 by 3 divided by 11 plus 44
by 3 times 3.3, which comes out
to be 4 over 7 times 3.3.
So that's my 4 over 7 times 3.3.
Now it's a good idea to do one where--
there are two of them that have a one.
So let's take this example of three,
which says now my equivalent circuit is
going to be one where I have a 0
here, a 3.3 here, and a 3.3 here.
So now I have this
circuit, which is my 0.
And I'm going to draw it
this way-- let me clear it.
So the equivalent circuit is this,
where I have my two resistances, which
are 22 K and the 44 K, which
are in parallel with 11 K.
And 11 K is at 0 volts.
One end of it is at 0 volts,
and this is my 3.3 volts,
and I want to find out
what the voltage here
is, which is my Vout,
which, by the way, is
the voltage across the resistance, 11 K.
So, again, my circuit is similar
because we already calculated it.
So this is a 44 by 3, this is
11 K, and this is my V out,
and that's 3.3 and 0 volts.
And so it's a voltage divided.
But now my Vout is given
by 11 divided by 11 plus 44
by 3 times 3.3, which gives me a
3 over 7 times 3.3 volts, which
is 3 over 7 times 3.3 volts.
So similarly, we can fill
in the rest of my analysis.
So this is a three bit DAC
using a weighted design.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So Professor
Yerraballi, what will they do in lab?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So in the lab,
you will take this idea of the design
and extend it to four bits, which means
that you will add an extra bit, which
is B3, and you will make
a four bit DAC, which
will be much better,
because it'll be better
at more levels, more
precision, more resolution.
Therefore, when we
hook it up to a sound,
you can produce really
high quality sound.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, sweet.