http://youtu.be/DfuhVG5LKxA
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's
analyze the R2R ladder circuit
that we've used for our design.
So we have three situations here.
The three situations
correspond to our bit2 bit1,
bit0, being 0,0,1, which is my first
one; 0,1,0, which is this scenario;
and a 1,0,0, which is
the third scenario.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
the Law of Superpositions
says if we look at these
three basis elements,
and prove that these three
work, the other five, which
are combinations of these
three will also work.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
we see that, in this circuit
here, let's analyze this one first,
we see that all of these circuits
have something common to them
in terms of their behavior.
When they finally reduce them,
they will have this form.
That is, we will have a signal
that is at 3.3 volts with a 2R
and a R. That is, the net resistance
from the powering signal to ground
is going to 3R.
it's just a matter of combining
them based on what you already
know about series and
parallel resistors.
So if you did that, then we can
find out what the current is.
The current as we see
here that is leaving out
of this node, this node, or this node
is simply given by 3.3 divided by 3R,
which in our case is going to come out
to be 0.1 milliamps because R is 11K.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I see
you also ignored the speaker.
The 32 ohms of speakers is a very
small number compared to 11,000,
so you just ignored it.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Yes, that is correct.
So now what we notice then is when
we look at each of these values,
and we find out what the current
is, which this is I,0,I which is,
in our case, the current.
The first one is a I sub
0,0,1, which is this one.
In the second case, it's a I sub 0,1,0.
and in the third case,
this is an I sub1,0,0.
so we can calculate
this is by looking at,
for example, how I sub
0,0,1 gets calculated.
We have I coming out of
here, which we know is this.
It gets split.
And it gets split in 2R and this net
resistance is also going to be 2R,
so it splits halfway.
So half goes here.
Half goes here.
And then, when it comes
here, the same thing
happens, which is this
is going to be 2R.
So it goes half goes
here, and half goes here.
so we've halved it again.
And eventually it goes
half here and half here.
So what we see is that I,0,0,1
has been halved three times,
so it's going to be I divided by 8.
Similarly, here, we will have
this divide half and half.
And again, it will be exactly half.
And then it'll divide
half and half and half.
And so it's only divided two times,
so that's going to be I divided by 4.
And in this case, it is
divided half and half.
So it's only divided once,
so it's going to be I over 2.
So the law of superposition the tells us
that if I had a different combination,
let's say I had a combination which was
up 0,1,1/ Then this will give me a net
current of I over 8, which is because
of this bit which is a 0,0,1 scenario,
plus the 0,1,0 scenario,
which is an I over 4.
And similarly, we can evaluate the other
situation, so no matter what we have,
it's a simple linear combination
of our individual bits.
And lastly, 1,1,1 is going to be simply
I over 8, plus I over 4, plus I over 2.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So we have a
linear relationship between the number
N, which is between 0
and 7, and the output
current, which is going
across our speaker.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
And the higher the digital
value, the higher the current.
And that's how we know it is doing
a digital-to-analog conversion.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Well, we still
have to make it oscillate, don't we?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: How
are we going to do that?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So what we did here
is build the hardware
part of our solution.
Now we have to look at the software
part of our solution, which
is going to be using SysTick.