http://youtu.be/XOOEUhV9w5I
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, Jon,
what are we gonna learn today?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Today we're going
to build systems that work with sound.
We'll import sound with
a microphone, and we
will produce sound with a speaker.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
OK, so you mean we're
going to build systems that look
like MP3 players and recorders?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Well, yes, but rather
than deal with the complexities
of a format like MP3,
we'll focus on the fundamentals
of signal processing
as it applies to sound.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we will be
looking at concepts like digitization,
the Nyquist Theorem, and maybe
apply these concepts to build
a circuit hardware that converts
digital information to analog form,
or analog information to digital form?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
First we'll build a Digital
to Analog Converter, or DAC,
and we'll use it to create sound.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: The DAC circuit
sounds interesting, but where will
we use it?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Well, you know me.
If we don't build something that's
interesting and useful, it's no fun.
So let's build a DAC system that outputs
a hundred Hertz sine wave connected up
to a speaker, and we'll
generate a pretty tone.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, so we could
also watch it on an oscilloscope,
so that we can verify the function
by looking at a sine wave.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
This sine wave we will
use to shape our world.