http://youtu.be/IjNN3gRmmxE
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's take a
look at the concept of digitization.
JONATHAN VALVANO: The world we
live in is inherently analog.
That means the signals are
continuous, both in time and space.
However, computers are
inherently digital.
So Professor Yerraballi, how
do we capture analog signals
in a digital form?
RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is right.
So we have computers.
For us, it's a micro controller,
which is inherently digital,
because it stores information
in the form of binary data.
And we have the analog world,
which conveys information
as a continuous time varying signal.
And we have to interface these two.
So our first kind of interfacing is how
do we read information that's analog
and store it in digital form?
So what we need is a
conversion, which we call analog
to digital conversation, ADC,
which does that act for us.
The second possibility is when we want
to affect the world that is analog.
And the affectation is performed
by, again, a microcontroller.
So we have the information
in digital form.
And we want to convey it to the
outside world, which is analog.
And we do that by introducing a
module, which we will call a DAC.
A DAC is a digital to analog converter.
In some cases, the DAC could
be part of the microcontroller.
But for flexibility, we
will use external circuitry
that will do the job for us.
So let's take a look at some examples.
So when I look at
examples of analog stimuli
that have to be captured
in digital form,
I can think of simple things
like temperature sensors.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Sound.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Sound, which
is where we're doing recording.
We're capturing sound.
And we can think of pressure sensors.
JONATHAN VALVANO: There are signals
in the body, Bio-potentials,
you could measure.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
Biosensors-- we can think
of proximity sensors.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh, I don't
want my robot to hit the wall.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yeah.
And we have optical sensors.
Now, the world of
embedded systems is all
about being able to work with sensors.
But we also have the
counterpart, which is actuators.
So if we call these sensors,
which is the input part,
then the output is actuators.
That is, we produce a stimuli
which affects the world.
So again, we can think of examples
like controlling our motors
so that we send voltages
that power our motors.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Sound
could be an output, too.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Speakers.
We could have lights--
dimmers, for example.
What else?
JONATHAN VALVANO: Pacemaker uses
an output to trigger the heart.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
JONATHAN VALVANO: So it's another
biosensor, a bio actuator.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Bio actuator.
And our anti-lock breaks are outputs.
And we want the braking
to be controlled.
It's not an on off thing, but it's
something that has to be a variable.
So that's one.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Just like
temperature was an input,
it could be an output-- so our
heating and air conditioning.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So A/C could be.
So we have examples of
sensors and actuators.
So in summary, then, we
have the analog world
interfacing with our digital computers.
And we have our ADCs and
DACs that accomplish that.
So this module is going
to be focusing on DACs.
JONATHAN VALVANO: What's next?
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
next goal is to understand
what the fundamentals
of digitization are.
So we saw that the
purpose of digitization
is to take an analog
signal and digitize it,
which means to store it in a computer.
So we have an analog signal that's
continuously varying in time.
And for now, we will think of it
as a change in changing voltage.
And we want to digitize this.
So digitization is done
using two concepts.
One is our amplitude quantization.
So by quantization, we mean
discretizing the signal.
So we have continuous.
The opposite of continuous, as far as
a computer is concerned, is discrete.
So when we store our
information in the computer,
we store them as digital values.
So our amplitude quantization is
talking about separating our amplitude
into levels.
So we'll call these levels.
So the counterpart to
amplitude quantization
is to do time quantization, which
is also referred to as sampling.
So time quantization is capturing
the signal periodically,
or as we say, sampling
the signal, so that we
can capture the essence
of the signal faithfully.
So we have periodic capture of samples,
which we call as time quantization.
So let's look at what the trade-offs
are when we do amplitude quantization
and time quantization.
So the way we like to look at this is
if I have more levels, from a computing
standpoint, I have to represent
this by more bits per sample,
which means I have more levels.
If I have only two levels, I would
represent all samples by just 0 or 1.
But more levels means
more bits per sample.
From an analog standpoint, what this
means is I have better precision.
So we'll define the term "precision."
The term "precision" is
telling us exactly the number
of levels we can represent in a signal.
So I am assuming that I
have around 16 levels here.
If I have 16 levels, I
have four bits per sample.
So the precision is 16.
Now, what I also have is
this concept of resolution.
Resolution is the smallest change I
can represent in the analog signal.
So resolution is the
smallest change, which
means it's the difference between
levels that I can actually capture.
So what we are saying is
this captures precision.
Now, what we also see, then,
is if we have more samples--
then the rate of capture is
high-- then what we are saying is,
from a computer's standpoint,
we need faster processing.
Whether we are producing these samples
or we're captioning these samples,
we have to do more
processing per unit time.
What it means from an analog standpoint
is the more samples I capture,
the more faithful the
digital representation
is with respect to the analog signal.
As a matter of fact, we
will capture this idea
of faithfulness using a theorem
called the Nyquist theorem, which
for us simply tells us how
faithful is faithful enough?
That is, how many samples
per second is best
to capture the essence
of the analog signal?
So in summary, then, digitization is
about taking a continuous time varying
signal and discretizing
it so that we capture it
by these discrete points
that attempt to make
a faithful representation of the signal.