http://youtu.be/mo0kEPlOIvQ
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's
look at the Nyquist Theorem.
The Nyquist Theorem says that if a
signal is oscillating at frequency F,
in order to capture
it faithfully, we must
sample at a frequency
that is strictly larger
than two times F. The essence
of the Nyquist Theorem
is that if a signal is oscillating we
must sample faster than it oscillates.
The mathematical proof
for the Nyquist Theorem
is beyond the scope of this class.
But let me show you an example
that illustrates the concept.
We have a circular
running track, and we have
a person who is running
around the track.
And our job is to count the number
of times they go around the track.
Let's say the fastest one could run
is around the track in one minute.
So every 60 seconds, a fast
person could get around the track.
I'm a lazy person, and I
want to know, how often do I
have to look at my runner in order
to tell how many times they've
gone around?
So for instance, if
the runner is running
at a rate of one lap per one
minute, and I look every 15 seconds,
I will see them here.
I will see them over here.
And I will see them over here.
And I can count because I've
seen them before the finish line,
and I've seen them
after the finish line.
And so I can count that I've seen it.
However, if I count every two minutes,
then I'm going to see them here.
They're going to go
around the track twice,
and I'm going to see them again there.
And they're going to go around the
track, and I'm going to see them there.
And so I will be unable to count
how many times they've gone.
There's something
special about 30 seconds.
If I count slower than every
30 seconds, I will see them.
So in other words, if I were to
count at 40 seconds or 45 seconds,
I could potentially only
seen them once per lap.
And if I only see them
once per lap, I can't
tell whether they've going around
once or they've not gone around at all
and not moving.
And so it turns out that this magic
number, in order to solve my problem,
is, in order to tell how many
times they've gone around the loop,
I have to look at least every 30
seconds, which is my Nyquist Theorem.
The oscillation of my runner has
a frequency of one lap per minute.
And I need to look at least twice
per minute in order to tell.
Here's another example
of the Nyquist Theorem.
We're stuck back on the island,
and we want to get to the mainland.
But this time there's a boat.
And luckily for us, this
boat takes a periodic trip
between the island, the
mainland, and back to the island.
It takes about 12 hours
for the boat to go
one trip, island to
mainland and back again.
And while it's at the island,
it'll sit on the dock.
And luckily for us, it'll
sit at the dock for 12 hours.
So if we look at the signal,
is the boat at the dock?
We will see that it oscillates.
The boat is at the dock for 12 hours.
And the boat is not at the
dock for about 12 hours.
At the dock, not at the dock,
at the dock, not at the dock.
This is a periodic wave.
And we see that the
signal oscillates at once
per day, which means, according
to the Nyquist Theorem,
we must sample it at twice per day.
For example, if I go down
to the dock every 11 hours,
I'm guaranteed to see the boat.
There's no time that the boat
could come, stay at the dock
and leave that I wouldn't notice it.
So regardless of when I start looking,
I will get onto the next boat.
On the other hand, if I sample
the signal every 13 hours,
I am slower than the twice
per day, and it's possible--
In this case here, we see that
the boat came to the dock right
after I looked at it and left
right before I looked at it again.
And so we see there's something
magical about this 12 hours.
And looking at the
boat every 12 hours is
equivalent to looking
at it twice per day.
And so we see that if we sample
faster than twice the frequency,
we will capture everything we
need to know about that signal.
And that's the Nyquist Theorem.