http://youtu.be/7YvyQfn7s1o
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: We have
written the software, downloaded
onto the launch pad, and we
have built the R2R ladder.
Next we're going to debug it.
What we have is one channel
of the logic analyzer
connected here to the DAC output,
and we have the second channel
of the logic analyzer
connected to the heartbeat.
And now let's look at the output
of the DAC when we push the button.
On this screen over here,
we see the oscilloscope.
The orange is the DAC output,
and the blue is the heartbeat.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So I'm
going to press the switch, which
should cause an interrupt, which it's
being interrupted by the SysTick,
and we're producing a sine
wave in response to it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
We see that the heartbeat
toggles the output.
Every interrupt.
And so we can see that each
time we get an interrupt,
a new value is output to the DAC.
The numbers that we're outputting were
a 1, 1, 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 7, 7, 6, 5, 4,
2, 1, 1, 1 again.
And this pattern repeats over and over.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So, how do we verify
whether the time between interrupts
is correct to 100 Hertz, Jon?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
That's fairly easy,
because all I need to do
is measure the time
here to the time here
to see that my system takes
approximately 10 milliseconds
to generate one wave form.
So that's something I
do with oscilloscope.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
what does it sound like?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
Plug it in.
Let's see.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So let's plug it in.
So we'll plug in a speaker to our DAC.
And I'm going to play the sound.
And it sounds like 100 Hertz.
So if you play around with this,
we could get something more fun.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
That's what lab is for.
DR. RAMESH YERRBALLI: All right.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Your turn.