http://youtu.be/sNGe_UR5LVY
PROFESSOR RAMESH YERRABALLI: So let's
take a look at how the ADC works
and get that information
from the data sheet.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: All right,
the first one we're going to look up
is PSSI.
OK, so we go to the data sheet.
I'm going to use my bookmark.
And the ADC is Chapter 13.
And I want to find the registers.
And I'm going to look for PSSI, PSSI.
Come on-- there it is.
This is the processor sample
sequence initiate register.
OK, so in here, it'll
show us how it works.
We're going to write to bit three,
which will start sequencer three.
PROFESSOR RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Hence the value 8 here.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: All right,
let's look up the raw interrupt status
register, which has our flags in it.
So again, I'm going
to use the bookmarks.
Again, I'm going to use the
bookmarks to search for the register.
And the register I want is
RIS, Raw Interrupt Status.
There it is.
So here, it will show us
that each of the sequencers
has a raw interrupt status.
And bit three is associated
with sequencer three.
PROFESSOR RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we just
check for that bit to see the sample
is completed.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: There we go.
What else do I need?
PROFESSOR RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Let's look at the result,
where to read the result from.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, so
again, we're searching each register.
So we go back.
So we go back to our bookmarks.
And we're looking for the
FIFO sequencer three register.
And there are a lot of
registers of the ADC converter,
so we need a way to find it.
There it is.
Click on it, and we can see this
register is not very interesting.
But we can see that it is
a 12-bit register, which
will contain the conversion result.
One more register-- that's
called the ISC register.
PROFESSOR RAMESH YERRABALLI:
This is our acknowledge register.
This is the one we
have to make sure we do
to indicate that we've
read the converted value.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO:
There we go, let's find it.
PROFESSOR RAMESH
YERRABALLI: Right there.
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: Right
there-- there it is, the ISC register,
click.
And this is one of those
interesting registers here.
And you can see that it
is a read/write register.
But when we write a 1 to
it, it will clear the bit.
So this is one of
those interesting bits.
Let's go down and look
at it in the description
right here, that if we
write a 1 to this bit,
it will clear the corresponding
bit into the raw interrupt status.
There we go.
Again, don't be afraid
of the data sheet.
It's your friend.