http://youtu.be/3VGVkLo_FDg
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: A robot
used a TIP120 to drive the motor.
And let's look up a couple
of parameters on the TIP120.
First, we can see how to wire it up.
There's the base, there's the
collector, and there's the emitter.
Second, let's look up
and see what the gain is.
The current gain here, the
hFE for the TIP120 is 1,000.
Next, let's look up the
relationship between the input
voltage and the output voltage.
And so we can see that
here, that on this plot,
we can see a relationship
between the base emitter voltage.
So we're going to
drive it in saturation.
And the relationship
between the base emitter
voltage and the maximum
collector current.
So for instance, if we have a 0.5
A that we're driving to our motor,
we're going to have or need
a base emitter voltage here
of about 1.4 volts.
And once we put in 1.4
volts on the base emitter,
we're going to see that
our collector emitter
voltage will be about 0.75 volts.
So from this diagram, we can see
here that if the voltage here
is above 1.4 volts, there will be a
half an AMP of current that can flow.
And that will generate,
at most, about 0.7 volt
drop across that NPN
Darlington transistor.
So this is how we used
the data sheet to look up
the parameters for our operating device.