http://youtu.be/VNftf5qLpiA
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Today, we're
going to demonstrate aliasing,
which is what happens if we
violate the Nyquist theorem.
I've invited our videographer,
Justin, to participate
in this next demonstration.
Hey Justin, does your video camera
capture data in digital form?
JUSTIN: Yes, it does.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oooh, so
it must have a sampling rate.
So, do you know what
that sampling rate is?
JUSTIN: 24 frames per second.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Oooh, so I wonder what
happens if I rotate the motor
at 12 rotations per second.
I wonder what would happen?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Oh, I guess it
has to violate the Nyquist theorem,
so we should see the aliasing effect.
JUSTIN: Stop talking, let's see it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
we're now at 1.3 volts,
and we're spinning at that rate.
So I'm going to increase the
voltage so it should spin faster.
And it slowly spins
up faster and faster.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, ramping up.
Ramping up to two frames per
second, so two rotations per second.
Three-- And steady at three.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So, we're still
under the 12 rotations per second,
so you should still see the blue dot.
So let's go faster and see what happens.
Increasing voltage from
two to three volts.
So it should be speeding even faster.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
we're at six and rising.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Let's go even faster.
At four volts.
We cranked up the voltage so
the motor will spin very fast.
As it spins faster and
faster, watch the white spokes
as they appear to first spin
clockwise and then counterclockwise.
Next we cut the power and the
motor will start slowing down.
As it spins slower and
slower again, the spokes
will appear to spin clockwise
and then counter clockwise.
What we have witnessed is aliasing.
Aliasing occurs when the
input signal oscillates
at a rate greater than or equal
to one half the sampling rate.
In this case, the camera
samples at 24 frames per second.
So any image moving at a rate
greater than 12 times per second
will get all messed up.
Aliasing causes the apparent
rotations per second
to be different than the
actual rotations per second.