http://youtu.be/Tt9uL9IRyIw
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Hi.
I'm Professor Yerraballi, and this
is the University of Texas at Austin.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And
I'm Professor Valvano.
And today we're going to demonstrate
this robot we've been building.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, so John,
let's talk about some of the components
on that robot.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
There are three components.
The infrared sensors together
with A to D converter
are used to measure
distance to the wall.
The background thread, the
interrupt service thread
will generate two PWM signals to
control the power to the two motors
so that I can turn left and right.
And the controller, the
main loop of the software
will adjust the power to
the two motors and attempt
to drive straight down the road.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, so we saw
the software, we saw the components,
now let's see it run.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Yeah, let's try it.
Straight down the road, there.
Straight down the road.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Wally.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh, yeah.
Nice and straight.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yeah.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Nice and
straight, nice and straight.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Take it easy.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Look out for the wall.
Yeah.
And around the corner.
Yeah, Wally.
Good job.
Don't hit the cameraman.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So Jon,
what have we learned from this lab?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Today we learned
that the sensors collect information,
and the A to D converter
on the micro controller
converts that information
into digital numbers.
The software then can make
decisions on those numbers,
and then have outputs connected to
actuators that can affect the world.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So that's it.
Embedded Systems shape the world.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Indeed.