http://youtu.be/4XuVDdLqKrI
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Professor Yerraballi,
what are we going to learn today?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Today we're going
to see how computers can take stimuli
from the external analog world and
store them digitally in the computer.
So take an example.
Here's an example of a volume knob
in a rotational form or as a slider.
What's essentially happening
here is that the position
is a variable resistance.
So if we can convert this
variable resistance to say,
voltages between some
range, 0 to 3 volts, 3.3
volts, then we can take
that voltage and store it
inside a computer as 12-bit number
using an analog-to-digital converter.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
That means that any signal
that we can convert into
a voltage could then
be entered into the
computer with the A-to-D.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let
me show you some examples.
The first is a strain gauge.
And it could be used to
measure force or pressure.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Here's a thermostat
that can be used to measure temperature.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Here's
another temperature sensor.
It's an integrated circuit.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Here's a
microphone that measures sound.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Here's a digital camera.
It looks at the image and creates
a two dimensional digital array
of what it sees.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Here is a GPS that
senses the coordinates of where you
are, latitude and longitude (actually
the HMC6352 is a compass).
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Here's
the infrared distance sensor
we're going to put in our robot.
And it measures distance.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Here's
another distance sensor.
This is an ultrasonic distance
sensor that gives you distance.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Here is a
catheter that measures biopotentials.
This ring right here
is inside the heart.
And it allows the pacemaker to measure
the biopotentials in your heart.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Yes, as a matter of fact,
the LaunchPad has internal
sensors which sense temperature.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
what are we going to build?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: We're
going to build a robot.
And the robot car we're going to
build is will use infrared sensors.
This is different from
our bump sensors, which
sensed an obstacle by
actually colliding with it.
Now we can measure the
distance from the obstacle,
and then we're going to
take evasive action so
that we can avert bumping
against obstacles.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So this
is a classic control system.
In other words, our
objective is to drive
straight down the middle of the road.
And we're going to begin
by sensing where we are.
To tell where we are relative
to the middle of the road.
And then the software in
the computer will then
adjust the power to the two motors in
an attempt to drive fast and straight.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
So let's build it.