http://youtu.be/0PefsLtHGVw
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we've
looked at a transducer which
was a potentiometer that
gave us a voltage value
from a corresponding
variable resistance.
Jon, can we look at a
different device that
has some significance that we can
then use to control something?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah,
let's look at the sharp sensor.
The sharp sensor is an
infrared distance sensor.
That means it takes a
distance to an object
and it will convert it to a voltage.
This means if we connect it up
to PE2 in our microcontroller
then our software has access.
Because it's an A to
D, we can get a number
which is between 0 and 4,095
which represents the distance.
In order to understand
this, we need to look
at the voltage created as a
function of distance of this sensor.
And this is a very unusual and nonlinear
sensor that has this sort of behavior.
It has two phases here.
This first phase where
it's really close,
and that's less than 100 millimeters,
it behaves in this weird way.
But after 100 millimeters it
behaves in a very simple way
such that the distance is
approximately equal to some constant
over the voltage.
And so I can use this relationship to
write software such that my distance
variable-- this is now in
software, in millimeters--
is equal to the sum
calibration constant.
I did calibrate it.
And so the result I got was
241,814 divided by this ADC value--
this number that comes from ADC.
So what we have is a
software conversion here
which converts the number 0 to
4,095 which is measured by the a
to d into a distance in millimeters
which works from about 100
millimeters out to 700 millimeters.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So just to recall,
the voltage to distance
graph here is non-linear.
Whereas for our
potentiometer the voltage
to distance-- if you think
of the potential meter
as measuring distance-- then
that would be a linear graph.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: That's correct.
And the software doesn't mind
dealing with non-linearity
because we can just compensate
for it in this equation.
But what do we use it for?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Well, we've been promising
that we will build a robot car that can
avoid colliding with walls by sensing.
So let's put this to work.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
So the next step in our control
system is to look at the blocks.
The parameter we want to control
is called a state variable.
In our case it will be
where we are in the road.
We're then going to use transducers
to estimate what we know
and learn where we are in the road.
And then we're going to use a
control equation, which in our case
will be software.
And then use these outputs to drive
actuators that affect the real world.
So this is our world, which
is our robot on the road.
And we're going to estimate
where we are on the road--
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: By using a
transducer that is our infrared sensor.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
And the A to D converter.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And we perform some logic
which is the control equation.
This is the intelligence
part of our code.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
And we're actually going
to drive 2 pulse with modulated
outputs for the left and right motors.
And you notice that a control
system has a loop, a feedback loop.
And again, the desire is to drive the
state variable to a certain set point.
All right, let's put
the pieces together.
Let's look at more detail
of the state variable.
Here's our road.
And we're going to have
a wall and another wall.
And we want to avoid the wall.
And we're going to have
our robot car here, which
is moving in this direction.
And we're going to have 2 sensors
on the front of the robot.
And we're going to measure the distance
between the robot and left wall
and the robot and the right wall.
So we'll call this Dleft, that's
the distance to the left wall,
because we're going this way.
And this is the distance
to the right wall.
And how do you know if we're
in the middle of the road?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: I guess
Dleft should be equal to Dright.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah,
so what we're going to see
is, we're going to say we are
going to look at our error.
In other words, we are
going to be unhappy
if the distance to the
left wall is different--
so we'll calculate the
difference to the right wall.
And so the goal state is
to drive the error to 0.
Because if this state variable error
is 0 we're in the middle of the road.
So you remember our robot had 2 wheels.
And so what we have is PWM
outputs for both wheels.
And so for each PWM
outputs-- for instance
we have the right wheel high over the
right wheel high plus right wheel low.
And this controls the
power to the right motor.
In this example we're
going to fix this to 40%.
So the right wheel is
going to spin away at 40%.
The interesting part will
be on the left wheel.
On the left wheel we're going to
take the left high and let it change.
And again, the pulse with
modulated signal for the left wheel
is the left high-- the time in
which the left output is high
plus the time in which the left is low.
This pulse width modulation here,
this duty cycle, is going to vary.
We're going to let it vary
somewhere between 30% and 50%.
So as this varies
between 30% or 50% it's
going to be going
straight-- if its 40, 40.
40, 30 will turn one way.
40, 50 will turn the other way.
So this parameter here is the one I'm
going to adjust in my control loop.
So let's look at the
software flow chart.
This is a real time
problem so we're going
to use SysTick interrupts
to run our control loop.
So every periodic time, at
about 100 times per second,
we're going to run this control loop.
We're going to measure the distance to
the right and the distance to the left.
We're going to calculate
the error, which
we saw last time, which
was the difference
between the left and the right.
And now comes the fun part.
What do we do with it?
What I'm going to do with it is I'm
going to actually look at the left high
and I'm going to adjust it.
Either spin it faster or slower,
depending upon the error.
And I'm going to do this in a typical
control way by using a number.
It's called the gain
of this control system.
And I'm going to take the
error and multiply it times 200
and subtract it off.
So if I'm too far to
left, it'll turn right.
If I'm too far to the
right, I'll turn left.
Notice what happens here
if the error is equal to 0.
What happens if the error-- if I'm
in the middle of the road, what
does my control system do?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So if the error
is equal to 0, the left high stays put.
It doesn't change.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So if
we're happy, we'll stay happy.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And remember that we've
kept the right high at a constant.
So that doesn't change either.
So now we don't change either
of them, we stay the course.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
if we're in the middle,
we'll just keep being in the middle.
There's one more couple
of problems we have
to deal with is that we have to make
sure that it doesn't go below 30%.
And so if the duty cycle goes below
30%, we will set the duty cycle at 30%
so it doesn't completely stop
or try to spin backwards.
If it's OK then we will continue.
So if we look at the duty cycle here
of the left wheel, if it is too slow
we'll fix it at too slow.
Similarly, if it's too fast,
we'll look at the duty cycle.
If it is greater than 50% then we
will set the duty cycle at 50%.
And these two comparisons will force
the range here to between 30% and 50%.
We do have to calculate the other side.
The left low has to be set so that
this number here is a constant.
And that constant is
80,000 minus the left high.
And then we return.
So these are the steps
of my control loop.
We sense our inputs.
We decide if we're were happy.
We adjust the actual actuator
output so that we become more happy.
In other words, if we're too
far to the left, we go right.
If we're too far to
the right, we go left.
And this is a gain.
In other words, how fast do we turn?
In a control system we want to
make sure we don't go crazy.
So we'll check and make sure we have
a minimum and a maximum value that
makes sense for our actuator.
And then we perform the output.
And zoom, our robot is spinning.