http://youtu.be/zilfgmsXeeE
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
In this video, we will
demonstrate the fundamental
concepts of sampling.
Here is a slide plot similar
to the one you will use in lab.
The analog signal is shown in
the plot as the blue signal.
And the data points are sampled
as plotted by the red signal.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So if the
sampling were done faithfully
to capture the signal, then the
red line would track the blue line.
That is a digital capture would
capture the analog signal faithfully.
So what if it doesn't track?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Then
we get the wrong answer.
So there are many ways in
which the digital samples
are different from the analog samples.
The first is amplitude quantization.
That means that at every
point, the only choices
we're going to have are discrete
values between some number
and some other number.
Additionally, there
is an amplitude range.
In other words, there is a finite
difference, a finite range,
between which our samples must exist.
So in our case, that's
going to be 0 to 3 volts.
The third is time quantization.
Because we have to collect
the data into a computer,
there will be a finite time.
In this case, we can
see where the times are,
a finite time, that
the data are sampled.
And furthermore, one more, and that
is, the time interval is fixed.
In other words, no matter how much
memory we have in the computer,
there's always a finite
amount of it, which
means that we can only represent
the data from some minimum time
to some maximum time.
And these are the four limitations
that exist in sampling.
So let's review the components
of the data acquisition system.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
This is the system
that you're going to build for Lab 14.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: It begins
with something we want to measure.
In our case we're going
to measure distance.
This distance is converted by a sensor.
The sensor is connected to a
circuit, to give us a voltage.
The voltage will then
be input to the analog
to digital converter, which will
give us a number, a 12 -bit number.
Software, that we write,
will convert that number
into something that means
something, to a distance.
And lastly we're going to output those
results to a display, which in our case
will be the UART.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Here we're
showing you the data flow diagram.
So the data initially
is resistance, which
gets converted to a voltage, which
then gets converted to a number.
And eventually it gets converted to a
string which is displayed on the UART.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Exactly.
So let's look at the ADC
parameters, the fundamental behavior
of the analog to digital converter.
The first is Precision.
The precision is the number
of different alternatives.
How many different
values can we measure?
In our case, it's going to be
12 bits, or 4,096 alternatives.
The second will be the Range.
In other words, what is the minimum to
maximum voltage that we can measure.
In our case it will
measure 0 to 3 volts.
And putting those two together,
we can ask what is the Resolution?
In other words, the resolution
is the smallest change in voltage
that can be reliably detected.
These three parameters are related.
In other words, the
resolution is a function
of the range divided by the
precision in alternatives.
In our particular case,
the range is 3 volts
minus 0 volts, divided
by a precision of 4,096.
And this will result in a
resolution of 0.7 millivolts.
So any change in voltage here,
greater than 0.7 millivolts,
is detectable by the analog
to digital converter.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So in summary then,
if we have a really good sensing system,
and an analog to digital converter that
has high resolution,
what we're saying is
that it has it can convert and measure
even the smallest change possible.
So the higher the resolution, the
better the sensor, the more expensive
it's going to get.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Exactly.
All right.
Next we're going to see how the A to D
converter works in our microcontroller.