http://youtu.be/mAtri-cYSvk
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So in this video, we
will show you the essential process by
which the analog to digital conversion
occurs.
This is called successive approximation.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: There
are a couple of components.
The unknown input exists here
that we're trying to sample,
and will eventually show
up as a digital output.
We're going to demonstrate how
this works by playing a game.
And we need one person to be
mean and one person to be smart.
Professor Yerraballi, which
one do you want to be,
the mean one or the smart one?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: If you ask
like that, I want to be the smart one.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
So I'm the mean person.
That's me right here.
And what has just happened is I have
guessed a number, an 8-bit number.
And this 8-bit number can
exist from zero to 255,
but I'm not going to
tell you what it is.
You're going to have to guess.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: But you're
going to give me some hints.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I am.
So Professor Yerraballi is going
to make the guess right here.
And then I'm going to tell him
whether his answer is high or low.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
I'm going to guess 128.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
Good guess.
Professor Yerraballi guesses 128.
My answer is lower than that.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So it's lower than that.
So I'm going to choose 64.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, good guess.
64.
But not right.
My answer is lower than 64.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
Even lower.
So I'm going to guess 32.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, 32.
Well, now you've stumped me.
My guess is actually
higher, or it might be 32.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
So I will guess between 64 and 32.
I'll guess 48.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Hm.
48.
My guess is lower than 48.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
So 32 and 48.
I guess 40.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
You're getting closer.
My guess is higher than 40,
or it might be 40 itself.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
So how about 44?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
Closer still.
My guess is lower than 44.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Go on.
Give me your answer.
I'm going to go for 42.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Hm.
42.
My answer is higher than 42,
or it might be 42 itself.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK.
How about 43?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: My
answer is lower than 43.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Ah.
You got to be kidding me.
It is 42.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: It is!
Good guess.
My answer was 42.
And that's what will come out over here.
Do you want to see a cool trick?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yeah, show me.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
What if every time you
guessed, I gave a binary value?
What if I said low meant
0 and high meant 1?
So you guessed low, low, high, low,
high, low, high, low, in that order.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Ah.
So what you've done is
in each guess you're
guessing one bit of the binary
representation of the number.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Starting
with the most significant bit
and winding down to
the least significant.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah.
So if you look at this
first guess, we can
see something very
significant happening.
By guessing 128, I was forced to
tell Professor Yerraballi what
bit seven was, and I did
that by saying it was low.
Then, knowing bit seven,
he then guessed bit six.
And one by one, he guessed each bit in
order from bit seven all the way down
to bit zero.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
That's a cool trick.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
It's not really a trick.
It's actually how your A to D converter
in your microcontroller works.
It's called successive approximation
because each guess reveals one bit.
So with our 12-bit
converter, the same process
happens, except it
has to guess 12 times.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
the ADC conversion speed
is linear with the number of bits.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is,
if I double the number of bits,
it's going to double the amount
of time to reach an answer.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.