http://youtu.be/YCScddUsZZA
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
we looked at the two steps.
One is the initialization step,
which is what this routine is doing.
The initialization ritual, which we
do one, which is a 13 step sequence.
You can look at all the details here.
We talked about it.
This part here is simply making the GPI
pin be an alternate pin and an input.
So this is saying input.
We did the clock.
We did the alternate bit.
And then we did select, and we
enabled (Disable digital) it.
Now, the second part is we
turn on the clock for the ADC.
We wait for a little bit too
for the clock to get going.
We set the sampling rate.
We set the priority of the sequencer.
We disable it and enable
it between these two steps.
And while we are configuring
it, the steps involved
are, what is the trigger we're using?
We're using software as a trigger.
We are saying, I'm using channel
PE2, which is analog in one(AIN1).
And we made sure that IE0 is set to one.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I have a
question, Professor Yerraballi.
Why did you disable the digital input?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Oh, that is correct.
In fact, what we did for the
D-enable is we turned it off.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah, but why?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That
is because it's not digital.
It's analog.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, yes.
You're right.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: All right.
So let's take a look at our second
routine, which is our routine
where we're actually
going to be read the data.
So this is a data read routine.
This is when there is a sample,
and you're ready to read it.
And this routine has been called.
This routine's responsibility
is to tell the ADC module
that you are ready to read
it, which is our first step.
OK.
Let's take a look at the read routine.
We've already seen it, so
I'm going to summarize it.
We start.
And once we get the
sampling going, we'll
keep checking to see if it is done.
So you're we're going
to check the status bit.
And if the status bit
says that it's Busy,
then we keep going back
and keep checking it.
And eventually, it's
going to say it's done.
And once it's done, we're
going to read the data.
And we're going to clear the bit.
So that's exactly what you see here.
This is a start.
We have a loop here, which
repeatedly checks the status.
Then we come out of this.
We read the data, which is
right here in the FIFO3.
And the last step is we cleared
the bit, which is right here.
And we return the results.
So we return.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
Shall we see if it works?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Let's do it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
So we have a analog signal
connected up to PE2.
So to test it, we ill
use this main program.
And we will ask the ADC
converter to capture the input
and store it into this variable.
All right.
Let's go.
Build.
Download.
Debug.
Let's look at the watch window.
And in this watch window,
we have the variable
that we're going to set
every time we sample.
So let's hit the Go button.
In this watch window, we can see
the results of the ADC converter.
That's a 12-bit number.
So Professor Yerraballi,
make it go smaller.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
I'm sliding the slide-pot.
And it's moving it to the right.
And I moved it as right as I can.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh,
that's a small number.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And it's a small number.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
The ADC converter goes from zero
to, what number does it go to?
Let's see.
Ooh, bigger.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Bigger.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Bigger.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: I'm moving it.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Come on, faster.
No, not so fast.
Slow it down.
There we go.
And the largest number is 4,095.
There we are, 12 bit converter.
Now, you try it.