http://youtu.be/tXt4c7_Uz98
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
in the last module,
we saw how stimuli in the external
world can be captured by our computer
as long as it's rendered as a voltage.
So in this module, we'll look at how
your micro-controller does this job.
That is, we'll look at the
process of setting it up,
and then we'll look at the
process of capturing the samples.
So on our micro-controller,
which is our launchpad,
we have several of the GPIO
pins that play dual roles.
So what we mean by the dual role is
we'll choose their alternate function.
So there are 12 pins which
are called 12 ADC pins which
are capable of receiving analog
inputs, which are as rendered voltages,
and then converting them to 12-bit
numbers using the ADC module on board.
So among these 12 ADC pins,
two pins are the ones we
going to focus in this course.
One is PE2.
And the other is PD3.
This is referred to as Analog in 1.
And this is referred
to as the Analog in 4.
By the way, we've already
been using PD3 all along.
This is that analog pin that
is used to measure voltages.
This was our way of measuring
voltage on our circuit all along.
But AIN1, which is what
we're going to use today,
is going to be used to measure
voltages from an input device.
So let's get started on
looking at all the device
registers that we have to
manipulate to make ADC work.
So like any device that we've looked
at, in order to manipulate the device,
we have to work with an
initialization sequence.
The initialization
sequence is done once,
or what we call as a set-up sequence.
And the setup sequence
for ADC involves 13 steps.
I'm going to summarize
the first few steps.
The first one through five steps
are things that you already
area familiar with, which
are make sure that the GPIO
pin-- here a GPIO pin for port E--
pin 2-- is properly configured.
So which means we turn on the clock.
We make it an input.
So we manipulated the
direction register.
We enable its alternate function, which
is the most important thing, which
is different from what
we were doing so far.
So we enable its alternate function.
And then we (disable) it.
DEN, we (disable digital) .
And once we are done with
it, we have another one,
which is an AM select function.
We do that.
So this is my five-step
sequence, which is something
that you're already familiar with.
So what is different to
make it an analog ADC pin
is the next sequence of steps.
So our first step that's specific
to ADC is we turn ADC clock.
Like we turn on the clock
here, we'll turn this one on.
We do that by making sure
that RCGC0 bit 16 is set to 1.
So the next step we're going
to do, which is step seven,
is we're going to configure the speed.
And the speed is the speed at which
we're going to capture our samples.
There are multiple speeds ranging from
1 million samples per second all the way
to 125K samples per second.
And we effect that--
we make that change--
by making sure that we
manipulate these two bits.
And for now, I'm going
to make these two bits
0 0, which says that
I've chosen the 125K.
So that's 125K samples
per second, which is
the minimum speed at which I can sample.
The eighth step, then, is our sequencer.
We have four sequencers.
We don't have to worry about them.
We're using sequencer 3.
Sequencer 3 is chosen.
And we also set the priority of it.
So because there are four sequencers,
the priority is set by a two-bit number
here.
And we're making it the highest
priority by making it 0 among the four.
The step nine is while I'm
configuring the rest of the system,
I'm going to disable.
And when I'm done at the end, which
is my last step, which is step 13,
I will enable.
This way, I'm making sure
that while I'm configuring it,
I can make sure that the
sampling doesn't occur.
So I do that by manipulating this
bit, which is my activation bit.
So I turn this off.
And I turn it on to affect that.
So it goes from 0 to 1 eventually.
So our next step is step 10,
which is we choose the trigger.
That is, when we have
analog input connected,
it can be triggered
by various mechanisms.
But in this class, we're going to
use a software-initiated trigger.
So it means that I will not
expect any interrupt or anything.
I'm simply going to tell when
I want to choose to sample.
And when the sampling is
done, I will read it myself.
So I do that by manipulating
these four bits here.
And these four bits for us is going
to be the simplest case, which
is all 0s, which says that I'm
using software as a trigger.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Professor
Yerraballi, how do we
tell it which channel to sample?
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, so everything
we did here doesn't really
tell us anything about
what channel we're using.
So our next step will
involve exactly that,
which is my step 11, which says
that I want to choose channel 1.
Remember, there are 12 channels.
They go from 0 through 11.
And so I'm going to choose
channel 1 out of those.
So 1 is the I'm trying to choose.
So I need to specify that.
And I do that by
writing a 0, 0 0 1 here.
And that's my channel select.
Channel is AIN1.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Now is channel
1 always connected to PE2?
Or is that some kind of choice?
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: It is
always connected to PE2.
And it's hard-wired.
And that's why we have selected
the alternate function for PE2
to be its alternate function,
which happens to be analog AIN1.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, OK.
One more step.
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we have
one last step left, step 12,
which involves manipulating
these four bits.
The only bit of real interest to us is
this bit here, which is the IE0 bit.
And what it's telling us is that we want
a flag to be set when the sampling is
complete-- set flag on sample capture.
The other bits, for now, are going
to be 0 here, a 1 here, and a 0 here.
So that's going to be 0
1 1 0 into this, which
is a 6 is what we're going to write.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: So we do this once.
And so next, we're going
to have to show you
how to write software that actually
does the conversion-- starts, waits
for it to be done, and captures it.
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
So we looked at the
initialization ritual.
Let's look at the sample
capture procedure.
So to capture a sample, I'm
going to follow this logic, which
says start with initialization after
sampling by writing to this bit a 1.
So I make that bit a 1.
And then the ADC device
starts its capturing.
And then I'm going to check for a flag.
So I'm going to check whether RIS bit
3 is a 0 to indicate that it is Busy.
So if it's busy, I keep
checking back again and again.
And when it's 1, it tells me
that the capture is complete.
So once the capture is complete,
I'm going to read the data.
So I will read data, which means
that I've done this busy step, which
I found this to be 0 for a good bit
of time and eventually it became a 1.
So I come down here and then
I'm going to read this data.
So read data.
So the last thing I need to do is
to make sure that I clear the flag.
I clear this flag by writing a 1 here.
So the act of writing a
1 there will make sure
that this flag goes back to a 0
so I'm ready for the next sample.
And then I return.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: I have a question.
Do these registers act like memory?
In other words, if I write a
1 to them, it will become a 1?
And if I write a 0, it will become a 0?
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Well, these
are really not memory registers.
These are device registers.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So they
don't behave like memory.
They behave more like inputs
and outputs to a device.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: So if
I write to one register,
it clears a bit in another register?
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yeah.
Because it's a memory-mapped I/O.
PROF.
JONATHAN VALVANO: I see.
Cool.
All right.
Enough talking.
Let's build it.
PROF.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: All right.