http://youtu.be/eKnmfacxfX4
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
In this video, we're
going to show you how to configure
the slide pot, the potentiometer,
to do this lab.
Most of the potentiometers
have these extra tabs.
Now, notice that there are
two types of pins on here.
The pins labeled one, two, and
three, those are the important pins.
Don't bend those.
But these other big
fat tabs we don't need.
So I'm going to bend
them out of the way.
So I grab my suppliers, I hold on
tight, and I bend it out of the way.
Now, notice I didn't bend
pin one, two, or three.
I just bent one of these tabs.
So I'm going to take all the
tabs that I don't need to
and I'm going to bend
them out of the way.
And that was two.
Take this one, bend it out of the way.
Take this one, bend it out the way.
OK.
So now I have left three pins.
Pin three is going to be
connected to plus 3.3.
Pin one will go to
ground, and pin two will
be connected to the
analog-to-digital input.
And as we saw, we're going to use
PE2, which is analog channel one.
So now I can flip this over and
plug it into the protoboard.
Notice that pin (three) is
going to be tied to 3.3,
and down here we have pin one going
to the ground-- that's this one--
and pin two is going to the
analog-to-digital input.
And so now we have our
slide pot here, which
can be used to create
our analog voltage.
One last important step is we're going
to convert this pot to a distance
measure by attaching a scale to it.
And so if I define the measurement
point as right here, that
is 0 millimeters, 5 millimeters,
10 millimeters-- you see,
my edge is right here at 10
millimeters-- 15, and lastly 20.
Now some pots have more
or less millimeters,
but they all go from
one side to the other.
And so now I've created the transducer,
which I can use to measure distance.
Have fun building it.