http://youtu.be/VyEAtqWR1dQ
PROFESSOR JONATHAN VALVANO: Next, let's
show you how to make your own images.
But this is an optional step
that you can do if you want.
So this is the starter project.
And I'm going to look inside the files.
And I'm going to edit one of
the Space Invader art files.
So I'll find an enemy and we'll edit it.
So I'm going to open this enemy here.
And I'm going to open him in Paint,
your favorite drawing program.
And any application that
can edit BMP files can work.
Now, as you can see, it's pretty small.
So let's make him bigger.
So in this mode, we see
that a white is going
to show up as a pixel on the screen.
And a black will show up as a blank.
So I'm going to change this guy
to make him a very scary guy,
like moving his insides.
And then let's make him a little
more meaty here and have great big--
and have great big ears.
Because ears are scary.
And we'll give him more
fluff around the outside.
Remember, I got to leave
two pixels all around.
So we'll make a really scary.
So now I have a new image
that I want to create.
Let's Save As.
And this step is important for you to
make sure you save it as a 16-color
.BMP.
And so we're going to
call him small enemy new.
Give him whatever name you want.
All right, so I've just created
a BMP file, a new BMP file.
And so now what I'm
going to do is, I'm going
to convert that BMP
file into a-- I'm going
to convert that BMP file into text file.
So I'm going to use
this executable, which
will take a BMP file
and create a text file.
So I got to remember the name
of the file I just created,
which was small enemy new.
And into this window, I'm
going to write the name
of this file I just
created small enemy new.
Hit enter.
And this created a text file.
So I'll find where it
went, small enemy new text.
So I will open up the one I
just created in a text editor.
You could see this is now C code.
I will copy it.
Now I'm going to go
over to my application.
And I'm going to paste the
bad boy right in there.
And now I have a new
image that I can create.
That I can display.
So let's draw him on the screen,
show you what he looks like.
So right here, I'm going
to copy, paste, take
his name-- he's called small enemy new.
Where would you like to put him?
Let's put them in the middle.
Halfway across is 48.
Halfway down is 24.
Again, this will put him at the middle
at location x equals 48, y equals 24.
So we will build, download, debug.
So again on the screen we see
nothing, left over from last time.
And so we will step over,
step over, step over.
This will clear the RAM screen.
This will draw the new enemy.
And then when I hit
the display buffer, we
can see our new enemy
is drawn on the screen.
Very scary-looking fellow is he.
So that's a summary of how it is
you could create your own bump
images if you want to modify
the game to make it more fun.