http://youtu.be/ZCNFdYtrNXw
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Next,
let's look at the graphics.
And we will show you
the high level functions
that we'll use to generate images.
Our Nokia image is a very small image.
The size is 48 pixels
high by 84 pixels wide.
And each pixel can be
a zero, which is off.
Or a one, which is on.
Which means the coordinates
go from 0 to 83.
And in graphics, this pixel right
here is located at coordinate 0, 0.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
That is the origin.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: That's the origin.
And this pixel, up in this corner, is
going to be at the x-position of 83
and the y-position of 0.
This one down in this corner is
going to be at the x-position of 0
and the y-position of 47.
And this corner will be at 83, 47.
And so in this way we will define each
pixel with a unique x, y-coordinate.
The basic function for
producing graphics in this game
will be to create or to draw
into this screen a BMP image.
A BMP file is a standard graphics
file that we can produce.
And when we place a BMP file onto the
screen we will specify which file,
which image to produce.
And we will specify the
position of this lower left dot.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
each sprite over there,
it's an object that's an enemy ship,
or the player's ship, or a bunker.
Each of these objects is a BMP
image and we call that a sprite
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And
we can have missiles, too.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And missiles too.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So the particular
function that we're going to call is
labeled Nokia5110_.
That means it's a function
in the Nokia module.
And it's called PrintBMP.
And the next coordinate
will be the x-position.
So if we write an 8
here then the x-position
of the lower left corner
of the BMP will be 8.
And if we put it at 47, then
the y-coordinate will be at 47.
That'll be the bottom row.
The next parameter of this function
is a pointer to the image itself.
And we'll see that there are
lots of images drawn for us.
The player ship zero,
is one of the predrawn
images, which will look
like the player ship.
And the last coordinate,
the last parameter,
is a threshold which will
decide which colors to produce--
which colors to be off
and which will be on.
And so if we produce a zero in
this, then any color which is zero
will be off.
And any color which will be 1 to
15 will actually turn on the pixel.
This is a threshold because our BMP
images are going to be 4-bit color
and we only have a 1-bit display.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So if
this display were a color display
then you could change the
threshold and render colored
sprite in the same place.
So Jon, it looks like the print
BMP, from what I understand,
is going to change a virtual imagine
and not the actual physical image.
It seems like there is another thing
called the Nokia5110_DisplayBuffer.
And this routine will
be the one that actually
displays the screen, entire
screen, onto the Nokia device.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
There's a third one.
The Nokia5110_ClearBuffer
will clear the array.
So there's an array.
You'll find it in the program.
It's called screen.
And this memory buffer contains the
virtual image that we will draw next.
So this memory buffer contains
the virtual image of the screen
that we will draw next.
And we can see that this 504 is
48 pixels by 84 pixels, divided
by 8 pixels per byte is 504.
So these 504 bytes contain the
48 by 84 pixel rendered image
that we're going to draw next.
So the software will first clear the
buffer, which will clear this screen.
And then it will draw
a whole bunch of BMPs
all over the screen where you want them.
And then when you're ready to create a
new image, we will call this function,
and the screen buffer is then
dumped onto the actual screen
and we'll see it.
This is the element that we're
going to call 30 times a second.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So Jon,
you said that the display buffer
routine is called 30 times a second.
The way we describe the flow chart, the
display buffer is called in the main.
So if I'm displaying in the main, the
main was not an interrupt-given one.
So how is it 30 hertz?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
It will be 30 Hertz
because we will set
a flag or a semaphore
from the interrupt service routine into
the main to say, draw me a new picture.
So that's how we'll
make it to be 30 hertz.
The other question is,
why is it 30 hertz?
If we make it a lot slower than 30
hertz, like 10 Hertz or 5 hertz,
the display will flicker.
And if we make it a lot
faster than 30 hertz
we're essentially wasting time because
our eyes can see that difference.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
That sounds perfect.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: This is
the starter file for Lab 15.
The first thing we see
at the top of this C file
are the hardware requirements.
These are the specific
connections you must
make in order for us to be able to
share your game with other students.
Again the slide pot is tied to PE2.
You have two buttons on PE0 and 1.
Your DAC is on port B. If
you want to flash some LEDs,
they can be here on port B4 and 5.
The Nokia display, which is
either a red one or a blue one
depends upon where you buy it.
But it's connected to
PA7, 6, 5, 3, and 2.
This is a sample BMP file.
And embedded in this file, in
this BMP image, are the pixels.
And down in this part of the
image we can see some F's and 0's.
0's are going to be off.
F's are going to be on.
This is a 4-bit BMP file.
And it will draw the
small enemy number 30.
And so there are a lot of images that
we can draw, small enemy 30, small enemy
20, small enemy 10, the player ship,
a small enemy, extra small enemy, some
of the bunkers.
Bunker 0 is actually one
that has fully functional.
And as the bunkers are being
destroyed they can be changed shape.
Bunker 1, and 2, and 3 are
bunkers being destroyed.
We have some explosions,
big ones, small ones.
We have missiles that can go up.
And we can have missiles
that can go down.
Missiles that go up
and lasers going down.
And so now we're at the
main loop, the main program.
The starter file is not the
game, that's yours to do.
But what I like to illustrate in this
main program is how the graphics work.
So this is not the solution
to the lab but rather
an explanation of how the graphics work.
We're going to be
running at 80 megahertz.
There is a random number generator
that you can use if you want.
And these are the functions
that we need to call.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So Jon, why would I
use a random number generator in a game?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Well,
it makes the game more fun.
Every time you play it, it's
just a little bit different.
All right, the initialization function
is the hardware initialization
for the Nokia display.
We talked about there being a buffer.
And so the clear buffer function
will clear the screen buffer.
And then if I display that cleared
buffer what we have at this point
is a completely empty screen.
Next we'll show you some
examples of calling.
Let's go ahead and download
the code and run it.
So download, click.
Debug.
Step over, where's my step over?
There it is, step over.
We're running now at 80 megahertz.
The random number
generator is initialized.
The hardware for the
Nokia is initialized.
Notice the screen has some
displays from last time I ran it.
And when I call the clear buffer we
can see that the screen didn't clear,
the software virtual array got cleared.
And it's only when I
execute the display buffer.
I'm going to step over
to the display buffer.
And we will see the
display is now cleared.
In a similar way, the next
function to call is a Print BMP.
And I'm going to produce or draw the
player's ship in the middle, that's
32 somewhere sort of the middle.
But in the bottom row, 47.
So I'm going to execute this function.
And again you notice the
display didn't change.
That's because I just drew that
bump into the virtual variable,
the virtual array.
So we'll draw a bunker,
step over, draw my bunker.
Draw a bunch enemies.
Here I'm going to draw a bunch enemies.
I'm going to put them on the top row.
A bunch of different enemies,
step over, step over, step over.
Again nothing happens
until I hit which--
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Jon, can you pause there?
I want to take a look
at what your passing
as the second parameter to a Print BMP.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, here
I'm going to draw an enemy.
64 is pretty much over towards
the right hand side of the screen.
This define function will
tell me how high the enemy is.
And so, as you can see, this
enemy is 10 pixels high.
So 10 minus 1 is 9.
And if I put him in the
y-position of 9, and he's 10 high,
this will be exactly on the top.
So he is as high as he
can go onto the screen.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And the third parameter
is our array that contains the BMP.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes, this
is an array, stored in ROM,
which contains the BMP image.
And the last parameter is the threshold.
A zero will show up as off.
And any number bigger than
zero will show up as an on.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: OK, now
we're ready to display the BMP.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah, come on.
Let's see what it looks like.
Step over.
And we see the imagine that was created
by these seven calls to the PrintBMP
is now shown on the screen.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
there are three different kinds
of enemy ships, a
bunker, and the player.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
Now no game yet.
That's your job.
This function for the starter file
is just going to wait five seconds.
Let's show you another feature
of the graphics driver,
and that is to do character output.
The clear function is a function
which will clear the screen.
And then if you want to output
characters or numbers to the screen,
we can set the cursor in
the row column location,
step over, and then draw
characters to the screen.
So it's in row number 1, column 1.
And it output the string.
Step over, step over, step
over, step over, step over.
And down here this could be your score.
As you can see, I don't have any score.
1,234 points.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So, in summary, what
we saw in the starter
file and the description
before is that there's a screen
buffer and a virtual buffer.
We cleared the buffer, which is
clearing the buffer that is our screen.
And then we have a display
buffer which will render it.
So the first thing we did is cleared
it, then displayed an empty buffer.
And then we added a bunch of
BMPs to the screen buffer.
And eventually, when we were
done with adding all the BMPs,
we displayed this buffer.
And once we did that, we
delayed for a little bit of time
and then went on to show a
text message on the screen
by calling these functions called
SetCursor, OutString, and OutDec.
So now you have all the
elements for building it
except we need to look
at a timer module, which
is very similar to the SysTick, but
we'll go through the details of that.