http://youtu.be/9BLtHUR5SME
JONATHAN VALVANO: In
this video, we're going
to show you how to create
and manage sprites.
A sprite is a living entity
which will exist in our game.
We're going to use the struct to create
a data structure to hold our sprite.
So in our data structure,
we have attributes,
like the x position, which is where
in the world is our sprite, its y
position, what it looks
like, and rather than storing
the whole image into
the structure, you can
see we're going to just have
a pointer to that structure.
But this image pointer will then
point to what the sprite looks like,
whether it's a bunker, or
an enemy, or a missile.
And lastly, we have the
status of this sprite.
We're going to have a very simple
status in this initial demonstration,
where 0 means it's dead,
and 1 means it's alive.
And so we're going to
create this structure
by defining a new data
type which has four fields.
We defined the struct, next,
we're going to create a new type.
This is our sprite type.
So a type is like hair, long,
short, except in this case,
it's going to create four elements
of x, y, pointer, and life.
RAMESH YERRABALLI:
The user defines type.
JONATHAN VALVANO: in this initial demo,
we're going to create four sprites.
So we're going to create a RAM-based
structure of four elements which
we will call the Enemy.
To manage the Enemy, we're going
to initialize their position.
So we're going to have four,
there's one, there's another one,
there's a third one, and
here is a fourth one.
So this is my enemy,
my array of sprites.
And I'm going to
initialize their position,
and so I'm going to set their
x-position along the row.
I'm going to set them so that
they occur on the screen in a row,
and they're going to pre-set their
y-position to be all in the same spot,
so they'll all be next to each other.
I'm going to set what they
look like, they're all
going to look like
Enemy30s, and then I'm
going to give them life by setting
their life parameter to a 1.
So when I execute this function,
these enemies will come to life.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So Jon,
how do I move an enemy
from one position to another position?
JONATHAN VALVANO: Now, I could
access the individual locations
by taking the first enemy,
taking its parameter,
and I can move it wherever I want.
So if I were to execute this code
here, I could set a value here,
I could set a value there,
and now Enemy number 0
is now teleported to that location.
But rather, I'm going to
use this move function,
and it turns out, if you look
very carefully at the BMP image,
each enemy has a border 2 pixels
on the left, 2 pixels on the right,
1 pixel on the top, and 1 pixel
on the bottom that are black.
So all of these sprites, all
these images of these sprites,
have a black border around the edge.
This means, if I move an enemy 2 pixels
to the left, 2 pixels to the right,
1 pixel down, or 1 pixel up,
the movement of that enemy
will automatically erase where it was.
So in this function, I'm going to
take all my enemies, 0 through 3,
and if the enemy is on the screen,
if he's not too far to the right,
I'm going to move him to the right.
And when this enemy reaches
the x-position of 72,
I will then kill that enemy
by making its life equal to 0.
So this function, when I call it, will
move all 4 of my enemies to the right
until they get to this
threshold, in which case,
then they are going to be killed.
We have one more operation
to write, and that
is the one that actually
renders the image.
This function is going to be
called inside our main loop.
Again, this function should be
called at 30 Hz inside the main loop.
And to draw all of the
sprites onto a single image,
I will begin by clearing the buffer.
Clearing the screen buffer,
this is the array in RAM.
And then, one by one, if the enemy
is alive, if the enemy has life,
it'll draw the image
associated with that enemy
at the position of where they exist.
And that's the threshold that
we've been using all along.
So this one element here will
draw the enemy onto the screen.
Then this one will draw that
enemy, and then this one
will draw that one, and that one.
So the four enemies will be drawn into
the array which is located in RAM.
It's not until this display function
that this RAM buffer is then
punched out to the screen.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
what we are showing
you is just an example of how to manage
the sprites, how to declare them,
how to move them, how to draw them.
So this is just an idea that
you can base your own game on.
So let's look at how this idea is put
together in a simple main program.
JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
So here we have a main program,
let's load it in, let's compile it.
Oops.
Let's compile it, build.
[DING]
Download.
Debug.
[DING]
So let's step over this main
program and see what it does.
Step over, step over.
So again, the Nokia Init will
initialize the hardware of the display.
The Init function that we just wrote
will then place all of my sprites
into the structure.
So I'll have my four
enemies that are created.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: This will only
put them in the screen buffer.
JONATHAN VALVANO: No, this doesn't
even put them in the screen buffer.
This puts them into
the array of enemies.
The next one is going to take the
enemy-- let's step into this one,
step into, step over-- here we cleared
the buffer, and now one by one,
I'm going to put the enemies
into the screen buffer.
Two, three, four.
Now when I execute this one, we see
that the enemies are on the screen.
The four enemies, near the
top, all on the same row.
All right, keep stepping.
Step over.
And now, the main loop is
going to move the enemies.
Now again, when I move
the enemies, the screen
doesn't change, because I
just moved their properties.
But when I draw it, they are now moved.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: Yes, they have.
JONATHAN VALVANO: All right,
let's move them again.
Oh, let's just hit the
Go button, because you
can see that this movement
will occur 10 times a second.
So you'll actually be able to see them
jump on the screen, so let's push Go.
So now you see the enemies
move over, and when
they get to the end of the
screen, they fall into the abyss,
their life is set to 0, and
there are no more enemies now.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
interesting thing as we see here
is, the loop is still
running, but there's
nothing to draw because we only
draw when their life is not a 0.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
All right.