http://youtu.be/YJ855nhKJeA
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So as
we saw in the introduction,
this module will bring everything that
you learned into one single concept.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Yeah, we can build a game.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
game that we're going to build
is the one that Jon
is playing right here.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And losing.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
It's a space invaders game.
OK, let's give it another
try, So we will collect first
the requirements for this game.
A requirements document is
the part where we start.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
a requirements document
is a legal contract between
the developer, which is you,
and the customer, which
will purchase your software.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
the requirements document
has to spell out in great detail the
requirements of what the system ought
to look like, what are its features,
what its form factor should be,
and what the cost ought to be, and
what components it may or may not
need so that a standard
can be delivered.
So now we'll look at what
discussions or exchanges go
in building the requirements document.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: The
requirements document has three parts.
The first is an overview.
Why are we doing this project?
We're doing this project to put
together all the pieces of this class,
and in particular, we're going to
build a 1980s style shoot 'em up
game like Space Invaders.
The second part of the
overview is the process,
and the process for developing this
game will be like all the other labs.
And that is we will begin with a
starting point or a starter project,
and you will add features
to this starter project
to meet the requirements of this lab.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So, Jon, are you saying
that they don't have to design
this project from scratch?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
That's what that means.
The other aspect of this project,
which is different than the other labs,
is since we have no grader that
will automatically grade your lab,
we encourage you to find
teams and work together
to perform or to develop
your game in teams.
We suggest somewhere between one
and three members of your team.
The most important part of
the requirements document
that you want to look into is
exactly how does your game fit.
In other words, there are some specific
requirements that your game must have.
It must be written in C, it
has to be developed on Keil,
it has to run on your LaunchPad,
and more specifically, we
have decided or defined exactly where
the input and output pins are located.
By specifying exactly
where the pins are,
this will allow one student to
play the game of another student.
When reading the
requirements document, you
will see we'll use specific
terminology like BMP files, sprites,
and public documents.
And you can read and
read those definitions.
We are worried about you spreading
viruses from one student to another.
So we are only going to allow the
upload of one source code file.
And since this game is not required
for your final course grade,
you don't have to actually upload it.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So you're
saying that if I build a software,
I could send you my project, just one
single file which has all the source
code.
And you will run it, and it will
work perfectly on your system
because you built a hardware
exactly to specification
that my software is following.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
That allows us to play
each other's games.
The second part of the requirements
document is the functional description,
and it specifies exactly
what the system will do.
It'll be an '80s style video
game with inputs and outputs.
These are the phases of development .
You will find a team,
if you'd like, to find
exactly what the rules
of your game will be.
We'll specify the modules, the various
hardware and software components.
We will organize or
architect your software
by defining prototypes for the
public functions and then one by one,
you will test the modules.
And then once all the
modules are tested,
you will put them together
to create a system.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So one
of the things it looks like,
Jon, is that you're hiding all
the details of implementations
by exposing only the prototypes of
public functions to the other modules.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: This is a common
development process for larger systems,
and that allows more than one person
to work on the project at a time.
We'll evaluate the beauty or
the wonderfulness of your game
by two very, very simple properties.
Is it easy to learn to play the game,
and second, is your game fun to play?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Oh, you mean if I have
to read a document to play
the game, it's not easy.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: It's not easy.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And if I
have to turn a knob a certain way
or do seven things before I can make a
missile fire, that's not fun to play.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: No,
and we'll have an option
to allow you to share your game
with other students in the class.
The usability is exactly how it is
the game will occur, and as I said,
we'll have very, very,
very explicit pins,
which must be for your
input and your output.
And these requirements
are specified in detail,
and it will allow one student to
play the game of another student.
And again, because we're
worried about spreading viruses,
we will only take one C file of
all your programs in text form.
And the last part of a requirements
document is the deliverables.
We won't make you write
a report, but we do
encourage you to put
comments in your C file.
We don't have any
audits, but we will allow
you to talk about your
game in the forums,
and the ultimate
deliverable, like we said,
will be one large C file that we
can upload and share with the class.
All right, let's start building.