http://youtu.be/9s85rfrV6nc
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Hi.
In this last video, we thought
we would recap the journey
that you have taken with us by asking
the question, what did we learn?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the first lab
you did introduced you to the Keil IDE;
the development process in general,
which involves writing new code,
editing it, then compiling it,
running it, testing, debugging,
and repeating this cycle.
You were introduced to
the TM4C microcontroller
and you will encounter similar
microcontrollers and similar IDEs.
The concepts will be easily
translatable to other systems.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: In the next
lab, we learned how to program in C.
And the first concept was this idea of
functions, or a functional abstraction,
where we would encapsulate one idea and
turn into a function and then use it.
We had if-thens and loops.
We did Character I/O with a printf.
And again, lab five was an introduction
to the process of programming in C.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
Lab six introduced you
to time, which is an important
parameter in embedded systems.
We saw a visual rendering of events with
respect to time using a logic analyzer.
And we were able to verify that
the expected behavior is precisely
measured by visually checking
it on a logic analyzer.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Then in lab seven, we
introduced the development life
cycle, the product life cycle.
And what we started with
were specifications,
and then we went to design and
implementation and testing.
And we did that whole
process using a concept
called functional
decomposition, which was
to break down a complicated
problem into smaller pieces.
And again, timing was a big
deal, and so we learned how
to both measure and control time.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So lab
eight was your first exposure
to building circuitry off board,
which is we were using mainly
on board switches and
lights, but now we have
to design knowing things
like resistances measuring
voltages, currents, and appropriately
choosing your components for the target
design.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
And then in lab nine
was our first effort of proving
that our software works.
Embedded systems, as
you know, are deployed
in situations where life-critical
functionality must be guaranteed.
And so we introduced this
idea of functional debugging,
and we use an array to
capture the input, the output,
but not only what they
were, but when they occur.
And so this was a minimally
intrusive dumping into an array, such
that we could demonstrate and verify
that our software and hardware was
working as intended.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: We know lab
10 gave problems to some of you.
It was a little challenging,
but what we want you to--
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: You
see my finite state machine?
That was my answer right there.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: What we
want you to take away from lab 10
is that finite state machines are
a very effective tool that you
will have in your toolbox when designing
complex systems because you separate
the engine from the data
and you focus on the data,
and the engine is the same engine that
you repeatedly use for any system.
And this was also your
introduction to SysTick,
which allowed you to
introduce time-related events
into your finite state machine.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Then
in lab 11, what you'll
notice that we communicated
between one computer and another.
And we did something
very simple, but this
is the essence of what people are
now calling the internet of things,
where all the computers
are connected up.
And in particular, embedded systems
are out there at the forefront,
at the edge of the world, gathering
information and affecting the world.
And so we saw the UART was a simple
way to send data in serial fashion
from one computer to another.
We saw that we could
represent non-integer values
using something called fixed point.
And we had a new programming
tool called a string, which
was a variable length
ASCII set of characters.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Lab 12
introduced interrupts in earnest.
Embedded systems derive the
responsiveness in practice
because they support interrupts.
So what we did in lab
12 is showed you how
you can use interrupts
to generate sound,
and the sound needs to be
at a particular frequency
and we can get a precise frequency
because we're using interrupts.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Lab
13 got harder and harder.
Now embedded systems
must shape the world.
And so we need a way to connect
the computer, which is essentially
a digital device into a
continuous real world.
And one of the tools we used was
the digital-to-analog converter.
And you built one yourself,
right out of bare resistors.
And so it took a digital number
and created an analog output.
Whenever we consider this conversion
between digital and analog,
we must sample or discretize,
both in amplitude and in time.
That's what we call sampling.
And once we do that, we need a famous
theorem, the Nyquist theorem, which
tells us that if we're interested in
oscillations up to a certain frequency,
f, then the data must be sampled
at more than twice that frequency.
That was the Nyquist theorem.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So lab
14 addressed the counterpart.
If embedded systems
have to shape the world,
they also have to input the world.
That is, they have to read the world
in its analog form by digitizing it.
So we program the 12-bit
ADC on the system.
We also made sure that we wrote
a driver for the ADC, which
involved a set of subroutines.
We used a modular design.
We made sure that we calibrated
the analog potentiometer
so that we have an accurate
rendering of its behavior.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
Lab 15, which was
optional, was the most fun.
We thought we'd put it all together
in one hand-held video game.
We added more interrupts so you can
have multiple operations occurring
in the background.
You've got your foreground.
And that's called multithreading.
This allows your game to be lifelike
because more than one thing can
be happening at a time.
The graphical structures, the images
that we generated on the screen,
we used a C programming
concept called structures.
And we rendered those structures
to produce the graphical image.
So again, the purpose of lab 15 was
to put all the concepts together--
the D-to-A, the A-to-D, the interrupts,
the C programming, the testing, all
of that into one program
that's fun to play.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So I hope
you enjoyed doing all these labs.
You learned something and you are going
to use these concepts in your life
as you develop as an
embedded systems engineer.
We would like to summarize
some of the best practices.
These are by no means
the only ones, but these
are things that we think are
good things to take away.
So rather than talk
about all these, we'll
talk about what is
our favorite of these.
My favorite is try until you succeed.
Keep trying.
Be courageous.
The best programmers in the
world didn't happen overnight.
They had enough failures
to talk about, and that's
how they showed that they're courageous
and not afraid to make mistakes.
And show your work to others.
That's how you make sure
that people can correct you
and you can become a better engineer.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: This
is my approach to life.
In order to be truly successful,
you need other people around you
to support and encourage.
And so I know that I
can only be better when
I'm surrounded by people
who are smarter than I am.
So I go out in the world and find
the nicest, and the happiest,
and the most intelligent people,
and I ask, can I work with you?
And that way, I know that
they will make me better.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So I hope this has
been a journey that
was worthwhile for you.
It's been really worthwhile for us.
And we hope to see you again.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yup.
See you on the internet.