http://youtu.be/O5S84d08kfQ
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Professor Yerraballi,
what are we going to learn today?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.Today we will
take stock of everything we have
learned in this class.
Put them all together to work
on a single, final project.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
That sounds exciting.
But if we include all things in one
project, it'll be very complicated.
To make it worthwhile,
can we do something fun?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.In fact,
that's exactly what it'll be,
as much fun as you want to make it.
After all, it'll be a game that
you'll design from scratch.
We will provide the basic idea, which
would be based on an '80s style arcade
game called Space Invaders.
You stretch your imagination and
make it as much fun as possible.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
So from a hardware standpoint,
we could make a game controller
using the switches, the
LED, and the slide pot.
And to make sound, we'll use the DAC.
And then we'll add graphics on an LCD.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.Yeah.
And on the software front, you'll
program timers, interrupts, the ADC,
and write device drivers
for the DAC and the LCD.
We'll put together all of these in
a game engine that we will provide.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah.
So this is quite a complex undertaking.
Will the students have to
write everything from scratch?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.Not quite.
We will provide a starter
project for this lab,
and the starter project will have the
support routines for the LCD graphics.
The rest of the stuff will
come from your own work
that you finished in the previous labs.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Can we
see what one might look like?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.Yeah.
Let's take a look.
So here you see the project
implemented in its entirety.
John is playing the game.
The controller involves
two buttons, two LEDs,
a slide pot which acts like a joystick.
The audio is implemented using a DAC.
And audio jack is connected
to a speaker here,
but you could connect
your headphones to it.
You see the display, which is
an optional display-- which
is a black and white display
that you can purchase.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: If
you don't have the display,
we'll have a way for you to
send the signals on to your PC
and display them on that screen.
Oh.
Dead.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:.Dead.