http://youtu.be/hqTA4uJ6nBg
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So in this module,
we're going to look at the game
from a modular design standpoint.
What we mean by that is we will design
our system using three important tools.
The first one will be a call graph.
The second will be a data flow graph.
And the third will be a low
level detail of flow charts.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Professor Yerraballi,
why is modular design important?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So modular design allows
us to manage the complexity
of a large project.
This project is going
to be one of the largest
that you will handle in this class.
So what we want to do is be
able to manage by modularizing,
which means that we break down
our system into small modules.
This will allow us to manage change.
It will allow us to debug easily
because if you break them up
into small modules, we test
one module; make sure it works.
And then we can hide that
module as if it were a box,
and look around it
and see other modules.
As I said, it allows us
to manage complexity.
So now we'll look at
each of these in turn.
We will look at the game overall
and break it down into modules
where each module will be
specified either as a circle,
if it's a software, or a
square, if it's hardware.
And we will describe which module
calls which module by using arrows.
This is what our call
graph is going to be like.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: What are
the three files that one normally
creates for a software module?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
The software module
is going to be managed by three files.
So let's take an example
of the ADC module.
So when we look at a
module like ADC, we will
have the specification
of the module in a ADC.h.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
And what's in the H file?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: The H file lists
the public functions as prototypes.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
these are the functions
that another module could call?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
So this is what the module
exposes to the outside world.
So we'll list all the functions.
And not just functions.
If there is any other data
that needs to be exposed,
that's also going to be exposed
in the header, as we call it.
And then we will have an ADC.c,
which will be the implementation.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So this is where
the code that actually runs exists.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
And we want to hide the implementation
and expose only the public function.
As we saw, this allows
us the flexibility
of improving the implementation
or changing the implementation
without changing how the
users call this module.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: But
what's the third file?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
And the third file
is not specific to the module
itself, but how is the module used.
So the main.c, in our
case, is going to be
the driver that will call this module.
The driver is also sometimes
the tester of the module.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
this file explicitly shows
how we're going to use the module,
and how we tested the module?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
And so at times when
we're developing the code,
we will have in the
main.c specific testing
code for each module
that we are building.
And we test that module, and then
we discard that piece of code
and we keep writing
new testing software.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Professor Yerraballi,
are there any guidelines
in developing modular code?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
There are guidelines.
These are something that
you learn by practice.
But the general idea is to
maximize the number of modules
by making sure that you
minimize the interdependency.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Give me some examples.
What you mean by interdependency?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the first
idea is the idea of maximizing modules.
Means that I'm going to
have as many modules as it
takes to break down the problem in
a divide and conquer sort of way.
That is I'm going to break it
into one module, another module.
If I feel like some functionality
needs its own module,
I'm going to build
another module for it.
But by interdependency we mean modules
are going to exchange information.
So there's going to be modules
communicating with each other.
This module may call this module.
This module may in
turn call this module.
But part of this is how
much data do they exchange.
The volume of the data, if
you will, that they exchange.
Now we want to make sure
that these modules are not
exchanging huge amounts of data.
And if two modules are
exchanging a lot of data,
maybe there's some reason to think
of them as one single module.
And so we want to maximize
number of modules,
but we also want to
minimize interdependency
because exchange of data
between modules where
it gets too much that
communication becomes bottle-neck.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So
let's look at modularity
from the perspective of our game.
Where do we begin?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So as I said, the
first thing we're going to look at it
is the call graph.
So for our game, the heart of our
game is going to be our game engine.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
So this is the main code
that controls all of the game function?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is
correct and so this game engine
is going to be using a
bunch of different modules.
The first module I'm going to
look at is that ADC module.
So the ADC module will encapsulate all
functionality related to the slide pot.
Remember the slide pot
is a piece of hardware,
so I'm going to write it like that.
So this is encapsulating the information
that we specify for the slide pot.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: What does
that arrow mean you just drew?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
arrow is the call, the interface,
where we say that the game engine
calls the ADC module, which
calls the hardware
which is our slide pot.
So our second module we're going
to look at is the switch hardware.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
These are our buttons.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So all the buttons, all the
switches, that we have on our system
are going to be managed by this module.
The third module.
Obviously we want our game to
be fun, and it should sound fun.
So we're going to have a sound module.
And the sound module will
interact with a piece
of hardware, which is going to be
our DAC, which, as you remember,
is going to be connected
to the headphones.
So the last module is going
to be our Nokia display
module, which is a Nokia 5110.
So this is our display module.
This is going to be responsible
for all the graphics,
and it's going to be interfacing
with our Nokia display 5110
hardware LCD display.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Now if you haven't
bought a Nokia display, no worries.
You can still build your
game because we built
into the process a simulated Nokia.
So you can actually run
your game even if you
don't have the hardware
for the graphics.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we are
indicating that simulated hardware
by this here, which is a cross
between a square and a circle.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: You just invented
something, Professor Yerraballi.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: I did.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: A circle-square.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: A circle-square.
So now that we saw the
call graph, Jon, do you
see interesting things about this graph?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: I see that
we have five modules 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
But there are only four
arrows between this.
This means that we have a lot of
modules and very little interdependence.
The switch doesn't call sound.
The Nokia doesn't call the ADC, and
the ADC doesn't call the game engine.
This is a very simple call graph.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
So we saw the call graph,
now let's look at the data flow graph.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
The data flow graph
is another way to
visualize the modularity.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we see,
we kind of recreated the call graph,
with five modules.
Our five modules are our game
engine, our ADC, our switch, sound,
and the Nokia 5110 module.
Now we're going to see what the
real exchange is going to be.
So let's look at one of them.
I see the slide pot, which is
going to give us a position.
And we take the position, and
we convert it into a voltage.
And we do this at 30Hz.
And what happens as I get
this voltage into my system
is it's going to convert
it to a 12-bit number,
and the 12-bit number is our measure
of the position on the slide pot.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
But in a data flow graph,
what do the arrows mean this time?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
arrows in the data flow graph
is the passage of information or data.
So in our case, the position,
which is resistance if you will,
is going to be converted to a voltage.
Which is moving from the
slide pot to the ADC.
Which is a zero to three volts.
Which is moving from
the ADC to the driver.
Which is then moving from the
driver to the game engine.
So it's the passage of information.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: And I can
see we're passing 12 bits, 30 times
a second.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: That is correct.
And so the other modules we'll
see, we can quickly list.
So there are two inputs,
our two switches.
And that is also being
read at 30Hz, which
is going to be the two
bits of information.
The two switches are two bits.
We pass that to the game engine.
These two together are what
I think of as a interface.
And the interface is being sampled at
30 Hz by using the SysTick interrupt.
And this is what comes into the system.
And this is what goes out of
the system, which is a sound.
Which in our case is going to be 11kHz.
Obviously, sound requires
a more demanding timing.
So we have that flowing the other way.
So you see that there's a 4-bit DAC.
So the four bits go from the
sound routine to the sound module
to the DAC, which is then fed to the
headphones as a single analog signal.
And so this is our
sound, which will also
be managed by a timing module--
which is a timer, which
we're going to look at later.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
Well so far, you've
just put the pieces together
from the last three labs.
But what's new in this lab?
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the new
thing in this lab is the graphics.
And the graphics are part of the LCD
display, which is a Nokia display.
And we will try and abstract
all the low level details
so that we can think of this as simply
calling certain routines that either
display an image, clear the
buffer, or redisplay a new buffer.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Also
in this data flow graph,
we have shown you the
explicit hardware connections
that you must perform in order to
share your game with other students.
And we see that in order to run your
game engine with other students,
you're going to have to
tie the slide pot to PE2.
The two buttons, whatever
they do in your game,
need to be connected to PE1 and PE0.
The DAC, in order to create
sounds that other people can hear,
we will specify the DAC
must be on PB3, 2, 1, and 0.
And lastly, the Nokia
needs port A. And so we're
going to use these five
bits on PA 2, 3, 5, 6, and 7
to interface a Nokia display.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: This is the
standard that we're talking about.
This will allow everybody to
play everybody else's game.
So the third piece of our
modular design is flow charts.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO:
The flow chart is a way
to describe the software algorithm.
And you don't have to
follow this explicitly,
but this is our advice on
how we build our games.
Every software needs a main
loop, so we have our main loop
which will begin when
we hit the reset button.
As all embedded systems, we will begin
our main loop with initializations.
So we'll initialize the PLL, the
graphics, the DAC, the switches, the A
to D converter.
We'll initialize all of
the components of our game.
And then after we've
initialized everything,
we will enable interrupts In this
way, all the initializations will
be complete before the
interrupts are turned on.
In order to make the game
extremely interactive,
our recommendation is that you do the
LCD outputs, the graphical outputs,
do all the graphical output in the main
loop in what we call the foreground.
So this is the foreground
thread, here, which
executes when there's no interrupts.
Of all the things we do, the
LCD output will be the slowest.
It'll take on the order of
milliseconds to generate actual output
to the graphics.
The other two things we're going to do
is things that occur very, very slowly.
And this will be a SysTick
interrupt occurring at 30Hz.
30 hertz is fast enough that
our eyes can't tell it's moved.
30 hertz is right at that range
where it will look smooth.
And in our SysTick
interrupt service routine
is where the actual
game engine will occur.
And so your game, whatever it is,
is going to look at the switches
and do whatever it is supposed
to happen with those switches.
You'll look at the A to D
converter, the slide pot
and do whatever your game is
supposed to do with a slide pot.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: Maybe movement.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah,
like moving your ship around,
firing missiles, whatever is
supposed to happen in your game.
And then we will decide to move sprites.
And a sprite we'll define
later, but a sprite
is one of the objects of your game, one
of the virtual elements of your game.
We will decide to move it.
Now we're not doing the
graphics, we're just
deciding where to draw all the sprites.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So the
movement is a virtual movement.
A physical movement is always
done by the main program
by rendering this
movement on the screen.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes, and
this is a virtual movement.
And you notice the flow chart of my
SysTick interrupt service routine
follows the classic;
arrows only go down.
This way the execution time of
this interrupt service routine
will be short and bounded.
One of the reasons we have threads
is so we can separate or define
individual software processes.
And the other process, the other
action, that we want to create is sound.
And so we are going to
separate the thread which
produces sound from
the thread which plays
the game by using two
interrupt service routines.
This interrupt service routine
is going to run a lot faster.
It's going to run at 11kHz
and generate a sound.
And so if it's time or if
we wish to play a sound,
we will do the output to a DAC.
And if we wish to not play a sound,
we won't do one output to the DAC.
And notice that this
interrupt service routine
separates the action
of playing the sound
from the action of playing the game.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
you're saying that it's possible
that when I choose to fire,
I want to produce a sound.
And so I schedule the
action, but the action
itself is performed in the Timer2A ISR.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Excellent.
So we could start a sound in
our game, but the actual sound
is going to occur with
a second interrupt,
occurring at a much faster rate.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI:
This will also allow
us to change sounds from
one sound to another sound,
depending upon what action
has caused the sound.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Absolutely.
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So
we've looked at the design.
We've delved into the
three aspects of design,
which are call graph, our data
flow graph, and flow charts.
And we are now going
to look at some details
that we haven't covered yet
in the previous chapters.