http://youtu.be/BPLeKETEUIs
JONATHAN VALVANO: Next,
we want to show you
another periodic
interrupt called Timer2.
Timer2 is a lot like SysTick.
It has, essentially, two registers.
One of them is a counter, and
just like SysTick, it counts down.
Another one is a reload value, in our
particular case it's called T-A-I-L-R,
and it's the reload value.
Just like SysTick, when this
counter goes from a one to a zero,
it will set the trigger flag.
This trigger flag is going to
cause an interrupt to happen.
Also like SysTick, the value
we put into the reload value
will determine the rate
at which it interrupts.
Different than SysTick is, this
timer and this reload value,
is now a full 32 bits wide.
The code shown here on the
page is the initialization code
for this Timer2 periodic interrupt.
We're going to pass in the value
that we want to interrupt at.
In our particular case, since
we're running at 80 MHz,
the interrupt rate will be this
value, period, times 12.5 nanoseconds.
Because that's the bus period.
Like all modules, we have
to turn on its clock,
and so this is the clock
bit for the Timer2 register.
And after we turn on the
clock, we will wait a while
for the clock to stabilize.
I have a couple of global
variables that I use to debug with.
This one will count the number
of times the interrupt occurs,
and this is a semaphore flag
which gets set every interrupt.
The 10 steps used to initialize
the timer are now shown.
We disable the timer
during set up, we set it up
as a periodic interrupt with a 32-bit
counter, the value of period minus one
is stored into the reload value,
so again, the interrupt rate
will be the value, period,
times 12.5 nanoseconds.
We set the resolution to
run at the bus clock, which
is going to be 12.5 nanoseconds.
I like to clear the interrupt service
flag in the ritual, that's step six.
We then arm that bit for
interrupts, we set its priority
by setting three bits of
the priority five register,
we enable-- this is
interrupt 23, and so we
will enable interrupt 23 and the
nested vector interrupt controller.
Then after the entire
thing is initialized,
we will then enable Timer2A.
If the main program executes
at interrupt enable,
then interrupts at this period
will occur periodically.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So we saw
the initialization ritual
for the interrupt service
routine, so we now
have interrupts happening on Timer2A.
When an interrupt occurs, the
handler, which is the Timer2A handler,
is called, and so we're going to look at
what we have to do within this handler.
JONATHAN VALVANO: All right.
So the main thread will
enable interrupts and then
perform some task over and over.
But when the timer goes
from a one to a zero,
it will set a bit in the
timer raw interrupt status.
This is the trigger flag which
will cause the interrupt to occur.
So our handler, then, here,
will then be executed.
Like most interrupts, we have
to acknowledge that interrupt
by clearing the trigger flag.
The trigger flag happens
to be in bit zero,
and to clear the
Timer2A timeout flag, we
are going to write a one to
the interrupt clear register.
When I write a one to bit zero, it
will clear the raw interrupt status bit
zero, which is our trigger flag,
acknowledging the interrupt.
Then these two steps are
the body or the function
of what we want to happen in
the interrupt service routine.
In this case, I'm just going to
increment a counter as a debugging way
to say yes, this is running.
And then we could use a semaphore
flag to signal other threads
that this interrupt occurs.
RAMESH YERRABALLI: So for
example, the main program
could be checking this flag,
and only when this flag is on,
it could perform a certain function.
When it's off, it's going
to skip that function
and keep checking this
flag again and again.
JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
So this is how semaphore works.
This semaphore flag here is set
in the interrupt service routine,
and then the main loop
will look for that flag.
If the flag is set, then
it will clear the flag,
perform some function
associated with the semaphore,
and this whole process is
repeated over and over again
So we have two threads, the foreground
thread and the background thread,
connected by a semaphore flag.