In your lifetime, you have probably stared
down any number of ability tests and course
exams and PSATs, SATs, ACTs, GREs, GCSEs,
whatever you got in your country. Humans,
it seems, really get a thrill out of measuring,
ranking, and comparing each other's intelligence.
Unfortunately, as you saw last week, historically,
we have been kind of bad at that. Today, we
think of intelligence as determined by a series
of factors related to genetics, environment,
education, perhaps even randomness itself,
some aspects of which may correlate with belonging
to a particular social group, and others not.
The key here, though, is that we don't fully
understand how or how much some of these factors
work.
How do elements like personal history and
conditions like poverty, access to education,
stress, even nutrition affect someone's scores
on cognitive tests? And if a group of people
share some of these conditions, how will they
respond--both as individuals and as a group--to
certain potentially biased intelligence tests?
In the end, the irony is that in our ongoing
effort to measure human intelligence, most
of what we've learned is simply what we don't
know.
[Intro]
What is a piano? Which one of these things
is least like the others? Juice is to glass
as hand is to what? Which one of these numbers
does not belong in the series? Bernice had
x number of jelly beans. She ate one, then
gave half of what was left to Bruno, then
she ate another and gave half of the remainder
to her dog. Now, she only has five beans.
How many did she--ahheh uhhhh.
These questions are similar to what you'd
find on today's most widely-used intelligence
tests. The Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale,
or WAIS, and the Wechsler Intelligence Scale
for Children, or WISC. Originally published
by psychologist David Wechsler in 1955, the
current edition of the exam consists of fifteen
different sub-tests that assess things like
vocabulary, similarities between objects and
concepts, and patterns in letters and numbers.
Cognitive tests usually fall into one of two
categories: achievement, or the kind that
reflect what you've learned, and aptitude
- the kind that's supposed to predict your
ability to learn something new. So the WAIS
and the WISC are aptitude tests, and your
final exam at the end of your math class is
an achievement test.
So, how do we know if an intelligence test,
or any other test for that matter, is actually
any good? Well, today, we do have some standards.
To be widely accepted, a test must hit three
important marks. It has to be standardized,
reliable, and valid. Standardization is basically
about comparability. Whether you answer 15
or 50 questions correctly on a test actually
means very little until you can compare those
scores against how others performed. So, to
achieve meaningful comparisons, test-makers
must first give the test to a representative
sample group, which sets a standard by which
to compare future test-takers. You've probably
heard of a bell-curve. Whether you're measuring
height or mental aptitude or love of the Beatles,
it's often assumed that everyone you're measuring
will fall into what's called a normal pattern:
most scores will fall in the mid-range, while
fewer hit the extremes. And actually, it's
those extremes that intelligence tests are
most widely and effectively used for. It might
help an educator identify a gifted student
who totally blows the roof off a test, but
they're also useful in helping clinicians
determine who might have a disability or be
facing some specific barrier. With victims
of traumatic brain injury or stroke, for example,
a WAIS test can do a nice job of sussing out
whether a patient who's struggling with language
actually has a problem remembering and identifying
words, or if they're just having a hard time
processing the information quickly.
But these tests should be regarded more skeptically
when it comes to issues that are either way
more specific or way more broad. Like, they
won't be able to answer questions along the
lines of, "Will Jesse get into Harvard?" or
"Are women smarter than men?" They're just
not designed to do that. And in any case,
simply knowing where you fall on a normal
curve on a standardized test doesn't mean
much if the test is poorly designed, so along
with being standardized, a good test has high
reliability, meaning it yields dependably
consistent results. One way to determine this
is to have people take the same test a second
time, or some similar version of it. If the
two performances resemble one another -- if
the scores correlate -- then the test is thought
to have good reliability.
And the third requirement for the testing
trifecta is simply validity, or the extent
to which a test measures or predicts what
it's supposed to. And there are different
kinds of validity -- for instance, if I take
the WAIS IQ test and my scores accurately
predict how good my grades in college will
be, that's a simple kind of predictive or
criterion validity. On the other hand, if
I take the test and my scores correlate strongly
with my results on another similar cognitive
test, like the Stanford Binet, that falls
under the broad category of construct validity.
The key is that all of these are ways to see
if a test measures what it claims to measure.
But the stickiest wicket of them all is what
we make of the test scores themselves.
We've all heard plenty about the influence
of both nature and nurture in psychology,
so the big question is: do our genetics influence
our intelligence, or does our environment?
And this is an easy question to answer because
they both do. And that is important. If the
history of intelligence testing has taught
us anything, it's that assuming everyone is
smart in the same way and for the same reason
can lead to disastrously bad conclusions.
So let's look at the scientific evidence,
and the best place for that is the wealth
of twin and adoption studies, which have been
fascinatingly helpful in illustrating how
genetics and environment can both influence
intelligence.
For example, research has shown that identical
twins who were raised together have the highest
rate of similarity in intelligence scores
of any group. Fraternal twins who share only
half the genes tend to be much less similar
in their scores, even when raised in the same
home. Likewise, neuroimaging studies show
that certain brain regions, like those associated
with language, are structurally similar between
identical twins, and show similar activity
while doing the same kinds of mental tasks.
The brains of fraternal twins raised in the
same home are very similar in some areas,
but less so in others. But identical twins
who are raised together have the same brain,
at least, according to neuroimaging scans.
Some studies even showed that identical twins
raised apart from each other show higher intelligence
correlation than fraternal twins raised together.
And maybe even more interesting is that these
intelligence correlations actually increase
over time.
In one mega-study of eleven thousand twin
pairs in four countries, that correlation
kept increasing from middle-childhood to adolescence
to young adulthood and continued to increase
through adulthood. Similar research has looked
at adopted children and compared their scores
with those of their adopted siblings, parents,
and biological parents. And the results can
be kind of surprising, because as adopted
kids grow up, their mental similarities to
their adoptive families actually get smaller
over time until there's virtually no correlation
by adulthood. Instead, they become more similar
in terms of mental aptitude to their biological
parents over time, even if they never met.
In other words: genes appear to matter. You
could take a hundred kids and raise them in
the exact same way, and as adults, they'd
still have different aptitudes. But, does
this mean that when it comes to intelligence,
we're all nature and no nurture?
Well, luckily, and somewhat obviously, no.
Life experiences and environment also matter.
One sad example of how early environments
affect children can be found in the work of
American psychologist J. McVicker Hunt in
a destitute Iranian orphanage in the 1970s.
Conditions were really, really bad; infants
received minimal care, and whatever attention
they did get was on a routine schedule, never
in response to whether they were cooing or
crying or anything else. Basically, they were
being raised with no cause and effect between
their behaviors and the responses of their
caregivers, and as a result, they didn't learn
how to communicate. With no stimulation or
social response, the kids were just kind of
passive, vacant lumps. Deprivation was essentially
trumping any inborn intelligence. So, Hunt
started a program. He trained caregivers to
actually talk to infants, to teach them how
to mimic sounds and actions, and eventually,
sounds and words from their language. The
results were tremendous. The kids started
to learn really quickly, and basically just
came alive. While it's an extreme example,
Hunt's research showed how malleable early
childhood intelligence can be, especially
in disadvantaged and stressful conditions.
So you can see that environment and heredity
interact to affect intelligence, and that
some tricky implications can come out of that
conclusion. But that's hardly the only controversy
when it comes to how we view and measure intelligence.
There have been some sensational headline-courting
studies of genetic and social influences that
have suggested that fundamental differences
in intelligence may exist between genders
and races, but many of these studies are tangled
up in questions of how potential testing bias
may affect performance. Basically, if a test
inadvertently measures differences caused
by cultural experiences or social factors
instead of what we might call "innate intelligence",
then you might say that the test is biased.
Extreme example: in the past, immigrants to
the US were classified as "feeble minded"
if they couldn't answer distinctly American
questions, like "Who was the first American
president?" or "What's a milkshake?". Today,
concerns about bias focuses on differences
among members of the same general culture.
Say, a poor, rural kid who might be plenty
smart, but will test low if questions involve
urban, upper-class concepts like taking taxis
and drinking tea out of china cups or the
rules of tennis.
So the questions themselves can skew performance
results, but who administers the test can
also affect outcomes. Women tend to do better
with a fellow female administrator, and African
Americans often score higher if their test
is given by an African American instructor.
And the risk of bias may even fall to the
test-takers' own expectations. For example,
many studies have found that if you give a
math test to equally capable men and women,
but just before starting, you tell the subjects
that women usually score lower than men, you
actually negatively affect the women's performance.
This self-fulfilling concern that you might
mess up and inadvertently fulfill some negative
stereotype is called stereotype threat. It
was first described by social psychologist
Claude Steele and Joshua Aronson, and it's
been demonstrated frequently across a whole
host of interesting studies.
Now, we've only scratched the surface of this
mess that is intelligence testing. An important
thing to remember next time you ace or bomb
a test is that you are far more complicated
and nuanced than any test score. Don't let
a number puff you up or drag you down, and
don't let it define you. We all have room
for self-improvement. We are all full of infinite
surprising potential. Ah, and answers to the
questions I asked earlier: A piano is a musical
instrument played using a keyboard, banana
is the least similar to the others, juice
is to class as hand is to glove, the number
two does not belong in the series, and Bernice
began with twenty-three jellybeans.
Today, your intelligent mind learned how we
currently use WAIS and WISC tests to measure
intelligence, and how important it is that
a test be standardized, reliable, and valid.
We also looked at how genetics, environment,
testing bias, and stereotype threat can affect
IQ test performance. Thank you for watching,
especially to all of our Subbable subscribers
who make Crash Course possible. To find out
how you can become a supporter, just go to
Subbable.com/CrashCourse.
This episode was written by Kathleen Yale,
edited by Blake de Pastino, and our consultant
is Dr. Ranjit Bhagwat. Our director and editor
is Nicholas Jenkins, the script supervisor
is Michael Aranda, who is also our sound designer,
and the graphics team is Thought Café.