Hi, welcome back.
https://youtu.be/3FoJ0P4lExE
What we are going to do now, or in this multisegment section,
but break it up into pieces that make sense, which is as you know,
best practice, in especially digital education,
is we&#39;ll talk about risk and return.
But to do that, we have to first do what I usually do is,
set up why we are talking about this.
And in the context of pretty much what we&#39;ve been talking about until now.
Then we&#39;ll spend time on statistics.
So in this particular ongoing segment,
chapter, week, whatever, we&#39;re going to do two things.
We&#39;re going to define risk, see why we worry about it and
the context, and then take a detour and talk about statistics.
When I talk about statistics it won&#39;t be everything obviously,
because I found I don&#39;t know all statistics.
But more focused even among the things I do know,
we&#39;ll talk about statistics as applicable to the context.
Here again, big advice like in accounting, it&#39;s good to do accounting.
I think it&#39;s even better to do more statistics.
Why more statistics?
Because it&#39;s everywhere, and many times as you know I love finance, but
I sometimes think statistics maybe kind of a little bit better.
More applicable with big data everything.
So it&#39;s not very useful in life,
to not worry about the implications of what you are talking about.
So, the nice thing about risk is, it&#39;s really easy to talk about it in context.
But finance makes statistics very applicable and related to risk directly.
So, let&#39;s get started.
Again, my favorite formula right in front of you, hopefully,
your favorite to know is in project analysis.
We have to worry about figuring out the NPV of the project.
I think it&#39;s fair to say that this formula is known in all over the world and
you understand what it is.
I&#39;m not going to repeat it, the most important elements is what?
Compounding, and that 1 plus r raised to power n over there
is something that you really, really need to worry about as Anstine said,
he found compounding the most fascinating things.
Okay, so there are two basic ingredients that
go into valuation, which are also related to the formula very directly.
The first is, cash flows.
And we have talked about cash flows.
If you entered the space, i.e., you want to just understand risk and
return, I would encourage you very strongly to first understand the big
picture of NPV and then understand cash flows and then come to risk and return.
I think that&#39;s a logical order.
Finance is very logical, very framework oriented, and there&#39;s a reason for that.
So cash flows have we done.
Have we done everything?, no.
Can you learn more on your own?, yes.
What will help you understand the cash flows?
A sense of business and accounting.
Now we&#39;ll turn to cost of capital.
If you look up on the slide and you&#39;re making notes,
I repeat what I said often before, which is, who do cash flows belong to?
Cash flows belong to, or
are the responsibilities of the project manager.
So, if you are doing that analysis, you&#39;re pitching your project,
you&#39;re making a case for it.
You better be careful about how you estimate your cashflows
including all layers, a special focus on your 0 and 10.
But the second piece to do the NPVa, as you know, is the cost of capital which
is now is taken as a number typically a round number 5%, 10 % or whatever.
Question is, who does that belong to?
This is a very profound point.
And it&#39;s related to the fact that all values is relative.
And who does r belong to?
It belongs to the marketplace.
And you&#39;ll see that in a very stock terms through our discussion.
We have spent a donor time in cash flows.
We&#39;ve also spent a donor time in bonds and stocks are debt and equity.
Why is that important?
Because those are the two main ways that will see risk emerge,
and they&#39;re also the two main ways of financing, and this will all fit together.
Cash flows are coming from whom?
Your projects, but financing will become important to figure out cost of capital
In a way that&#39;s really very subtle.
So please hang on.
I could&#39;ve done bonds and stocks way later or in the sequence of courses,
or if you look at a textbook, bonds and stocks could come way at the end.
But they don&#39;t simply because they&#39;re intimately tied to cost of capital,
especially the way it&#39;s measured.
What we are going to, therefore, spend time on is r now?
So, if we are talking r, why are we talking risk?
Why do we talk about return and risk at the same time?
And, please take this one takeaway.
It makes no sense to talk about return in isolation,
like the financial press talks about all the time, and
I think that&#39;s wrong, because returns seen in isolation make no sense.
Always think of risk and return as a pair, both go hand in hand.
So high risk, typically, high return.
So if you look at a high return relative to a lower return,
what&#39;s the first thing that you should think of?
Risk, they always go hand in hand and we&#39;ll see why.
So, why?
First, I think most people would agree that different projects or
ideas, project is a refection of an idea, some good, some not so good.
Most people would agree with the statement that different projects have different
risks.
It&#39;s almost a no-brainer, everybody would say of course that&#39;s true.
So, selling bananas is a different kind of proposition than selling a BMW.
Different risks, different cash flows, and so on.
Most people, and this is where, I really, really do love finances,
is that it takes real stuff and makes it conceptual, not the other way around,
that you are thinking only conceptually and not really about the real world.
And that deep connection between the real world and
conceptual thinking is what I think is the value proposition of financing.
Most people are risk-averse I would say, almost all people are risk-averse.
And hence, when they look at risking as of different projects, what do they expect?
They expect to get a higher return if a project is riskier than another one.
Remember the first bullet point?
Different projects, at different risks.
If there are risk averts, which we are, what do we look at?
We look at the return, but we immediately,
look at risk simultaneously, usually the other way round.
So, for example, if risk go up, you want to be compensated for
it, because you are risk avert.
Risk avert means you don&#39;t like risk.
Given all this, what our purpose today is to understand and measure risk.
And our next step is to take that measure of risk.
So, first understand risk, take that measure of risk, and
then go and relate it to return.
And when you relate it to return, that return becomes the cost of capital.
So for the time being, if you&#39;re having trouble, think of the following scenario.
Think of a spreadsheet of an institution, a company, or
a project with no debt financing, it will help you a lot thinking through.
So, whose risk and return are you worried about?
Shareholders, because they&#39;re the only people who are financing the whole firm.
That may help you.
And when you look at textbooks, when they talk about risk and
return, they&#39;re mostly focused on stocks.
Having said that, be careful, bonds also do have risk.
The mortgage-backed securities, the loans, were all bonds.
So, it&#39;s not [LAUGH] as if risk doesn&#39;t exist in bonds, okay?
So, what I am going to do now is take a break, I would love for
you to think about what we just talked about.
Why the heck are we thinking about risk?
We&#39;re thinking about risk because every project has different risks.
And, how will that risk be incorporated or manifest itself?
In the return.
And risk and return always go together.
See you in a minute.