Welcome back.
https://youtu.be/84X0GJ8elTo
So we introduced the notion of risk and return and
the purposes to kinda try to understand risk before relating it to return,
because risk is the kind of the source of return, if you may, right.
So let&#39;s make it a little bit interesting.
Let&#39;s assume our goal is to value a company called Rainforest, Inc.
And by the way, this is my attempt at being humorous.
Just hang on.
We want to evaluate an idea/project/firm that is launching an online portal
to sell everything under the sun, and we&#39;ll call it Rainforest.
And anyway, I&#39;ll leave it at that, my attempts at being funny.
So you want to value Rainforest.
What you have done is your job, you&#39;re the manager.
Or you&#39;re being hired by a set of people, by stockholders,
to run the company, this new company.
And you projected all the cashflows.
Remember, who do the cashflows belong to, belong, in quotes?
You, if you haven&#39;t done your cash flow estimation,
there&#39;s nobody who&#39;s going to give you money.
Right? Even you shouldn&#39;t put your money in that
idea because you&#39;d have no clue what value it&#39;s going to provide in the future.
So you&#39;ve done that.
And we know how to do that.
I recommend that you don&#39;t do this section
until you know how to do time value of money and cash flows.
We have done that.
How would you determine the cost of capital?
In other words, you have this new idea,
you have all the cash flows over which you have more control in estimating.
Of course it depends on market share, market place and all that.
But you have done it.
How do you determine your cost of capital?
And this is where a lot of people just pull things out of thin air.
And this is again where I just love markets.
I love finance, I love competition,
not to say that it exists even in the best of markets.
But this is the beauty why we like markets.
This is the value of information.
This is the value of democracy,
that people can actually participate in the marketplace.
So how do you determine the cost of capital?
To answer that question, you have to remember and
I&#39;ll answer it in a second, you remember one big hint.
All valuation is relative and
the law of one price is lurking behind the background.
So what will you do?
You can pause here.
Take a break.
Go for a run.
Think deeply about it.
What I want to do is I&#39;m gonna keep moving so that we are on track, and
these short segments of videos make sense, contextually, and within this.
So, if you realize that all pricing is relative, what will you do?
You will go looking for a company that has a very, very similar business proposition.
And that&#39;s why I thought Rainforest was a pretty funny choice.
So what will you do?
You&#39;ll go looking for a company that&#39;s very similar and that company,
we know what it is.
We&#39;ll call it, for simplicity, Amazon.
So this is what you&#39;ll do.
Please stare at the screen or the slide.
What will you see?
My favorite picture all over again.
And you have a fundamental problem.
So you go to Amazon, what do you see?
You see its balance sheet.
And you see on the balance sheet what?
Real assets and equity and debt.
Let&#39;s assume this number is relatively close to zero,
it would just make matters a little simple and we&#39;ll do debt financing,
equity financing and the you have two courses that you could go into,
which are sometimes built in a series, they are on financing.
And in this particular x series, we&#39;ll have them.
But you can do this course in isolation, that&#39;s why I&#39;m emphasizing it.
For the time being, let&#39;s assume only equity.
So what is your problem?
The real assets of Amazon are sitting here.
They are generating cash flows to Amazon, but they are based on that.
They are being returned.
And that return, I&#39;m going to call Ra.
Please remember, this is very important.
The return on assets we&#39;ll call Ra, and as you go, it will make sense what Ra is.
So where does Ra come from?
Where do the cash flows come from?
They come from your returns.
And, I mean, from your real assets.
And then you take those returns and distribute them all to whom?
Equity in this case, because the data is relatively low.
So what is the challenge?
The fundamental problem is you can&#39;t see Ra.
Because Ra is return on real assets.
Heck, you don&#39;t even know what real assets Amazon has.
I would claim that even Amazon can&#39;t figure out its return on assets.
Now here&#39;s the beauty of it.
And that&#39;s why markets are so good.
That one of the main primary functions,
main primary functions, that will count is to figure out value.
Markets are created so that we can make it transparent so
if there&#39;s no debt, what will Ra be?
Ra has to be equal to Re.
In other words the return on equity and the return on assets have to be the same
because there&#39;s no debt, there&#39;s nobody else sharing the pie?
So but what comes first?
Return on assets, and then you decide to give it all to equity holders
because they are the main financing source for this company, okay?
So here&#39;s the beauty of finance.
If we didn&#39;t have this trading going on, if we didn&#39;t have markets,
And we didn&#39;t have trading going on.
It would not be easy to determine this.
And because we have markets, and we have trading going on, there should be a Ts.
I got excited.
You could never forget our table.
So you&#39;re catching your nose the long way through markets.
Markets reflect value.
Right? So I work for a not for profit.
One of the best creations is a university.
I work for a university.
But the one thing about not for profits is you don&#39;t know the rate of return.
If it, even if it first making some cash flows.
Because nothing is public, right.
So when you have shares trading,
one of the beauties of it is it gives you information about value.
And therefore the fundamental problem is resolved.
Of course it&#39;s challenging, and there&#39;s debt and so on, so forth.
We&#39;ll get into that later.
So return on equity and return on assets are the same, therefore we can go and
figure out return on assets based on the information about Amazon.
I&#39;m going to take a break now and
when we come back I&#39;ll spend a few minutes going to Amazon on the web.
Remember whenever I teach I try to go to the information that&#39;s readily
available with one major caution.
As soon as we get into estimation, like we will,
of risk, there&#39;s data available on the web, freely available.
That doesn&#39;t mean it&#39;s the best data.
Okay, so be a little careful.
We&#39;ll come back in a minute and go visit Amazon.