Welcome back.
https://youtu.be/8AWiQeCSkHI
Quickly capture the main elements of what we are trying to do,
because to me context is very important.
It&#39;s very easy to get caught up in statistics which we&#39;ll do.
But before we do that, I always like to emphasize why.
I hope I made you understand why you need accounting.
I hope I&#39;ll motivate you to do statistics and more of it, but for a reason.
And that&#39;s makes learning more fun, right?
So what did we do?
We said we now are going to worry about risk because, not in isolation.
In this course with a very specific reason, and
that is to figure out the cost of capital.
We assume for the time being that there&#39;s only equity financing and
of course change that.
But by the way that&#39;s not a very drastic assumption first because the rest
becomes mechanical, so conceptually challenging if there&#39;s debt that is.
But also that equity and
financing and estimation of cost of equity if you can figure out,
then that&#39;s be a good return on asset, but that itself is very challenging.
So let&#39;s understand that piece, how to figure out return on equity.
Okay, so what are the issues, so you got a cash flow your in forest, you have
estimated the cash flow, you go to Amazon because your investor will go there.
So that first step is, when you think about risk and return your always thinking
of the context project analysis, not of your risk and return, of course you are.
But you&#39;re thinking about a comparable because all pricing is relative.
Determining the return that would compensate investors for
that risk of what?
The comparables risk!
In this case again, Amazon.
So the first is figure out the comparable, figure out risk,
the third is figure out the return that matches that risk.
We are all together on this right?
For simplicity again, emphasizing just for simplicity, and it&#39;ll help us a lot.
We&#39;ll assume only equity financing.
And I took you to the website of
Amazon just to make sure you understand that that&#39;s not an unrealistic assumption.
A lot of growth firms, a lot of technology firms have very little debt,
you can talk about that forever, that&#39;s a very interesting topic.
So now let&#39;s go to risk.
And risk will be a lot of statistics, but before we jump in, what is risk?
So let me ask you the following, go back to understanding bonds.
Why is it that the treasury bill is a riskless bond?
Why is it that the treasury bill, and of course you have to understand that lingo
and I&#39;m assuming you do, but quickly.
A treasury bill is zero coupon bond issued by the government of the US.
So why is it riskless?
Because suppose I buy it today and
suppose I hold it til maturity and suppose the maturity is one year away.
And supposed I&#39;m promised $1,000.
Why is it riskless?
Because I&#39;m standing here, I suddenly pay a price for it,
because if I hold this maturity, I&#39;m going to get $1,000.
Chances of default of course some countries are defaulting,
unfortunately, or at risk of defaulting.
Even postponing your payment is a default, effectively,
because the time value of money.
But we are calling it a riskless treasury bill,
because we think you&#39;re going to get paid this for sure.
Okay?
So, what is risk?
Remember I told you risk will start in the context of equity?
But I’m starting at the basics, where something is riskless, so
that you can gradually work your way up.
What about an identical bond issued by an average corporation?
What is that bond saying?
Identical, 0 pays $1,000.
What&#39;s the difference between these two bonds?
Both of them say they&#39;ll promise 1,000.
Both of them, you&#39;re standing one year away.
Assume for the time being both of them has no coupons.
The zero coupon bonds are issued mostly by treasuries or governments.
The difference is that one could end up defaulting.
And if there is default, what will happen?
There is risk.
So what is risk?
Risk is all about the future and
all about not getting paid what you thought you would get paid.
That&#39;s the notion of risk.
In this case, there is no ups side and
that&#39;s why I like this example too, what do I mean by that?
If times are good, will the government or the corporations suddenly pay you a more?
No, they will still pay you thousand, however,
if times are bad, what would happen?
The government bond will still pay you 1,000 and
the corporate bond is likely to pay you less.
So the question becomes, really important question, which one will you pay more for?
To answer that question, what do I have to assume?
What are you?
Risk adverse, risk neutral, what?
I&#39;ll assume you are risk adverse.
So what don&#39;t you like about the second bond?
The fact that it would actually pay you less than 1,000.
And we don&#39;t like losses, we like gains, right?
There&#39;s not compensating gain here, so which one will have a lower price?
You got to figure it out for yourself.
Which one will have a higher price,
the one that&#39;s more risky will have a lower price.
Because you value it lower, because of chances of default.
What&#39;s the difference between this and a stock, before we jump into stuff?
The difference between this corporate bond and a stock, is stock can lose money.
Of course you can.
I mean hey, in a day you could lose a lot of money.
But first thing you also happen, it could make a lot of money upside.
So that is, what this 1,000 bucks is.
This could be thought of, on average you&#39;ll get 1,000.
But there could be a upside, or a downside for a stock.
Let&#39;s keep talking about this for a second.
So if there&#39;s upside and downside, what are the sources of this risk?
So, capture it again.
Risk is not getting what you were promised.
In the case of a bond, it&#39;s all risk, less you&#39;ll never get more.
Think more broadly.
Suppose it&#39;s a stock.
You could get less ore more than you&#39;re expecting.
What are the sources of this risk?
What is going on?
And this where things become interesting.
There are typically two broad types of risk.
One is called economy-wide/macro/systematic,
non-diversifiable.
I&#39;m throwing that name out there, but not written it, because you&#39;ll see why I
called it that, and the second is, specific, meaning, it&#39;s idiosyncratic,
it&#39;s unique, it&#39;s related only to the thing that you&#39;re thinking of.
So, let&#39;s go back to Amazon.
Can you think of a market-wide risk that&#39;s built into Amazon?
Why am I thinking of Amazon?
Because I want to start a company similar to Amazon, so
I want to figure out what types of risks it faces.
So what is the market-wide macro risk you can think of?
Well you can think of what&#39;s happening to the whole GNP, what
happens to the economy, if the economy goes up what do you expect to happen,
people will buy more, when the economy goes down, people will buy less.
Chances are Amazon&#39;s stock prices will go up and
down based on how the economy is doing.
But what is specific then?
And this is very, very important.
Especially important because of the way we deal with risk, and
what are we assuming throughout?
That we don&#39;t like risk.
We are hypocritical.
We actually like the upside.
But we don&#39;t like the downside.
And you see that in life all the time.
Everybody likes things going up.
And they don&#39;t call it risky, of course it&#39;s jumping around, but it&#39;s going up.
As soon as things start going down, we think it&#39;s risky, right?
Because we are risk averse.
So Amazon broad risk easy, market, GNP.
What is specific risk?
Oddly enough, Jeff Bezos, who started the company is a specific risk.
Right?
I mean so he is the CEO, he is the founder.
He is a specific risk, why?
Because he is very peculiar to Amazon.
Please remember that.
Other types of specific risks could also be there,
right which are only peculiar to that firm.
So for example, giving you a broader sense of oil in one of my examples.
Oil became and is one of the major issues of the future is.
We&#39;re just exhausting the resources that are not renewable.
So what oil was.
Oil probably was a specific risk at some point.
For some companies that used oil.
But with transportation taking off, and with the boom
in railroads and cars, oil started becoming an economy wide factor.
So the reason I&#39;m raising this is, this is all art.
Nobody knows what is for sure, systematic risk or specific risk.
It&#39;s a way of thinking.
And we&#39;ll throw statistics in and you&#39;ll see how beautiful it all fits together.
So hang in there, think again.
I&#39;m thinking of Amazon,
because it&#39;s my comparable, because I want my cost of capital through Amazon,
because that&#39;s what investors will use to think about rain forest.
And when I think of Amazon&#39;s rate of return, it&#39;ll be determined by risk.
And there are two types of risks that you always need to worry about.
Broad, economy-wide risks and risks specific to your project.
See you in a bit.