https://youtu.be/0O-GRgSBXg8
Xin chào.
Những gì chúng ta sẽ nghiên cứu trong khóa học,
đó là đánh giá rủi ro dự án, hay là cách sắp xếp mọi thứ lại với nhau.
Và có một điều tôi khá thích thú về những gì chúng ta đã nghiên cứu là nó có hệ thống.
So remember, I&#39;ll walk though what we are doing again, and
bạn sẽ thấy những gì tôi muốn nói là một phần có hệ thống.
But the way I would title this last finishing content,
week, module, whatever you want to call it.
Tôi sẽ gọi nó là định giá của cái nhìn đầu tiên.
Nếu bạn nhìn vào chương trình học, đây là những gì tôi dùng để gọi nó.
Lý do là chúng ta muốn đưa tất cả mọi thứ lại với nhau,
và làm một ví dụ rất dài.
Tôi sẽ phá vỡ ví dụ đó thành những phần có kích thước nhỏ hơn
để bạn làm việc với tôi dễ dàng hơn.
Và nhiều khi, các video này có thể không dùng được nữa,
nhưng tôi vẫn muốn thực hiện video này
both conceptually and practically, so that you&#39;re left with a good
sense of why the heck did we do course one, on time value of money typically.
Course two on risk assessment, and how they belong together.
So let&#39;s get started.
As always, I show this equation so
that it grounds you in where we have been and where we are headed.
So we are doing project analysis, and most projects,
we would like them to go through this exercise, if not all of them.
In server and payback, IRR, whatever,
always do an NPV analysis because it&#39;s the deepest analysis you can do.
Does not mean your answers or your numbers are right, because law of
analysis is making assumptions largely because you don&#39;t know the future.
And to me that&#39;s the critical part of finance.
Which is it forces you to be in decision making mode in an uncertain world.
So, let&#39;s get started.
So -I naught is the cash flow today.
And bunch of cash flows in the future.
You, in a project, would idly like this to last forever, not true.
For simplicity and calculations, we will make the risen infinite
many times because we can use c over r minus g, or simple formula.
But you can always use a spreadsheet instead of doing calculations, so
there is a little disconnect sometimes between the notes and the problem sets.
But some of the disconnect,
it is by design, because I want you to be able to use Excel.
And I don&#39;t want the class to become about Excel.
I think Excel has its value, but
we want to use it when its value is worth it, right?
So okay, so we&#39;ll assume N is the life of the machine and
allow N to be as long as possible.
There two basic ingredients, the first is cash flow.
Very quickly, who do they belong to?
They belong to the project,
they belong to the manager who&#39;s responsible for projecting it.
We have done them.
You should know how to get free cash flows.
You should be able to do revenues, COGS, SGMA, depreciation,
taxes, working capital, cap-ex, all of those items.
And you should be able to understand the importance of the whole horizon.
Beginning year, end year, and so on.
Then we have spent a lot of time in this module
in trying to figure out cost of capital.
And we did that in many layered steps,
including statistics, and understanding finance,
understanding how the world works, how stocks and bonds work.
And we have assumed, for the time being,
that the cost of capital will focus mainly on equity cost of capital.
We have assumed no debt for the time being.
The important key, however, in doing cost of capital, framework key,
setting your mind right, is the r, who does it belong to?
R belongs to the marketplace,
to the investor, to the world that&#39;s looking at you.
So remember we were talking about rainforests,
how did you evaluate rainforests?
You didn&#39;t do the valuation, the marketplace looks for
the R and the best place to go for R is the next best alternative.
It&#39;s also called cost of capital or opportunity cost of capital.
And the reason why it&#39;s called opportunity cost,
because if you don&#39;t invest in rainforest, you&#39;re going to invest in Amazon, but
you&#39;ll do that only if Amazon is a better deal for you.
We have spent some time on cash flows.
We spent some time on risk and cost of capital.
For convenience, we have assumed all equity returns.
So let&#39;s stare at this graph for a second.
On the righthand side I made DEBT = 0.
And on the righthand side, the only thing that remains is EQUITY.
So when I do cost of capital I also do return on equity.
So let me just write for a second.
Return on debt will be called Rd.
And just setting things up is 0 because DEBT = 0.
We&#39;ll call EQUITY E and the return on EQUITY we&#39;ll call Re.
But our goal is to first pass get a return on assets.
Why?
Because assets generate cash flow.
And it&#39;s the return on assets that we want.
We cannot see it, so we go to an alternative, the next best alternative.
We cannot observe the REAL ASSETS; once we have DEBT = 0,
we know that these two numbers have to be the same.
So that&#39;s the logic of what we have been doing until now.
Cost of capital in an all equity firm is the cost of equity or
the return on equity by the way I used those and we do the cost and
return is synonymous.
The return on equity is obtained by figuring out what?
The beta of equity and
all published quote unquote betas, if you see out there, unqualified.
They just say beta.
So remember we went Yahoo Finance and we went to Amazon and it just said beta,
it didn&#39;t say beta equity.
And the reason is, beta equity is very easy relatively speaking to calculate.
Because stocks trade frequently but
bonds, here we have assumed bonds are not issued by Amazon.
Bonds don&#39;t trade that often, trade infrequently.
So even if you wanted to calculate as I see later,
beta of debt, it&#39;s tougher to calculate given the real world.
So, equity betas are what are published.
So, if you go anywhere and see a beta, that would be beta equity.
Please remember, a lot of people therefore think that debt can&#39;t have a beta.
Not true.
There&#39;s no such thing as debt can&#39;t have a beta.
The only place where we say beta is zero is risk-free debt.
So what I&#39;m going to do is now
try to build a world where your project is more real.
Or the project analysis is more applicable.
I&#39;m doing this for two reasons.
One, most of the world&#39;s firms have debt.
And therefore it&#39;s more realistic.
However, I&#39;m also doing it for the reason that this is a nice bridge for
bringing in markets and financing.
So what you want is to understand all of finance,
you just don&#39;t need to understand the valuation piece.
You need to understand now what are the details of debt and equity?
What are the markets in which they exist?
What are the characteristics of debt and equity?
How do firms go raise them?
That&#39;s not being covered right now but this section will be a good kind of
this module is a good tie-in into all the financing issues.
So let&#39;s take a break here, and come back.
And now consider what I call a firm that has got a capital structure.
By capital structure, you almost automatically mean mix of debt and equity.
And does that mean that there are forms without any debt?
Of course there are.
But typically it means Capital structure by definition means how much debt
versus equity you have, or vice versa.
So see you in a minute.
Just think about it for
a second, same graph, all we are going to make is debt is positive.