Welcome back.
https://youtu.be/sfnKDxnPJa8
We are still with the problem.
It&#39;s rich.
Let&#39;s do an interesting question.
Suppose Kitchen Inc has 100 million shares.
They just financed this new business through its existing cash flows.
What will happen to it&#39;s stock price?
Let&#39;s first ask qualitatively, meaning without calculating any numbers.
Do you what will happen to it&#39;s stock price, will it go up or down?
You know it will go up.
Why?
Because you&#39;re taking on a positive NPV project, point number 1.
When will it go up?
That&#39;s so interesting.
And if you have done finance before, dealt value money,
the courses before this, what you&#39;ll recognize is that in an efficient market,
where prices reflect value, prices will jump up today.
Unless information is not easily available, blah, blah, blah.
You&#39;ve assumed that the market is competitive and there are no frictions.
So let&#39;s do the exact calculation.
So we know that we go up,
because it&#39;s many times written like that, three dots inverted.
Because NPV positive.
But you can do better.
You can see by how much.
So let&#39;s take $100 million.
Right, which is the investment in the new project, and
add to that the present value of all the cash flows.
Cash flows are expected to be $15 million a year and
I am not going to add all the zeros.
You know what I am talking about.
Divided by 0.125 which is the cost of capital we just calculated.
Okay, so if you do that, what you come
up with is $20 million is the NPV, right?
However, I am not asking you the total value.
What I am saying is how many shares and what will happen to share price?
So price per share will increase by 20 million
divided by 10 million, which is $2 per share.
I want you to think about this very carefully.
And the reason is, it&#39;s so cool, you don&#39;t even need to know the market value of
the rest of the firm before this, right?
[LAUGH] So
I can figure out changes in prices, because I know the base case is common.
And I&#39;m adding positive NPV, okay?
Think about it,
it&#39;s pretty cool and I would encourage you to go redo this problem on your own.
Let&#39;s move on and ask the following question.
What&#39;s the new cost of capital of Kitchen, Inc.?
Is this good or bad news?
What&#39;s the new cost of capital, is this good or bad news?
So let me ask you the following question.
If you take this project, which you should,
your 50 business percent will be in Kitchen,
and 50% business will be in construction.
The cost of capital of this business was 7.5%.
The cost of capital of this business was 12.5%.
So, your total cost of capital for Kitchen, new
cost of capital will turn out to be 10%.
Half of 12.5 is 6.25.
Half of 7.5 is 3.75%.
So the cost of capital is now 10%.
What was it before?
7%.
Question, is this good news or is this bad news?
What should your answer be?
It&#39;s no news.
The good news was you took NPV positive.
This is not news.
This is a new cost of capital.
Next time, the good news will be what we will do next will,
matters whether that&#39;s NPV positive or not.
Why is this the case not good news?
What was your beta equity here, earlier?
One.
That was also your beta of asset because you have no debt.
But now what is your new beta asset?
If you do the calculations, turns out your new beta asset
would have to have gone up for your return on assets to have gone up.
Please do the calculation yourself and you&#39;ll work out that it should be 1.50.
And the reason is that the cost of beta
asset which you need to calculate, which you already know for this business is one.
Calculate the beta asset of this.
How will you do it?
You know the return on asset, you know risk-free rate is 2.5.
You&#39;re left with what?
Take 2.5 to the other side.
So this has to be equal to 2.5%
+ 5% times beta asset.
2.5 subtract, you are left with 10%.
Divide by 5, you have 2.
So the beta asset is 2.
So the beta asset of the business is 2, beta asset of the old business is 1.
The average of the two, half and half, is 1.5.
Very easy to calculate.
The point I am trying to make here is the fact that your return
went up because of a reason, your risk also went up.
But that is not the important point here.
High risk, high return.
Not good, not bad, it doesn&#39;t matter.
The real good news here was what?
That you took a positive NPV project and created share price jump of what?
Two bucks a share.
$20 million was created because you chose to take a project that was different.
Another way to think about it is did you take on a high risk project?
The answer is yes, is that good or bad?
No.
What&#39;s good or bad is not whether you did a high risk project or not, but
to get a positive NPV proposition from it.
And that&#39;s the key you want to take home.
So let&#39;s take a break.
I hope you like this example.
I really, really like it because it puts everything together.
It&#39;s not got too much on cash flows,
because cash flows we know have spent a lot of time on.
Which is a lot about valuation and how you think about it,
un-levering, why and so on.
And as you go into more advanced classes, just on valuation,
even if you don&#39;t do more on financing, which I hope you do follow on courses.
You&#39;ll need to know this to go to the next level.
So let&#39;s take a break, wrap up a little bit, and
add what you&#39;re going to see in the real world, and that&#39;s frictions.
At least one of them, which is taxes and the beneficial treatment to debt.
See you in a minute.