So now let&#39;s go to the real world a little bit and actually just a flavor of it, and
https://youtu.be/um8tlN90mwQ
the most blatant flavor, because I don&#39;t want you to get a sense that this is it.
What is really powerful in what we have done is,
that its flavor will remain with you throughout.
You need that as your basic way of thinking about the world, and
then changing the world based on reality, based on problems,
based on frictions So, let&#39;s go to The Real World.
There are two reasons why capital structure might affect value of the firm.
One of the reasons, broadly speaking, one of the reasons is,
that the realization of tax benefits provided you the tax shield.
So, one of the things that&#39;s happened in The Real World is,
that the interest on debt is tax deductible.
So it is, after tax, more appealing to go with debt than equity.
And that benefit of that tax deduction goes to equity holders.
And cost of capital, after tax, goes down.
The capital structure policy adopted by a company&#39;s management,
may however also lead to high chances of bankruptcy.
So these two forces, one a positive reason to take debt,
one a negative reason to debt.
Create in many people&#39;s minds, and rightly so,
some kind of optimal capital structure.
And that capital structure, books are to be different for
different industries, and so on.
But I wanted to give you a flavor of that.
But it&#39;s happening because on purpose, debt is being
made sweeter than equity due to the tax deductibility.
So, let me show you WACC, and this is the WACC you&#39;ll often see in The Real World.
Till now, if you look DL/ VL, VL we have written as, and
let me write it out a little bit so that you don&#39;t get confused.
VL = E + D, L just for leverage.
So we&#39;ll just read it and
just a little bit, because that&#39;s always true of balances.
The part that&#39;s new is this, so think about it.
Suppose you are paying 10% on debt,
like in our example to your debt holder you promised it, you pay it.
However the government allows you to deduct it, so what you are actually paying
suppose Tc is 34% what you&#39;re actually paying is 6.6.
After tax.
So what happens, your cost of capital becomes subsidised and
this is what emerged as a result.
Your return on assets is greater than WACC.
Because your return on assets is what you get.
But what you pay gets subsidised a little bit.
So your cost of capital is lower.
So that&#39;s why you kinda lean towards that a little bit.
Many companies have it.
Note that WACC is an after-tax measure, it&#39;s not before tax.
And tax benefit to debt is a man-made thing.
If you notice there&#39;s a huge debate going on, that if you take a debt,
corporate level is structural but if you take it at a personal level, you can only
deduct interest in the US and I think most countries on the interest portion of it.
And only on housing debt.
Many people have believed therefore,
it has encouraged house building as opposed to say renting.
And that may have led to the huge drop in the house prices too,
along with low interest rates and so on.
So the question then becomes, in a world with no frictions, I mean, with
frictions and a tax favored treatment, why don&#39;t firms finance 100% debt?
[INAUDIBLE], no bank will give you all that.
You&#39;ll run away with that because if you have no skin on the game,
why would you not take more risk and you&#39;re nothing to loose.
And by the way, a lot of that happened [LAUGH] in the recent crisis.
So why is that the firms are an average for example,
is about 50% is the average debt to value ratio across all industries in the US.
Some industries more, like airlines, some industries net zero,
like in the tech industry, close to zero.
Why is it that debt is not everywhere?
There are two contributing effects,
the first one is called bankruptcy-related costs.
As we&#39;ve said, the closer you go to a lot of debt, chances of bankruptcy go up.
You better take account of that.
Even if it is a very low probability event, but everything could be lost.
The multiplication of the two is very high, so for
example there&#39;s lot of work on signs on climate change,
which I think is bankruptcy of the whole earth in some sense.
So the reason why it&#39;s so important,
is not because the probability is necessarily high.
If that were the case, I am telling you, forget about it.
Even if the probability is low but you could learn to lose everything,
you better worry about it.
So, that&#39;s the gross product.
So bankruptcy costs are important.
It&#39;s how what you lose and not just the probability of how much you lose.
But the secondary reason, which we haven&#39;t spent too much time on and
which unfortunately,
we do not spend much time on, is that we&#39;re only talking about corporate taxes.
When you go to the personal tax level, equity
is probably being subsidized more than debt.
By that I mean, is if you&#39;re getting interest payments you&#39;ve got to pay taxes,
you can&#39;t do anything about it.
But actually what can you do you can postpone capital gains.
So because of that and because of different tax rates and so
on so forth, what do you want to do a complete study is,
firms may not have a lot of debt because firms are eventually held by people and
there may be countervailing effects of having too much debt, that account for
the fact that debt is only about 30% of capital structures,
say 30% to 40% somewhere on there.
And not close to 100%.
At least in the US or in the rest of the world.
And when it&#39;s very high, let me tell you, we have seen a spate of bankruptcies.
When the economy goes south, in fact,
nobody expected all house pricing to drop across America.
Very rare event, very rare event.
But it happened.
And it devastated the economy for a long time.
I hope you&#39;ve learnt this module and done a lot.
What I would recommend is keep at the problems, keep at the assignments, and
keep smiling.
See you.