Welcome, so we are talking about now a firm that has assets that
https://youtu.be/zrwBoRhs87k
are financed by both equity and debt.
Please remember things are gonna get a little tricky.
In fact, quite tricky.
But if you stay focused on where value&#39;s created, you&#39;ll understand.
Why one of the things we&#39;ll talk about now got another Nobel prize.
You see, that&#39;s the amazing thing about finance, is it&#39;s the only
discipline in business that has gotten Nobel prizes repeatedly.
And the reason is because it is very framework strong.
And it provides you ways of looking at the world that are not necessarily
give you the right answers because right answers are tough to come up with but
gives you the right way of approaching things.
A much better way.
Okay, so it&#39;s discipline, it&#39;s framework oriented, and it&#39;s extremely practical.
Things that you would want to like, right?
About any subject matter.
So let&#39;s assume a firm is financed by equity and debt.
As you learn in the financing course, those are the only two instruments.
They can be many different kinds.
Convertible debt, referred equity, name it.
But the neat thing about debt and equity is that there are two things,
combinations of them describe everything else.
So in the notes I call them hybrids.
So if you understand equity and debt,
you&#39;ll be able to understand any other instrument.
Not automatically.
You have to think about it.
But debt and equity I talked about most because they characterize the entire
spectrum of possible kinds of financing you could have.
Equity and debt capture most important aspect of financing,
and they&#39;re also called the capital structure of the firm.
A path-breaking result, and this got the Nobel Prize.
Please stare at the screen while I talk.
In a world with competitive markets and no frictions.
What does competitive markets mean?
That the money flows to the best ideas.
And the best ideas are not monopolistically controlled by any firm.
Not true most of the time.
Competitive markets, if they existed, we won&#39;t have many big companies
become bigger and bigger but we are very close to competitive markets and
that&#39;s the pressure we have like democracy is
kind of a law of nature almost among humans beings wanting democracy.
Markets are similar in nature.
So we&#39;re going to assume more or less competitive markets.
Because if you assume markets are not competitive,
a lot of what we are talking about becomes almost irrelevant.
It&#39;s a good way of thinking, but doesn&#39;t become practically very useful.
And markets are competitive, the less there are frictions.
So frictions are things that prevent competitiveness.
So let me give you an example.
An obvious friction is taxes.
So what does taxes do?
They throw distortions that create problems of stuff.
And we&#39;ll talk about it in a second, what that happens.
So friction taxes is one form of friction there are other forms of friction,
extremely important so for example we will assume here
that the manager is working in the interest of the company and
the company is owned by shareholders who work in the interest of the long term.
So we are making a lot of assumptions which are fundamental foundational
assumptions of modern man so that you understand what&#39;s going on.
And those are the kind of things that get Nobel Prizes.
And then you tweak the system based on reality and
know which direction and what magnitude effects you&#39;ll have.
If you can&#39;t understand the basic world
in a competitive environment with very little friction, I don&#39;t think you can go
to the more complicated world as easily, or in fact, you may get confused.
So here&#39;s the path-breaking result.
It&#39;s called M&amp;M.
Not as in chocolate.
But it has Modigliani-Miller.
A very profound, Nobel Prize winning idea.
It says the following, regardless how you finance your company
or in this case your project, your project&#39;s value will not change.
When this was said it was in the late 50s, 60s people talked including academics.
Are you kidding me?
This can&#39;t be true.
We&#39;ll not prove it but I&#39;ll give you an intuition for it and
then you&#39;ll see it over and over again, but then with frictions.
So you&#39;ll see more and more frictions come in more advanced courses or
even more basic courses on financing because that&#39;s the real world.
And we&#39;ll end off with some frictions here as well.
But as you see more and more frictions, you&#39;ll be able to understand why the world
changes with frictions, because you understand this word.
Value is created by your ideas, and not how you finance them.
This is what got the Nobel Prize.
So let me give an example.
We just valued Amazon with or without debt.
We assumed it had close to zero debt and
its value turned out to be whatever, $350 billion.
What this says is that if there were no frictions in the world,
then even if Amazon had debt, its value would still be
created by its real assets and remain at $350 billion.
Why?
Because where exactly is your value being created, and how?
And I&#39;m not gonna put up that one page because you&#39;ve seen it so many times.
It&#39;s on the left hand side, from my side.
The left hand side, where the real assets sit.
Financing is the way to make it happen.
But the real idea generates cash flows, and
you discount it by the return on assets.
Not return on equity.
Not return on debt because that&#39;s what you take your asset return and
split up between the two.
Extremely important and I can prove it and talk about it forever.
What&#39;s extremely important about this is its intuition.
And intuition says the following.
Very simple.
You create value by coming up with an idea.
And then if you put in only your money or
raised equity, your money will go only to equity.
And what&#39;s the difference between equity and debt?
You know a little bit about it.
You&#39;ll know a lot more as you go into financing.
Debt is a fixed contract and
equity is not a contract, it&#39;s an expectational relationship.
So which is more risky equity, which is less risky debt.
And here&#39;s your cost of capital and stare at the next equation please write it down.
Cost of capital is also in this world called rated average cost of capital.
I again emphasize, what do I mean by this world?
I mean a world in which there are no frictions, there are no taxes.
We&#39;ll understand this world completely and
then we&#39;ll start messing with taxes and so on.
And there developments have happened that you can go pretty deep
even in the introductory set of courses.
For now, no taxes.
So this is what you cost of capital will look like.
The first proposition was that the value of your firm
will not change based on financing.
The second proposition is the following, that your return on assets will be called
weighted average cost of capital, which is WACC, weighted average cost of capital.
Please stare at the screen while I talk, this is one of those moments So
return on assets will be D over E+D.
What is that?
D+E is the value of the whole firm.
Why?
Because in a balance sheet, remember and
let me just draw a little balance sheet on the side.
You have assets.
And you have equity and you have debt.
So, the value of the return on the assets.
And the cash flow of you assets, cash flow determine the value of the firm.
So cash flow, I&#39;m assuming you&#39;ve estimated, we&#39;ll do an example later.
Now you focused on return on assets.
So how do you determine your return on assets?
If there is no debt your return on asset is equal to return on equity.
Why? Because D is zero and E is everything.
Now you are ready so now stare at this.
What is D over E plus D.
It&#39;s the proportion of the value of the firm, total firm that is financed by debt.
Do you see that?
Because E plus D will be what?
The value of the firm, total firm we&#39;ll call that V.
So very straightforward this balance sheet has to balance.
The value for whole firm has to be split between equity and debt.
In fact that&#39;s the notion that&#39;s pretty straightforward.
The critical notion here is what generates value.
People think equity can generate, no, no, no.
Value generated by cash flows of the firm and the discount rate.
And we know this we&#39;ve done this, we&#39;ll do more at the end.
So what is the cost of capital?
The cost of capital is the weight of debt in your capital,
multiplied by return on debt.
Why this E and we are dropping it here simply because it&#39;s expected return.
Right, as soon as you go to corporate you don&#39;t have RF.
What do you have?
Risk and therefore expected return.
And what is this, expected return on equity.
What does this stand for?
A little bit superfluous But
this stands for leverage and many people call it leverage, leverage, whatever.
But leverage means the following.
It means an equity of a firm that also has debt.
Because if the firm has no debt the E will be by itself.
So this is just emphasizing that you&#39;re looking at a capital structure which has
both debt and equity.
One more time.
Ra expected will be a weighted average of Re and
Rd where the rates will add up to one.
If you stare at this without any numbers what are the weights?
One, which makes sense, because the whole firm is financed just by equity and debt.
Now if there&#39;s perfect equity, if there is convertible debt, what will it become?
More terms with rates that all add up to one.
Take it from me that has to be true because the balance sheet has to balance.
Take it with me a more complicated point for the time being.
Rd, Re, our debt and equity capture almost all characteristics.
If you combine the characteristics you can create new types of securities.
So what I want to do is take a pause here, when we come back I&#39;m going to
focus on one element on the right hand side before we go there and
I&#39;ll talk about what on this equation will not change, and the things will change.
So let&#39;s take a break, come back, please write down this equation.
I hope you already have, and we will go back and forth.
This is one of the most famous equations in the world right now, no taxes.
So don&#39;t get too confused when you see the real world equation with taxes.
See you in a minute.