Now comes the trick question for you, and this is a tough one.
https://youtu.be/d4_-iucmwK0
And I&#39;m using intuition for you to answer it, and
we are going to repeat this so many times that you&#39;ll can get tired of it.
But believe me, the world gets very confused.
Which return of these three, Ra, Rd or
Re and in this case back and Ra are the same.
Which of these three returns ,does not depend on financing?
This is a trick question It&#39;s a very obvious answer.
If you&#39;ve been listening, and if you&#39;ve been thinking, and if you have intuition,
you should be able to answer it.
The problem with this equation is,
many equations you think the right hand side is determining the left hand side.
So the answer is the following.
Think deeply.
What determines return on assets?
Is it the financing that determines them intuitively, or
the product you&#39;re selling, the cashflows?
So the answer is, the business your are in and
the cashflow it&#39;s generating determines the return on assets.
And then you divide it up between whom and whom, equity and debt.
So here&#39;s the really powerful result.
Financing does not change the value of the firm.
Because financing cannot change the cost of capital which in this case,
and I would like you to remember that for the assets, cost of Ra.
So Ra will not change and this is such a profound result,
that it will not be but, it&#39;s very simple to understand.
You can do equations, you can do all the math, and Matt Miller had this story.
When approximately said.
So, I&#39;ll say it with a little bit of spice, here, and there.
So here&#39;s what Matt Miller was asked when overprice was announced,
and people Chicago showed up, and they were taking pictures of him,
and so he don&#39;t talk to the cameras a lot.
Doesn&#39;t talk to the, they like talking to the public
a lot in the sense of being a celebrity or whatever.
But he was.
So they asked him, what did you prove?
He said I proved that if you have one pizza,
and you break it up, cut it up into two pieces.
And one you call e, and the other you call d.
And how many pizzas do you have total?
So some people would just turn and they said, one?
You said, that&#39;s what I showed you.
He said if you take up your pizza and divided it into two pieces,
you still have one pizza.
So they said is that all you solve?
He said yes with a lot of math.
[LAUGH] But it&#39;s a very powerful, it&#39;s one of the most powerful results in finance.
And that&#39;s why I say,
it&#39;s good to understand it completely in spite of some unrealistic assumptions.
And I would say, when did the assumptions thrown in its power is phenomenal.
So what I&#39;m going to do next is, say that
you know your expected return on asset because you know your idea.
Your idea, you generate the cashflows and the marketplace goes to Amazon,
to figure out the expected return on assets of rainforest.
I know that number.
I calculated last time, 10%.
Right now is the following.
In this world with no frictions, Ican do nothing about the 10%.
But changing the financing and rainforest.
If I started out with equity, return on equity would be 10%.
If I started out with equity in debt, return on equity would change.
But return on asset would still be 10%,
because financing cannot affect what you&#39;re doing fundamentally.
Have you ever gone in and said, tell me what the difference
between the financing of Apple,
Notebook is, iPad or Samsungs.
You don&#39;t ask how those are financed when you buy them.
What do you ask?
What is the quality of the product?
You don&#39;t worry about financing when you worry about evaluation.
Anyway take a break, bless you.
See you in a minute.