Okay, so we said value doesn&#39;t change, cashflows don&#39;t change because
https://youtu.be/MmI1zB9AsNI
they&#39;re coming from business, return on assets don&#39;t change.
The key was to figure out return on assets won&#39;t change because if they don&#39;t change
cashflows don&#39;t change, value can&#39;t change.
And vice versa, meaning value and
return on assets are extremely closely correlated.
Okay.
So what does change?
It turns out that return on equity changes when you take on debt and equity.
And who is you who&#39;s taking on debt and equity?
The firm, the owners of the firm.
So the equation that I just showed you, in a while ago,
or let&#39;s go back and you can stare at it.
This is the WACC equation, forget the WACC part for a second.
E(Ra).
If I take this equation, and
recognize that Ra is not changing but Re is changing.
And we are carrying the expectation signs here.
What I&#39;ve done is I&#39;ve simply flipped this equation and
written the dependent variable Re with changes with financing.
So it&#39;ll be equal to this equation,
you can play around with it, this is what you are going to see.
So what does the question say?
That expected return on equity has two components.
One is expected return on asset which is determined by whom?
By their assets, by the business you have.
And financing cannot change that, but it&#39;s also dependent on the second piece.
And that second piece depends cryptically on the first factor, and
that is your capital structure.
Which is, what is the ratio of debt to equity?
By the way, we many times will talk about ratio of debt to equity.
But we&#39;ll also talk about a proportion of debt in the firm.
Which is d over d plus e.
So be very careful.
The proportion of debt on the firm is different than
the proportion of debt over equity, right?
Okay, just keep that in mind.
So let&#39;s assume there is no debt.
What happens to the second term?
It drops out by definition.
Doesn&#39;t matter what&#39;s on the other side.
If D is zero, everything multiplied to it is zero.
Therefore, what will you get?
Expected return on equity will be expected return on a asset.
And go back to what we did with rainforest and Amazon.
When we assumed no debt.
All we had to do is figure out expected return on equity.
Let&#39;s ask you, how did you do that?
What did you need to know?
You used CAPM, CAPM and figure it out.
Now let&#39;s assume that there is debt.
And so this ratio is positive.
Then, the expected return on equity will be a function of this ratio,
minus this difference.
Okay?
And this is expected return on asset which is given.
You know it&#39;s fixed.
So I&#39;m going to kind of, for
the simplicity stake, please don&#39;t misunderstand it.
I&#39;m gonna put a bar on top, meaning this is not affected by financing.
Not that it&#39;s not affected by things, it&#39;s affected by the real world, but
not by your financing.
Financing is under your control but return asset is not under your control.
It&#39;s under your control in the sense that your choices of different projects but
once you choose your project Forget about it the market controls it.
What is this?
Cost of debt.
And this thing is typically positive.
That the return on that and you&#39;ll see why is because it&#39;s very unlikely
the two will be equal because there&#39;s no such thing as a firm with al debt and
you&#39;ll see why not.
In the real world it can not be for some reasons that we&#39;ll get there.
Return on equity will go up because this is remain you cannot change.
And this goes up debt-equtiy ratio.
This tends to be positive and that&#39;s the idea.
Is that return on equity will up with more debt financing.
So let&#39;s see why.
Returns are determined by betas.
And here&#39;s the beauty, the return and beta equation are identical to each other.
Return and beta equation are identical to each other.
So let me without expected parts write the return equation.
L was for the Beta, Ra
+ D over EL.
Ra- Rd. Do you see a connection?
They&#39;re both mirror images of each other except Ra is being replaced by beta.
And why is it, why is it that you can replace Re by beta E,
Ra by beta A and so on?
And the two equations mirror each other because this is related to beta equity,
this is related to beta asset, and this is related to beta asset, and
this is related to beta debt,
which we&#39;ll get to talk about in a second, through which aggression, and that&#39;s why.
Sorry, got excited about all this.
All of these are related to each other through one equation which is the same and
which is linear.
One equation which is the same cap-end, numbers are changing, you put in equity,
you get Re.
You put in a beta you get Re.
And beta that you get RD but the cap in the question is same.
And what is it?
Let&#39;s write it.
R is equal to R F plus expected R n minus R f times Beta.
So if I put E here I will need to put E here.
If I put A here I&#39;ll need to put A here.
If I put d here I&#39;ll need to put d here.
And usually causality goes from risk to return, not the other way around, right?
So now look at the causation for that last equation which was return on equity.
Suppose there&#39;s no debt.
What happens to the second part?
Disappears.
So, equity holders will face all business risk, that&#39;s what&#39;s going to happen.
In this equation, there&#39;s a second component, which is called financial risk.
So let me kind of explain what financial risk is.
You will have no financial risk if you have no debt in your Capital structure.
As soon as you&#39;ve capital structure, and
this difference is positive, this is positive, what happens?
Equity holders, who are also the owners of the firm, also the managers of the firm,
or at least the manager behaving as if they&#39;re working in the interest of
the equity holders are.
They become riskier, why?
Because they&#39;re taking on both the risk and business risk they have, but
they&#39;re now sharing financial risk.
And that&#39;s what equity becomes very risky,
and this is really not very well understood in the world.
So just pause,
stare at this, I&#39;ll take a break, I&#39;ll come back to it before I go forward.
See you in a minute.