Welcome back, I introduced you to the one thing that will change as you change your
https://youtu.be/eB2ghRjii3I
capital structure, and that is beta equity, risk of equity, because the equity
holders are now taking on the risk of the assets and the financial risks.
Let me explain that a little bit because it&#39;s highly misunderstood.
If you know that very simple, the same balance no worries.
Very easy, right?
Because all you need to figure out is the return on the asset and
not worry about all the other stuff.
Important, regardless of how you finance your return on asset,
beta asset can&#39;t change.
We talked about that, so beta asset, let me put this equation, a little bar on top.
Your business risk, you have no control over.
What you do have control over is whether you finance your business with debt or
equity, and both have advantages disadvantages.
More details will be later, however, here for our purposes,
does everybody hopefully understand that debt is a contract and equity is not?
So, that&#39;s why equity faces financial risk.
Who gets paid first?
A company&#39;s making s hundred bucks, hundred bucks,
hundred bucks every year a hundred million.
It take on a lot of debt and promises to pay interest of $90 million.
What is likely to happen?
First, there&#39;s likely to be default but more,
even before that, What&#39;s likely to happen?
This conceptually.
You should know who&#39;ll get paid first.
$90 million has to get paid first.
That the contractured form of debt, it&#39;s a contract.
Closer you get to 90 million, all of the firms cashflows go to whom?
Debt holders before equity gets to see it.
So who&#39;s becoming risky?
Equity holders, before debt was there you were 100 million.
Who&#39;s getting all the 100 million, equity holders.
Of course the good news is there&#39;s no chance of default you can&#39;t go
to the bank.
[LAUGH] Sorry you can&#39;t go to the court and sue yourse.f
When you never promised anything to anybody you can&#39;t sue yourself,
so it could be held as their money and
said: &#39;if it all goes, fine.&#39; Debt holders can sue you if you don&#39;t pay them.
They are not only to be paid, but they have to be paid before.
That part that came before makes it equity a secondary residual claimant.
It&#39;s the senior most, I mean sorry junior most claimant.
Senior being the one who gets first.
And therefore beta equity goes up with debt.
Beta asset remains the same, beta equity goes up.
In a world without taxes.
This will be true in general, but let&#39;s assume no taxes.
So what will be the extreme case?
Beta equity equal beta asset otherwise beta equity will tend to
be higher than beta asset, okay?
In this world beta asset will be the weighted average of what?
Beta equity and beta debt.
We have just flipped that equation to get this one.
Let me first discuss the basics of it.
Business risk is the risk that of all the firms assets inherent in its operations.
It is also the risk of the equity of all of equity firm.
Financial risk is the additional risk placed equity as a result of a firm&#39;s
decision to get a senior fixed-income security in place.
Fixed income, promise payment, and so on.
Payment to equity holders happens after you&#39;ve paid of the amount you owe, debt.
This, by the way, if you look up any textbook, is probably the most
famous graphical representation of what we have been talking about.
Before I delve into it, I will just let you Stare at it for a while.
I am going to take a little break.
Okay. And I am going to come back and
explain each bit which you should be able to understand already.
But we covered.
Thank you. See you in a minute.