Welcome back.
https://youtu.be/0K92v3GnUXg
Staring at a graph, one of my favorite, if not the favorite all time graph.
So what do all do we have?
We have returns on the y-axis and
we have debt to equity ratio on the x-axis.
Let&#39;s start off with the firm that has debt,
but it&#39;s riskless.
If it has no debt, what is rD?
Zero, you&#39;re not paying any, and so on.
So, first of all, as you go along, initially your debt is riskless.
I&#39;m just making a claim, it probably for a corporation never is, right?
But, close to riskless.
Now, remember we talked about Amazon.
So there was a very interesting article, and
you may want to Google finance, Yahoo Finance or Google in general.
When Amazon issued debt,
which was a miniscule part of its capitalization of equity, remember?
Miniscule, two rating companies had very dramatically different interpretations.
So one rating company rated it as risky.
The other said, almost as risky as the government bond.
So the fact that the two had different ratings is pretty peculiar and
interesting.
But the fact that one of them said, almost like a used treasury,
should seem appealing to you, right?
So even if you promise to pay a lot of coupon, and
a very small amount of debt, face value.
You&#39;re not gonna cover so much, you won&#39;t need so
much cash to pay it off, before you use other things.
So, risk free, close to risk free, is possible.
If Google take on debt, most people will say, almost surely they will pay.
Doesn&#39;t have to be the case, right?
So you could for some reasons have a risky debt,
even from the beginning and by risky it means chances of default.
Anyway, so you start off with rf, and
as you notice what&#39;s going to happen is as you start off with rf, rf, rf,
rf, rf, for this range, I am not increasing it much.
But look what&#39;s happening to return on equity, it&#39;s taking off.
Why is it taking off?
It&#39;s taking off because equity holders are facing two risks now.
Where there was no debt they had only business risk.
Now they are doing what?
They are taking out all the financial risk.
But at some point debt holders will start also facing risk.
These are called junk bonds.
And junk bonds are where the probability of default is high because the value
of the whole firm is converging to less, as much as the value of the debt.
Or improbabilistically,
maybe you won&#39;t even be able to pay off all the debt, and so on, so forth.
So debt is risky on the right hand side, and it&#39;s close to less risky on this side.
I love this graph for the following reason.
Remember there are no frictions and no taxes.
And this is just unbelievably cool.
So as you go along this axis, this axis,
what happens to WACC, which is rA?
It remains the same, this is what got the Nobel prize.
Basically saying,
return on assets can&#39;t change, regardless of how you finance them.
What changes though, return on equity changes and
rD also changes but here&#39;s the cool part.
The weighted average of the two are always the same.
So in some senses,
it&#39;s wrong to think of return on assets equal to weighted average of rA and rD.
Because you&#39;ll start thinking that rA and rD are changing,
therefore RA should change.
No, yes, rA and rD are changing.
But what are changing, as well?
D over E.
So even though rA is taking off, its weight is going down.
And therefore, the weighted average of the two is a different animal.
Because rates are changing, rA is changing,
after a while rD is changing and they all balance out to rA.
This is such a profound result and it&#39;s so intuitive.
That is unbelievable, so let&#39;s look at the graph again.
You can do whatever you want on this side in a world without taxes and frictions.
You can have Re, you can have Rd and you can have the weights E,
I mean the total amounts E over D.
And the capital structure is D over E, or E over D, whatever you want.
Typically we say D over E.
But Ra and value of the firm are unaffected by all
the action going on here.
What is being affected?
This, why, because beta equity is being affected.
Why is this important?
Because it will also help you understand the business of banks.
So banks, by definition, are highly levered entities.
And if you want to read about banking and why there&#39;s a failure,
is because a default will happen when you&#39;re 90% [LAUGH] in debt, right?
Chances are, so banking is a highly levered play, and
therefore highly risky play.
And people have been writing about this a lot, and
you&#39;ll see how it&#39;s important to have buffers in risky business.
And the buffer really is having a lot of equity.
Because equity is something that buffers what happens to the debt, right?
And there&#39;s a whole misunderstanding about how this works, and so on.
And there&#39;s a colleague at Stanford, writing with another
colleague in Germany about how we need to understand banking
from a miller perspective, to have good regulation.
So I really think this is a very profound thing.
And the cost of capital issue that we need to worry about before doing the example.
And I&#39;ll take a break after covering all this, is to evaluate investment projects,
we must find the beta and the return on the assets of the firm.
Since the beta of assets are not observable, we have to go
the beta equity of the firm, because that can be calculated using returns on equity,
and return on market big difference.
So you want to see return on assets, you want to see beta assets,
because that&#39;s what you need to figure the value of.
Your firm or your idea, or your cost of capital is rA, but
you cannot observe it, you cannot see it.
Luckily, if you have a publicly traded firm that has equity and debt.
If it has no debt, return on equity through CAPEM and you get return on asset.
But if there is debt, what you have to do is you have to remove the effects
of financial risk from return on equity.
You cannot take the return on equity and make it the cost of capital.
Think about it.
If you did that, what would you do to the present value of your cash flows?
I&#39;ll leave you with that part.
Suppose you systematically just put beta equity and CAPEM and
ran with rE to evaluate the cash flows of rainforest.
What will you do to the pres bv of your cashflows?
Will you overestimate them or underestimate them systematically?
When we come back, we&#39;ll answer that question briefly.
And we&#39;ll get into an example that will have somewhat more choppiness to it,
but not in terms of concept or execution.
But I will stop and repeat that example and the concepts over and
over again, because we are wrapping things up and we are doing a evaluation exercise.
See you in a minute.