Welcome back.
https://youtu.be/G4W1tU-u1LE
What I&#39;m going to do is, I&#39;m going to do a detailed example,
which takes all the stuff we have talked about, and put it together.
And I call this a mega example.
Before I do that,
I just want you to recognize graphically, again, what we are up to.
So I&#39;m going to just write some stuff.
You have assets, liabilities and
I clearly keep saying real assets.
Because if you&#39;re not producing something like a product, or a service,
and you have money on both sides, how could it create value, right?
So, realize it&#39;s extremely important.
These generate cash flows.
And they&#39;re evaluated at Ra,
which also turns out to be weighted average cost of capital.
In our world, we&#39;re going to change that towards the end and
then you can go into financing, you&#39;ll learn more and why, okay?
But for time being, as I said, let&#39;s keep frictions and taxes away.
They are man made.
They don&#39;t belong in the natural world and, therefore,
let&#39;s understand the natural world.
In this world, we know that values created on the left-hand side
value sheet from my side and then you have only equity.
What will happen?
I&#39;m after cost of capital in this case.
I&#39;ve done my cash flows.
I&#39;m just focused on this.
This, And this will be the same.
How do I get this?
I go to Beta equity, calculate it from returns, put it in,
which equation to go from here to here?
Cap m.
That&#39;s what I&#39;m going to do.
However, life is a little bit complicated.
I can calculate beta equity, but turns out, I&#39;ve forced debt to be here.
And there will be a corresponding Rd and a corresponding Bd.
Many times, and I&#39;ve warned you of this, many times,
people assume beta delta is zero.
That&#39;s simply because in the original proof for
convenience assumed, let the debt be risk free.
That can&#39;t be true of all debt.
You just have seen the disaster in the last few years.
Because there is risk.
Phones, houses to default, whether that&#39;s due to bad practices or
due to general reasons, whatever, default can happen.
So beta debt, think of it as 0 all the time as a bad idea, okay?
So very quickly, I&#39;m going to now introduce debt,
but keep taxes out of the picture.
You&#39;ll see debt, in the real world,
does have an advantage that&#39;s given by the government to you in most countries.
Interest on debt is tax deductible.
We are assuming that&#39;s not the case right now for simplicity and actually for
understanding the basics.
Okay, how would you go from here to here?
Again, Cap m.
But the thing that now I&#39;ll have to do is I&#39;m valuing a company,
I go to my compatible, the compatible has equity in debt, imagine Amazon.
So what do I have to do?
I can&#39;t put this is Cap m and call this Re.
What do I have to do?
I have to remove the effects of debt from this.
And that&#39;s called unlevering.
And that&#39;s what I will do using an example, and
that&#39;s closest to the real word, but just a first peek on valuation.
And focus not on cash flows.
We&#39;ll have cash flows, but focus more on cost of capital.
So since we are going to do an example,
what I&#39;m going to do now is show you the details of the example and
I will let you write out the details while I talk through.
Then I&#39;ll take a break, and we&#39;ll do six or seven questions, which are very,
very interesting, keeping the calculation simple but
really digging deep into evaluation.
And by the way, venture capital, private equity do use complicated financial
models but often c over r minus g can be used.
Multiples is another way to look at c over r minus g.
Anyway, so Kitchen Inc is a high-end company that supplies kitchen fixtures.
Kitchen Inc has no debt and
their stock trades on the NYSE, New York Stock Exchange.
I&#39;m just trying to make it very interesting.
And it has an equity beta of 1.00.
Either you&#39;ve calculated it, or you&#39;ve gone to Yahoo fiance, or
you&#39;ve gone to Morningstar and you know this.
What do you infer from this?
That is what I do when I read something in finance.
What strikes you about Kitchen, Inc?
It strikes you that the beta asset and the beta equity will be the same.
And the reason is they have no debt.
The return on equity and the return on assets will be the same.
That should strike you right away.
That&#39;s the kind of capability I want you to develop is that you don&#39;t even
need to do calculations to understand what&#39;s going on.
The numbers will just confirm what your thinking is.
Okay, Kitchen,
Inc is considering investing in the home construction business.
So it was doing kitchen business now getting into home construction.
The project to that it&#39;s looking at is huge because construction requires
a lot of investment, you need buy all kinds of stuff.
So let&#39;s, to make it exciting, say that the investment is $100 million.
Okay, I many times forget how many zeros in a million,
I believe there are 6, so 100 million seems right.
If undertaken, meaning if they choose to do it, which we&#39;ll try to evaluate for
if they should, the construction business will represent 50% of the total business.
So right now, construction business is zero.
It will become 50% of the value of the firm if you choose to take it.
So what are the cash flows from this new idea?
To make matters simple, I&#39;m not going to give you a complicated spreadsheet.
I&#39;ll make life simple from a calculation perspective.
But you know how to do this.
So let&#39;s see what the cash flow scenario is.
Remember, the world is uncertain, so
with a 40% chance, you are expected to get $25 million forever.
Why forever?
Because I can do c over r.
Otherwise, I&#39;ll use a spreadsheet, and
there are many probabilities then and many possibilities.
Don&#39;t need to worry about that.
40% chance, 25 million.
30% chance, 15 million.
30% chance, nothing.
This is a risky business, right?
So lets first stare at these numbers, I&#39;ll let you write them down.
I will do another page with some more information, and then we&#39;ll take a pause.
What I&#39;ll also do is, I put up these numbers in a separate note,
calling it the mega example.
Because whenever I do that, we have a lot of numbers like I had in risk,
I gave you either the spreadsheets, or I posted something.
And if there are a lot of formulas, I put up formulas.
If there are a lot of statistics, I put up formulas of statistics.
But I don&#39;t believe, I&#39;m sorry, in making copious notes and handing them out.
They work out to be a little bit dysfunctional actually.
So let&#39;s finish this example with some data.
So I&#39;ve given you all the data about the two businesses.
Some more about marketplace.
Companies solely in the construction business, have an equity beta of 2.50.
Remember, you are in the kitchen business, you are going into which business?
Construction.
You go to look at comparables and
you find that the equity beta of the comparables is 2.50.
Equity beta, why did I give it to you?
Because that&#39;s what you usually see.
These firms on average have a debt to equity, d over e, ratio of 1.
And the yield on their debt is about 10%.
For simplicity, keep that number in mind.
What is another name for a yield on debt Rd?
Kitchen, Inc is forecasting that the average market risk premium, remember 5%,
and the long-term bond is paying, treasury bond is paying about 2.5%.
I&#39;ve changed numbers.
Yesterday, we saw a real number from the Wall Street.
Here, I&#39;m keeping numbers round so that we can do the calculations.
So what I&#39;m going to do is I&#39;m going to let you think about these issues.
Please remember that in this page,
the important variables that lenders offer are Rd 10% for what?
The construction business debt but the Cap m numbers are fixed across everything,
which is 5% risk premium, 2.5% Rf.
When we come back, we will dig in and start doing some work.
There are multiple questions, and
at the end of it, we&#39;ll wrap up this whole module.
See you in a minute.