Welcome back, so now let&#39;s get into some number crunching.
https://youtu.be/HqfUAWmMGh8
Okay, focused mainly on valuation, but also mainly on cost of capital.
To me, that needs more emphasis, because we have spent a lot of time,
especially over, in finance, we spend a lot of time on time value of money,
and bond pricing, and stock pricing, a lot of examples.
But risk and return, I think,
are much more powerful because of compounding at huge impacts.
So we need to get that right.
Really right, at least the way we think, and
then refine our practical applications.
Okay, so let&#39;s get started.
Question number 1, what is Kitchen Inc&#39;s cost of capital
before it undertakes the construction business?
So important, I&#39;m not asking you the cost of capital of the new business, But
what is Kitchen Inc&#39;s cost of capital?
Remember, no taxes.
Simplicity, let&#39;s keep it simple.
So, let&#39;s draw a graph first.
And let&#39;s call it K Business, Kitchen Inc., I mean Kitchen business.
You have assets, and what do you have?
Kitchen stuff.
And what do you have on your liability side?
You have only equity, you have debt zero.
Do you remember that?
Yeah?
You also know or have estimated the beta equity equals one.
What else do you need to know here?
I want to figure out what, cashflows I&#39;m not interested in right now.
I&#39;m interested in cost of capital.
Which is equal to what?
WAC.
But because debt is zero, it is equal to Re.
And Re is equal to what?
Rf plus Rm minus Rf.
I&#39;m not using the expectation signs, beta equity.
But of which business?
Kitchen business.
Do I know the numbers?
Yes.
2.5.
This much is 5 percent.
And since I&#39;m figuring out beta equity, how much is it?
One.
Answer is Pretty straightforward, pretty easy, right?
And that&#39;s what I meant,
the beauty of a powerful idea is how parsimonously you capture it.
Meaning, how simply you can capture it, and how far it can take you.
Of course, you don&#39;t wanna make things so simple that you basically trivialize them.
But I think capital is not doing that.
Capital is extremely powerful, making assumptions, not right,
perfectly, but on the right track in such a simple equation.
Dangerous to abuse that, okay.
So, we got that first question.
I&#39;ll do a couple of questions at a time, and
then take a break, because I want you to work along with me, okay.
Question number two.
What is the IRR of the new project?
So, let me just qualify that, and remind you, what is the new project.
Construction.
So, construction is not equal to, I&#39;m giving you a hint, Kitchen.
Okay. They are not the same business.
You may require construction to put in Kitchen staff.
Sorry.
I thought that was really funny.
But they are very different businesses, right?
So, even though, kind of we could&#39;ve taken a totally different business, but
I thought, let&#39;s start with construction.
Okay, quick question.
Why am I asking to do calculation of IRR?
For two reasons.
The real world does it.
And secondly, I have given you the cashflows and they&#39;re well-behaved.
What do I mean by well-behaved cash flows?
Negative, positive, positive, positive.
Point number one, so IRR will be well behaved.
Point number two, I&#39;m not comparing two different projects of different lives.
I could have problems there.
I just have one project.
So if the well-behaved cashflows are there, and one project is there,
IRR greater than R will work, right?
Or NPV positive.
Okay, let&#39;s write out the cash flows.
If you recall the numbers, how much are you spending at time 0?
Negative $100
million, right?
Yeah?
That&#39;s the easy part.
Now what&#39;s new is the cashflow in year one could have three components.
The first one was what?
Its expected c1, not c1, is what we need to calculate.
So the three components,
the first one is 0.40 times 15.
Let me double-check whether this is the right number, or not.
I knew I was off by a little bit.
So, this was 25 million.
So .4 times 25 million?
But 30 percent probability.
That&#39;s the part I was thinking of, 15 million and
30 percent probability, was how much?
Nada, nothing.
The good news is that my analysis,
probabilities add up to 1, and on average, how much do I get?
.4 times 25 million is?
10 million.
.3 times 15 million is?
5 million.
So my expected cashflow in period 1 is 15 million.
Yeah?
Let me make sure, 15 million.
So I am making 15 million in the first year, but what is the good news?
These cashflows are expected to remain the same.
So C1 is equal to C2, is equal to C3, is equal forever.
So you&#39;re going to get $15 million every year, till infinity, more or less.
More or less I say, there&#39;s no such thing as infinity, right?
So the question I&#39;m asking you is, what is the IRR?
Tricky, no?
You should be able to tell me.
I&#39;ll pause.
IRR Is that rate of return which makes NPV 0.
IRR is that rate of return which makes NPV 0.
So, quick question.
What is NPV?
C/R- I0 should be = 0.
Why did I add C over R?
Sorry.
Expected C.
And this is IRR.
So E(c) over IRR- I0 should be 0.
If I solve this equation, I get IRR.
Why did I write expected C over IRR?
Because I know it&#39;s a perpetuity, and what&#39;s the formula for a perpetuity?
C over R.
Substitute, do I know this, do I know this?
Yes, and yes.
And the answer, IRR is 15 percent.
You see how cool it is.
So I&#39;ve always, I&#39;ve almost done a review of the whole finance course,
the one thing missing is.
[LAUGH] Sorry.
The only thing missing is, I don&#39;t have a G in this.
So we&#39;ve figured out the IRR of this project is 15 percent.
I&#39;ll ask you one more question.
Pause there, come back.
Should Kitchen Inc take the new project?
See you in a minute.