https://youtu.be/pZp_0fltLgw
Leadership is always based on a vision.
A vision for the long-term.
A vision that is based on the big picture.
Leadership also calls for decisiveness.
Courage.
A can-do attitude.
To transform vision into reality.
I am the mayor of New Portland, one of the largest cities on the continent
with one of the biggest sea ports.
The port is the region’s economic powerhouse and I have developed a vision for the port,
based on an analysis by one of the best consultancy firms in the country.
The result of that analysis were very clear.
If we want to remain the biggest port on the continent,
we will need to go offshore.
An offshore port is good for the economy.
It makes the area stronger and provides more jobs.
An offshore port is also good for the environment.
Because I will phase out the old, polluting inland ports.
They will be replaced by a modern, green,
offshore port.
An offshore port is a very cost-effective investment – thanks to our location,
we need less funding for an offshore port than our competitors.
In the year ahead, I will transform this vision into reality.