[VANESSA COBHAM] I have a client who is suffering from
depression who&#39;s boss told them that
they should just snap out of it. That
they just needed to think positive
thoughts and treat themselves to a short
holiday or a new wardrobe to make them
feel happier. As outsiders it can be hard
to comfort those feeling depressed.
We try our best to give them advice on
how to feel happy again. But if we don&#39;t
really know what it&#39;s like to experience
depression, some of our advice might not
be so helpful.
It&#39;s difficult for others to understand
what an individual suffering from
depression is actually going through.
Let&#39;s take a look at the type of advice
people give for dealing with depression.
What we&#39;re about to see is actually
pretty representative -- most people coping
with depression will tell you that they
have been given at least some of these
pieces of advice by different people in
their lives.
[INTERVIEWER] So, if you had a friend who is suffering from depression,
what advice would you give them?
[SPEAKER 2] Um, well, I&#39;d say, maybe they should get out of the
house and go see funny movie because that
always makes me laugh.
[INTERVIEWER] If a friend who is suffering from depression,
what advice would you give them?
Keep drinking.
Um, go shopping.
Oh, I&#39;d just let them know that I was available.
They could always give me a call.
I&#39;d probably just say,  Get over it. Like, life&#39;s too short. Move on.
Get some drinks or do something.
Maybe get a coffee with friends and maybe just
really try to pull themselves out
of the rut that they&#39;re in.
Well for me I go through periods when I&#39;m exercising a lot and
periods where I&#39;m exercising less. And I
find that when i&#39;m not getting out and
going for a run or doing some sport I&#39;m
a lot more tired and I start to feel sad.
So I would tell them to try and get out and
do something energetic.
It&#39;s okay to be struggling with difficulties
from time to time.
There&#39;s nothing wrong with you if you
struggle with sadness or depression from time to time.