So, of the different advice and comments given in the video, which, if any, do you think
is actually likely to be helpful to a person suffering from depression?
The advice about exercising is actually the only piece of advice that has any real merit
in helping someone experiencing depression, with research having shown that exercise can
be related to decreased symptoms of depression.
The rest of the advice is actually unlikely to be helpful.
I’d go further and suggest that, at least some of that advice might actually make someone
who is depressed feel even worse.
This is important because these comments are exactly the sorts of things that well-intentioned
people say to people suffering from depression or other kinds of mental illness.