Behaviourism as a movement began in Psychology in 1913 when John Watson published the classic
article, ‘Psychology as the behaviorist views it’.
According to Watson, all aspects of human psychology could be explained by the process
of Classical conditioning.
In other words, everything from speech to emotional responses was simply a pattern of
stimulus and response.
In his experiments with dogs, Ivan Pavlov showed that classical conditioning applied
to animals.
To begin with, Pavlov presented a dog with meat powder.
In response to the meat powder, the dog would salivate.
So the meat powder is the unconditioned stimulus or trigger, and the salivation is the unconditioned
response.
The salivating responses Pavlov’s dogs had to the meat stimulus are referred to as unconditioned,
because dogs don’t have to be trained or taught to salivate when they’re presented
with the meat powder.
This association exists automatically.
Then unexpectedly, Pavlov observed that his dogs began to salivate not only to the meat
powder itself, but to stimuli that wouldn’t naturally elicit salivation but were associated
with the meat powder.