In the current version of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders – the
DSM-5 – there are a number of depressive disorders.
These include:
Disruptive Mood, Dysregulation Disorder, Major Depressive Disorder,
Persistent Depressive Disorder, also known as Dysthymia,
Premenstrual Dysphoric Disorder, Substance/Medication-Induced Depressive Disorder,
Depressive Disorder Due to Another Medical Condition,
Other Specified Depressive Disorder; and Unspecified Depressive Disorder.
We are going to focus on two of these – Major Depressive Disorder and Persistent Depressive
Disorder or Dysthymia.
We’ll begin by reviewing the DSM-5 diagnostic criteria for each of the two disorders.