https://youtu.be/vY2l2xfDBcE
Yvonne said to me she said Jeff you watch the TED Talks I say yes honey I
love to toss
she say you know they're like really smart talented guys I know I know
she said they don't want like
angry black me toss a normal be good honey I'm not because I am
but I am angry and the last time I looked
on
this is this is why I'm excited but I'm angry
this year they're gonna be millions
Obama children that we're gonna needlessly
loops just ate that we could right now
we could save them all you saw the quality of the educators who were here
tonight
Helmi they could not reach those kids and save them I know they called
it is absolutely possible why haven't we fix this
told of us in education have held onto a business plan
that we don't care how many millions of young people fail
we're going to continue to do the same thing that didn't work
and nobody nobody is giving crazy about it
ride another to say enough is enough is a business plan
that simply does not make any sense you know II
I grew up I Indiana city and
there were kids who were failing
in schools fifty-six years ago when I first went to school
and all schools are still lousy today
fifty-six years later and you know something about a lousy school
it's not like Obama love why right
where you say like 87 was like a good gr rights
I just think on me every single hiya
it's still the same approach right one-size-fits-all
if you get it behind and if you don't tough lock
just awful ok why haven't we allow
innovation happy do not tell me we can do better than this
look you go into a place s failed kids
for fifty years and you say so what's the plan and they say what we're gonna
do
what we did last year this year welcome to business model is not
banks you stop open
operate between 10 and three
that were $10.3 they
they will cole slaw much how ok
hope you bank what we intend to wake the unemployed
Sony banks got no money in the press
fool created that business model want
and it went on for decades you know why because they don't care
so in about the customers it's all about it was about
thank goodness they created something that works for them
how could you go to the bank when you are at work
didn't let up then they don't care whether or not jeff is upset he can go
to the bank
go find another bank they all operate the same way
right now one day
some crazy bank I had an idea maybe we should keep the bank open when people
come over to work
might like that what about a Saturday
what about introducing technology now look i'm a i'm a technology fan but I
have to admit to you on a little
among the old social slow and I did not trust technology
and when they first came out with those new contraptions
these tellows that you put in a call in a give you money
I was like is no way that machine is gonna count that money whites
I'm never using that writes soul
soul technology has changed
things have changed yet man education
why why is it that when we head rotary phones
when we will having folks being crippled by polio
I that we would teach in the same way that we're doing right now
and if you come up with a a plan to change things
people consider you radical they will say the worst things about you
I said one day, well look if the science says--
this is science not me--that our poorest children
lose ground in the summertime, right? You see where they are in  June, they're here, and you
look at them in September and they are going down. Woo.
So I heard about that and in '75 when I was at the Ed school at Harvard. It was
an important study because it suggests
we should do something.
Every 10 years they reproduce the same study that says exactly the same thing.
Poor kids lose ground in the summertime. The system
decides you can’t run schools in the summer.
Now, I wonder who makes up those rules.
For years I went to the Harvard Ed school
and I thought I knew something
the agrarian calendar and people and let me tell you why that doesn't make sense
I never got that I never got that because anyone who knows about a farm knows
you don't plant crops in July and August you plant them in the spring
so came up with this idea who owns it and
why did we ever do it well it just turns out making forties we did have
schools were open all year what will you because a lot of folks
who had to work all day they have any place with the kids the gold a perfect
place to have schools
so this is not something that is on Dane from
the education gobs so why don't we
while because our business has refused
to use science science
yeah Bill Gates come out and say look this works
right we can do this how many places in America are going to change
non mom
okay got it all are my yes they'll be someplace
got some folks to do to do the right thing are
as a profession we have to stop this the science is clear
here's what we know: we know
that the problem begins immediately
might this this idea 023
my wife Yvonne and I we have four kids
three grown ones and a 15-year-old
so long the story with our first kid
we did not know the science about brain development
we did know how critical first three years work we didn't know what was
happening in those young brains within normal role that language
a stimulus in response call and response how important that was in developing all
strip
we know that now we doing about not
wealthy people no educated people know
and their kids have an advantage four people don't know
and we're not doing anything to help at all
we noticed is critical now you take
pre-kindergarten we know what's important for kids
poor kids need that experience nope
lotsa places doesn't exist
we know health services matter people
know we provide health services that people always fussing at me about
you know because I'm all into you know our accountability and dade having all
that good stuff but
we'll do health services I have to raise a lot of money people you see
this come find us jeff Wyler leave while you provide these health services I said
make stuff up
right I said you know a child I'll
who has cavities is not going to
are be able to study as well and I had to go I had to raise the money
right but now on hold up and you know what I tell Mom the wild provide kids
with those health
benefits in the sports and recreation arts
cause I actually like it's lights actually my kids one is really good for
shoes people really get pushy
I do because you do it for your kit and you've never read a study from
MIT that said given your kid dance instruction
right is going to help them do algebra bed of
but you will get that kid dance instructor and you will be too well
that kid wants to dance instructor and it'll make your day
and why shouldn't poor kids have the same opportunity
it's the it's tough mall from still
Sol sold the other thing
well I'm a tester got I believe you need a deal
needed to make you couldn't you work at something you think it's working
and you find us not working my I mean educators you were kissing you think you
got to do great no you find that they didn't get
up with his diploma testing the testing that we do
we'll have our test in New York next week run
is in April you know what to get the results that maybe in July
me you and then so in the end the results have great detail
they'll tell you Rahim really struggled
couldn't do two digit multiplication it so great a dull
but you get my bad school saw and saw what doesn't kill
you caucasian to come back from vacation I got all this test date up
from last yup you to look at
I just got it wanna go into shape
so how much money did we just spend on all billions and billions of dollars
for data that it's too late to use it
I need that data in September I need a data in November
I need to know you're struggling and I need to know whether or not what I did
corrected that
I need to know that this week I don't even know that at the
end of the year when is too late because
in my all the years I've become somewhat of a clairvoyant
I can I can predict schools course
you take me to any school I'm really gonna in a city schools
that is struggling and you tell me last year 48 percent adults kids
were on grade level and that's okay what's the plan what we do for matches
issues they were doing the same thing
I'm a make a prediction this year somewhere between forty for
and 52 with animals kids will be on grade level and I will be right every
single time right
so with spending all this money when getting
what teaches me real information right now
about what's happening to the kids the high-stakes is today
because you can do something about it soul
is the other issue that I just think we've got to be
are concerned about we can't stifle
innovation and now this we have to innovate
and people how did this get made about innovation to get angry if you do
something different if you try something new
people without you always charter school on Stardust rising star plus
this does not work for 55 years let's try something different and he is the
love
someone that's not gonna work the of people tell me a little start school I
will not work
I won't go they should be closed
I we believe they should be closed but we can't confuse
figuring out the science and things not working
with we shouldn't therefore do anything my
because that's not the way the world works you think about technology unless
engine
if that's how we go about technology every time something didn't work we just
do what I want said let's forget it
right may convince me I'm sure someone you would like me
the latest and greatest thing the Palm Pilot
they told me jump you get the Palm Pilot you'll never need another big
acting lasted all of three weeks it was all law
outlets I'll discuss tonight spend my money on this day
d anybody stop invented not a purse
not a soul the full swing out there they kept in the
the fact that you have failed nope that shouldn't stop you from
from pushing the science forward are our
job is educated this some stuff we know that we can do
and we've got to do better the evaluation we have to start with kids
are we have to make sure that we provide to support to young people
we've got to give them all of these opportunities so that we have to do
but this innovation issue this idea that we've gotta keep
innovating until we veal email this science now
is something that is absolutely critical and this is something by the way
other i think is going to be a challenge for our entire field
americore cannot wait
another 50 years to get this right we have one
out of tough I don't know about a fiscal cliff when I'm known as an educational
clip that we are walking
over white this very second and if we allow for ok
to continue this foolishness about say we can't afford this
so Bill Gates is gonna cost $5 billion dollar what is five billion dollars to
you non stick
what did we spend in Afghanistan this year how much
comedy trillion when
when the country cares about something will spend a trillion dollars
without blinking an eye when the safety of america is threatened
we will spend any amount of money the real safety of our nation
is preparing its next-generation so that they can take
our place I N be the leaders
of the world when it comes to
thinking and technology in democracy in all that stuff we care about
idea say it's a pittance
it's a pittance all what it with
require for us to really begin the SOL somebody's problems
are so I what we do that I'm no longer be a friendly
soul of you guys
right contradictory thank you all very much
so what is the high school dropout rate Harlem Children's Zone
well you know i John a hundred us about kids graduate high school last year in
my school
under the Sun and went to college are this year's seniors allow hundreds and
graduating high school
last I heard we had 93 percent accepted the college
we better get that other seven percent all 44
go after saddam
so how do you stick with them after they
they leave high school you know that wanted a bad our problems we have in
this country these kids the same kids the same vulnerable kids
when you get in the school they dropped out in record numbers and so we figured
out that you gotta
really design a network of support for these kids that
in many ways mimics what a good parent does
they harass you right they call you they say I want to see a great how you do on
that last test
well what are you talking about that you know you want to leave school are you
not coming back you
so much mike is no you can't come to Harlem good job looking for you and i
got really care come not
know we gotta stay in school but but you know I'm not kidding about someone this
I think it's a little bit to the great issue when kids know
that you refuse to let them fail fight it puts a different pressure on them
and they don't give up is easy TomTom times they don't have it inside
and then like you know I don't wanna do is gone all
Ahmad mothers gonna be mailed all that matters the kids and help get them
through
we try to create a set of strategies that gets them
tutoring in helping support what also a set of
encouragements to say to them you can do it is going to be hard
we with feels to let you fail well thank you doctor Canada please give it up on
one more time
of