https://youtu.be/3dkhGEmStyo
MATT MCGARRITY: So what we're going to do this week is we're going to finish our
work on the impromptu speech.
So we left off last week by looking at claims and evidence and now this week
we're going to look at how we put it all together.
So we're going to work bit by bit through how you're talking about your
evidence, and how you're performing your arrangement.
And then the second half of the week we're going to move into just focusing
on delivery.
So first we're going to look at what fear of public speaking is.
And most importantly, how you can deal with that fear of public speaking.
And then we're going to shift by just looking at some models
for good speech delivery.
So that's what this week holds.