https://youtu.be/nqRTv4WdL2s
About ten years ago I took on the task to teach global development to
Swedish undergraduate students
That was after having spent about twenty years together with African
institutions studying hunger in Africa, so I was sort of
expected to know a little about the world and
I started in our medical university Karolinska Institute an
undergraduate course called global health
But when you get the opportunity you get a little nervous. I thought
these students coming to us actually have the highest grade you can get in the Swedish
college system, so I thought maybe they know everything I'm going to teach them
about
So I did a pretest
when they came in. And one of the question
mortality
of these five pairs
And I put them together so that in each pair of countries, one has twice the child
mortality of the other
And this means
that
it's much a bigger the difference than the uncertainty of the data
I won't put you to a test here, but it's Turkey which is highest, then Poland
Russia, Pakistan and South Africa
and these were the results of the Swedish students. I did it so that I got the
confidence interval, which is pretty narrow and I got happy, of course
and for my course
But one
late night when I was compiling the report I really realized my discovery
I had shown that Swedish top students know statistically significantly less
about the world than the chimpanzees
Because the chimpanzees would score
half right. If I gave them two bananas, which: Sri Lanka or Turkey?, they would
be right in half of the cases
but the students are not that. The problem for me was not ignorance. It
was preconceived ideas
I did an unethical study of the professors of the Karolinska Institute
that hands
out the Nobel Prize in medicine and they are on par with the
chimpanzees there
So this is
where I realized that there was really a need to communicate because the
data
of what's happening in the world and the child health of every country is
very well aware
So we did the software which displays it like this
Every bubble here is a country. This bubble is a country
this country over here is not
disease china
and these easy india the size of the public is the population
and on this x's here i'd put fertility rate
because of my students what they said wendy looks upon the world and i also
then what do you really
think about the world
whether at first discovered that the textbook was clinton mainly
and they said the world this did we end them
and we is west of the world them is third world
and what do you mean with western world i said well that's long life in small
family and third world is short life and large family
so this is what they could display here i put fertility rates here
number of children per woman one-two-three-four up to about eight
children per woman
we have very good data since nineteen sixty two nineteen sixty about on the
size of families in the country the error margin is narrow
here i put life expectancy at birth
from thirty years in some countries up to about seventy years and nineteen
sixty-two that was really a group of companies here that was industrialized
countries
and they had
smaller families
and long lives and these were the developing countries they had large
families
and they had relatively short lives
now what has happened since nineteen sixty two we want to see the change on
the students write it's still too types of companies or have these developing
countries got smaller families and they did here
or that they got longer lives and live up to the airport c we stopped the world
and this is all u_n_ statistic that has been available here we go back to see
that it's right now they're moving buildings better healthier improving
their core the green latin american countries
into a smaller families you get the ones here are the arabic countries and they
get larger families but they did not rule on the lack of milk larger families
the africans are the green don't have the still dreaming excuses india
indonesia is moving on pretty fast and in the eighties here got bangladesh
fears among the african countries that but mel bangladesh it's a miracle that
happens in the eighties teen moms stock to promote family planning at the moment
the entire corner campaign nineties we have the terrible h_i_v_ epidemic that
takes tom the life expectancy of the african countries and all the rest of
the mall
mall stopping to the corner but we have long lives and smaller family and we
have a completely new world
let me make a comparison directly between the united states of america and
yet now
nineteen sixty four
america had smaller families and long life
yet and had large families and short lives
and this is what happens the date down during the war
indicate
that even with all the deck that was an improvement of life expectancy by the
end of the year the family planning started in vietnam and he went to a
smaller families and the united states up there is getting for longer life
keeping family size and in the eighties now they give up
communist planning and the global market economy and it most fast even a social
life
and today
we have been vietnam
the same
life expectancy and the same family size here in vietnam nineteen two thousand
three
as the united states
nineteen seventy four by the end of the war
i think we
old if we dont looking the date that we underestimate the tremendous change in
asia
which was in social change before we saw economical change
so that's more work to another way here in which we cordial display that
distribution in the world of the income
this is the world distribution of income
of people
one dollar
ten dollar or one hundred dollar per day
does not get the green rich and poor and the longer this estimate
as a little comptia
but they are people all the way
and if we look where the income ends up
the income this is one hundred percent the world's annual income
the richest twenty percent
they take out of that
about seventy four percent
and the poorest twenty percent they take
about
two percent
and this shows that the concept developing countries is extremely adult
phone
we sort of thing about eight
like these people here
giving aid to these people here but in the middle we have most of world
population her
and they have not twenty four percent of the income we heard it in other forms
and who are who are tds
where all the different countries yeah
i can show you africa
africa
ten percent the world population most imp over tea
this is always cd
the rich country in the country club of the u_n_
and they are over here on this side and pointed overlap between africa
and always cd
and this is latin america it has everything on this from the poorest
to the richest
in latin america
on top of that
we can put east europe we can put he's patiala and record south asia
and how did it look like
if we go back in time
to about
nineteen seventy
then that was
more about hum
and we have mostly lived in absolute poverty workstations
the problem in the world with the poverty impatient
and if i know
let the world move forward
you would seem that white population increase
there are hundreds of millions in case you're getting out of poverty and some
others get into poverty
and this is the fact that we have today
and the best protection from the world bank
is that this will happen
and we will not have a divided world will that most people in the middle of
course it's a logarithmic scale here but dont concept of economy is growth with
percent we looked up on that
a possibility
percentage increase if i change these
and i think g_d_p_ per capita instead of family income
and i'd turn these
individual it date back into regional dadar of gross domestic product
and i take the region's dhoni of the size of the bubble is still the
population
and you have the always see the video and you have sub-saharan africa there
and we take off the arab states they're coming both from african from asia and
we put them separately and we can expand these axes
and i can give it up and you dont mention here
but acting at the social values that shine survive in a lot of money on their
taxes
and i've the possibility of children to survive and some countries ninety nine
point seven percent of children survive to five years of age
only seventy and here it seems that the subject between always see the
left in america
east europe
east asia arab states
south asia
sub-saharan africa
the new year it is very strong
between charge survival
but let me split
sub-saharan africa
dresses there
better uh...
at is out there
i can go here
and i can split sub-saharan africa into its cos and when you burst the size of
these country bubble is the size of the population sierra leone the bombay ip
more reaches up there
mile reaches was the first concrete
to get away with trade barriers and they could sell racial group
they could sell their textiles
on equal
terms as the people in europe and north america
does he huge difference between africa and bombers hitting the middle
in sierra leone humanitarian aid
he moved there you've got
development they need if you have time to invest
then you can go for all of the day
it's a tremendous variation within africa which we read often make
becky t when everything
i can split salvation here
ingest the big bubble in the middle but u jz difference between afghanistan
sri lanka
and i can speak arab states holiday same time at sing cultures and religions
huge difference
even between neighbors vehemence into the war united arab emirates money
which was quite equally and when he was
as the mixes
and that includes all the children albrecht
foreign workers who are in the pump
they canceled them better than you think many people said that they case that
there's an uncertainty marched
but we can see the difference here cambodia singapore the differences are
much bigger than the weakness of the day
east europe
soviet economy
for long time but they come out after ten years it's very very differently
and there's latin america
today we don't have to go to cuba the finding of the country mcnamara techy
we'll have a
bill which i don't i don't think you but within some few years from now
and here we have high-income companies in those cd and we get
behold packed in here or the world
which is more or less like like this
if we look at it how it looks the world
in nineteen sixty
it starts to move nineteen six if this is not sad tumhi broadcast of china
and then he died and then things up in came and brought money into china and
brought them into the mainstream again
and we have seen how companies more
be spent
shins like this
it's sort of
difficult to get them
fix on both comfortable chose the pectin of the world
but i would like to bring your back too
about here
at ect nineteen sixty
and i would like to compare
uh...
south korea
which is this one
wid with brazil
that they'd been went away form here
and i would like to compare uganda which is there
and i can run late
forward
like this
and you can see
south korea is making its very very fast advancement
where is brazil
is much lower
and if we move back
again here
and we put on
traders on the night dress
you can see again
the speed of development is very very different
the companies
are moving
more or less in the same rate
as money
enhanced but it seems you can move much faster if your healthy first
then if you know when he first
to show that you can put on the way talk united arab emirates they came from here
a mineral country
they catch all the oil
they got all the money
health cannot be bought at the supermarket
you have to invest in how do you have to get kids into schooling you have to
train health stuff yet the educate the population
and shakes a did that in the fairly good way
and in spite of falling oil prices
he brought this country up here
so we got two mm much more
mainstream appearance of the world by record companies tend to use their money
that uh...
then be used in the past
this is more or less if you look at
if you look at every chick
data of the country's
they are like this
not that's dangerous
to use averaged eight them because
such a lot of differences within countries
so if i go
and look here
we can see that uganda
that today
is where south korea was nineteen sixty five split cucumber
there's quite a difference
winding uganda these other quintiles of you've gone by the richest twenty
percent of your guns on their the poorest and on the air
if i split south africa
is like this and if i go down and look at
nigeria
where there was such a terrible famine lastly
is like this the twenty-percent poorest of nigeria is out here and a twenty
percent richest of south africa is they are
and yet
weekend to discuss
on what solutions they should be massacre
everything in this world existing africa
and you can't discuss universal access to h_i_v_ fought that quintile up here
with the same strategy
as down here the improvement of the world must be high in the context allies
and it's not
relevant to have the on regional level we must be much more details
we find that students get very excited when they can use this
and even more policy makers and the corporate sectors
would like to see c_e_o_ how the world peace
seems you know why doesn't this take place
wyoming not using the date that we have we had a thing the united nations in the
national statistical agencies
and universities and other non-governmental organization because
the big guys have been down in the database is and the public is their and
intellect is they are but we have still not used it effectively
or that the information resource hinging on the world
does not include publicly-funded statistic that some web pages like this
they take some url irishman saddam from the databases by people put prices on
them
stupid passwords and boring statistics
hampton park
so what is needed we have in the database is developed a new database you
need
we have wonderful designed to withstand more and more i added up here
so we started among profit venture
at which we called
linking date that would be assigned to call it dept minder from london on the
ground where they warn your mind the gap
so we sort out my misappropriated
and we started to write software which could link
the data like this
and it wasn't that difficult it took some person years
and we have produced
animations
you can take a dataset them put today we have been breaking you and they thought
some fuel u_n_ organization some countries except that their data bases
can go out
on the world but what we really need is of course the search function
a search function where we can copy of the day thought up to a searchable
format and get developed in the world
and what do we hear when we go around i've done that apology on the main
statistical units
everyone says is impossible
this can't be done all information is so peculiar impeded
so that cannot be searched as out there can be served we cannot give the date
dot free to the students free to them for perimeters of the world
but this is what we would like to see isn't it
the publicly-funded database down here and we would like flowers to grow up on
the net and one of the crucial point is to make them searchable and then people
can use the different the assigned to to animated banner and i have a pretty good
news for you
by the good news that the press some new head of u_n_ statistic he doesn't say
it's impossible illness is weak on dude
and that's a quite clever guy
so we can see lots happening indate duck in the coming years
we would be able to look at the income distributions
in completely new ways
this is the income distribution of china nineteen seventy
this is the income distribution or the united states nineteen seventy eight
almost no overlap
almost no overlap and what has happened
with those happens this the china's growing it's not so equal any longer and
he's appearing here overlooking the united states
almost like a ghost isn't it time have reduced their
but i think is very important to have have all these
information
weenie we need to really two-seat
and instead of looking at basic
i would like to end up by showing
the internet users per one thousand
this software we excess about five hundred variables from all the countries
quite easily it takes some
prime tool to to change for this but
on the excesses
you can quite easily
get in the very beginning with like to have
the pricing would be to get up the databases free to get them such a bill
and with the second thing to get them into the graphic formats
weightlifting spent only
understand i'm not statisticians doesn't like the because they say
that this will not this will not
and uh...
show
the very ality we have to ask that these people analytical methods but this is
hypothesis generating
i can't now with the world
bedding tonight dot com and the number of internet users are going up like this
this is the agreed to pay per capita
and using new technology coming in
but the amazingly how where it keeps tapes
to the economy of the country's
that's one of one hundred dollar computer will be so important
but five candidates he says he is the world is flat morphism these companies
are lifting more than the economy
and will be very interesting too full of these over the year
as i would like you to be able to do with all of the publicly-funded data
thank you very much
peers cherished
with security one points
the realism
if there is a place where artistic vision is protected inspired design and
his little here we come
kicking me she needs