https://youtu.be/MhdUolqapOQ
MATT MCGARRITY: This week has us deep in the informative.
So last week we began the assignment.
And now we're getting into the nitty gritty details of mastering your
informative content.
So we're going to look at how you can identify key points in your content.
What are the key things that have to be addressed in talking us through
this new idea?
Then we're going to shift and look at how you can rearrange this content
clearly and effectively.
And then finally, we're going to turn to this key skill of explanation.
Being able to help an audience understand a new concept through
examples and elaboration.
So that's what we're going to be working on this week.