https://youtu.be/BZoKfap4g4w
my mother and father had been saving money for years to be able to buy that
machine
and the first day is going to be used
even grandma
was invited to see the machine
and grandma was even more excited
throughout her life she had been heating water with firewood
and she had hand washed
laundry for seven children
and now she was going to watch
electricity
do that work
my mother my mother
carefully opened the door
and she loaded the laundry into the machine
like this
when she closed the door grandma said no no no no let me let me
push the button
and grandma
pushed the button
and she said
ooh
fantastic i want to see this give me a chair give me a chair i want to see it
sat down in front of the machine
and she watched
the entire washing program she was mesmerized
to my grandmother
the washing machine was a miracle
to date
in sweden and other rich countries
people are using so many so many different machines they are so
full of machines i can't even name them all you know
and and they also when they'd when they don't want to travel
they use flying machines
that can take them to remote destinations
and yet in the world there are so many people who still need the water on fire
and eight cook their food on fire
sometimes they don't even have enough food
and they lived de lo the poverty line that to billion
fellow human beings
will leave the on less than two a dollar a day
and the richest people over there
as one million people and they merely bob court i caught the airline
because they have more
spend more than a controller today you know on their consumption
but this is just want to three million people and obviously there are seven
million people in the world so there must be one do three
four billion people more will it do you need to be in the poverty line and the
airline
they have a nick leeson
but the question is how many have washing machine
i'd done this scrutiny or market data
and i found
that indeed the washing machine has penetrated
deal with the airline and today there's an additional one billion people out
there
will live bob the wash line
vacancy alone for more than forty dollar per day
thirteen billions have excess the washing machine
and the remaining
five billion
how do they watch
what will be more precise
how do we most of the women in the world walks because it remains the hard work
for women to watch
there was like this by hand
it's paul dekhte hein consuming
labor which they have to do for hours every week
and sometimes they will send to bring water from faraway to do the laundry at
home or they had to bring the laundry away to a stream far off
and they want the washing machine
they don't want to spend such a large part of their life
doing this hard work
we still relatively low productivity
and there's nothing different in their wish
than it was from my grandmother nuclear dude generations ago in sweden picking
water from the stream
heating with firewood and washing biker
they want the washing missing in exactly the same way but when i lecture to
environmentally concerned students
they can't make no everybody in the world cannot have cars and washing
machines
have compelled his woman dirty and going to have the washing machine
and they lost by students at boston over the last two years about how many of you
and i think he was a card as some of them probably raise their hand miller's
yeah i don't use a car
and then i put the really tough questions
how many of you hand wash your genes and your bed sheet
no one raised their hand
even the hog according the green movement
use washing machine
so how come something that everyone views and they think others with most of
the what the especially with this
i had to do in another six about the energy use in the world here we are
nokia you see the seven million people up there
the air people of the worst big brother
bid by all the people and the fire people
at one unit like this
but energy use lethal force if you would all you would call with our guests
that's what most of the electricity and energy in the world this
and needs twenty units used in the entire world
and the reaches bonding and they use six up
half of the image is used
by one-seventh of the world population
and these ones who have washing machine but not the house for the by the
machines
that used to
this group used to eat one leach
and they are setting a precedent over there they don't even use one leach that
makes twelve
but the main concern for the environmentally interested students and
they are right is about the future
what are the printing we ask for a long veterans without any really advanced
analysis to two thousand feet you've got to do things that can increase the
energy use first population growth second economic growth
bubble asian growth we may need a car among the poorest people here because
they are high child mortality and they have many children per woman
and that they would get to excel but that won't change their images used very
much
what will happen is a case
economic growth
the best of hearing the emerging economies i called and then you eat
they will jumped the airline wap they would say and they would start to use as
much as the old west are doing well read
and these people they want the washing machine i told you a bit and all that
and they will dot but then did you use in the hope that the poor people get the
into the electric light
they would get to shock family without a stop in population growth
but the total energy consumption will increase to twenty two units and these
twenty-two units you know
spin the richest people use most often
so what's needed to be done because
the race the high probability of climate change is re
israel
of course they must be more energy efficient
they must change behavior to some way they must also start to creep use green
and which much more green engines but dont feel they have the same energy
plans on several persons they shouldn't give advice to others what to do well
what a lot to do
fear we can get
here we can get
more green energy all over this is what we hope many had
is a real challenge in the future
but i can assure your that this woman and a far better lighting real
she wants the washing machine
she's very happy about a minister of energy that provided any preceded
reveron
so happy that she even even voted for heart you know what
and she became a day tomorrow so if the president-elect over
one of the biggest democracies in the world you know moving from in this job
energy too oppressive
if you have democracy people in wartime vote for washing machine laminin
and what and that he played
my math
explain the magic with this machine that very very
the she said
now homes
we had no did the laundry them if she would make it work
and now we can go to the light
because this is the magic
loads of laundry
and what do you get out of the machine
you gift books
part of the machines
children's books
and mother got time to read for me
seal of this i've got the a_b_c_ this is why i started my career as professor
when my mother had time to read for me
and short of accounts for a second
tim anderson study english and learned that
as a foreign language
and she read so many adult burns so many different melbourne sia you know and and
we really will be there la
this machine
and what they said that my mother and me
fact you industrialization
thank you's deleon
thank you cholera station
and thank you can make the processing industry that gave us time to read both
thank you very much