who make this cafe possible
who have not promise supported this and not gross season but who have committed
to this adventure again next year
it is selling exciting to the able to see
and that's how this time destroyed
mendacious public thirst for science
and specialty cocktails
despite a show of hands i want to know how many people here have been to aside
half a at this museum before
yang nice and how tentative into more than one
how did you have been sup all
night tonight is the nineteen th
anyone anyone
bright die hard it's very nice
at as those of you have been here before no tonight we've really expanded our
pariah since we've moved beyond that got us in the hall of planet earth
and into the column in the heart of the universe
were also switching up the format tonight instead of our typical speak for
cement tomb in a discussion is going to be entirely q and a
and then you can tell us what you think of this and and the moves the space in
our surveys which as usually will collect at the end of the evening and to
lucky survey respondents will received and will be able to win raffle tickets
for drinks later tonight
to do your service
scan marks that tenth anniversary
of the opening of this beautiful hauled the rose center for in space
and celebration we are throwing open the doors of the universe to all of you
and i can think of you know better
denied
cosmic died through this universe then tonight's first
so it is with great honor and great pleasure that i introduce to you
that director of the hayden planetarium
the great popularize are of science
does best friended me
and the man who needs no introduction
doctor neil depressed etc
this is uh... great turnout
this is supposed to be an intimate
kinda coffeehouse sort of saying so
we have to have to let move it out of the
we had another room plan
so i want to try to be skipping intimate
i don't know how
but will try
okay awkward welcomed
to the universe
i can say that the way james earl jones at welcome to the universe
you were here under disputes fear
properly supported above your head
when we first thought of designing it
the natural thought was to support it from below
how else would you support us here
but views from the outside of look like a golf ball and golf team so that's not
cosmic
and so the architects figured how to supported from the start
city walk under the sphere as though you are in space so welcome
to the whole of the universe if you have a chance before the evenings over
you can actually fines pluto
it is expected
on that planet wall there
at the bottom
grouped with other of its icy brethren in the outer solar system
the type herb dot
that is worth little appears in this solidity
ten years ago
where the first public institution
readjust plumes associations
in the solar system that we got into trouble
with the new york times about that
but then the rest of the world caught on and so now
that hate mail has diminished significantly
from third-graders
they've gotten over it and so should you expect
ut this evening i'd this is
this is a cafe
it's a big cafe but it's a cafe
and i'd want to
this to be principally
and open session
where i will walk among you
you ask questions
out toss up a few other sort of current events e kinds of things just a warm you
up but this will be driven
by your curiosity
not by my curiosity
we have playing behind me the known universe
it is our first
first youtube video to go viral from this institution
you may have seen it
if not beard would not than among the three half a million people who have
it's assume out from the surface of the earth
out to the edge of unknown universe
produced here in collaboration
with the rubin museum of art
down in chelsea
board exhibit that's now closed sorry
exhibited studied
the ancient concepts
for eastern concepts of cosmology sp
but we felt to complete that story you include modern cosmology as well
in the zoom out now resuming back in
social play the whole night
give you some of the dead if you're tired of looking at me
just check it out that's fine
so a couple other current events e thing so you know poodles gone
is still out there but
we have other relationships with it
we can talk about the past present future of nasa
we can talk about the black holes that were not made in the supercollider n
switzerland
many people thought the world would end
and speaking of ending of the world
there's twenty twelve their people still a little worried about that
anyone here dragged by their friend
to this event this evening who themselves
is still worried about twenty twelve raise your hand to be honest
your freight to say that in this the center of the universe okay but we can
put we can straighten that out
if you'd like
uh... either things if you've forgotten what the latest is on dark matter dark
energy
black holes
this is the chance
and this is a bit of statistic that i've shared
on some youtube somewhere
if you haven't seen it how you will hear it now for the first time
there's about
six-and-a-half seven thousand astrophysicist ps
in the world
there's about
six-and-a-half seven billion people
in the world
divide those two numbers what do you get
that decry up here he's got he's got the answer
one-in-a-million
cell
if you ever find yourself in the company of an astrophysicist
that's the time to ask all the questions you have
good you'll never know the next time that will happen
this is one of those occasions
we are also we have someone here who will be
pumping questions also
from the twitter verse
it's intermittently will grab one off of
of twitter
i tweaked the universe
the more the more like cosmic bring droppings pound
these they just sort of random
thoughts
that by had anyway
buttttt shame to keep them to myself
took earlier today you might have missed it treated
actually
adding some words because otherwise it's like a high clue you wouldn't build
understanding
actually
america is
inching its way towards the metric system
uh...
but i liked
the photo
we're actually
mostly metric
okay our money is metric you never thought about that eject
you're not paying for things in pounds and shillings in
uh... a money is metric
our work
ingin displacement in cars is now metric
plus you have never in your life consumed aquat pepsi
it's been leaders to leaders three liter bottles wine is metric
health but we have one does over here apparently
what you think it would be glad her quest
wind is metric
uh...
are the nutrition labels
are metric
they tell you what how much protein carbohydrate fat you're consuming all of
your food
that's metric
uh... photography is metric
the emergence
field of ammunitions and
that's metric to but this is new york so you shouldn't know about that
but here from texas
right here today i'm
out so where inching along
hand it's happening without anybody even
taking notice
it's slow but israel and i think it's irreversible
but any help
block on the floor there'll be a microphone roving so what you have to do
is hold your hand up sort of earlier
so that they can find you with a microphone we have one right there
superbowl great raise your hands
yes we have to high microphones there
and will come around to you as you raise your hand and i'll just keep talking to
you
raise your hand
and pose the question
by the way you came here for free
but it's a cash bar complete ability to that's free booze by the way
you we've got our first question the first question yes
trying and
outside
uh... i'm dissident this is my space here
so i willl endowment educator
so i will require
that you don't start your question with the word on
okay
allies you get doctor terms
to start again don't start with
yeah
battlestar
but it's for the greater good i'm sure you
okay go
but
hello start coming out of her
and sinunu andrea
to wafer
middle started saying things about
away uh... times magazine
that you say
uh... the e ask do
was this time ten questions
the tennis in general okay
yet reporter from time magazine
came into my awesome office and asked
ten questions
submitted to the magazine
and then that was podcast it and it's a little video of it
for the pockets has the story and sir
the video is truncated so it doesn't you on youtube
but continuous event
ke asked do you know uh...
if you could go back in time
weights
test you would
genes to speak with moving in you say
so isaac newton all yes
and that inspire is just very moved by the way that you spoke about him and you
say
really
felt the universe and he really an aesthetic and isaac newton was in touch
with the cosmos right
and he said that you
but you have a question that we'd wait a minute now provided the eaton and i was
just want to share that with everyone yeah i just didn't want to be moved the
second time this what you're saying
you remove that first time
good i'll talk about isaac newton
mean you can go way back
okay
challan
yeah i would let you know i break because the way he said he said that fly
will elaborate about sir isaac
okay high-voltage self at
accident
he did ask me what scientists what i see if i went back in time
he asked me
what percent do i want to meet if i went back in time right i've said it'll be
the scientist
isaac newton
isaac newton british scientist
he was a professor at university of cambridge
he held the endowed chair that stephen hawking
now holds duplication professor
of mathematics
and he's a physicist today we would think of him as a physicist back then he
was what's known as a natural philosopher
who pose questions about the natural world as opposed to the human world
human philosophical questions like the meaning of wife in the sort of thing
their natural source article questions
what is the origin of the universe and uh...
so i certainly wouldn't
was brilliant that i i almost of anything he's ever written
and i sit there and i read it
and as i read the sentences he put to page
here it goes up on the back actually have here they're but if you look at www
if you'd like to commence bumpy kinda thing
defied hair on my neck it would be standing on edge
as i see the dept
to which he was connected
to the operations of nature
there is no doubt about it
the man
discovered the laws of gravity
by sitting there
okay it's rumored that he sat under the apple tree
but what is certain is that he knew
in the same field if you if you saw on apple drop
and the moon
it worked
around the earth
okay he sees the two of them
one is falling to the ground and the others like up there in space
he connects the two
suggests
that the same force of gravity is operating on both of them
they're both falling towards arts
he hypothesized or how's that possible
if i can drop this camera on the ground
they would fall
but if it's a morbid it's not falling
plate is full
deities
if you're in orbit you are falling towards earth
he drew a diagram to illustrate this rebecca diagram is on the wall over
there called orbits
there's someone who's head isn't one of the work right now
typing on is that there's porpoises and hope orbit adult
where we describe this but i'll do it for you cuz i'm here in person
right he suggested suppose you had a hill
any sort of fire a cannibal
not very fast it was a sort of assault
fired a little faster
it goes farther before it hits the ground doesn't it
even faster hilton even farther
but wait a minute purses curved
so if you keep this up
this thing is coming around the back side of the earth
so yes constructive must be a speed
sufficiently high
so that that cannonball comes right
to the cannon
and all you have to do at that point his tuck
and aquatic animal off or just slide on by and stay in orbit
the fact is the catalyst for a every moment it's there
the difference is it's going sideways so fast
that the amount that it has fallen
is the same amount that the earth's surface has curbed away from it
that does the speed the kitchen port
he figures this out
and that's why the moon is behaving the same way the apple is
the apple just doesn't happen to have sideways motion
brigade someplace other than right below
and when you are in free fall
you are weightless
that's the coolest thing to be we have in our midst
an astronaut
we have time hendrik hertzberg where are you
reject please stand up
official astronaut
on uh... several shuttle missions so you got to get the away it was cool
it's kolkata when he had put that on microphone
it's cool epic i'd
and so he's a free fall around the earth not only is the
shuttle orbiter in free fall everything in the orbiter isn't free fall so
therefore everything is weightless
if you're in an elevator and you cut the elevator cable
uh...
up until the point you hit the bottom of your weightless
you're in free fall
uh... here's an experiment you do
if it were a very cool cheap experiment take a tall glass of water
on the paper cup mixed-race call
one of those at starbucks
culture people to get it but you get a tall
filled with water
punch holes in the side
obviously what is going to leak out
the water at the bottom hole will spew out farther
then the quarter
entire pin pin holes are because the waterways more above it is more pressure
at the bottom
just to spray the word around so the the bottom line is far
and the higher ones are a little less
it's all because of work pressure
the widgets of the water
take a couple water while spilling
dropping
into a sick
does not what you drop it into but this to minimize mess
instinct it leaves your hand
despite works
because it's in free fall
the couple's weightless orders went at the water has no wait
then the war does not know
to exit the whole in the side of the cockpit puncture
so the institute drop that cup
the water caps off
it just stops and the cup false hits the bottom and spills in your sink awhile it
fell is evidence that the war became weightless
the apple is waitlisted ms weightless
that was amazing
on top of that he discovers the laws
of motion
famous equation f equals an egg
you may remember that from highschool physics or not that's an important
equation
the combined ethical zeb it was a crappy gets us to the moon
allows us to team
projectiles and land where we want on mars
you also discovered that then the laws of optics
put like three prison show the white light is composed of colors
he named the colors of the rainbow
worried she business
wat you know what you did
what you did
red orange yellow
was there appear more debates named
with but
active problems some people but to sign-in it was
violent left without the art
indigo indigo so easily i think it will have at this table fascination for
number seven
and so they're really to most people only six colors they're he threw an
indigo
puts it spells were cheaper if you can't you can't give that up
affirmed so if the parties to enter colors coming out of white white
this freak out the artists writers that's not how colours worked in art
within each of the colors put it back together
got white line again
so he can understood
the behavior of light
of these different
uh... fans
so to game of the laws of optics was a gravity laws of motion
and on a dare
practically on a dare
he invented
integral and differential calculus
on a dare
somebody said hike
why do the planets orbit
into shape we call elections
phillips flattened circle
why factsheet
you know i don't know it comes out of my classes but i don't know why statute
in a somewhat
i'll get back to you
so he goes home for a couple of months
comes back years and here's why it statute
well it's actually a cut from a car
ticket conan make cuts in if you get an ellipse a circle of parabola hyperbole
it's best people notice
this guy would know that we've got the prototype good earlier
then the friends i will have to get school how do you think that worried
that the calculus too far to find the answer
most people struggling with the just to learn it in school
he invented
for no other reason but a friend of him
pose a challenge in question
isaac newton
after all of this
and turns twenty six
decided
you read in the back of one of his books called optics
ready discovers als laws of
optics
in the back yes queries
he isn't like spilski i'm at the time to figure out yet
maybe some others will find out
he said i wonder
if the stars in the night sky
or just like the sun
much much farther away
yeah it's like okay xd
he's wondering stuff that became entire branches of study
the crumbs off his plate
are the entire careers of other people
he then later on with the eye
okay suggest these are factors you might want to
consider
jobs and just
artisan disclosure are just want to make sure
you got all the facts
but when i read that in nyc communes through time
and feel connected to the cosmos
and
i don't know if i'd moved you a second time in regarding this
but that's why i feel about icing it and i have a blast of his head
on might
table in my office busted there
buzz actual head started casting
of his head
the other long hair before that was like fashionable for guys you know today
at those curls
newton curls
okay i i took a long time answering that let me get your
your opinion
should i spend a long time answering it if i got a lot of places to go in the
answer
or do you want sound-bite answers to get them off of
even though i'll get a few are of you
your you're cool with that
uh... only flush it out if this flash to give
so another pic
the public to track the microphones who's got the next one
so a couple weeks ago ives anticipated
announced the results of an experiment in which they showed that in big bang
like explosions
matter is produced slightly higher proportion an anti matter
and my question is if the results had been just the opposite is anti matter
were
produced preferentially by a little bit
could anti matter have created the universe that we live in now and if so
would be just like this or would we be living in a bizarre like universe
okay so let's back up a little bit
him
in a world that's actually
uncommon
for what goes on routinely in the universe
if you go to the center of the sun for example recommend this book if if you
went to the center of the sun
and you managed to not get vaporized
you would find that the lights
that is passing your head
it's primarily x_-rays
little bit gamma rays it's mostly x_-rays
at his other like too but it's dominated by x_-rays
x_-rays is just another band of why i think that we didn't know that
he didn't know everything
the whole spectrum rory jeep they have on the other side of the city
we have all survived
invisible to our eyes
we can detect it though
he detected
by oksana
you detected by
your sunburn
it while you detect a little too late suitor time delay there
then you really detective with skin cancer tree so if you want to up beyond
beyond ultraviolet you have
x_-rays
and that we can't detect those either
uh... and then get worse
but you could eventually to techies were again we detect them with cancers and
things it's not
southern effective way to detective
go to the other side of red
we find infrared
can see that either
beyond that we have microwaves
and the radio waves
all of his life dole travels at the speed of light
so if you go into the sun here these
x_-rays
such energy visa photons
this so much energy
energy goes up with
violet ultraviolet rays dennis goes up goes down in the other direction
as so much energy
that you can ask
what happened to plug that energy into the equation equals m_c_ squared
just do that
if that's the energy on the left what comes what hammer what mass
equivalent is that
you know what you find out
it has so much energy he could spontaneously make matter
he can make a pair of electrons on its own
soak in the center of the sun
matter
is being forwards
out of the shoe of energy
every moment of the sun's light
what kind of matter doesn't make it makes
electron and entire which
positron
mattered anti-matter pick anti-matter israel
we need invented it not the science fiction writers
until they take until the end of it
but its power idea
we gotta take we gotta get the get credit when we can
because a science fiction writers can be so good at this
so
when you have a high note energy for the white people spontaneously become matter
and he'd better anti-matter care come back together
it makes the
the x_-rays again is this true
that's unfamiliar to us we don't see that visible light doesn't do that
it's not energetic enough
stays as light
buckets absorb it doesn't become energy doesn't become particles
the early universe
this went on beat
and it's one of the same actually lost a particle physics
that light becomes too particles veteran anti-matter
bring together they become white again
always symmetric
always
we're made of matter
here's the answer that so there's some discussions
that if an alien cayman landed from another galaxy
before you shake it and or whatever appendage it's offering you
flip a coin
if the alien spontaneously
explodes
it's anti-matter food
that's always be ready to have some cults touch their liam
so
anti-matter art perfect counterparts to matter
so something happen in the early universe to create an asymmetry
it's one of the mysteries of the early universe
one out of one
hundred
millions
of these
particle in type article pairs
one out of a hundred million of them
was just a particle enough theater part
hundred million
i mean brackets renner
but it happened enough to account for all the matter that we know when see a
lot in the universe
there's no reason to think that that happened the other way
that we would just be anti-matter talking about matter aliens
flipping them in anti-matter panic
but then they probably wouldn't call themselves anti anything
so kasagic it's one of the great mysteries in the early universe
how it came to be
that there's an asymmetry
induce
very symmetric process that we see all the time
so it's a long answer but you get the full context of that it affects the big
bang as well as what's going on in the center of the sun
info technically because symmetry breaking
more broadly can google wiki
symmetry breaking and they talk about
the laws of physics
that are broken
by some phenomena process in the early universe
of microphone over here
yet to be what writing amalia wearing outfits on the and offices into
off-topic
sorry this is the universe while participating in the copper send this to
them that universe but i don't know why dont universe had a little have
astrophysicist at again
so in light of card events involving
and at the will still in on
and
but something that i read in the by the way yeah
at one twenty three
but it's our oil spill the oil filled and harley disaster and i will we all
had a la carte
we are collectively that is that for conflict
in light of that and something that i read the times on sundays thing that we
know
or about deep space and we do about the deep-sea indeed
would you protests that perhaps the c_ span more time setting
things that we don't know in our wealth
as that pastor faces
can you suggest anything that might be done
that they are not
time
okay so the two questions there
uh... how do we help b_p_ fix the problem
uh... should we study
so we spend more money on earth and space
deal with them into the same question that's awesome that that is to do that
but
uh... i only had one suggestion for p_p_ but we did this a couple days ago
i said
what's all this effort trying to
plugged the hole
it's coming out of the ground ultimately that's what we what they will do anyway
right
put another pipe in phila barge with it
so rats are just treated at because i've
exceeds may be easier dot i've got a little word that they tried that
but that failed
that's gotta be easier
then try to stop
the leak
to put kid you could put up with another
perfect just
okay and i gotta come in here reduces acute right to put pieces of things
together
if i think it would be put in a bar
when you go out later on anyway with polly need it right now alright
so i don't understand why did that wasn't the first thought
one of my concerns about this failure
if it's actually been in a refill
and if u
create a world
absent of engineers
because all the smart people would have become engineers had no grand
plans to
go into his job
the nineteen sixties we're going to the moon
it was a militarily drip driven enterprise it attracted cited engineers
method mathematicians to want to become those fields
when there's a disaster that happens
i don't want people saying all we plug it with golf balls
by what kind of solution is that
like where is the genius that we know the human mind is capable
well i think they all became investment bankers award they're not scientists and
engineers
so the fewer scientists and engineers in your next
the more susceptible you are
to the failure infrastructure could you have people thinking about how to
prevent it in the first place
for example
the day we find the asteroid is coming weather is one coming
if there's time will get to it but okay
but just if there's time i don't know we might
we got sc
the asteroids coming
most people
you know what they'll do the same
rong
stockpile food
you know they'll set okay
that's not all i want sitting next to me
bookmark what i want to be sent
how can we deflects
that's a different brent
that's a brain that sees
a natural disaster as a problem to be solved
not has as a
disaster to run away from
that if you don't have engineered dot was thinking
nobody the sting out of runaway from the problem
that's a problem
in our modern society
getting back to spending money on earth amount of space
that's a common
criticism
of nasa actually
one spending money up
then when we got perfectly good problems down here
and i and i and i think i decided that
but not at all your deck rushton
but is missing some context
some context for example
did you know
global climate change
did not exist as an understood problem on purpose
until we studied
if explicitly about meat
week the community
studied the effects
of the asteroid impact
they took out the dinosaurs sixty five million years ago
all portfolio
of reasons everybody's giving for what killed the dinosaurs
then we find two hundred-mile diameter crater all three of the temp initially
and what is now mexico
dated sixty five million years ago all the dinosaurs
croat
i'm sayin we got an asteroid took out the dinosaurs
you talk about
the ugh but it was colder than if i uh... i got an asteroid
okay so that forced people to ask
well if you were in the two hundred mile diameter
where your we know you're toast
howlett how might you have died on the ortho rounding errors
so you look at the fires that would have been created you look at the earths
crust cast into the atmosphere you notice static locust birth
blocking sunlight from reaching the photosynthetic
of plants
if you take up the pace of the food chain than a wave of extinction
percolate across the tree of life
we learned about this at this this force the climate models
to understand global climate in a way no one ever had the occasion to pick up
before
that's when it was born
not because somebody was looking down dot i got the solution here looking down
i'll figure it out no sometimes you have to look up
you know that planet wide greenhouse effect
was first discovered on venus
venus has really bad greenhouse effect it's nine hundred degrees
fahrenheit on p_b_s_
and i did the math you could
you could cook
you ok over there
so much is planning to visit venus and that you've got a cancelled
the vacation plans
via society to take a sixteen inch pepperoni pizza
point of the windowsill it'll cookin nine seconds
you would paper rise as well so this is a
this is a thought experiment if you could do this
global greenhouse effect
it was understood there before we could bring it over
this is not something i was in the middle of no where
connected to the cosmos
nolls science can claim in understanding of its subject
if it's subject is number
only one
you need multiple objects to compare and contrast
you have to that's how we learn
what is special what is not special what israel
with the phenomena are
and so to say but only spend the money here
best suicide
not only that how much does not so good
isn't that why i thought this experiment
unless people
those that say well it's been these people
okay i have to how much you think this is going to
here's your tax top a lot about your tax dollars how much of a cat
and here we go
come about
that's five minute
itself
tax dollar
asia text of his ten cents twenty cents thirty cent which is nasa getting
it is getting
one-half of one penny
this tax dot
one chu hundred
that's not even going to leave it in the e_p_a_
here during the edge
pays for the brokers
the space station the space shuttle
that
problem telescope all the nasa centers
nasa headquarters
all of that
and i ask you
how much of the universe
works tune
ethics equipped
but from the twitter verse with my twitter twitter verse list
it looks like a question every year
you compare to cluster
month-old
won't
seeking the only for the every twenty request
joking dot replacing had
x week
from matter
what inventor palms
s_l_s like akito leaders coming right there
wet
well mankind's the interplanetary travel
when that sounds like a deeper question that actually is
being when we got a marked this with that is
latina interstellar tribe
interplanetary with that we'd have to we're not going to be nice
there
banco hugo y if you're going to be a comeback pretzels one-way trips
uh...
mars is the only other
sensible planet we could possibly visit
and in the current
nasa budgets
which is actually increased from previous yours
under the obama administration
it has plans to develop
political heavy lift vehicles
heavy lift would enable you to not only reached orbit
as current
once vehicles to go to go beyond the low-earth orbit
like we did back in nineteen seventy two
and those vehicles you be able to scale them in such a way so that they would
get us to mars
are beyond beyond the moon on to mars
if at all goes well
shirley before mid-century
and
one of my concerns however
is the motivation for going into space
if it's not clearly defined it may never happen
in the nineteen sixties we told ourselves we're discovers
where barricades
we explore meanwhile the subtext was where at war with the coming straight
briefed the colonies to space right that's really what that
flow of monies was doing
and so if we want to go to mars
hoan
if there's i don't believe the nation can rally around a simple question
explore
the history of human civilization
does not support that
what does support is the first to get rich
so if i'm like boil on mars will be there at like next week will be cut
rockets will be there
so i'd say by two thousand fifty
another question
i'm going to go where that microphones are
okay
the senator
greater scientist i didn't criticize thank you
runner after beyond belief two thousand six lecture
you said that we know there were did you watch the you know what's the youtube ok
on you said that what stop middle eastern scientific progress was
theological takeover yes do you think that's a shorthand for what i said but
there are if you can't make the case a little more
relatively than actual uh...
but do you think that's happened here in light of what's happening with like
scientific textbooks in texas and things like that
yeah i just read recently about
the plight of textbook textbooks in texas
i spent some time in texas six years actually
and
of course texas has
johnson space center
these are the folks who
everything we put in orbit with humans on a after it passes through it
launch sp him
uh... the watchtower
in cape canaveral
or command goes over to houston so texas does that there's a fundamental part
of our space enterprise
culturally and historically
so that for them to have now have textbooks
where the sites content is altered
to be different from what is going on a mainstream science worries me greatly
what you're referring to
the the talk that i gave it that lectures and san diego two thousand six
uh... it referenced what was going on a thousand years ago
thousand years ago
the
intellectual center of the world
with baghdad
was busy disavowing heretics at the time
baghdad
was open to all box
at the time
between eighty eight hundred and eleven hundred around there
if you look at the advances
that unfolded
in that period in that location
it includes
the
delete the invention of algebra
algebras an arabic word
algorithm is an arabic word
two-thirds of the stars in the night sky that have names have arabic names
how does that happen
what with the navy rights comfort
it came from the fact that at that time
advances
in the middle east in baghdad in particular
um
was
unfolded
in engineering mathematics specially mathematics
astronomy navigation
uh... physiology
didn't you say well why is that so if you look at what was going on through
open to all lines of thought
jews moslems christians
they were doubters back then today we would call the macy's they would all
come around a table
and share ideas if you have some philosophy that's got a hold of some of
the find it
and to get a challenge you on those ideas and what happens is
the conversation ratchets pop
you discard what doesn't work and you keep what does
and when you do that you make discoveries in you make discoveries
rapidly
and at the time
that terry drew to a close if you read history books
typically described sort of the
sacking of baghdad
bedtime for the city
until they all came to an end
however
the islamic culture rolls at other times later
and those other times science an engineering discoveries were not a part
of it
so yes what why not
you got the cultural heritage i didn't show up again
and that you gotta dig a little deeper from the sacking a baghdad and you find
out there was a of muslim cleric
alters always business name
was to islam what saint augustine was to christianity
sinatra seemed kinda laid out the rules for how to be a good christian at the
time to black people were practice in their own way he called a fight
he was that was a scholar figured it out
according to his own read
told everybody how to behave there's the book
you follow this you're good christian augers always had to follow this your
good moslem
in fact text included
the assertion
which james influenced socially but then politically so that it had power of
influence
in there was a assertion that mathematics and the manipulation of
numbers
was the work of the devil
it's hired a prize
collapsed and never recover
it has not recovered sense
if you look at the number of muslims who have won the nobel prize in the sciences
the virtues of won the nobel prize one fourth of all noble prize is in science
have been one budget
how many muslims in the world one point three billion
how many jews in the world fifteen million tops
so you look at what effect
the culture of discovery learning can have on what you discover about the
natural it's extraordinary
so just because you're making discoveries doesn't mean it's forever
and i look at the twentieth century in america
as a period of great
discovery
nicely forces now operating against it and i look at the history for the
consequences of this and i see america just simply fading
into insignificant
no it's not off of the cliff
it's a slow
that every next day or a little bit further down on the slope you barely
notice it right
until one day you can see over the hill that you just came from
and they try to make do with what you have down here then you find out there
to rest of the world making the inventions
and knock you
you're trailing no longer leaving you're not even
abreast with what's going on
your running behind trying to catch up
have a nice day exquisite
we've got a question right here
got a question that's
part of the look how many times you've got in your pockets i smelled peak
believed that he wants to
manly all about six seven eight nine proper
we got a teacher right here the heads of the aircraft up
what's your address that
seventy-year-old question about that before adn part of the basis for
the defense theory
is redshift occurs as the
calcite six sevareid away from us
how do you distinguish b that pressure from that which for the car
from the into your bones at all because they were born first
because
there is this the president
you should be able to calculate
trajectories of all the galaxies
and throwing center what's
cannot do that
excellent questions sup
of the first one yes
for those who have been living under a rock we live in an expanding universe
we know this because we look out to the universe we see galaxies
and in a discovery made by hubble edwin hubble
back in nineteen twenty nine was first published
he noted but for the people behind the media right here
i'd look at you every now and then give i can't
thinking about your thinking about it
but this is really cool to look at
buoyed by the way right there
this is where steven kobe rlic
right right in that spot okay
the so you know
cyclical bear visited the row center
one afternoon worried that
his talk show comedy talk show host job
would be in jeopardy
in one of the before back job as an astrophysicist
so had they train and to be an astrophysicist that afternoon
s_l_ showed him to be right then
he just decided to lick it
i said that's the oldest thing your tongue has ever touched
at five billion years old he said no
i want to jane fonda on my show
it's upto ballads like while read that come from
but then i got up on youtube clip
and jane fonda is on the show and she saw it was around the table sis's lap
dance from texas
was like in his head when that was happening
so but i digress
jane fonda and the big bang in the same center
so we see the galaxies and hobbled notice that you've data provided by
others
and
common sense like for two very
a brilliant
experimental esp
in the astronomical world we call them observers
so they look at the couches you find out
at the spectrum
criticizing newton the spectrum
this features of the spectrum between a tribute to various
chemical elements
carbon has a fingerprint revealed inspection oxygen has a separate
fingerprint
by use the fingerprint almost literally here
that's got itself
every element has its own signature in the spectrum
so if you know what the pattern of lines the features looks like on earth
you look at the galaxy can find that same pattern but it's shifted
he saw how much does interest
that means the galaxy is moving away from us we learned this from chris jon
doppler
the german physicist in the eighteen hundreds
did an experiment with training
and so
what happens
the train whistle goes by
we know this intuitively even if you've never thought that doesn't go
well let's let's do it with a race car because that's what i can make that
sound better
the car
well
right that that i get a writer pretty good
but i get a better than it right
the card does not go
and he is
doesn't do that
doesn't help
but doesn't do any of that
cal
high-pitched solo pitch
so the sound waves up front
every sound wave it makes it now travels closer to that sound wave
before it makes the next wek
so that pitch
so the wavelength this shorter the pictures hotter
and when it receives the sound waves gets stretched apart
you get a lower pitch
so n malad rising what we see in the universe
you could conclude again you can conclude
the galaxies that show the shift to longer wavelengths of light
are moving away from stay indeed work even smell test
that if you were twice as far away
the object moving twice as fast
and he looked in every direction and found
with some kind of case of cosmic beall or something called the galaxies
work scattering away from us
all except for a couple
that are really nearby like the andromeda galaxy
which we will collide with
in a few billion years more on that later
if you're interested get the media right before that 'cause that'll be more
important so
it's later turns out
feinstein
shows us that this redshift is not specifically
accomplish if it's a car
we call a cosmological redshift
it shifts because
space itself is expanding
as all the way it as it moves through space
gets stretched
in the expansion the fabric of space and time itself
and so everybody's move in a while
turn the clock back
you can ask the question when was it all in the same place
at the same time
that was fourteen billion years ago
that's how we dig the big bang
look around turn the clock back and which way is everybody got back to the
same spot
it looks like we're at the center
but the signature of this expansion would be revealed no matter where you
are
if you go to this other galaxy over here
this expanding fabric of the universe will look like i said about this galaxy
as well
so everybody was at the center forty billion years ago
discussing center somewhere else
we all occupied it in a different state
at the same time
at the same place
fourteen billion years ago
to answer both questions
well agent yet so how do you know this ship is not because the things getting
old because if you're getting older
you might have some red stars in there
it doesn't actually shift the lines
you can change the color but without shifting
that the pattern of lives that's why we look at the
fingerprints here there are there
and you know it's not something else going on
let's get another twitter verse question you got one
anoop now you can start with our man will know you're just messing with me
but you're a good omg
abs
carelessly
okay
actor tyson
and this is a tweet from the are awesome
or a career
what percentage of outer espy's estimated to have in a deserved
and what is estimated that can be it served
potato parts of the universe data blocked from our view
because
we live
pancake
so implementing we are blueberry in a pancake
now most blueberries are slightly wider than the width of your pink most
so they've sort of punch out above and below
our galaxy is like the pancake
we are like the blueberry
if you want to see the rest of the universe
you have to look above and below the pancake
because i was the pancake itself is in the way
so all the data we have on this universe
comes to us
from looking above
our flattened milky way galaxy and bowls
all the data we have on cosmology
and so
in the known universe in fact
there is a part where we sexually showing you can only universe
it means where there isn't another universe you get to see the unknown
universe is the absence
of the known universe
and so i will moderate and i'll show you
the cut through the sky where we don't yet have deep data
on the universe because woodstock
inside of attendance disk
of clouds of gas and dust
that prevents you from outside so here we are rising from the d'amato you guys
can see
sobbed i'll describe it for you
weeks we are now overheating above the earth or fiza
we don't get to see how thin respect this year it is
the first
were schoolroom glowed
shrunk to that size that hurts atmosphere
would be the thickness
of the lacquer on that schoolroom glow
yet we think of it as this huge motion appear but it is in fact not
and if earth were school globe
the moon would be thirty feet away
mars would be a mile away
the space station the space shuttle
will be forty three x of an inch above its surface
nasa tells us that that's going into space
boldly going out where hundreds have gone before looked at it
so we're still sending from earth
it's a slow ascent actually be awhile before we get released a minute or two
before we get to the edge of the known universe there so there are section so i
would say we have mapped
to the edge of the universe
uh... we've looked
in
artsy eighty percent
of the universe were not given the reason to think
that if we could look
in those blocks zones that would be fundamentally different from the other
eighty percent
so nobody's really worried
that they're like gremlins on the other side of this
this this this song
and by the way that for a while that was known as the zone of avoidance
because we know it we did see the catholic season that band
it's not that the galaxies were boarding up is that they were simply not visible
to us
you can see the clouds the cloudy band that is the milky way
they'll give way is not visible from new york city
but it is up there
it's plus a feasible from the hayden skier above us
if you come to one of our celestial highlights evenings
to get to see the night sky
and so there's a galaxy in view
we're about to sab still describe the play-by-play
you guys were behind the screen
and whistles zooming out officially the constellations will distort
people think also which is a real things with reopens just
this pattern that you happen to see from earth
and restore expanded that here we go
we that
that's the radio bubble that into that bubble has like howdy doody radio show
on it
and so
there's our galaxy the milky way
and so now you'll see data now you'll see these empty spots in the data
just watch as the nearby galaxies come into view
you'll see these
uh... almost
chance
here we come
now
take a look at these two slots
above and below
looks like a butterfly diagram those two slots
stifle lines unavailable to us because our own fricking galaxies in the way
so i give it about eighty percent of
of the universe
other questions who's got the most manly time for a few more questions like this
ok this one's from behind the meteor
behind the media right but you know if you have your voice this priced dies in
this for you personal in the person where what point in your life was it
that you became like this is what i want to do
it was the grown up with a
very
afoot family and they were like okay let's check out you know astrophysicist
was very big part of my life growing up you get to a point like carl sagan was
seen that's me almost a god is a younger guy they going up like you you've
brought back like the passion note that's in there
this kind of something that's been lost very noel was almost two decades at what
point near life or was it like this is it this is what i want to be a man
you've brought back a lot of the passion to it that's kind of been missing for a
very long time well thank you
say that the passion
uh... mp
high almost can't control
disputes that
but the universe is stuff
when was that i was
nineteen years old
where was i do
in the dome of the hayden planetarium
haha
how did i get there
my parents took me my brother my sister on another weekend trip so the cultural
offerings
of the city
it was it wasn't here it would have been at the art museum warranty
the place
is even operas and weird stuff that you're ten years old it's kinda weird
but we got that exposure
and there i am
i'm in the sky and the delam i'm looking up that lights did the stars come out di
grew up with the broths
and in the bronx we say
we got brought to the house apparently
liberty st dot roxbury so
their the stars come out
and i say let's charming you know
but so that's an interesting hoax
aren't that many stars in the night sky i've seen all eight of them from the
bronx i know by there's a lot
i'll go along with it anyway sister humor them
and i'm mayor and then that voice comes over the you know
the planet envoy says the next
thing to god you'll ever hear is the planetary directors voice
coming out of the sky alright
and we know
mckinney's descendants of you know it's like howard's or your vet
and at that point
it's as though
i had no choice in the matter and the universe called me
and from then on our end of the something really cool about the universe
which takes three years
so i was eleven to know that it could be a career
at nine oh two humming to make money but i think i think in that
eleven i knew enough
that it was time to direct my life in such a way for to become a career
fence for exciting extra classes
here at the hayden planetarium i still have
certificates
of graduating from those classes signed by the director
at that time
when i became direct
ice or
that i would try
to have the influence on others that the educators and scientist
back then
had on me and
until just recently and so we shifted our programmatic
offerings
ice-t's
in those certificates of those who graduated from the courses
just as the director had signed my certificate
i sign up with my pocket full of hands right
so that's how and that's why
and as carl sagan said when you're in love
the you got to tell the world
that's not a heart blood
to catch
pretty easy to catch
and one of those caught at that uh... it they're off
they're doing it
and effect without a kid i thought i could i would be a national physicist
because everyone will want to be there
but they do this they don't want to be etc
the beetle jobs that i had that fight crazy thought
that i found out know most people actually don't care
no maybe package change
the state of the war question on the basis for what so quickly
the lady who wants to go to phoenix yes
funny
pilot hobbs we don't want to talk about kolkata pepperoni pizza
monsters among the twenty nine started
uh... here's my question for the future of nasa it's it they concern for those
of us to believe in the president's never planet and
the world in which we live
can you elaborate on what the status is with that and then can you talk about
that last right that's your president after i put folk at self
bobby nasa it right now there's a political battle going on in congress
regarding what happens over the next several years with nasa
the obama plan
as it was
put forrest
would shifts
emphasis from the kind of launch vehicles
that serve the shuttle
to the kind of what's vehicles that we serve a trip
tomorrow's bypassing the moon
meanwhile there people there's a huge industry built up
that serves the shuttle
meanwhile there's a whole community people who want to go back to the moon
uh... i would even count myself among those
my next trip out of low-earth orbit
i wanted to be a four year journey i like that i will remind myself how to do
this animal is three days away
into that in a new cycle right you can get them back
jected reasons you know kick the tires make sure everything's working
but i don't you'll be in the middle of that today
i actually celebrate
because i try to be stratospheric here eyebrow to celebrate the fact
that we have the luxury to argue
over what nasa's next destination would be
rather than worry about neces budget at all so i think it's it's actually happy
time that we're having these debates
debates in congress
antelope putting the alarm strong against the next generation
entrepreneurs disorders there's some shocking going on
i'm not i'm not idon't
get in the middle of those fights
that's the concern is if we
break are
presence in
on their presence in space
for five years
maybe it'll never come back at all
that's always a risk you cut the budget in the government as some sp something
else happens all the priority comes up it's easy to never bring it back again
you know the pyramids in egypt
they stopped building pyramids a lot of the renata farrow's to build terrorist
who are they ran out of my
that one day they stopped
guild appeared at the top of the tallest pyramid
do you know what year
we'd build something caller then that in it
after that pyramid was built
anybody now
it was in the pass expo
the eiffel tower
was the first object we ever built
as a species
taller
then the pyramids
so just because you're doing something of one particular
doesn't mean it will continue for ever
effect one of the migrate fears is that univ taking it for granted because it
surrounds you all the time
it forget what investment a previous generation may fit
his cults
but you don't realize that you coasting downhill
and you end up what like i said no longer be able to see
above where you need
so
uptick there's some people worried about that gap
i'm a little more confident i know people working within the obama
administration
and
and i've met him
east seem sincere to me
uh... steven factoring in the car is worth
subtracting that out but that would be no matter what he tells you you know
it's this charisma they're such type i got a filter for that right
the filter that is it still real and i got the sense that it still real but
we'll see
we've got to see how that goes
your next question was or the asteroid
are you worried about the asteroid
stall liam
the apple there's an asteroid headed our way
about i want you to describing this ad who we have not seen that youtube it
so this fucking versions of the aisle my utube version of okay
december two thousand four
effect i may have to end on this question present
other flesh it out in ways that there's no way another question can follow
december two thousand four
we discover
we again next month my community a man out there
occasionally out there but most the time i see week
it's not me it's just we the astrophysicist
december two thousand four
we discover an asteroid
we have a couple of data points on its position in the sky
you look at its speed to get a doppler shift on it
you get its direction you plug it into the computer
there was at some twenty percent chance it was that if it works
on april thirteenth twenty thirty six
did you hear about this asteroid when it
was discovered no because that same week
was the indonesian tsunami
that same week
and so rightfully so it did not believe the headlines the way the tsunami did
however if you did the calculation you would show
if it hit the earth in the center of the uncertainty range
he would hit the pacific ocean
five hundred miles forty five a co-authors
west of santa monica
would plunge
g into the ocean
to a depth of three months
it would explode at that depth
cavite eighteen the ocean
in a whole three miles wide
now you have a wall of war
three miles high
what happens to that wall of water
expert just bills back into the hall that was just made
splashes into itself rises high again
the fullest that's first impact crater tsunami
this five stories told by the way
this asteroids the size of the rose bowl
in other words the it would fit neatly
in the rose bowl the way in taking does intake cup
is the first place
the first wave is just from the first impact
decapitate the ocean it fills up again
rises high into the stratosphere forced back
cava takes the ocean again
now it's water capitated notion not the asteroid that sends another way
at this repeats
calculation show this will be about forty times
forty time sc
forty tsunami that one right after another
what's interesting to me
is that that somalis
would take up the entire west coast of united states
potentially in dollars in damage
it would make the indonesian tsunami look like a slightly over flooding pablo
so it was a lost opportunity to compare and contrast magnitudes of disaster
it would later makes the news with better data became available
but let me explain this salon it to you
so it's a father to wall of water five stories tall
the next somani forty seconds later good to be pollster very forty to fifty
seconds
the next monday needs that work
is not a deliberate supply of water
the first wave is got some of the water but the second somali wants to use
so what happens the friction on egos in only as far
because forty seconds into it
they default with what twenty seconds it away
twenty-second back
for the next summer
so in fact if you do the calculation you can show
the tsunami would not go past about a quarter mile inland
the set up a rope
you know like one of those club ropes
anticipated watch the whole thing happened
the waves come in
passed through the mud million-dollar multi-million-dollar malibu homes
the way it comes out bring almost
next wave comes takes the holding back
in a slightly different shape that it was before
this process basically of the lates
the entire west coast of united states
we would know this in advance
thanks to isaac newton and his two equations
he developed as any
twenty six-year-old urgent
and so
so actually nobody has to dark
they'll still do the ten trillion dollars in damage but nobody we
we notice in advance
but i thought about it there to people who will die
two people
and you know there
use the idiots surfer who wants to get that last way
you know
radnor barbara you know
the the excerpt we've got one dead surfer
one dead weatherman
you know the weathermen try to get the camera closer to the allocate
you look at the white
it's crashing on the golf get out of the chemically is back it up in the polls
event
wondered whether
two dead people right that's what you get
so a little later we would learn we get better data
once you discover an asteroid
and you know it's trajectory
you could look in historical photos
for where it would have been in the past if you've got your trajectory
if that becomes useful data team it's called a pre discovery photo
it's comin' in my field
once you have a general direction that something's going and you just turn the
clock back
one suite
pre rediscovery photos
that's a better data later
we'll be able to to
what was going to happen
so here's what will happen
april thirteenth in the year twenty twenty-nine
that's one orbit away from the twenty thirty six date
it has a seven-year intersection orbit with her on that day people thirteenths
which by the way
friday un so
april thirteenth
twenty twenty-nine
this asteroid named pop artists
maine for the trip shin guard of death and darkness
named of course only after we calculated extra jaxtr
to intersect art
if there were not going to hit earth we couldn't name date like bambi or
something non-threatening right
freddie you know something that no it's not hurting anybody
name that one up office
so
we know for sir
that apocalypse
on friday the thirteenth people twenty twenty-nine
x the size of the rose bowl it'll get close enough to earth
that will tip
hilo earth's communication satellites would be the biggest closest thing
advert to come
known to come nearer
the communications satellite sergio synchronous orbit about twenty three
thousand miles up
this will come in at eighteen thousand miles
it'll be visible from northern europe
the the the says already went to the hotel rooms they are so you're not
you're out of block
because they did the math and i knew when when and where it's going to happen
uh... it'll look like a very to success moving bright object across the night
sky
moving at about what speed do i give it all around ten miles per second
this best paul that that's fast
so
here's the catch
it's borge remains sufficiently uncertain
buddy back up
in the possible range of war but it could have
on that fateful day
there is a dc interval range
where if it's rank that whole called akeel
it's a six hundred mile about six hundred mark several hundred mile
range
diverse work goes through that range
earth's gravity will be just flat
or rather
she was wrong
so that
it will alter its orbit so that it will hit us seven years later
so the test is isn't going to go through the keyhole
the latest estimates or that the likelihood
with updated data
at the likelihood that it'll go through the keyhole is several in a million
much better for us then the
thirty percent first estimate or the one in forty two thousand estimate
that have been around for a couple of years
jason all i'm not a problem
their people think that problem watery
with work spots then that expecting that they're going to win
would you put ten trillion dollars
in harm's way
actually if any any insurance people here are no that's gotta be
you just do the math right ten trillion dollars divided by the
the the probability of a fitting
spread out among the total population of the west coast
and you have an insurance policy
that's how that works
right that's how you calculate insurance policy
well by the way
i think i saw steve so eager my colleague
asleep so do we tell our berated
on all the exhibits here in the row center ten years ago
and our anniversary
steve could you remind me who of the famous astronomers of the past
actually invented actuarial tables
all right sir edmund halley
invented the acting notion that you can calculate the risk
using actuarial tables
that astronomer
so it's good to have people who think about the universe where we want to look
at her
which you go
with my performance
she leave
but useful here
obviously cannot over here on it
not only want to look at our
people look up might also advanced stuff just want you to know
cell
the problem is if we
so we don't know the orbit well enough to say whether that's going to go
through the keyhole
we need better data on its location in space
so what we really want to do
and in fact one of the plans of mass is next for ages
is to visit an asteroid
why not visit the ash with it has our name on it
who was headed this way
just call bruce willis you know that's all you have to call you
put him on your speed dot save brooks
we did was lost for the world week in the bottom of a thing right now dead
week seven into space
is immoral rick driller
if you remember from
armageddon
about that
movie was made with the whole of the universe of laws of physics just so you
know
not from this universe
that's why don't really into made that movie
was where was i before distracted myself
opposite so here's what you do
you go to the asteroid
then you stick low-tech bonnet ok something
where it is telling us
where it is
to like one centimeter per second accuracy
and it's velocity and its location with that accuracy
he put it back into the equation sharpen the orbit you reduce the uncertainty
it you'll know when it'll go through the keyboard act
if it goes if it's target to go through the keyhole
all you have to do
if you're like
military generals would know you've got like nukes in the silo
it was sort of out of the scott cook week we got those folks we know who they
are
the people wanna blow stuff up problem here in america
is that we've really good at blowin stuff up
endless good it no one with the pieces go afterwards
which is let's call it that alright
so article about a blow-up office that we have two pieces one headed for new
york one headed for l_a_
i don't want to pieces
good we all know what'll happen when you blow it up
so dot the kinder gentler solution would be to nudge it
out of harm's way
only have to do
is not shit
so that it misses
the keyhole
that's only a six hundred mile three hundred mile knowledge
one way or another
and if you get a pearly enough
you've given us i'd ways motion i'm headed towards you
give me a sideways motion
a few centimetres per second
that accumulates
so that after a tough time and i miss you completely
and this case you just have to miss
the keyhole
twenty twenty-nine that's the right amount of time in the future
most of us will still be alive we hope
and that's what we cannot just budgets to make this happen so we have two new
isn't gauged
international space agencies to do this
dharma hadn't with there is no organization
to do this
and who's going to pay for it
we would certainly pay for that
but suppose it was headed for the set the indian ocean
does effect america
would in fact us
so what kind of earth insurance policy does the world's takeout
how do you worked at
and we have an apologize astronaut
rusty schweitzer
with a web page called
b six twelve
dedicated to studying
not only the says x of asteroid collisions but the politics
of how to alleviate
p six twelve with i've seen that before
he six twelve
that is the name of the asteroid
at the little prince linda
haulers in that the cutest thing you've ever and her
so that's be six twelve so people are thinking about it and even some
influential people
we don't mobilize in time
because we have too many
lawyers among us and not engineers
but we can always
get on the case of lawyers reikers
i'm not alone amit lawyers arbitrator here
owes a lot he has a lot
but everybody makes fun of lawyers right
effect mike favored lawyer joke was told to me by a lawyer
that tell you what that was
it's the ninety-eight percent of all are thick at the other two percent a bad
name
i thought that was pretty fun
lawyer told me that you know
but
a pretty good at srebrenica
so here's what happens if you recall mobilizing time
and it does thread the people
we still have another seven years the problem is it's headed straight
earlist now
now when you have to deflect it
you've got a deflected by two thousand four thousand miles
but first brady steps up much harder job
the deflecting it three hundred miles past of the people
so
i suggest that massive go ahead and do this just as an exercise
even though it's only several in a million chance of it in
i want to know
that we have the power to deflect asteroids so that we do not suffer the
same state
as our reptilian ancestor sixty five million years ago
who did not have
engineers among them so that as they're standing there
dining on power metal ancestors
for export there
earners
i'm reminded of the gary larson comic t_ rex is talking to
some other t_-rex and they just sit there just chillin
and one says
now with the time to build an asteroid defense experts
because i don't want to be the laughing stock of the galaxy
where others know that we were smart enough to have a space program
but too dumb to put it into effect anti save us
uh... extinction
so thank you all for coming this evening
i have one encore if i'm a tech hold an encore
i have it by ever fought
that i find completely disturbing that i just want you all to have said that you
will lose sleep tonight just as i do
are you reading this be marked
are parting thoughts together okay
humans tend to be
unjustifiably hubris stick
about who would what we are in the animal kingdom in in the world
just one example
we have these books that have
optical illusions and who doesn't love a good article
we all love articles
is simply the better
why do we call it optical illusions when it really should be called
a book of brain failures
because that's what it is
electronics is a diagram i cant figures praying failure
we don't call it that but that's what it is
okay we think very highly of ourselves
we call ourselves intelligent
by what measure
well so weak list things that we do that no other animals can do
so we still we have poetry and philosophy
web hubbell telescope ridley compose something
where intelligent
that is our measure alright
well i'd studied this briefly
and yes well what is the next closest species to human beings
basically the chip
and how much d_n_a_ do we have incomes like ninety eight percent
identical d_n_a_
but we are prone to say opera water difference that two percent
all that you can do baby can stack boxes of each of the mana
maybe
maybe you can combine a few hand signals
made the
but look what we
so we are convinced
that whatever is in that two percent is significant
but i want to pose to you disturbing fault
maybe the difference
in our cognitive capacities
the current between hudson shipped we and chips baby that difference
is as small as that two percent suggests
maybe
the hubble telescope in our greatest of operas and use it can poetry
is not much different from stacking boxes in reaching a banana
is eight tyson how could you send what you could meet what just block
that's hubris
because of magic
in whatever it is this
cognitive scale
what what what woman the smartest chimps
the private authors rolling forward
and they're doing what our problems do is not right a promise to stack boxes a
promise to put up a number of a toddler is can make sign language
that's left almost
but those are smart chips studied by the primate experts imagine
a species
two-percent beyond us
in the same scale
in which we are two percent be on the trip
how smart with baby to us
all that's just think about that
different
smart compared to us as we are
to chance
that to them bill do you know difference between stacking boxes
and the hubble space telescope
because they be capable of mental feeds far beyond anything we could possibly
conceit
day there
humid telecasts
would steven stephen hawking forward
it's safe
this was slightly smarter than the rest
'cause he can do
astrophysics calculations initiative light little junior over here does
our greatest works of art
and literature ensign its
their toddlers
would it create it could be a kindergarten and would be on the
refrigerator with magnets
almost junior just drive all the quantum mechanics isn't that cute
dead on the reserve door
politician twenty of some not all that is so view
we call ourselves mark
you don't know if you're smarter not to have another species
blow you out of the water
at one of about six weeks
this evening
because it's a disturbs me i gotta get off my chest
there's a worm in the street
you walked by it
does the worm note that you think you're smart
the world has no concept of your smarts
could hurt that much smarter than the work
so a worm has no idea of the celtics martyrs walking by
which makes me wonder what do we have any concept
it was super species
walk bypass
maybe their own interested in us
because we're too stupid for them to even imagine having a conversation
you know what i want to chat with the worst thinking that make
usage is not of plot that you have
so one of the best pieces of evidence
for why we haven't been visited
by aliens
is that they have actually
observed us
and concluded there is no sign of intelligent life on earth fake you off
it