https://youtu.be/Ts_To4zmEdE
the parents after
they requested
her to do so and i might add free of charge in your richard is anyone to do
that
on this and he said the on the world trade center case though that it was
before those people have been named we did a google search did that that the
guy's name is all over
nexus all over and the newspapers multiples times
i don't know about the exact date of that but i do know when soviet put forth
a prediction when it was publicized might be a different matter
but which she put forth a prediction that name was not now well in the f_b_i_
uh... the video which you sent us which is her f_b_i_a_
testimony
according to you guys that was at least some two weeks after this guy in oregon
reston after his name was aria
and the shunned really the case they were already searching
in the park is not correct
on they were searching in the park during the time but not
alan
not during a time when she talked to the family income where they were
only when they did the interview and sharon james do you feel she is so
successful and i talked with c_s_ sherin james
myself personally she testified to the fact that during the time when she got
the notice that she received from
uh... tennessee
that she felt that that was a delegation from the standpoint that he was in las
vegas and had never in fact in tennessee and she felt he must have had some type
of insurance connection in tennessee
the point being
he was found allied in well granted it was after the time it'll be a thought
that you would
but nonetheless that he was found alive and well so they were centers and wait a
minute i would like to adhere first and foremost
that sylvia's this a_c_ teachers spiritual teacher and humanitarian
the actual first and foremost on our web sites a psychic
first and foremost uses spiritual teacher appear that sex is siding on my
part of that
this this psychic part of it is a part of that i could not initiate work in
this world so ensure accurate on her website when you go go over
and i just went to a website is so they're brown psychic and spiritual
teacher
exactly for so far though she's a psych
well first she has
did you can't separate the psychic part from her spirituality but destination
money from being a psychic
she supports a religious organization and her corporation for being a psychic
yes that's a fact alone which is returned back to her spirit organization
ever corporation sylvie gets no money all firmer psychic readings personally i
want to bring james randi james you've actually call soderberg fill-in we spoke
to said to understand who's a retired senior special agents charge the f_b_i_
los angeles he's worked with sylvia
he says says he's worked with her quite a bit and he says this about a racist
code i work with numerous psychics in the past
and very few are really on target the sylvia brown is probably one of the most
accurate psychics
in the country and that's from a former senior f_b_i_ official are you saying
he's wrong
i think that brad she doesn't know enough about his subject i'm not talking
about law enforcement now
not talking about detect your work
but he has to judge these things much more carefully i would think addison
he has to not at the total
redeemed everything that she says about anyone fact
and evaluate that
what you've done here and what has been done here i should say
is that
cases that were successful are apparently successful
have been selected another very much like the the racetrack a
devoted who go live now to see if i could finishes foreigners
decision for executive
the point is that the fellow at the racetrack keeps on very proud to tell
you about the number of horses idid bet on that have come right up front and
that made money in such but he's in tatters because he doesn't win in the
long run politically let ladies out forget about the way you want to get
your point windowsill be maintains a she's not a hundred percent accurate as
she never claims to be add a little girl when she told trong hoang bricks frantic
parrots and he was dead and where to find his body she sounded pretty certain
she didn't say
i think he's dead but i could be wrong she said he's no longer with us and
here's where his body is because ait we still don't have the bottom of this case
we don't know if you don't you think you may be dead
no night john hardback but we need to be you know if she could have seen another
person that was
that was all i wanted to say i can maybe it's another person she said he's dead
and here's where i a m your stand that this is what she said that
she is also claimed she is not a hundred percent
she is a vessel by which her the energy conservator information concerning she's
just merely a vessel from god
you can't separate the two
and four
randy as a professed eight eunice to judge anyone on spirituality is jsuazoc
okie has now negated now when he is all mickey everything she does is through
guide with guide she gives got credit for everyday grannies are professed
eight years who claims that anyone who believes any religion
is weak minded and superstitious he's begin christianity he's making why is a
great at behave better that's like a high school debating tactic to attack
the guy has asked the question i think i think it's an example right but wait a
minute
anderson you cannot separate the psychic ability from the spirituality waiting
but without looking at a later could buy up to me asking questions of my god list
too
all of course not okay but so you know black and white why are you doing is
you're doing a fair-minded reporting what he's doing is he's judging
and as a magician
he doesn't have the credentials to judge anyone up here and i think ability
amazed i ought to take a short break and i wanted to discussion
again appreciable to be on the program director
or computer discussion sylvia brown joining us on the browns business
manager linda ross seems like it a bunker james randi ugly no i want to ask
you something 'cause earlier sean hundreds parents had stated that bound
on the montel williams show after they were told a sean was dead
they want to speak to sylvia more outside of the primers and show we're
told that they'd have to pay her rate of seven hundred dollars for half hour is a
trend high rule
a stand with my life
agnes
that that is not true now somebody might have told her that that was a connected
with our office that i can attest to but silly has never ever
charged
any individual who is coming with a missing person case or law enforcement
of tea
that i want to be clear they didn't say based more unclear who told them that so
exactly strengthens our mail
it could've been somebody from the show who didn't know anything but
our staff thus the shortest turned that any member of our staff is being with
some of the year
it's been twenty years i myself have been there thirty five
i had never ever and i seen people from all walks of life religious whatever but
she does a senate also for a half-hour it
she does make seven hundred out she doesn't make seven hundred dollars
the seven hundred dollars that you charge is
unsolicited
she never asks for anyone to do that dealing with
at the same with our religious police or every if the people come to us
seeking our help took what i really want to question james rainy before we go
into him
for now anything bordering on a malicious persecution sylvia why doesn't
he go after
and charlotte has a true sharply at times there but i wouldn't let out so we
could what's so bad about soderberg
there's nothing you
intrinsically bad about sylvia brown that is a bad about all of the people
who pretended
to the greeting people out there who need them or believe they need them
that they can speak to the dead
no i don't know if you're still going to be clear great figure windshield buying
hide the laughter sylvia brown because she is a major figure in the field and
she gets a lot of publicity a lot of exposures on shoals all over the world
she is one of the major figures that i go after yesterday's your chance of a
proud to take a test of her psychic ability
what do you know exactly that test be very quickly
very quickly well she would dil readings for ten people
ten people live with the chosen
because they believe sylvia brown and that they believe she has powers and
they believe in psychic powers of that chart she would do send readings we
would them shuffle those ten readings and give them all up to the people who
had the readings done for them an awsome to sort them out which one is your
reading it should be pretty evidence that you could take the reading it was
made for you window you could without ever take that test
absolutely not because she has nothing to lucky all right we have to do it
wait a minute recently hill shutting them shouting which has become ok first
of all she has nothing to prove to randy
do you want somebody who's an a_p_ is is already coming up but i felt a lot of
indians thing all right below your desolate habitat
line or give cochran cable news that we just don't like on the show settling
that you're saying so they would not take the test but now because she has
nothing to prove to james randi
occasion epping to prove to james randi per square inch of work
speaks for itself lolololol only return false hopes that the audience years
alone on that randy i appreciate you being on the program linda
as well thank you very much and sorry when he was the
you can decide for cells before you get a br