[Blake McKimmie] Welcome to the PSYC1030 X-Series of courses.
This series includes Introduction to Social Psychology, Developmental Psychology, Clinical Psychology,
and Psychological Research Methods.
You will learn why we think and behave the way we do, how we develop throughout our lives,
about some common psychological illnesses and treatments, and how we conduct and report
psychological research.
Hi, I’m Blake McKimmie.
You will be hearing from me throughout the series, as well as from a number of my colleagues
here at the School of Psychology at The University of Queensland.
Together, these four courses are PSYC1030, an introductory psychology course, taught here
on campus.
Each year about 2,500 students take this course, and now you can join them.
You can take each course on its own, or together as a whole series.
For each topic in these courses, you will watch a series of course videos, do some activities,
and also complete some quizzes.
There is a quiz before you watch any videos, and one at the end.
Don’t worry, we will only be grading you on this second one.
Research shows that repeated testing is one of the best ways to enhance your learning.
To make sure you do your best, it’s a good idea to do the topics in order, especially
because we will be quizzing you on the previous topics as we go through.
And don’t forget to take a look at the list of extra resources at the end of each topic.
We’ve got quite a bit to cover, so it’s important that you spread your learning out
over a few weeks for each of these four courses to give yourself the best chance possible.
By better understanding ourselves and others, we hope that we are in a better position to
create change in our lives and the world.
And world peace.