Next I will describe some commonly used words that we should be deleting in our writing.
Number one: some people call it the “OF THE” issue.
For example, the sentence “The leader OF THE research team”, can be simplified to
“The research team leader”.
Another example, “One OF THE researchers at the university”, can be simplified to
“A researcher at the university”.
So, avoid writing “of the” when constructing a sentence is a good way to simplify its structure.
Number two: the “OTHERS” issue.
For example, in this sentence “These findings are consistent with a study conducted in 2011,
but inconsistent with two OTHERS conducted earlier.”, the word “others” is not
needed, because we know that two studies were conducted earlier.
Rewriting the same sentence as “These findings are consistent with a study conducted in 2011,
but inconsistent with two conducted earlier”, does not change the meaning of it, but it
sounds so much better.
Number three: the “BOTH” issue.
Let’s look at this sentence.
“Both Smith 1991 and Jones 1996 concluded that there was support for this theory”.
Here, the word “both” is not needed.
Rewriting the same sentence as “Smith 1991 and Jones 1996 concluded that there was support
for this theory” doesn’t change the meaning of it, but it shortens the sentence––making
it more concise and clear.
Number four: “THAT” issue
Writing “That” in a sentence often slows down the pace, so we can sometimes leave it
out.
For example, the sentence “Jones 1996 argued that his findings supported the first theory”
can be written as Slide “Jones 1996 argued his findings supported the first theory”
without changing the meaning of the sentence.
However, the sentence becomes shorter and more to the point.
So, the words “OF THE”, “OTHERS”, “BOTH”, and “THAT” are the commonly
used words that we should avoid using in our writing.