STOP (FILE NÀY TRÙNG VỚI FILE 4.2B BÊN SOCIALPSY)
two lists of traits.
Now, when we look at the generosity ratings, you should notice something curious.
Most people who saw the first list tended to think that Mike was not very generous.
Those who saw the second list, generally thought that Mike was generous this is what Asch (1946)
found when he presented the same lists to research participants.
So, what’s going on?
Well if you take a close look at the two lists of traits, you will see that there is only
one difference between them.
In the first list, Mike is described as being cold, while in the second list he is described
as being warm.
Surely if we are forming our impressions algebraically, the two lists should have produce pretty similar
impressions - they only differ by one word after all.
However, that is not what happened.
The reason why warm and cold make such a difference, is because according to Asch, they are central
traits.
This means that they give meaning to the other traits that are presented - these other traits
are the peripheral traits.
So someone who is described as being warm, intelligent, determined and industrious sounds
like a pretty good person - you probably want them helping you with your assignment or working
in your team at work.
Someone described as being cold, intelligent, determined and industrious sounds a bit scarier
- more like a serial killer.
They probably have a coiled rope, shovel, and some plastic sheeting in the back of their
car &quot;just in case&quot; the opportunity arises.
Now, you might be thinking that the warm/cold pairing produces the different impressions
because &quot;warm&quot; is a positive word and &quot;cold&quot; is a negative word.
Asch thought about that too.
He also showed his participants another pair of positive and negative words.
Namely &quot;polite&quot; and &quot;blunt&quot;.
As you can see from Asch’s results, there was a systematic difference in the impressions
when people were shown warm versus cold – the person was seen as being more generous, wiser,
happier and better natured.
For those shown polite versus blunt, there was no such systematically more positive impression.
There were no differences in how generous the person was seen as, and the person was
actually seen as wiser when “blunt” was presented - so if you want to appear smart,
just be a bit rude perhaps?
Polite people were seen as being better natured though.
So Asch thought that this meant to impressions were not formed algebraically, but rather
that an impression is based on an emergent pattern that depends on the total context
of the information that you have access to.