- We are learning virtually all of the time.
From the moment we are born, throughout our lives,
and even in our sleep.
If we watch a baby or a toddler interact with the world
around them, we see them constantly trying to make meaning
of sensory patterns in their environment,
consciously or unconsciously asking how and why.
What do we mean by learning?
While there are many definitions of learning,
Robert Sternberg, a cognitive scientist,
provides one that is clear and concise.
He says, &quot;Learning is any relatively permanent change
&quot;in the behavior, thoughts, or feelings of an organism
&quot;that results from experience.&quot;
Notice Sternberg mentions not only that learning
is reflected in visible behaviors and actions,
but learning is also reflected through changes
in interior thoughts and feelings that are indiscernible
by the outside observer.
And this is one of the biggest challenges of teaching,
trying to figure out what our students have learned
so we can respond accordingly.
Learning takes on many forms and occurs in many settings.
For instance, one form of learning called implicit learning
develops without our necessarily being aware
of its happening.
Examples would be first language acquisition,
and learning social norms a cues.
Much of what we learn in school, however,
is explicit learning.
In order for explicit learning to happen,
we have to consciously attend to learning
and make memories for later recall.
Learning develops in different contexts or settings.
In fact, learning often happens in informal situations:
on the playground, at home, in museums, and often with peers
during various forms of recreation and related activities.
Learning, of course, also occurs more formally.
Formal learning occurs in structured educational settings
like schools and colleges.
Our focus in this course mostly will be on explicit
and formal learning in schools.
Explicit formal learning is not always easy
for children to do, since they are most naturally inclined
to learn implicitly in informal settings.
Learning to read or write or think about abstract concepts
like metaphors, multiplication, Newton&#39;s Laws,
or dangling participles, is not usually intrinsically
motivating to most kids.
That is, kids don&#39;t usually gravitate to this kind of
learning on their own.
Additionally, many students don&#39;t find learning
within the confines of four walls of a classroom
for extended periods of time consistently alluring.
As a result, motivating a child to pay attention
and learn in school is often a challenge,
as any teacher will tell you.
Another reality of school learning is that deep thinking
is not something we usually do just for fun
or even naturally.
Cognitive scientist Daniel Willingham speaks to this
when he says, &quot;People&#39;s minds are not
&quot;especially well-suited to thinking.
&quot;Thinking is slow, effortful, and uncertain.&quot;
This means we tend to automatically rely on past habits
and memories to guide our actions, and are less likely
to think deliberately and deeply.
To further complicate matters, struggle and confusion
are usually necessary for deep and transformative learning
to happen, something that many students tend to avoid
or incorrectly interpret as a sign of
their ineffectiveness as learners.
We&#39;ll talk more about this later.
It&#39;s no surprise then that teaching is
an incredibly difficult and demanding profession.
Lee Shulman, who for years headed the Carnegie Center
For Teaching And Learning, and spent his career
researching expertise in medical doctors and K through 12
teachers, said this near the end of his career,
&quot;I have concluded that classroom teaching is perhaps
&quot;the most complex, most challenging, and most demanding,
&quot;subtle, nuanced, and frightening activity
&quot;that our species has ever invented.&quot;
Daunting, yes, but reflective teachers all over the world
have been addressing these challenges for a long time.
So why are we here?
Cognitive science research about how people learn,
what we are calling science of learning,
has been going on for well over half a century,
but it is only relatively recently that this research
has reached a point where it can powerfully inform
the day to day practice of any classroom teacher.
The really exciting aspect of this research
is that it can help students develop deeper
and more enduring understanding
of our important learning goals.
At the same time, developing such durable understanding
makes it more likely that students will be able
to use and apply that understanding to their lives
well beyond school.
And that&#39;s for all learners, not just the ones
who might struggle the most.
Finally, while our focus in this course
is on the science of teaching, it almost goes without saying
that effective teaching is also about much more
than the insights provided by cognitive science.
There is a creativity, empathy, an art to what we do
as we respond in the moment to a child before us.
No amount of science will replace the fundamentally
relational quality of great teaching.
This course, in providing an introduction
to the science of learning and the brain,
aims however, to allow educators to develop knowledge
that puts their art and conversation with the robust science
of learning, all towards more deliberately impacting
the learners in their classes.
With that said, we&#39;re ready to begin.
Let&#39;s start with how we make and recall memories.