Angela Duckworth là phó giáo sư
ngành tâm lý học
tại trường đại học Pennsylvania và 2013
ông đã nhận được giải thưởng MacArthur Fellow Angeles cho nghiên cứu về
những năng lực không thuộc về chỉ số IQ bao gồm khả năng tự kiểm soát và
và tính kiên trì bền bỉ một thuật ngữ mà bà đã đưa ra
được dự đoán là sẽ thành công trong cả
học vấn và chuyên môn. Những công trình nghiên cứ của bà rất nổi tiếng.
Tôi rất thích các công trình nghiên cứu của bà
bao gồm cả các học sinh của học viện West Point
lớp National Spelling Bee giáo viên mới vào nghề cuối cùng
người bán hàng và cả học sinh.
Duckworth nhận được bằng cử nhân ngành Sinh học thần kinh
Đại học Harvard năm 1992 và bằng Thạc sỹ khoa học thần kinh năm 1996
của Đại học Oxford.
Bà hoàn thành bằng tiến sỹ ngành tâm lý
tại Đại học Pennsylavania trước khi
sự nghiệp nghiêm cứu của bà. Angela đã thành lập
một trường học hè phi lợi nhuận
cho học sinh nghèo,
một trong những giải thưởng của chính phủ cho bang Massachusetts
và được mô tả như trường hợp trường Harvard Kennedy
Angela cũng là
một tư vấn quản lý của McKinsey
và làm giáo viên dạy toán trong 5 năm
tại trường công ở San Francisco, Philadelphia
và New York nên bà biết khá rõ về những gì mình làm.
David Yeager là một trợ lý giáo sư
tại khoa tâm lý học phát triển
tại Đại học Texas ở Austin
và là hội viên của Qũy Carnegie
hoạt động vì sự tiến bộ của việc giảng dạy
Như tôi đã nói là một hội viên, tại casbah.
Năm nay ông đã giành được bằng cử nhân tại
Đại học Notre Dame .
Đây là lần đầu tiên tôi có thể nói rằng
một người học tại Notre Dame và một người không học tại Notre Dame
cùng giành được bằng Thạc sỹ ngành tâm lý học và
bằng Tiến sỹ ngành khoa học phát triển tâm lý
của Đại Học Standford. Công trình của ông
tập trung vào các học thuyết tâm lý học
và các can thiệp để làm tăng
động lực cho học sinh và các phương pháp luận khoa học xã hội
Ông nguyên là một giáo viên tại trường trung học
và ông có niềm đam mê
trong việc sử dụng các nghiên cứu thử nghiệm
để tạo ra sự bình đẳng trong giáo dục.
Và giờ hãy cùng tôi chào đón Angela và David
Thật vinh hạnh. Tôi sẽ không lãng phí thời gian.
Cám ơn bạn đã mời tôi.
Như tôi đã nói,
tôi đến với ngành tâm lý này
thông qua một lớp học
chúng ta đều trải qua các lớp học
nhưng với tôi, tôi trải qua lớp học đó
với vai trò là một giáo viên đứng lớp. Tôi chỉ muốn nói rằng
những hiểu biết sâu sắc đã đưa tôi đến
với chương trình nghiên cứu này
vốn rất đơn giản. Những đứa trẻ thông minh,
chúng học hỏi rất nhanh
và ngay cả những học sinh không học tốt
Tôi sẽ chỉ nói trong phạm vi
lớp học của mình, những em học sinh không
học tốt. Nếu bạn ngồi gần chúng và nói chuyện với chúng
về những việc mà chúng thực sự quan tâm
như việc thông minh, đó chỉ là phần bên trong
như kiểu không ngờ rằng bạn biết.
rất nhiều những đứa trẻ tôi đã dạy
theo quan điểm của tôi thì,
chúng rất sáng dạ.
Điều thứ hai đó là về toán học.
Bọn trẻ phải học môn toán,
ngữ pháp, viết một đoạn văn thì khó,
thực sự khó, nhưng không hề
nằm ngoài khả năng của chúng. Ken tôi chỉ
cảm thấy rằng phần lớn văn hóa
và các thông điệp mà bọn trẻ đang mã hóa
giống như là, ai là người đủ thoongminh
để học được điều đó. Thử nghĩ về điều đó,
ai là người thông minh hơn để biết được cách tìm ra X
bằng cách lấy chính nó ở vế trái của phép tính
Cả tôi và anh đều bắt đầu có suy nghĩ rằng
đó không phải là
vấn đề về năng lực trí tuệ,
đó là sự lý giải ban đầu của người Mỹ.
và việc điều trị
cho những đứa trẻ
đang ngồi trước mặt tôi
Tôi muốn am hiểu được tâm lý
của sự nỗ lực và chính điều đó đã mang tôi đến với ngành tâm lý.
Không chỉ bởi tôi có thể trừng phạt bọn trẻ
hay chỉ tay hay là đổ lỗi, mà tôi còn
có thể thấu hiểu một cách thật sự lý do vì sao
mọi người vất vả làm việc, làm việc chăm chỉ để làm gì,
khi nào ta nên làm việc chăm chỉ và khi nào không.
Tôi sẽ nói cụ thể
về một lĩnh vực của tâm lý,
một lĩnh vực trong rất nhiều lĩnh vực
mà tôi nghĩ chịu tác động do bởi
khối lượng công việc mà bọn trẻ đang tiến hành
trong trường, hay với bất cứ những gì các em quan tâm
Tôi lấy nó từ trang web nhật báo New York Times
nhưng bạn biết đấy, tôi chắc chắn rằng
tôi có vận may, và tại sao nó
lại có trên trang web. Tôi nghĩ là bởi vì
có một thứ gì đó cộng hưởng với nó,
có thể là về từ ngữ, nó tượng thanh như tiếng sào sạo
giống như có sạn vậy.
ý tôi muốn nói về lòng gan dạ
Tôi thực sự nghĩ rằng có một sự liên quan ở đây
khi tôi trò chuyện với các huấn luyện viên, mục sư, rabbis,
các giáo viên, phụ huynh, cô gì chú bác,
phi hành gia và những người khác
những người thực sự có sự đồng thuận với vấn đề này
sự xây dựng này rất quan trọng
Tôi cho rằng bởi có sự nhận biết rằng
rất nhiều điều trong cuộc sống buộc bạn
phải làm việc trong một khoảng thời gian đài
với sự nhiệt huyết và nỗ lực. Mục tiêu thì có thể là
bất cứ thứ gì bạn bạn quan tâm
nó có thể rất xa vời, có thể tốn của bạn
hàng tháng, hàng năm trời, và trong nhiều trường hợp
thời gian còn lâu hơn. Do vậy ý tưởng này chỉ là tạm thời
Tôi đã từng nghĩ nhiều thứ
và tôi có một lòng thương cảm đặc biệt
cho bọn trẻ. Nhưng tôi cũng có suy nghĩ rằng
chúng trải qua những điều mà
tất cả chúng ta ngồi đây đã từng trải qua.
đây là một biểu đồ đơn giản
đã lược bỏ hết những yếu tố nghèo đói chính trị xã hội
mà tôi cho rằng chúng có những ảnh hưởng
đến việc học của trẻ và cố gắng của các em.
Tôi nghiên cứu những hạt sạn này vì tôi là một nhà tâm lý học
Trưa hôm nay tôi có ngồi thảo luận qua
một vài vấn đề xã hội với những nhà xã hội học
và tôi nhận thấy rõ ràng rằng
đây là một bức tranh
không toàn vẹn về những gì đang diễn ra
nhưng đó chỉ là khởi đầu và tôi rất muốn
hiểu về tâm lý của trẻ em
Những học sinh giỏi hơn chăm chỉ hơn
có phải các em đang tích lũy nhiều hơn
những khoảng thời gian quý giá vào các bài tập hơn là vào những thứ khác
và nếu như vậy, tại sao chúng lại làm như vậy
Quan điểm của tôi, những người can đảm làm hai điều
Chúng thể hiện như những gì
Woody Allen đã nói với chúng tôi trước đây,
tám mươi phần trăm của sự thành công trong cuộc sống vẫn luôn tồn tại ở đó
đang được giữ ở đó và sau khi chúng chúng xuất hiện
chúng làm những thứ được gọi là
tập quán hàng ngày. Bây giờ tôi thực sự
rất hứng thú với công việc của mình và sẽ nói rất ít về chúng
nhưng bạn biết rằng
David và tôi muốn kéo bạn vào
hội thoại, là phần cuối của
thời gian cuộc thảo luận. Tôi nghĩ rằng
children or grown-ups decide to you know
do things that are   hard over long
stretches of time they do things
essentially based on the expected costs
and benefits that's right I pretty much
think kids are rational agents
I know that's very unpopular to think of
people as rational these days but I
think at some level deeply people are
fairly sane including children including
children who are driving   crazy at the
moment but in their  head something must
be going on that makes their behavior
sensible to them and now of   course we
have to understand what it is that's
going   on when it     doesn't make sense to
us now what I   mean     by deliberate
practice is nicely summarized by this
graph not from my own research but from
the work of andre's  erickson pretty much
everyone in the room has read or heard
of outliers by   Malcolm Gladwell and I
will say that   the work on deliberate
practice thousands and thousands of
hours of this   special kind of practice
is not  Gladwell's own idea but in fact
shocker a scientist named Anders
Ericsson who studies experts and in his
study  of experts in as diverse fields as
you can think   of from sodoku to soccer
he finds that there's a skill curve so
skills on the vertical axis and what
he's got graphed here as years of
deliberate practice on  the      x-axis you
really  only have a chance at      world-class
levels of performance that's the dotted
horizontal line after you've accumulated
thousands and thousands   of hours over
years and years of this kind of practice
there's nothing magic about the number
ten thousand except for that it's round
and it was one average  in one study but
i think the generalized insight is  that
getting really good at anything  i mean
anything being a chef or a mathematician
does you know take a tremendous  amount
of work  over time and in particular when
onder's studies experts he finds   that
they practice in a very particular way
which he dubs deliberate practice they
do   all fourth of these things at once
they're working   on something very
self-conscious and specific that they
cannot yet do so they have set out to do
what they cannot do they concentrate
completely true full 100% concentration
they get immediate and informative
feedback so for   example Olympic downhill
skiers have themselves videotaped and as
soon as they can they   get their hands on
the videotape   and they watch it so they
can then learn on what to do a little
differently than
I'm and then finally  they practice to
fluency my husband's a former violist
like as in he played viola in college
and then he went   back to take vo lessons
and he came   home one day and he said you
know  feola teacher said      that he had to
play this single piece that he had  been
assigned right  ten times flawlessly
before he   would be given the next viola
piece and I thought   to     myself oh right
that's how   expert practice not to like
be plus not to kind of like yeah kind   of
get it but truly to complete fluency and
automaticity and what does it   feel like
to do deliberate practice I love this
essay that Martha Graham wrote towards
the end   of her career for National
Public Radio she says it takes about  10
years to   make a mature dancer right so
again nothing magic about 10 years or
10,000 hours but it does come  up again
and again it's true she says dancing
appears glamorous easy and delightful
but the path to the paradise of   G
achievement is not easier than any other
there   is fatigue so great that     the body
cries even in its sleep there are times
of complete frustration there are daily
small deaths this is what it feels like
to do  deliberate practice      at least
according to one very great artist it's
not always that bad but when we went to
the National Spelling Bee we wanted to
know what kids were doing and how it
felt so we had them keep Diaries of the
kinds of things that they   did and they
listed all sorts of  things and they kept
track of not only how it felt in terms
of its effort and its enjoyment but also
how many hours   and minutes they were
doing and here's our data so there's
three bars in each cluster the dark bars
are doing deliberate practice things
like writing the same word over and over
again singing lay down a page in  the
middle and the light bars is being
quizzed like your mom might say moose
bracha and you say you spra CH e Luce
bracha which was the winning word that
year and that which I just learned how
to spell by the way and   then what they
really want to   do all day     is what we
coded as leisure verbal activities
mostly reading right which kids actually
in the study rated as enjoyable as
eating ice cream so super enjoyable
things on in some case
is you know high effort things in it but
in the picture that we're painting here
is not that   unlike Martha Graham's
description of low enjoyment high effort
for deliberate practice but   when you
throw everything into the same model and
you ask in  terms of time which kind of
practice uniquely predicts Spelling Bee
performance in the finals it's only
deliberate practice and a great was the
best psychological predictor of how much
time kids spent now some of  us may have
children in  the room or grandchildren or
you know nieces nephews I just want  to
point out one thing being quizzed is
actually a very  good thing for studying
in part because you can identify what
you don't know but then of  course you
have  to go      and practice it and that
might be why in this   model it falls out
as not being super predictive so do quiz
your children   grandchildren nieces
nephews but also recognize  that there's
a certain   amount of practice that they
have to do with full concentration
working on something they can't with
feedback repetitively in order for them
to improve now I want to transition to
this expected value idea this idea that
kids are in a way little  economist
trying to figure out   how they should
optimize their benefits and minimize
their costs we created  an intervention
which simply taught kids what I just
explained   to you we told them Martha
Graham hates to practice says it kind of
feels like dying completely frustrated
sometimes totally confuse you know we we
spice it up you know with cartoons which
are more fun to look at the knee we also
tell them   that if you look at scientific
studies of kids and adults learning the
signature emotion of learning is not
flow it is not necessarily even
curiosity or happiness or pride the
signature emotion of learning seems to
be confusion it is confusion which you
have to   sustain in this concentrated way
that you don't  enjoy because confusion
is a negative emotion and that we should
maybe   in reinterpret the experience of
studying and homework as something   which
is normal and also potentially even a
good sign like I'm in my discomfort zone
kids at the end this   is very     Dueck Ian I
say has you know this exercise at  the
end where they write a letter to another
student where they simply summarize what
they've learned and actually tell a
story from their own life that brings it
to life so for   example on the far right
dear student deep practice helps me a
lot with soccer it makes me a better
player I used to   be the one that was
behind on my team but now that I use D
practice I'm one of the top players it
makes me frustrated but I push through
it with hard work and that equals
success right so we created a task that
force kids to do deliberate practice we
took Khan Academy material but we
increased the algorithm so that kids
would   be constantly pushed into doing
problems that they   were actually getting
a certain percentage of   them wrong but
when we SAT them in the lab we said you
know if you need to take a break
whenever you want   to you can go we have
negotiated with your school to      take off
the firewall you can go to youtube go to
Facebook you go to      Instagram we were
like   the most popular study that has
ever been run because kids never get to
do that   in their own computer labs and
this is a screenshot of one of our
studies and you can kind   of     see that
some   of the kids are on Instagram then
some of   the kids are actually on the
task itself this deliberate practice
test and what we found is that learning
about deliberate practice compared  to a
placebo control group actually can I
would say either you  could say the red
line increase the amount of deliberate
practice kids are willing to   do a
relative to   a control group or at least
mitigate against the decrease right that
the control group is like I really don't
want to do this and we're   sort of
buffering against that in the
intervention group we also change their
beliefs about practice once you go
through this intervention you say things
like      you     know what when you're      doing
your homework and you're studying you
should focus on weaknesses and things
that you don't know and stop repeating
all the things that   you do know which of
course feels better and also their
beliefs about frustration what is
frustration a sign that you should give
up and you know like it's over or a sign
that you should actually persist because
this might be the real moment of
learning and   i will say finally that
we're excited that among the lower
achieving students which is a finding
that      I think David and I and Carol and
many others of us who are all in the
kind of   Carol Dweck extended family you
know we often   find that there     is a kind
of bringing up of the most vulnerable
suit
and these interventions and in this case
we find that so      for example in the high
achieving kids there's no effect on
grades but in the low achieving kids
there is an increase in the intervention
group and finally I'll just say   for my
own self that I want   to give the credit
for   the intervention we're completely to
my graduate student Lauren and then  our
funders and also   David who among other
people to selflessly like tells me what
the heck I'm doing wrong when we call
him  and ask him to look at our
interventions so let me transition to
you David  and thinks I'm a developmental
psychologist but I I much my training is
in social psychology   and a hallmark in
social psychology is the idea that the
situation the setting you're in provides
information   to you about the kind of
person you might be my beer might be
viewed as what's worth your effort what
is what is the meaning of your actions
in your behavior in this setting in the
eyes of others and so where where where
where we build on the story that Angela
developed is to try   to look at at an
even   earlier level in the diagram to say
what are the discernment that
individuals make as they  enter a setting
that this is a place where   I can trust
that my effort will be valued and will
pay off in this setting is this a place
where I belong where people will respect
me where when I when I push myself to
the as Claude Steele says to the
frontiers of my ability and put myself
out there where I might look dumb I
might look like someone who lacks
ability that this is it's   it's a safe
place for  me to invest my efforts and so
where I love where this work comes
together is the   idea that there's a
particular   type of practice that
develops ability but  it takes trust that
that unpleasant feeling that frustration
the the judgment you make about about
that aversive emotion isn't worth it   to
me from my perspective given what I know
about the setting and we this is a long
tradition of research that builds
Angela's co-author and some of this but
certainly  a lot of my collaborators
either at Stanford or from Stanford and
the work i'll present is really it grows
out of a number of wonderful people     in
their work what's a good   setting to test
the psychology of effort specifically
your judgments of whether you can trust
that this is a safe     place well      I'm a
former middle school English   teacher and
every I would assign writing assignments
and every Sunday   I would get or every
few Sundays I'd get i get   the drafts the
kids the essays  of the kids wrote and I
go   to this     coffeehouse shades of brown
and Tulsa Oklahoma and as before shades
of   gray so it was slightly it was less
weird at   the time and and I sit     there in
it anyway out great essays and I just
have this stack and I just hated it
right it's  just so such an aversive
experience for me and I just  listen      to
the like the high schoolers chitchat
about the boring stuff that they're
doing   and whatever and I just you know
just like drinking coffee and I'm the
only  thing that comforted me was these
kids are  so lucky because every comment
i put  on there sa they're going to get
so  much better at writing how fortunate
that I went out of my way to tell      them
how they could improve I mean I'm   gonna
get something just going to get thank
you note after thank you know when they
get essays back and they look like this
right and   that's kind of our theory of
like getting good teachers in the
classroom that really push kids you know
like the kids are going to love it but
from the kids perspective like what are
they saying right and they look a little
bit like this guy   you know they're
thinking this is a if you google first
batch of comments on   your dissertation
proposal this image comes up so the
question
that's  actually true uh from their
professions like this guy went out   of
his way on a Sunday just to crap on all
my work and like what a horrible person
right and so there's this
intersubjectivity problem right we're
like  that their effort from their
perspective is viewed as just this
complete lack of competence by an
authority figure and absent trust that
that if they try their hardest that
they're going   to meet a standard and be
treated   fairly why would it be rational
from their perspective to not play with
her friends at night but instead revised
an essay and so this   is work that grew
out of Jeff Cohen's dissertation and we
carried out a study also with Val pretty
vons where this  is a real essay from the
study where middle schoolers wrote
essays about their heroes this was
designed to be a self relevant topic and
we instructed the teachers to do their
best on providing comments and you know
I     was again I was an English teacher
you're told to do something to buffer
your critical feedback and now you can
ask yourself   well how do you give
critical feedback and I  talk      to a lot of
parents and   teachers and they say I'll
tell you how you   give a critical
feedback step  one give      someone a
compliment about something that's
completely unrelated to the domain
you're about to talk about   like their
enthusiasm step to tell them that all
their work is bad and tell them all the
ways that it could  be revised step 3
remind them  of their competence      in some
completely unrelated domain like   their
taste in music or their shoes but   the
assumption   is that like self-esteem is a
cup   that you take a gulp and you know
you you fill it up a little   bit with a
compliment you   take a gulp with a
critical   feedback and then you have
don't forget to fill it back up again at
the end   but subjectively from the
perspective of the kid they may not   be
wondering like you know do I have high
self-esteem but they may be wondering is
this person viewing me as an  idiot or as
someone who  has no confidence and if you
don't if you   don't create a trust that
this is a place where   your abilities and
perspectives are valued it can be
difficult   to make a judgment     of that
this is worth my effort so what teachers
did is they kind of intuitively knew to
use the
compliment sandwich approach and it's
like   this is really good good job and
then you know it's lots of substantive
feedback and  bye-bye      professional
development standards this is great
feedback on essays um but then what
happened is after the kids wrote the
first essay and then they and then the
teachers commented on it the researchers
intercepted the essays and we randomly
assigned post-it notes  on the essays
designed to assuage the concern   that
this teacher views you   only in light of
a   negative stereotype for instance or
enlighten who'd lacks ability and then
this   is     a technique developed by Claude
Steele and Jeff Cohen called wise
feedback and and what it does  is it has
two parts of   the message first an
invocation of high standards   in the     end
that I'm   giving you these comments
because I have high   standards and the
idea is   to     take off the table the
alternative attribution that you're
being criticized because of bias or
dislike but just appealing to a high
standard doesn't assure a person that
they have the potential to meet it it's
like going to the two you know
astroworld that's in Houston six flags
and you see the you see   the thing you
have to be this big   to right that's the
standard but you're this tall and   you're
never going   to meet him and you wonder
well who developed that standard and so
the idea is to both appeal to the high
standard and then say I'm with you to
the bitter end until you reach that   high
standard and   so the note said I'm giving
you these comments because I have high
standards and I know that you can meet
them it's a simple   sentence but it comes
directly   from observational work of the
world's   best teachers hi my Escalante
the   movie Stand and Deliver that's a
real story of   a real teacher and he said
this is     the standard      free AP AP Calculus
and we're studying in my   living room
until midnight until everyone here and
passes that we try to invoke that spirit
in the kids for kids in the control
condition they got a note that said I'm
giving you these comments so you have
feedback on your essay which conveys no
information however   some beautiful work
by Ellen Langer shows us that any
explanation for behavior that
grammatically sounds correct can have a
beneficial effect and so it's
truly titled a placebo and there's the
footnote it's a beautiful set of studies
if you want to cut in line  at the copier
for instance it's you   know if you just
say I'd  like to make my copies or can I
cut in line people  like now it's
ridiculous you're a jerk and you're
selfish if you say can I cut in line and
you know I'm in a hurry i  need to      pick
up my   kids at soccer practice it's like
oh right   away     i would be a      jerk if i
stood in your way  but in the third
condition if you say can I cut in line
I'd like to     make my copies faster then
you're just as likely to get compliance
and it took you a second to laugh
because grammatically it sounds like an
explanation and conveys it fulfills a
conversational norm and so here  too we
said  like just something that kids
wouldn't question in fact we knew
through  follow-ups follow-up surveys and
interviews that kids didn't question
this okay so researchers intercept the
essays append the post-it notes randomly
signed at  the individual level in real
7th grade classrooms at a racially
diverse middle school fifty percent   of
students of white fifty percent of
students were african-american but all
teachers were white so we're looking at
trust across the racial divide in  the
face of critical feedback essays had a
cover page put on them so teachers were
blinded to the treatment condition they
handed back the essays kids walk out the
door and then a week later they either
revise the essay or not and so what
happened on  the      y-axis here is the
percent   of kids who revise the essay in
the real middle school classroom and
what you  see is that      in the control
condition in  the placebo you see a
racial achievement gap that
unfortunately is reproduced in on a
number of metrics again and again in
many American classrooms and absent this
type of social psychological perspective
absent a perspective on the legitimate
concerns that students might have but
whether it's fair to trust in this
setting you might wonder are these kids
different are their traits that differ
is this the fixed state of affairs
however  for kids who received the high
standards and assurance post-it note
white students showed a marginally
significant modest benefit of around
twenty five percentage points but for
African American students there was a
dramatic increase in the proportion who
revised their essays up to   seventy-two
percent statistically this     eliminates
the achievement gap on this metric
in this moment and what what's important
about this is that what can seem like a
stable set of findings again and again
can in fact be a legitimate discernment
that an individual might have about
whether this place is is safe for me to
trust   that my effort will be valued and
respected by  the authorities we thought
this   is at the end of the 7th     grade year
at a time  when we knew trust was just
was declining just as in  angela's data
people wanted less deliberate practice
over time and   this data said we surveyed
kids twice a year on their trust their
their beliefs that teachers were fair in
the  control condition it looked      like
this every single measurement occasion
especially  African American students
showed lower trust in the treatment
condition there was still a decline but
that decline leveled off after the
post-it note throughout the eighth grade
year from official records at  the end      of
the school year in eighth grade we
looked at discipline incidents and the
reason  for this is this this this
finding   that grows in a part out     of some
theory that   Jennifer     eberhard who's here
has developed that individuals discern
whether institutions are fair is this a
place where the policies are applied
fairly to me and specifically to my
group and that that discernment once
developed can might apply across domains
of interaction so in this school we know
for instance that   African American
students   are aware that they're more
likely to for instance be stopped in the
hallway and ask for a  Hall Pass as
compared to white students that type of
discernment in turn predicts whether
they   revise the rest day in the
classroom  but it also predicts whether
they earn   discipline incidents in eighth
grade net of whether they were
disciplined themselves   previously and so
if Trust is this mediator if individuals
form a mental   model of trust based on
interpersonal treatment then that might
create the very reality that students
might have have perceived that as
students now distrusting may act out
against those very rules that  they see
is unfair  and unjust however if trust
could be restored in in fact the reality
is ambiguous if you could   lead students
to see this as  a place      where perhaps
maybe sometimes I might be treated
fairly then perhaps you could prevent
some  of that discipline and in fact
that's   what we find where
in the control condition you see a
dramatic racial disparity in discipline
just it consistent with what was
perceived by individuals however   for
kids who receive the post-it note there
was about a fifty percent reduction in
the discipline incidents note that this
is different teachers a different school
different school year   and this is in
many cases outside  of the classroom so
there's   this dynamic interplay between
discernment of trust in the classroom
and discernment of fairness of the
institution that you're a part   of now in
turn trust   in this in this study
predicted whether students made it to
college four years   later but what we
were interested in  is whether these
mental models of wariness about fairness
and belonging might might still be
malleable even later in development for
instance among individuals who are
transitioning from high school into
college so what'll end with is a study
we worked on Angela worked on or   closely
with   Greg Walton who's here we've
thought about this   idea where a
student's belief or a mindset that is
the product of experience might predict
their everyday behaviors whether they
feel it's safe to invest their effort or
not over time that might lead to
differences in learning achievement and
in turn reinforce a mindset that they
may have that is that perception becomes
a reality what Tim Wilson calls an
exacerbation cycle but you might  be      able
to   to cut that through psychological
intervention of the   type that were
developed   here at Stanford and so we did
some work in the transition  to college
which what I'll end with and
specifically we looked at graduates of
high-performing urban charter networks
these are students from communities
where the base rate of college
enrollment and subsequent graduation is
very low however these schools help
students develop skills academic skills
and gain admission to college in many
cases at around one hundred percent
rates but   the college graduation rate
among those  students that      one hundred
percent who made it to college is ranges
from   twenty to forty percent so there's
this   tragic loss of potential among
individuals coming out of in many   cases
low-income      communities many cases
first-generation students many cases
students of color who head off to our
nation's colleges
but never earn degrees and leave with
with debt so we wondered  if helping
students appraise early experiences of
difficulty that first critical feedback
on your freshman seminar  essay and then
probably everyone in this room remembers
your first freshman to like anyone
willing   to share those I'm not right
does that first calculus test you might
have failed the first time in in that
that's academic what   about social the
the first time you have lunch with
someone   and then you know     that they go
to a party the next day     and they don't
invite you those are   all experiences
where you might legitimately wonder is
this a normal part of   the transition to
college or is this do more   generally to
something about my group that people
like me may not belong may not be valued
here and that   again that discernment
about belonging may in turn affect
whether you feel like it's a safe place
for   you to put yourself to the frontiers
of your abilities the frontiers of your
knowledge to be lost confused to
struggle to ask  questions in      front of
peers whether you worried they might
think that you're done and so with Greg
and Angela we had a design school day
here at the   Stanford design school we're
trying to bring the fun of product
design methodology into the design of
psychological interventions that's
andre's Erickson who came for that day
and there's   Angela so much from Angela
staff Chris  gabrielli Donald commence
one of our partners   from yes prep public
schools Chris Broughton  and what we did
is we interviewed a ton of students
graduates of urban charters  for
transitioning to college and we tried to
craft a message that could just help
them have a little psychological space
before they face inevitable difficulties
we had students draw what we   called a
journey map this is a journey of their
transition from high school to college
you see stress stress stress when the
admissions process this   student went to
CSU East Bay and then dropped out after
one month for a financial   matter going
back   to college this     is a      woman young
woman that Claude Steele and I
interviewed and this told stories of
worries that that professors didn't care
nearly as much as her teachers in high
school and wondered   if it meant that
they weren't valuing her respecting her
we building on this   kind of design
process we took a series of notes we
worked with  addie school for several
months and rewrote materials that just
help students have a   little space to
potentially interpret early common
difficulties as things   that might be
able      to     overcome as a place see college
as a place  where they might trust we
develop      then distilled all these
insights into a very brief web-based
survey takes about 25 30 minutes to
complete and students go into their
school computer labs and they completed
it in may have senior year in high
school so it says you're finishing high
school you're going   to college you're
excited you probably still lots of
questions about  what to expect etc etc
and  then they read a series of quotes
that were taken from the real members of
our focus groups and interviews talking
about how college is hard you're going
to you're going to struggle in school
you're going   to struggle socially but
over time you get better these are kids
taking the   the survey they're randomly
assigned at the individual level from
their perspective all the materials look
very similar they read these quotes
again it   takes about 20 to 25 minutes
from their perspective the study is over
at the end and then we track them
through the National Student
Clearinghouse which is a government
database that allows you to know whether
people are enrolled full-time in college
or not and so on the y-axis here is
full-time enrollment rates this we did
this two years in a row   and replicated
in two different charter management
organizations one is in Philadelphia
almost exclusively  african-american
students   the other is in cities and
Houston Texas almost exclusively Latino
students so what you see is that  in the
control tragically although one hundred
percent were admitted to   college only 61
percent show up in the fall so there's
what's called summer melt our treatment
doesn't stop summer melt really but   even
more tragically you see that even   among
the students   who made it to the first
semester  of college      you lose an
additional half by fall of junior  year
and   this is the most recent     data for the
treatment though you see a slowing of
that decline the the pipeline is   Leslie
key for   these students and it may not
look like much   but by spring of
sophomore year there's a 12 percentage
point increase in full-time enrollment
rates for students from this one time
message
with no  reinforcement we read in this
significant at every time point after
the first     year in in cohort to what you
see is that again a hundred percent were
admitted   to college tragically only     51%
made it and then they lose about ten
percent over the first year      and a half
of college but but by the by   the fall of
sophomore year there's a significant
treatment contrast and importantly  the
size of the effects may look modest but
they're big from the perspective of
social science   so the flagship
intervention that paid students
thirty-five hundred dollars per semester
for staying  full-time students had an
effect   of around two to two point four
percentage points and it faded out after
one year these these effects are much
larger and they can be  achieved at much
more modest cost so in   summary what I'd
like to suggest is that sometimes some
of the withholding of effort that some
students especially across group lines
that we might see   may be due     to a
legitimate questioning of whether this
is a fair place where I could trust and
where I can succeed and then allowing
students to stay in the game just long
enough where they can have some success
where it can build on itself can have
surprising effects that can that can
last and  that can      reinforce themselves
over time and in what I and so in
conclusion I think you know what
Margaret is leaning here at the center
is really big integrated behavioral
science that that takes basic scientific
ideas and thinks of ways to   use them to
address important social problems and
all of the work I presented here  builds
on great work by cosmos fellows people
like Claude Steele and so I mean I'm
really excited to see the kinds of
effects that   we can have on important
social problems going forward from   the
kinds of work that   cosmos fellows this
year and next year   will be doing thank
you very much
you