The 48 Laws of Power ... by Robert Greene
Law number ten... Infection: Avoid the unhappy
and unlucky
You can die from someone else's misery—emotional
states are as infectious as diseases. You
may feel you are helping the drowning man
but you are only precipitating your own disaster.
The unfortunate sometimes draw misfortune
on themselves; they will also draw it on you.
Associate with the happy and fortunate instead.
The infector possesses an inward instability
that radiates outward drawing disaster to
all that they touch. Marie Gilbert A.K.A Lola
Montez of Ireland was one such person. Lola
found herself in the role of a courtesan (prostitute
of the royal court). In today’s society
Lola would be considered a gold-digger. She
only sought out men with high social standing
in the community that she could use for her
own gain.
Once she would have her hooks in these men,
their slow demise began. One of her victims
was king Ludwig of Bavaria, who felt compelled
to help Lola yet once he was warned of the
dangers of his affair with her, he could not
seem to resist Lola’s aura and almost found
his once peaceful country in a state of civil
war. It was not until then that the king finally
ordered Lola to leave but a month after she
left King Ludwig was forced to relinquish
his throne.
There are many men who suffered because of
their association with Lola Montez.
King Ludwig said that he was “bewitched”
by Lola. Lola was an unstable, incurable and
infectious character type. This is not to
say that these characteristics are only restricted
to women, this is to say that there are some
people whose emotions are so powerful that
they infect the very soul of the people that
they touch.
How to Recognize an Infector
1. They draw misfortune upon themselves.
2. They have a turbulent past.
3. They have a long line of broken relationships.
4. They have an unstable career.
5. They have a forceful character that sweeps
you up and makes you lose reason.
6. They have a desire to destroy and unsettle
and is chronically dissatisfied.
7. Look at the effect that they have on the
world around them.
What to Do When You Meet an Infector
1. Don’t argue with them, this is part of
how they trap you.
2. Don’t try to help them no matter what
they say.
3. Don’t pass the person onto your friends
or you will become enmeshed.
4. Flee the infector's presence or suffer
the consequences.
Learn To Fear the Power of Infection
The risk of associating with infectors is
that you will waste valuable time and energy
trying to free yourself. Through a kind of
guilt by association, you will also suffer
in the eyes of others.
On the other side of the spectrum of infectors
are those people who attract happiness through
their good cheer, natural buoyancy, and intelligence.
They are a source of plea-sure, and you must
associate with them to share in the prosperity
they draw upon themselves. All positive qualities
can infect us, but taking advantage of the
emotional side of this osmosis may be difficult.
5 Ways to Affect Positive Change through Your
Associations
1. If you are miserly by nature, associate
with the generous and they will infect you,
opening up everything that is tight and restricted
in you. Only generous souls attain greatness.
2. If you are gloomy, gravitate to the cheerful.
3. If you are prone to isolation, force yourself
to befriend the gregarious.
4. Never associate with those who share your
defects—they will reinforce everything that
holds you back.
5. Only create associations with positive
affinities.
Your rule for life…
Recognize the fortunate so that you may choose
their company and the unfortunate so that
you may avoid them. Misfortune is usually
the crime of folly, and among those who suffer
from it there is no malady more contagious:
Never open your door to the least of misfortunes,
for, if you do, many others will follow in
its train… Do not die of another's misery.
(Baltasar Gracian, 1601-1658)
That's it for this law, if you seek more resourceful
reviews you might just want to subscribe.
Thank's for watching.