The 48 Laws of Power by Robert Greene
Law Number 12... Use Selective Honesty to
Disarm Your Victim
One sincere and honest move will cover over
dozens of dishonest ones. Open-hearted gestures
of honesty and generosity bring down the guard
of even the most suspicious people. Once your
selective honesty opens a hole in their armor,
you can deceive and manipulate them at will.
A timely gift—a Trojan horse—will serve
the same purpose.
7 Ways You Can Disarm Anyone
1. Through an act of apparent sincerity and
honesty.
This is called selective honesty. Who will
distrust a person literally caught in the
act of being honest? This is an unexpected,
well-timed gesture that conflicts the emotions
and distracts the one being disarmed and have
the most brutal and cynical beast in the kingdom
eating out of your hand. In ancient China
this was called the “giving before the take.”
The giving makes it hard for the other person
to see the taking.
Count Victor Lustig is one of the best examples
of this law at work. Lustig was a con man
of great distinction, refinement and culture,
and his knowledge of human psychology was
his most important characteristic. He was
so confident in himself that he was able to
con Al Capone, the most feared gangster of
his time, out of $5,000. Capone never knew
what happened because Lustig disarmed him
through selective honesty.
Lustig returned $50,000 to Capone for allowing
him to take the money in order to double it
in sixty-days. Lustig took the money and left
it in a safety deposit box until the sixty-days
were up. He went back to Capone, apologized
profusely about the deal falling through and
returned the original $50,000. Capone had
already pegged Lustig as a con artist, but
when Lustig returned the money, it confused
Capone and he dropped his guard and gave Lustig
$5,000 just for “being honest.”
2. Learn to give before you take.
It softens the ground, takes the bite out
of a future request, or simply creates a distraction.
And the giving can take many forms: an actual
gift, a generous act, a kind favor, an "honest"
admission—whatever it takes.
3. Use selective honesty on your first encounter
with someone.
First impressions last a long time. If someone
believes you are honest at the start of your
relationship it takes a lot to convince them
otherwise.
A con man by the name of Lord John Gordon-Gordon
proved to Jay Gould, another con man, that
phony Erie railroad stocks that Gould had
invested in was the work of top executives
at railroad. Gould was so grateful to Gordon-Gordon
that they became friends buying the controlling
interest of the railroad. Soon Gordon-Gordon
betrayed Gould and disappeared. Gordon-Gordon
was a con man, but his initial act of honesty
and support had so blinded Gould that it took
the loss of millions for him to see through
the scheme
4. You must build a reputation for honesty
based on a series of acts.
Duke Wu of Cheng married off his daughter
and killed one of his ministers in order to
take over the powerful kingdom of Hu. The
ruler of Hu heard that the minister was executed
for telling Cheng to conquer the kingdom of
Hu. Hu’s ruler also considered the marriage
of Cheng’s daughter and other acts of kindness
from Cheng and let down his guard. A few weeks
later Cheng forces swept through Hu and took
the country, never to relinquish it.
5. Give a gift.
Few people can resist a gift, even from the
most hardened enemy, which is why it is often
the perfect way to disarm people. A gift brings
out the child in us, instantly lowering our
defenses. Although we often view other people's
actions in the most cynical light, we rarely
see the Machiavellian element of a gift, which
quite often hides ulterior motives. A gift
is the perfect object in which to hide a deceptive
move.
6. Practice the tactic with caution
Unless you can make the gesture seem sincere
and heartfelt, DO NOT PLAY WITH FIRE. If people
see through it, their disappointed feelings
of gratitude and warmth will become the most
violent hatred and distrust.
7. It is better to play the rogue
When you have a history of deceit behind you,
no amount of honesty, generosity, or kindness
will fool people. In fact it will only call
attention to itself. Once people have come
to see you as deceitful, to act honest all
of a sudden is simply suspicious. Overt deceptiveness
will sometimes cover your tracks, even making
you admired for the honesty of your dishonesty.
if you're known for lying, don't lie about
not lying.
if you try, you may insult your enemies' intelligence
"he's a deceitful man, but at least he doesn't
try to cover it pathetically"