The 48 Laws of Power by Robert Greene | Law Number 14... Pose as a Friend, Work as a Spy
Knowing about your rival is critical. Use
spies to gather valuable information that
will keep you a step ahead. Better still:
Play the spy yourself. In polite social encounters,
learn to probe. Ask indirect questions to
get people to reveal their weaknesses and
intentions. There is no occasion that is not
an opportunity for artful spying.
5 Reasons to Secretly Put the Clients’ Staff
on Your Payroll
1. You will gain some valuable information.
2. You will know their comings and goings,
changes in taste, and other such tidbits of
information that will be priceless.
3. You will appear to be all knowing because
you will be one step ahead of your competition.
4. Your knowledge of your mark can also make
you seem charming, so well can you anticipate
his desires.
5. No one sees the source of your power, and
what they cannot see they cannot fight.
The Risks of Hiring Spies
· You have little control over the people
who are doing the work.
· Perhaps they will ineptly expose your spying.
· They may secretly turn against you.
6 Tips on the Art of SPYING
1. Pose as a friend while secretly gathering
information.
People will think that you genuinely like
them and mistake your interest as friendship.
2. Learn to possess the ability to suppress
your thoughts in the conversation, speak when
only necessary.
3. Learn to make others talk endlessly about
themselves.
They will inadvertently reveal their intentions
and plans.
4. Organize social gathering with people whom
you are interested in knowing.
This is when most people’s guards are down.
5. Stir up people’s emotions by contradicting
them.
In their emotional state they will reveal
all kinds of truths about themselves, truths
you can later use against them.
6. Give them a false confession.
By pretending to bare your heart to another
person, you make them more likely to reveal
their own secrets.
This can also be a test to see if you can
trust the person with your secret and reveal
their true character, loyalty and honesty.
This kind of knowledge is often the most valuable
to predict future actions.
The Risks of Spying Directly
· People may begin to suspect you are worming
secrets out of them under the guise of conversation.
· Your search for gems of information cannot
be too obvious.
· Your probing questions will reveal more
about yourself and your intentions than about
the information you hope to find about them.
Information is critical to power, but just
as you spy on other people, you must be prepared
for them to spy on you. One of the most potent
weapons in the battle for information, then,
is giving out false information. By feeding
people wrong information, then, you gain a
potent advantage. While spying gives you a
third eye, disinformation puts out one of
your enemy's eyes. A Cyclops, he always misses
his target.