The 48 Laws of Power by Robert Greene | Law Number 15... Crush Your Enemy Totally
All great leaders since Moses have known that
a feared enemy must be crushed completely.
(Sometimes they have learned this the hard
way.) If one ember is left alight, no matter
how dimly it smolders, a fire will eventually
break out. More is lost through stopping halfway
than through total annihilation: The enemy
will recover, and will seek revenge. Crush
him, not only in body but in spirit.
4 Ways to Kill or be Killed
1. Do not sympathize with your enemies.
Your enemy will bide his time and strike back
when you least expect.
2. When you pity or hope for reconciliation,
it will make you hesitate.
They may act friendly for the time being,
but they will eventually destroy you
3. An enemy that is left around is like a
half-dead viper that you nurse back to health.
You only strengthen their fear and hatred
of you.
4. Give your enemies nothing to negotiate,
no hope, no room to maneuver.
Do not humiliate, yet nurture these resentful
vipers who will one day kill you.
This is all the truer with a former friend
who has become an enemy. The law governing
fatal antagonisms reads: Reconciliation is
out of the question. You must exterminate,
crush, and deny them the chance to return
to haunt you.
Such is the case of Hsiang Yu and his enemy
Liu Pang. Hsiang had proven his ruthlessness
on many an occasion, but with Liu Pang he
acted differently. Every time he had his rival
in his hands, something made him hesitate—a
fatal sympathy or respect for the man who
had once been a friend and comrade in arms.
But the moment Hsiang made it clear that he
intended to do away with Liu, yet failed to
accomplish it, he sealed his own doom.
Liu would not suffer the same hesitation once
the tables were turned. Now Hsiang Yu was
on the run from Liu and when he came upon
a small group of his own retreating soldiers,
he cried out, "I hear Liu Pang has offered
one thousand pieces of gold and a fief of
ten thousand families for his head. Let me
do you a favor." He then slits his own throat
and dies.
It is not, of course, a question of murder,
it is a question of banishment. Sufficiently
weakened and then exiled from your world,
your enemies are rendered harmless.
They have no hope of recovering, insinuating
themselves and hurting you. And if they cannot
be banished, at least understand that they
are plotting against you, and pay no heed
to whatever friendliness they feign.
Sometimes It Is Better To Let Your Enemies
Destroy Themselves
Leave your enemy an escape route. A retreat
is the ultimate demoralizing defeat. Let them
be the agents of their own destruction. The
result will be the same.
The risk of crushing an enemy is you embitter
them so much so that they spend years and
years plotting revenge. Do not let your guard
down, but simply crush them again.