The 48 Laws of Power by Robert Greene | Law Number 17... Cultivate an air of Unpredictability
Humans are creatures of habit with an insatiable
need to see familiarity in other people's
actions. Your predictability gives them a
sense of control. Turn the tables: Be deliberately
unpredictable. Behavior that seems to have
no consistency or purpose will keep them off-
balance and they will wear themselves out
trying to explain your moves. Taken to an
extreme, this strategy can intimidate and
terrorize.
5 Ways to Keep Your Opponent Off-Balance
1. Appear to have no clear strategy.
2. Scramble old patterns.
3. Alter your behavior, to improvise and overcome
the weight of routine and habit
4. Unsettle those around you to keep the initiative
on their side
5. Strike without warning, to make others
tremble when they least expect it.
To illustrate this law we will use the game
of chess. Chess, contains the concentrated
essence of life: First, because to win you
have to be supremely patient and farseeing;
and second, because the game is built on patterns,
whole sequences of moves that have been played
before and will be played again, with slight
alterations, in any one match.
Your opponent analyzes the patterns you are
playing and uses them to try to foresee your
moves. Allowing him nothing predictable to
base his strategy on gives you a big advantage.
In chess as in life, when people cannot figure
out what you are doing, they are kept in a
state of terror—waiting, uncertain, confused.
It is a device that the powerful have used
for centuries
Scrambling your patterns on a day-to-day basis
will cause a stir around you and stimulate
interest. People will talk about you, ascribe
motives and explanations that have nothing
to do with the truth, but that keep you constantly
in their minds. In the end, the more capricious
you appear, the more respect you will garner.
Only the terminally subordinate act in a predictable
manner!
2 Reasons that ‘Predictability’ Will Work
In Your Favor
1. It sets up a smoke screen, a comfortable
front behind which you can carry on deceptive
actions.
2. It allows you on rare occasions to do something
completely against the pattern, unsettling
your opponent so deeply he will fall to the
ground without being pushed.
In 1974 Muhammad Ali and George Foreman were
scheduled to fight for the world heavyweight
boxing championship. In a press conference
before the big fight, he said he was going
to change his style and punch it out with
Foreman. No one, least of all Foreman, believed
this for a second. To everyone's amazement,
Ali did exactly what he had said he would
do.
As Foreman waited for him to dance around,
Ali went right up to him and slugged it out.
He completely upset his opponent's strategy.
At a loss, Foreman ended up wearing himself
out, not by chasing Ali but by throwing punches
wildly, and taking more and more counterpunches.
Finally, Ali landed a dramatic right cross
that knocked out Foreman.
The habit of assuming that a person's behavior
will fit its previous patterns is so strong
that not even Ali's announcement of a strategy
change was enough to upset it. Foreman walked
into a trap—the trap he had been told to
expect.
WARNING: (this law just like many of the laws
of this book can backfire on you, if not practised
with caution)
Unpredictability can work against you sometimes,
especially if you are in a subordinate position.
There are times when it is better to let people
feel comfortable and settled around you than
to disturb them. Too much unpredictability
will be seen as a sign of indecisiveness,
or even of some more serious psychic problem.
Such power should only be used judiciously.
That's it for this law, I hope you found it
resourceful as always. Subscribe if you'd
like to see more and thank's for watching.