Vào năm 1950, một bà mẹ tên Brownie Wise bắt đầu làm việc cho công ty Tupperware,
chuyên bán hộp nhựa chứa thức ăn
Brownie Wise nghĩ ra một ý tưởng mang tính thời đại
Bà nghĩ tới việc tìm một nhóm người chuyên tổ chức 'tiệc Tupperware' cho bạn bè mình.
họ hàng, hàng xóm và đồng nghiệp.
Người dự tiệc sẽ được giới thiệu một loạt sản phầm của Tupperware.
Người tổ chức tiệc sẽ nhận được một phần hoa hồng từ doanh thu bán hàng trong bữa tiệc của đại diện nhãn hàng.
Khách dự tiệc đều biết điều này.
Họ biết bạn bè họ sẽ được trả tiền nếu họ mua hàng
từ đại diện nhãn hàng.
vậy nên, họ không chỉ mua cho bản thân họ, mà còn mua giúp
người tổ chức tiệc, cũng là bạn của họ.
Không chỉ có thế, bạn bè họ đã đổ thời gian và tiền bạc vào việc chuẩn bị đồ ăn.
và tổ chức bữa tiệc đó.
vậy nên, họ cũng có trách nhiệm tri ân trong việc này.
Chiến lược hiệu quả đó đến mức giúp doanh thu của công ty Tupperware hiện tại
đạt tới mức vài triệu đô-la một ngày qua 1,9 người bán hàng trực tiếp của họ.
Trong thực tế, cứ mỗi mỗi 2,3 giây có một bữa tiệc Tupperware được tổ chức.
và 'Tupperware' thường được nhắc tới như là một nhãn hàng chung cho tất cả các loại hộp chứa nhựa.
Cladini nhận ra rằng tình bạn và tình cảm giữa chugs ta có thể là một tác nhân quan trọng
we are persuaded.
The idea is that we should be more willing to comply with the requests of friends or
other liked individuals.
Tupperware sales depend on these social factors that persuade us at an interpersonal level.
Outside of our friendship network, there are also people trying to persuade us who are
not our friends.
Luckily, for them at least, liking can also be generated in other ways and used to persuade
us.
Physical attractiveness is one way of creating liking.
We generally see physically attractive people as being more talented, more kind, honest,
and intelligent (Eagly et al., 1991).
Attractive people can be more persuasive at changing attitudes (Chaiken, 1979) and also
in getting our agreement with requests (Benson et al., 1976).
Similarity between ourselves and others also produces liking.
We like those who are similar to us (Byrne, 1971).
Some sales training programs urge trainees to “mirror and match” the customer’s
body posture, mood, and verbal style because this can lead to greater persuasion.
Similarity in dress also increases liking and persuasion (Emswiller et al., 1971).
Cooperation can also create positive feelings, similar to liking (Aronson et al., 1978).
This is partly why when the car dealer goes into battle with the manager of the car yard
on your behalf, you are more likely to buy the car.
Giving someone a compliment before asking them to do something can increase your chances
because compliments can also create liking (Byrne &amp; Rhamey, 1965).
This is the case even if we know the compliments are untrue, and we know that the praiser stands
to gain something by complimenting us (Drachman et al., 1978).
While I remember, have I told you yet how intelligent and good looking you must be if
you are taking this course?
Clearly you are very perceptive and smart.
Before I forget, would you be willing to write a positive review of this course?
It would really help get the word out to as many people as possible.