In the 1950’s a single mother called Brownie Wise started working for the Tupperware company,
selling plastic containers for food storage.
Brownie Wise came up with a revolutionary idea.
Her idea was to get a range of people to host “Tupperware parties” for their friends,
relatives, neighbours, and work colleagues.
People go to these parties, and are shown a range of Tupperware products.
The host gets a cut of all of the sales sold by the representative at the party.
Everyone going to the party knows that.
They know that their friend is going to get some money if they buy something from the
representative.
So, they are kind of not only buying something for themselves, they’re also buying from
and for the host, who is their friend.
Not only that, their friend has arranged for the party, and spent money on food and time
organising it.
So, there is the obligation through reciprocation there too.
This was such a successful strategy that the Tupperware company now sells several millions
of dollars of product per day through their 1.9 million direct sales people.
There is actually a Tupperware party every 2.3 seconds around the world.
And the word “Tupperware” is often used as a generic label for plastic containers.
Cialdini found that our friendships and interpersonal liking can be a strong influence on how much
we are persuaded.
The idea is that we should be more willing to comply with the requests of friends or
other liked individuals.
Tupperware sales depend on these social factors that persuade us at an interpersonal level.
Outside of our friendship network, there are also people trying to persuade us who are
not our friends.
Luckily, for them at least, liking can also be generated in other ways and used to persuade
us.
Physical attractiveness is one way of creating liking.
We generally see physically attractive people as being more talented, more kind, honest,
and intelligent (Eagly et al., 1991).
Attractive people can be more persuasive at changing attitudes (Chaiken, 1979) and also
in getting our agreement with requests (Benson et al., 1976).
Similarity between ourselves and others also produces liking.
We like those who are similar to us (Byrne, 1971).
Some sales training programs urge trainees to “mirror and match” the customer’s
body posture, mood, and verbal style because this can lead to greater persuasion.
Similarity in dress also increases liking and persuasion (Emswiller et al., 1971).
Cooperation can also create positive feelings, similar to liking (Aronson et al., 1978).
This is partly why when the car dealer goes into battle with the manager of the car yard
on your behalf, you are more likely to buy the car.
Giving someone a compliment before asking them to do something can increase your chances
because compliments can also create liking (Byrne &amp; Rhamey, 1965).
This is the case even if we know the compliments are untrue, and we know that the praiser stands
to gain something by complimenting us (Drachman et al., 1978).
While I remember, have I told you yet how intelligent and good looking you must be if
you are taking this course?
Clearly you are very perceptive and smart.
Before I forget, would you be willing to write a positive review of this course?
It would really help get the word out to as many people as possible.