[MUSIC PLAYING] BLAKE MCKIMMIE: All right, Alex, thanks for joining us today.
ALEX HASLAM: Thank you.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So what I&#39;d like to do is just talk a little bit about Milgram&#39;s study
and the idea that around the end of World War II when people became aware of a lot of
the horrors and the atrocities that had been committed during the War, one of the explanations
that was commonly given for those events was that there must be something wrong with the
German people, and that&#39;s why they all went along with it.
Milgram conducted a study where participants were asked to shock learners.
And we&#39;ve heard about that so far in the course.
Now, he arrived at a slightly different-- or a very different explanation for why those
sort of horrific events happened.
Can you tell us a bit about that?
ALEX HASLAM: Yeah, so the Milgram-- Milgram did his studies sort of 15 years after the
war in the early &#39;60s.
And as you say, he was, I think, unconvinced by individual difference, personality-based
expectations of tyranny.
The pretty obvious point is that it seems unlikely that all the Germans had the same
personality, or they all had the same personality deficit, as it were, or pathology, that had
led to the kinds of events that you saw in the Holocaust.
So you needed some different type of explanation.
And Milgram was, I think, casting around, so he was trying to find what that might be.
He was quite influenced by the work of Solomon Asch on social influence.
So the idea that people were influenced by other people and perhaps would conform to
the views, wishes of other people was something that Milgram thought was plausible.
And so he devised a paradigm in which participants came in, and as the viewers will be kind of
aware, were asked to play the role of teachers in a learning experiment.
The experimenter instructed them that every time their learner made an error on the task,
they had to administer an increasing level of electric shock going up in 15 volt intervals
from 0 volts all the way to 450 volts, which was labeled XXX, beyond the point which was
labeled danger, a severe shock.
So ostensibly, they were-- this was actually all rigged, so none of the shocks were real.
But the participants didn&#39;t know that.
And obstensibly, the question is, would just a normal person, a resident of New Haven,
just outside or around Yale in Connecticut, would they be willing to kill somebody because
they were asked to do so by an experimenter in a psychology experiment?
When Milgram asked psychiatrists and other people whether they would, they all said,
of course, no, of course they wouldn&#39;t.
They said, maybe only 2% of people would go all the way to 450 volts because that&#39;s the
level of psychopathology in the community.
What Milgram found is-- again, pretty much everybody who studies psychology knows-- is
in what he called his baseline condition, that 65% of people went to the end of the
scale.
So that suggests that this was not a behavior that was peculiar to a very select group of
people, rather, there was something much more fundamental that is common to everybody&#39;s
psychology.
And his idea was that, in some sense, people are programmed to obey authority, that that&#39;s
the way society is structured, that&#39;s what we learn to do, and that we typically in kinds
of situations, where there is clear authority, we cede responsibility to them.
We cede accountability in many ways to them, and really ask, what is it that you want me
to do, and I will do it, rather than ask, what is it you&#39;re asking me to do?
And should I do it?
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So it&#39;s probably more about-- it&#39;s not about the personality, but it&#39;s more
about the social context that people are in.
ALEX HASLAM: That was Milgram&#39;s argument that this was very much a-- it was about the situation
not the person and that in these kinds of strong situations with these high demands
that most people would go along with those situational pressures.
So it was saying-- there&#39;s nothing really here about individuals, much more about the
situation.
The problem, though, was if you look at his data, first you see, well, actually not all
the participants went to the end.
Actually across all of his studies-- he had about 30 variants of his studies-- on average,
most participants didn&#39;t go to the end, and that in those studies, willingness to go to
the end varied from 100% in some conditions down to 0% in others.
So actually, the idea that we just go along with authority doesn&#39;t make sense either because
there&#39;s also clearly a lot of variability.
And the problem with Milgram&#39;s analysis that we just enter what he called an agentic state
where we just obey authority is that it doesn&#39;t really explain his own data either.
I think his contribution is important.
But it&#39;s clearly limited.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So you&#39;ve done a bit of work following up some of these ideas and exploring,
well, if that&#39;s not the explanation, what might actually be accounting for the behavior.
ALEX HASLAM: So it&#39;s, I think, there&#39;s lots of places you can kind of start on this.
But one of the most fruitful places to start is to look at the different versions of Milgram&#39;s
study.
As I said, there&#39;s about 30.
And look at, well, which were the ones where people went all the way?
And which were the ones where they didn&#39;t go all the way?
And what you see very clearly is that the ones where people went further was where they
were very locked into their identification with the experimenter and with the science
of the study.
And they were not exposed to the countervailing influences of the learner.
So what you see-- and actually in the baseline condition is where obedience is 65%.
They&#39;re torn between, should I listen to the experimenter, or should I listen to the learner?
And actually, what you see is depending on, I think, their patterns of identification,
the extent to which they identify with what the experimenter is trying to do versus with
what the participant is saying as a normal, decent member of society, depending on which
way they go, that&#39;s how they make-- that&#39;s the critical variable.
And what you see is in different versions of the study, Milgram actually varies the
extent to which the participants are oriented towards the experimenter or oriented towards
the learner.
If the learner is in the room next to them, then they identify much more with him-- it&#39;s
always a male-- and so they are much less likely to administer the shocks.
If the learner is not in the room, and, indeed, you don&#39;t hear from him, all you hear from
is the experimenter, then actually-- and that was in the very first study that Milgram did--
they go all the way to the end.
So again, it&#39;s really about identification and buying into the task that you&#39;re being
asked to contribute to.
And if you undermine the identification in some way or other by-- and there&#39;s lots of
ways in which Milgram does that-- what you see is that you don&#39;t get the effects that
everybody associates with that study.
So they&#39;re very much contingent upon participants thinking that what they&#39;re doing is worthwhile
and useful and helpful and valuable.
And to the extent that they believe, then, that that is the case, they do it.
It&#39;s not that they&#39;re blind, or they&#39;re ignorant, or they&#39;re stupid, or they&#39;re not paying attention.
They are paying attention.
They just think that this is a very important scientific project and that they&#39;re doing
something helpful.
And that&#39;s really a very-- and so they&#39;re cooperating with the experimenter and not
just obeying blindly.
And I think that lends itself to a very different understanding of why people commit-- perpetrate
obscene atrocities.
Again, typically what you find is not that they&#39;re just-- not they don&#39;t know what they&#39;re
doing.
They do it because they actually really believe in the cause that they&#39;re following and the
leadership of that cause.
And they also believe that it&#39;s actually a good and worthy cause.
That&#39;s actually very critical.
It&#39;s not that they think, oh, this is a bad thing, but I&#39;m just being asked to do it.
No, they&#39;ll actually convinced themself it&#39;s a good thing.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: And I think you&#39;ve also looked at what some of the participants in that study
actually said when they&#39;re interviewed after participating.
And if you look at the words they&#39;re using, it&#39;s clear they&#39;re not just blindly following.
They&#39;re often quite torn about what they&#39;re done, and--
ALEX HASLAM: Yeah, so I think the thing is, clearly, at that time, the participants are
very stressed by what they have to do.
But they steel themselves to that task, and they follow it through because they believe
that they&#39;re making a contribution to the science.
So yeah, this is-- they believe that this enterprise is valuable, so they struggle on.
And then at the end, of course, Milgram says, well, actually, thanks very much for participating
in the study.
You&#39;ve made a fantastic contribution to science because now we understand why people behave
in the way that you did and we see in other kinds of situations.
And the participants feel good about what they&#39;ve done because they&#39;ve made a contribution
to that.
So they actually-- Milgram does a really good job of explaining to them that they have,
indeed, been good subjects and that what they have done is good.
And one of the really interesting consequences of that is that while we have a sense as outsiders
that the participants must have felt pretty crappy because of what they&#39;d done, actually
they felt very good because they didn&#39;t really undersee it from other people&#39;s perspective--
look you&#39;ve done a terrible thing.
No, they didn&#39;t think they&#39;d done a terrible thing.
They thought they&#39;d done a good thing.
And actually, that really, really comes through in their responses.
They&#39;re happy is-- the signature hallmark emotion is one of happiness, not really of
stress or disaffection or regret even.
No, they think this is great.
I did a wonderful thing.
And Milgram helped them to see it that way.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So even after shocking somebody all the way to the end, they feel like they&#39;ve
actually achieved something.
ALEX HASLAM: They&#39;ve achieved something.
They&#39;ve been good participants.
They made a contribution to science.
They&#39;ve pushed science forward.
And of course, from Milgram&#39;s perspective, that was indeed what they had done.
They had made that contribution to this cause.
It&#39;s only as outsiders we say, well, but look, hang on a minute here.
You were pre-- you just killed this person for no good reason.
Well, there was a good reason.
And the reason was science.
And again, when you see people do bad things to other people, that&#39;s typically because
they believe in what they&#39;re doing and the value of it, the utility of it, and its contribution
to making the world a better place, not a worse place.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So knowing what we know now then, looking at it through those eyes, what
are the sorts of things you can do to maybe undermine some of the negative consequences
of following-- identifying with and following those sorts of goals?
ALEX HASLAM: Yeah, I mean, I think that&#39;s a very important question.
I mean what you see is that Milgram was able to induce obedience because he had created
a kind of total-- where he did, because he didn&#39;t always, bear in mind, when and where
he did-- it was because he created a totalizing environment where you didn&#39;t hear from the
other.
You weren&#39;t aware of the other potential perspectives or identities that were in play.
It was just about the science.
And you&#39;re caught up in the science.
And if you look at most organizations or enterprises which cultivate what we understand as evil,
what you see is they have that totalizing character.
So whether you&#39;re talking about extremist political groups or terrorist groups or cults,
again, it&#39;s very much about one version of reality, one leadership.
And those organizations go to a lot of difficulty to silence and to peripheralize other interests.
So again, you see that in totalitarian regimes.
You don&#39;t allow other perspectives to enter into people&#39;s consciousness.
So I think one issue there is that that&#39;s the importance of pluralistic democracies
in a sense is that they provide a perspective from which to critique your own stance.
And they allow you to sometimes step outside one identity and look at it from the perspective
of another identity.
And that&#39;s really very critical.
And I think with that, comes a particular form of insight and, indeed, a sort of recognition
that maybe what you&#39;re doing isn&#39;t quite as wonderful as it is presented as being.