BLAKE MCKIMMIE: Well, thanks for joining us, Barbara.
So, hostile sexism seems to be a pretty obviously negative attitude towards women.
And benevolent sexism, on the face of it, looks to be a pretty positive attitude.
Now, it seems like a bit of a contradiction to believe in both, but the research shows
that they&#39;re quite-- you know, people who believe in one tend to also believe in the
other.
How&#39;s that possible?
BARBARA MASSER: So you&#39;re right, hostile sexism, whether directed towards men, or directed
towards women, seems like a fairly negative attitude towards people of that gender.
If we concentrate on just women, it&#39;s a belief that women are incompetent, inferior to men.
And it&#39;s based on this notion of women being inherently very competitive or trying to take,
usurp men&#39;s power.
Benevolent sexism, at least on a surface level, looks very positive.
It&#39;s full of positive connotations towards women, it looks very much like chivalry.
And the person who holds those attitudes can feel very positive about themselves, because
they only wish well towards women, and they&#39;re trying to protect them and trying to look
after them.
But I guess once you go beyond the surface, you can start to see that it has its roots
in the same sort of ideology that hostile sexism does.
In that it comes from a fundamental belief that women are inferior to men, and therefore
in the context of benevolent sexism, need to be protected because they&#39;re inferior and
can&#39;t cope without men by their side.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So one of the interesting things about the research on benevolent sexism
and hostile sexism is it&#39;s not just men who believe in these things, it seems to be also
that, to a large extent, women have similar levels of belief in hostile and benevolent
sexism.
BARBARA MASSER: Yeah, so when you look at mean scores on the hostile and benevolent
subscales of the ambivalent sexism inventory, you can see that often you get a gender difference
in scores on the hostile sex subscale, so that men typically score higher than women.
But when you look at scores on the benevolent sexism subscale, it&#39;s not that unusual not
to get a difference.
So women endorse these statements to the same degree that men endorse those statements.
And that&#39;s probably related to the subjectively positive tone of those statements-- they&#39;re
saying nice things about women and their relationship with men.
And so it&#39;s not unusual to get equivalent scores on that subscale.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: Now are these sorts of beliefs sort of, you know, specific to a particular
cultural background?
Or is there evidence that they&#39;re fairly common around the world?
BARBARA MASSER: There was a large scale study done that sampled over 15,000 people from
19 different countries, and what you see there is there are, obviously, variations in the
level of endorsement of hostile and benevolent sexism.
But the two subscales always remained positively associated, so people who tend to endorse
hostile sexism also tend to endorse benevolent sexism.
And in fact, the level of hostile and benevolent sexism were associated with the level of gender
inequality in the country.
So these do tend to be pretty prevalent beliefs, with some variation, obviously, in mean levels,
but they are prevalent in a wide range of cultures around the world.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: And probably, you know, the most important question-- what effect do they
have on people?
You know, if you really believe in benevolent sexism, how&#39;s it going to affect how you treat
people?
BARBARA MASSER: Well, it&#39;s a curious thing.
So I mean, obviously, I think if you think about hostile and benevolent sexism, how can
you reconcile if you&#39;re like, both loving and hating women simultaneously?
And I think this occurs mainly because people tend to subtype women and direct their different
forms of prejudice, their hostile or their benevolent sexism towards different subtypes.
So when we look at the research, and certainly the very early research in this area, we saw
that hostile sexism was really directed towards women who were challenging men for power in
society.
So people like feminists and career women were negatively evaluated by those who endorse
hostile sexist views.
And we see that come through in the research since, in terms of outcomes.
When we look at benevolent sexism, benevolent sexism is related to positively endorsing
groups like housewives, or women who don&#39;t overtly challenge the status quo in terms
of the gender hierarchy.
Because both hostile and benevolent sexism actually feed into that sort of legitimizing
ideology which keep women in an inferior position to men.
So when we look at the behavioral effects of hostile and benevolent sexism, hostile
sexism looks like pretty much any other prejudice that we could recognize.
So it&#39;s related to negative evaluations of those women I just spoke about.
So it&#39;s related to negatively evaluating women in workplace, particularly when those women
are challenging for higher management positions within those workplaces.
But more recently, we actually also see that hostile sexism has some quite negative implications
for men.
So there&#39;s been a great deal of work done recently looking on relationship implications
of endorsing hostile or benevolent sexism.
And men who endorse hostile sexism tend to be less satisfied in their relationships,
they have a more antagonistic view towards that partner.
And generally they&#39;re quite unhappy, because of their fundamental beliefs they have about
women and what women are trying to do, which is essentially take their power away.
I think, also, when you look at the effects of hostile sexism in terms of experiencing
that as a woman, if someone is hostilely sexist towards you, it&#39;s very easy to recognize that
it&#39;s a form of prejudice or it&#39;s a form of sexism.
And what we see in the literature is that women obviously feel quite angry about that,
they can immediately attribute this to being a form of prejudice, they get angry about
it.
And it actually results in some cardiovascular reactivity, but it&#39;s like a flash fire, so
it comes and it goes pretty quickly.
What we also see is it also motivates women because they recognize it very quickly as
a form of prejudice to engaging collective action.
So while it may build their uncertainty about their group and make them feel quite uncomfortable
about the fact that women are being discriminated against, it actually motivates them to actually
do something about this inequality they see in society.
So hostile sexism, because it&#39;s quite blatant, quite easy to identify, can actually have
quite a motivating impact to women when they experience it.
Benevolent sexism on the other hand, is a bit more difficult, because you&#39;re actually
faced with someone who&#39;s saying something quite positive towards you and yet there&#39;s
an uneasy undertone that actually the bigger implication of what they&#39;re saying is less
than positive.
And because women have more trouble in identifying it or attributing it directly to being a form
of prejudice, or this person is discriminating against me, that causes longer-termed effects.
So in terms of cardiovascular reactivity, they have a less intense reaction to it, but
it&#39;s a slow burn, it takes longer to recover from.
And that&#39;s really because it&#39;s kind of ambiguous.
You know, am I reacting to something more or is this person just being nice or are they
being prejudiced towards me?
So it&#39;s a slow burn reaction.
And when we look at the research that&#39;s looked at how women cope in the workplace when people
are benevolently sexist towards them, we can see that it causes them some confusion.
They suffer an impact in terms of self-efficacy, in terms of their confidence, or about their
competence.
But it also impacts in terms of things like mental intrusions-- they feel confused about
what they&#39;re actually encountering.
So it has a more insidious and long-lasting effect, which is really difficult to counter,
because of course this person is just being nice to you.
We also have seen that there&#39;s been a whole bunch of research done on the effects of benevolent
sexism in relationships.
So there&#39;s been a really nice longitudinal study that shows that women who are in relationships
with men who are benevolently sexist, actually then tend to alter their personal level of
benevolent sexism to match their partner&#39;s.
But what we can see is that when that person-- that woman has a high level of benevolent
sexism and the relationship starts to go wrong, obviously that&#39;s more confronting to her and
less pleasant, because all her ideals about what a relationship should be have gone out
the window.
And so it can have a more long-lasting harm for those individuals.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: So to sum up, it can basically have like, a pervasive effect on people&#39;s
interpersonal relationships, but then also how they treat work colleagues and just generally
perceive the social world.
BARBARA MASSER: Absolutely, because you clearly attribute it [INAUDIBLE] this person is clearly
saying something very negative or very nasty about me as an individual, it has that kind
of underpinning effect, whereby you&#39;re a little bit uneasy with this individual.
Are they being nice to me or are they being nasty to me?
And it can undermine all aspects of your performance, which, of course, just goes towards the greater
will of benevolent sexists, which is to keep women in the place that is inferior to men.
BLAKE MCKIMMIE: Thank you.