Việc đúng đắn về mặt chính trị hơn không có nghĩa là
những định kiến nhất định về người Mỹ Trắng
và Mỹ Đen được cải thiện.
Điều mọi người nghĩ không phải lúc nào cũng phản ánh điều họ nói.
Và diều họ nói không phải lúc nào cũng phản ánh điều họ làm.
Vì thế, nếu chúng ta bám lấy vấn đề phân biệt chủng tộc trong cuộc sống hiện thời, chúng ta phải
Bắt đầu với kiến thức dó.
Tôi không biết bao nhiêu người trong số các bạn đã từng bị cáo buộc là có định kiến vào một lúc nào đó
trong cuộc đời.
Bạn kể một chuyện đùa, và mọi người sợ chết khiếp.
Hoặc là, bạn cho vài câu phê bình, và mọi người phỏng đoán là bạn phân biệt chủng tộc.
Nếu chuyện này đã từng xảy ra với bạn, gần như chắc chắn rằng mọi người quanh bạn đã hoảng loạn.
Người ta không thích bị cáo buộc là phân biệt chủng tộc, và họ cố gắng tỏ ra
rằng họ không phân biệt.
Thái độ điềm tĩnh về chủng tộc đã trở thành một quy tắc đạo dức cực kỳ mạnh mẽ.
Nhưng trong vài hoàn cảnh, những cảm xúc tiêu cực này vẫn âm ỉ bên trong.
Vậy thì, khi nào những cảm xúc tiêu cực này sẽ rò rỉ ra bên ngoài và trở thành thành kiến?
Gaertner &amp; Dovidio vào năm 1986 đã tranh luận trong thuyết phân biệt chủng tộc ác cảm của họ rằng phần lớn mọi người
được thúc đẩy duy trì hình tượng không thành kiến-- họ thấy thành kiến chủng tộc
aversive, and endorse fair treatment of all groups, and fear appearing prejudiced.
However, many of these people do subconsciously harbour negative feelings toward those from
minority groups.
And discrimination leaks out in situations where behaviour can be justified as non-prejudiced.
In 2000, Dovidio and Gaertner investigated the change in people’s racial prejudice
and biases over a 10-year period.
Dovidio and Gaertner asked white college students to assess the credentials of white and black
candidates for a job.
The actual qualifications for both white and
the black candidates were the same.
However, there were three sets of qualifications that differed.
The qualifications of both the applicants were either strong, ambiguous, or weak.
Strong qualifications consisted of information that included:
Being co-captain of the swim team in high school
Being a member of the disciplinary board in college
Being sensitive, intelligent, and relaxed.
Ambiguous qualifications consisted of information that included:
Being co-captain of the swim team in high school
Being sensitive, intelligent, and emotional.
Weak qualifications consisted of information that included:
Being co-captain of the chess team in high school
Being independent, forthright, and intense. Consistent with other research, Dovidio and
Gaertner found that general self-reports of prejudice were lower in 1998 when compared
to reports from 10 years prior.
However, in both time periods, white participants did not favour the white candidate when both
the candidates’ qualifications were clearly strong or weak.
In fact, participants actually viewed the black candidate more favorably than the white
candidate when their credentials were very strong or very weak.
However, participants were more likely to
recommend the white candidate for the job when the candidates’ qualifications were
ambiguous.
In line with the theory of aversive racism, it seems that, although self-reports of racial
prejudice may have declined over the years, it’s possible that there’s still subtle
manifestations of racial bias.Therefore, it seems that, in situations of uncertainty,
people are less likely to give the minority group members the “benefit of the doubt”.