[MUSIC PLAYING]
https://youtu.be/7tJW4a4RlTo
Following on from Helen's topic,
which discussed early
childhood settings, in this
topic we're going to explore
some of the codes and laws and
standards that guide and
govern Australian practise when
working with children.
Let's start by talking
about regulations.
In Australia we have national
regulations.
These are law.
These are things that have been
passed in legislation.
And they're rules that
govern our practise.
So some examples of regulations
might be that
anybody who wants to work with
children is required to have
the appropriate
working-with-children check.
So these checks that they
haven't got a criminal history
that would prevent them from
working with children
appropriately.
We also have regulations about
the number of staff per
children in an early
childhood setting.
These are called ratios.
So these are things
that are law.
They're set in concrete.
There's no shifting those.
The only time they change is
when legislation is passed to
change them.
The next thing we'll have a look
at is what's called the
National Quality Standard.
In Australia we have the
National Quality Standard as
our assessment and
writing tool.
It's a way that we can look
at all the early childhood
settings and services that are
provided and write the quality
of the service that's
being provided to
children and their families.
Within the National Quality
Standard there are different
quality areas.
And these cover everything from
health and safety, such
as hygiene practises and food
handling practises, right
through to relationships
with children.
So how warm and reciprocal are
the relationships that are
happening between educators and
children in their service?
The next guiding document that
we'll have a look at is
Australia's national framework
for early learning, and that's
called the Early Years
Learning Framework.
The Early Years Learning
Framework guides educators in
their practise, so the way
that they do what it
is that they do.
It also gives them some guiding
principles for working
with children, as well as
providing the learning
outcomes that children should
really be achieving when
they're in early childhood
settings.
Next we'll have a look at the
Early Childhood Australia's
Code of Ethics.
This is a code of ethics
for people who are
working with children.
The code of ethics talks to us
about how, as professionals
working with children, there are
certain practises that we
really need to abide by.
Last but certainly not least,
we've got the UN's Charter on
the Rights of the Child.
This is a charter of articles
that outlines what the United
Nations signatories believe are
rights for children, so
what children have a right to.
Very similar to the Human Rights
Charter, but this is
specifically about children's
rights.
&quot;Acknowledge the uniqueness and
potential of all children
in recognition that enjoying
their childhood without undue
pressure is important.&quot; This
is an example of one of the
ECA Code of Ethics.
And it speaks to what we talked
about at the very start
of this module when we spoke
about the uniqueness of
children and the importance of
allowing children to develop
at their own rate and
their own pace.
&quot;Every child has the right to
relax, play, and join in a
wide range of cultural and
artistic activities.&quot; This
quote is an example of one of
the articles from the UN
Charter on the Rights
of the Child.
It also relates back to
information that Helen gave us
in one of the earlier topics
in the module about the
importance of play and how
children learn when they play.
OK, so just to recap, we
discussed the laws, the
regulations that we
have in place.
And these are the rules
that don't change.
They provide the foundations
for our
early childhood settings.
Then we looked at the quality
standards and the framework,
both of which are guiding
documents that help us with
our structure, our
practise, and the
principles in our service.
And finally, we looked at the
ECA Code of Ethics and the UN
Charter on the Rights
of the Child.
These are our overarching
documents that inform all the
other things that we do in
early childhood settings.
But it's important to remember
when you're looking for an
early childhood setting, either
for your own child or
if you're thinking about working
in one, that you do
some investigation.
Because there's lots of
different settings out there,
like Helen talked about
earlier in the module.
And remember that each setting
is going to be unique, just
like children are unique.