Hi, my name's Andrew Heys, and
welcome to this subject,
Negotiation and Conflict
Resolution.
I'm a lecturer at Macquarie
Graduate School of Management
at Macquarie University
in Sydney, and I teach
negotiation in our MBA.
In this subject I'm going to
introduce you to the field of
negotiation and conflict
resolution.
I want to introduce you to a
little bit about this world
that I inhabit with my students
and with my clients.
I want to give you some ideas
about how you can take your
negotiation and your conflict
resolution to the next level.
The field of negotiation,
conflict resolution, is quite
fascinating and I've been lucky
enough throughout my
career to work as a university
lecturer, a corporate trainer,
a consultant, and a mediator,
involved in this field both as
an educator and as
a practitioner.
So I want to bring some of that
experience to the table
in this course and give you an
idea of not only some of the
knowledge in this field, but
also some of the practical
aspects of how you can
take these skills and
put them into practice.
It's a fascinating area and my
students often talk to me
about how the frameworks and the
ideas and the skills that
they've learned in my courses
have been useful not only for
them in their business lives--
whether that be negotiating with
their customers or the
suppliers--
but also in their personal lives
in terms of enhancing
their relationships with their
families, with their partners,
in their communities.
And so it's a really practical
skill for you to develop
through this format.
Negotiations apply in families,
in personal
relationships, in communities,
in national affairs, and
international affairs.
So there's a lot of great
examples we can draw upon and
I'll be doing that throughout
the course.
In this course we'll be looking
at four modules.
The first module is called
Thinking Like a Negotiator.
In this module, what I want to
do is introduce you to some of
the terminology that we use to
describe different elements
within a negotiation.
I want to introduce you to
some different styles of
negotiation.
This will help you recognize the
type of negotiation that
you're in and the way that you
need to respond and behave to
be successful within
that given context.
I also, in this first module,
want to look at the concept of
thinking like a negotiator.
I want to introduce you to
some thinking errors that
people commonly make when
they're negotiating.
These stem from some pretty
fundamental intuitive
responses we have to a context
such as negotiation.
In the second module, I want
to look at some different
phases of negotiation, and I
want to introduce you to what
we can broadly term five main
phases that we see in
negotiation, passing through.
I want to introduce you to some
skills that you need to
use at each stage of that
negotiation, and some things
to watch out for, and some
errors that people can make.
So we'll start to really break
down a negotiation into its
component parts.
The third module, we're going
to be looking at conflict
resolution.
I'm going to introduce you to
some theories of conflict and
some theories of conflict
resolution.
I want to give you some
insights into what
philosophers and various social
scientists, some very
famous names, have said about
conflict, what causes it, and
we'll look at some
pathways for how
conflict can be resolved.
In the final module, I want to
really focus and drill down on
communication skills.
We're going to focus on about
seven or eight main skills
that we'll look at, that you
can use, when you're
approaching a negotiation
or a conflict.
These skills will be put in
context by us referring to a
couple of case studies that I'm
going to introduce you to
throughout the course, and
that we will refer to at
different stages.
We come to a question
now which is,
when should I negotiate?
And in fact, what
is negotiation?
Let's start with what
is negotiation.
Negotiation is problem solving
between people who are in an
interdependent relationship.
You'll notice I didn't say
dependent, and I didn't say
independent--
interdependent.
People who are in interdependent
relationships
depend on one another.
I depend on you and
you depend on me.
Irrespective of an instance
where, for example, you may do
nothing, you might be unwilling
to move forward, I
can't move forward because
you're doing nothing.
So let's say you aren't
responding to a proposal.
I can't move forward
with the project.
So I'm in an interdependent
relationship with you and we
have to work together.
That implies a style of
negotiation as well, which is
a collaborative style
of working together.
It's interesting why we
shouldn't negotiate.
Sometimes I think people
negotiate when they don't
actually need to.
They can make an independent
decision.
They've got legitimate
authority.
They've got the means to do
something by themselves and
yet they choose to negotiate.
Why shouldn't you negotiate?
Essentially the reason is this,
negotiation typically
involves what we call
concessions.
A concession means you're giving
something up, something
you wouldn't normally give
to the other side,
to fashion an agreement.
A concession involves usually
some material cost, some
financial cost, or some extra
effort on your part.
So we typically trade
concessions when we're
undertaking a negotiation.
I want you to also start this
course out with a degree of
confidence.
I want to give you a quote, and
that's this, "Negotiation
is a learned skill."
A learned skill--
there's no gene for
negotiation.
You should be able to, through
some focused effort and some
concentration, some deep
debriefing and some planning,
you should be able to execute
a negotiation reasonably
effectively, particularly if you
concentrate and do some of
the exercises through
the course.
And I'll suggest to you, you
maybe want to go to the
discussion boards and debrief a
little bit with some of the
other people taking
the course.
Share some of your stories and
maybe get some feedback and
some input from others about
how you're going.
There's a nice way of describing
negotiations, and
it's by an American author
called Lee Thompson.
What she talks about is the
difference between a
negotiation of opportunity and
she then contrasts that with a
negotiation of necessity.
Let me talk about those
for a moment.
A negotiation of opportunity
is where we spot an
opportunity to negotiate,
but it's not compulsory.
Let's say for example, you
notice that your job's getting
more responsibility or
a heavier workload.
That's an opportunity, surely,
for you to negotiate a higher
salary with your boss
or your employer.
Negotiation of opportunity
might be talking to your
housemate about how you
reorganize the workload for
the share house you live in,
or with your partner to
arrange so you can both
pursue more of you
hobbies on the weekend.
An opportunity negotiation is
one where we need to open up
the opportunity to negotiate.
We can contrast that with a
negotiation of necessity, and
this is one that we
have to undertake.
A good example of a negotiation
of necessity is an
enterprise bargaining agreement,
which happens every
three years between an employer
and a group of
employees, usually represented
by a union.
An EBA negotiation, as they're
called-- enterprise bargaining
agreement, has to take place
every three years for the
negotiation agreement to be
current, for it to reflect the
conditions of the employer, and
the cost of living, for
example, for employees.
So that's one that we have
to undertake, even though
sometimes it might be a little
bit laborious, and it can be
quite acrimonious at times, we
have to renew that agreement.
So it's a negotiation that we
have to do by necessity.
So there's two quite different
types of negotiation.
I'd like to introduce you now
to a little case study we're
going to come back
to periodically
throughout the course.
It's two people I used to
work with, Anne and Joe.
We worked in a consulting
firm, we had this shared
services arrangement, where we
had some researchers who did
work for the consultants.
Joe was a sort of guy who used
to work reasonably, in a
steady sort of pace.
He used to do a lot of very
considered work and he would
get these researchers doing
extended projects for him.
Anne, on the other
hand, traveled a
lot with her clients.
She would come home and she
was always a little bit
frazzled and rushed.
She would quickly want to have
the researchers working on her
projects straight away.
So she'd kind of run in and dump
work and expect it to be
done the next day.
These two people really clashed
over their very
different work styles, and yet
they had to share this
resource of the researchers'
time.
So we're going to look at this
quite simple and quite
commonplace problem we would see
in a workplace of sharing
a shared resource when two
people have very different
styles of work.
I'll give you some examples when
we look at Anne and Joe
and how they interact to give
you some examples of how they
might negotiate this agreement
more effectively.
I also like to direct you to
the discussion boards.
And there's quite a lot of
activity that goes on in these
boards, in the Open2Study
units.
So if you head there you can
make some comments about your
own negotiations, give some
feedback to others about how
you might have approached
that.
You can talk about the ideas and
it's a social way of you
sharing ideas and becoming
involved with others who are
doing the course.