Welcome to module two.
In the last module, we
introduced the field of
negotiation and conflict
resolution, and I introduced
you to some subtle differences
in the language of
negotiation.
We talked a little bit about the
concept of strategy in the
negotiation process.
And I talked about some
different cognitive
heuristics, and some thinking
problems that cause us to make
faulty decisions when we're
trying to negotiate.
In this module, we're going
to look at the negotiation
process, which is, I suspect,
why some of you are doing this
course in the first place.
Broadly speaking, there are five
stages that a negotiation
will move through.
So we'll look in this topic
at the structure of a
negotiation.
And those five phases
are these.
We'll look, first
of all, at the
preparation/planning stage.
And it's really important to
plan your negotiation, plan
your strategy, think about how
you'll negotiate, and do some
research and analysis before
you sit down to negotiate.
And we'll cover that.
Then we're going to look at
the agenda setting stage.
So this is when the parties come
together, when they set
the scene, they talk about the
context for the negotiation,
and also the particular
issues that they're
going to talk about.
And sometimes they'll also try
to steer the negotiation away
from issues they don't
want to talk about.
We'll also, then, look at stage
three, which is the
proposal and counter-proposal
stage.
And this is where parties are
making proposals to one
another that formulate
an option.
And then they move into the
all-familiar bargaining phase.
And this is where parties swap
concessions, and sometimes
tactics emerge in this stage.
And we have to be thinking very
carefully about how we
make concessions and how
we trade concessions.
And I'm going to talk about
those skills and some
strategies to use there.
And then we talk about how we
move into the final stage,
which is finalizing agreement.
And this is putting it all into
practice, coming to the
final terms that we're going to
settle on, and moving the
negotiation towards
an implementation.
So these five phases are quite
generic, in a sense, in a
negotiation.
Not all negotiations will move
this cleanly through these
five stages as this module, or
this topic, may make it seem.
Sometimes negotiations move
around, and they're a little
bit complex and unstructured.
But I want to just introduce
this as a framework for you to
guide your negotiation, and to
allow us to talk about some
different stages and some
micro-skills that we'll use
throughout any negotiation.
When we think about the first
stage of negotiation, we think
about what we do before
a negotiation begins.
I like to liken that process to
what I would call the "back
office" of negotiation--
all the preparation we do that
allows the front office to be
successful.
So the better prepared you are
before a negotiation begins,
the more flexible, the more
responsive you can be once all
the action starts.
So let's think about three main
things that we can do
before a negotiation begins.
And those three things are
research, planning, and some
emotional preparation.
So those three points are a good
way of summarizing all
the things that we can do in
what we call the "back office"
of a negotiation.
Your research will entail
analyzing the market, the
context that you're in--
trying to understand people's
predisposition to what you
might be arguing.
So for example, if you're buying
a house, you want to
know it's a buyer's market or a
seller's market, to know how
much competition you've got.
And also, what the buyer's
thinking--
whether they're desperate to
sell or whether there's plenty
of buyers lining up.
So we want to understand that
context, and we want to do a
little bit of research about
our own position.
Maybe there's an objective
standard that we can quote
when we're negotiating.
The second thing we want
to think about
is doing some planning.
So we're going to work out
what concessions we might
make, what concessions the other
side might be willing to
make, what they might be looking
for, what our common
ground and our common interests
are, and what
objections the other side might
have to our proposition
and what we might
be proposing.
And then the third point is we
want to get ourselves ready
emotionally.
Negotiations can be quite
fraught in terms of the
emotional intensity that we'll
experience when we're in front
of the other person.
And we want to think about what
those emotions might be,
and get ourselves ready to
negotiate emotionally.
And if there's one thing that we
can do to make the biggest
difference in terms of the
outcomes that we achieve when
we negotiate, it's
to plan more.
Most people don't spend enough
time in that back office.
They assume that every
negotiation's generic, or they
assume that they've got the
skills and they'll know what
to say on the day.
But I really advise you to spend
a little bit more time
before you actually
start negotiating.
Let's drill down into
these three elements
a little bit further.
Let's start with research.
So if we think about researching
the situation, the
market beforehand, what can we
do to do that effectively?
If you're buying a house,
obviously you want to scan the
market, the same type
of houses that
you're looking for.
If you're going for a new job,
you might want to look for
what the pay or the salary and
benefits might be for a
comparable position.
You could ring your friends up
and put the word out in your
in network--
does anybody work in
this industry?
What would I expect
to be paid?
What could I ask for?
That way, we've got some
objective standard that we can
use to compare a negotiation
outcome against.
We want to have that
objectivity, that weight to
support our argument.
So research can also entail
researching the market--
or our counterparty, sorry,
who we're going to be
negotiating with.
How do they typically
negotiate?
What sort of clauses
do they put in?
What sort of arguments do
they typically make?
We can do a lot of research
before a negotiation begins so
that we're really
well informed.
And information is power.
The second thing we want to
do is to do some planning.
So let's take, for example,
our house purchase.
When we think about planning
our approach to a house
purchase, usually people
focus solely on price.
That's not the only thing
that we can negotiate.
Let's think about what else
we can negotiate.
Price is obviously going
to be up there.
But we also want to think
about settlement--
that is, how long will it take
before we pay the bulk of the
purchase price.
We might think about repairs--
are we going to ask them to do
any repairs on the house
before we settle?
We might also ask about
inclusions--
so what else do we get as part
of this purchase price?
Are we're going to be getting
the blinds, the plants?
We want to think about all the
things that we can negotiate,
not just price.
So when we're planning, we want
to think about, what do
we want from this negotiation?
What's reasonable to ask?
What might there be some
flexibility on?
It might be that the other side
wants to settle quickly
and we've got plenty of time.
Well, that gives us a
bargaining point.
So we need to do that planning
of our own position before we
sit down to negotiate.
And the final thing we want to
accomplish in the back office
is around our emotions.
What are we likely to feel when
we're sitting in front of
the person who we're going
to be negotiating with?
That idea of our emotional
readiness is a complex one.
But if we want to think about a
few simple tips, we want to
get ready to--
to be ready for the emotions
that we're likely to feel.
And so we can think about the
process of sensitization, or
desensitization.
That is, we can do a role play
where we might ask somebody to
become angry with us.
Maybe we could get them to play
the role as realistically
as they could so we can actually
experience some of
the emotions that we're likely
to feel in the moment the next
time we we're talking
to this real person.
We can also think about how
we're going to cope with those
strong emotions that we're
going to be experiencing.
So what are some ways that we're
going to deal with that?
We might think about, what
is it that gets us most
comfortable with that?
To give you an example, let's
say it's Sunday afternoon and
you're enjoying a nice lunch
with your friends.
Then all of a sudden, you get
this horrible, knotting
feeling in your stomach.
You're anxious about something
out of the blue.
It's probably not indigestion
from your lunch.
Maybe it's anxiety about what's
happening the next day
for you at work.
Well, those emotions are
telling you something.
They're telling you that you're
either not ready enough
or that you feel strongly about
it, or obviously it's a
strong emotion coming up like
anxiety, fear, or anger about
the situation.
So I think it's a good idea to
take some time after your
lunch is finished.
Write down why you're
feeling that.
Write down maybe a little
bit more preparation.
And steel yourself
emotionally.
So become a little bit detached
from your emotions--
understand, why am I feeling
so strongly about this.
Am I under-prepared?
Do I need to do a bit
more preparation?
Do I need to get a bit more rest
or think about how I'm
going to approach
the negotiation?
So don't let that emotion
just simmer.
Do something about it.