OK.
And this topic--
it's our final topic
for the module.
And this is around implementing
your plan.
At the end of an agreement,
we usually put in
place an action plan.
Who's going to do what?
When's it going to start?
How do we get this
thing rolling?
I think it's a good idea to
start to be really realistic
at this stage.
So is this plan going to work?
We need to reality test before
we actually agree to it.
Once we've got that agreement in
place, we need to start to
put it in place, and we
need to stick to it.
Having said that, once we get
an agreement in place,
sometimes, we realize that
it has some weaknesses.
Sometimes, we realize that hey,
maybe we're going to need
to revise this a little bit.
So in the case of Anne and Joe,
where it's a relatively
informal agreement, they
probably want to do a review
or a check back with one another
after a few months.
Hey, is this working for you?
Because it's working
for me in this way.
This is a little thing
I'd like to change.
But in general terms,
it's working.
With a contract, that will be
a lot more difficult to do,
obviously, because we've signed
and we've committed and
we've got a legally enforceable
document that
says, hey, this is the terms
of our agreement.
That's always going to be true
if we're working in the one
jurisdiction.
But sometimes, in international
business, we
might be working across two
different jurisdictions.
And we may actually have trouble
enforcing a contract.
So we really need to be a little
bit more flexible in
some cultural contexts, where
we're willing to amend and
flex and shape an agreement
so that it works on
going for the parties.
Some agreements--
for example, in the IT industry,
we have what are
called service level
agreements.
And a service level agreement is
something where we agree on
the response time, the amount
of hour of maintenance, the
amount of hours of support that
we are supplying to a
customer to support that IT
infrastructure that we've put
in place or the software that
the customer has bought.
And that service level agreement
is something that
the parties are essentially
committing to.
This is what we're buying
from you, Mr. Provider.
What you don't want to have
happen is every meeting, we
drag out the contract or every
meeting we drag out the
service level agreement, and it
becomes this formal binding
contractually-based
discussion.
Obviously, this sets the
commercial terms for the
arrangement.
But we want to still manage
the relationship.
We want to still nurture
And we want to build a
relationship that the contract
just formalizes.
So we want to, if we can,
particularly in commercial
client-based negotiations,
keep the agreement in the
background.
It's there if we need it, but
what we want to do is manage
the ongoing relationship
as well.
So just because you've got a
contract doesn't mean you can
forget about the relationship.
Implementation requires ongoing
commitment and ongoing trust.
Sometimes, we need to
do a review and
check that it's working.
But as a general rule, we
want to stick to what
we've agreed to.
So this module has looked at
the phases of negotiation.
I've broken negotiation down
into five main phases.
Of course, as I said at the
outset, sometimes a
negotiation isn't always as
clean and neat as stage one,
stage two, stage three,
et cetera.
Sometimes, it'll move
around a bit.
But try to recognize when you're
moving from one phase
to the next in a negotiation,
and recognize when
it's time to move.
OK.
We've talked about it--
enough.
Let's move on to bargaining.
OK.
We've got most of our
issue sorted out.
Let's now move to the
agreement phase.
We've got an agreement, now
let's implement it.
You need to just keep watch
of how the negotiation is
progressing.
In the next module, we're going
to look at conflict
resolution.
It's a little bit different to
what we've been talking about
so far with negotiation.
We're really going to focus in
on conflicts rather than
negotiation.