In this topic, I want to
look at the language of
negotiation.
And I want to draw some
distinctions for you in some
different elements we can
look at and focus on in
negotiation.
And I want to give you some
insight into how we use
language in order to
be more effective
in building an agreement.
The first thing I want to
start with is to draw a
distinction between
what are called
positions and interests.
Positions in a negotiation are
usually a starting point.
That is one side will say we
want this project completed by
next Monday, and that's our
absolute drop dead date.
It's got to be done
by this date.
Or I'll pay you $500,000 for
your apartment and I won't pay
you another penny more.
This is my final position, or
this is my bottom line.
Those are good examples of
positional language.
And they are a feature of
distributed negotiation.
People take a position, and
they stick to it, and they
hold on to that position
for dear life.
That becomes their starting
point or sometimes it's their
bottom line.
And positions in negotiation
are important first to
understand, but they're also
important for us to be able to
deal with and manage, to manage
that positional language.
We want to also contrast that
with what sometimes sits
behind a position which is what
people call our interests.
And interests in negotiation
are a broader suite of
concerns, the things
that are driving us
often to take a position.
So we can sort of articulate
these as
being why we want something.
This is the underlying
suite of interests.
And in integrative negotiation,
we usually like
to focus more on interests.
So we bargain and we solve
problems by identifying one
another's separate interests and
also try and then identify
what are our common interests?
What are the things that we both
have driving our behavior
or our coming to the table
in this negotiation?
So positions in interests.
Why is it useful to focus
on interests?
Interests are more malleable.
We can come up with different
solutions to make the interests.
Whereas a position is a firmer
statement of intent.
And it will sometimes
conflict with the
other side's positions.
So what we want to try and
do is drill down into the
interests and work out what's
driving the behavior.
Let's look at another sort
of contrast here.
Another way of thinking about
some language here.
Sometimes you'll hear people
in negotiation say, well, I
think the solution is this.
What we have to do is
we have to structure
the deal this way.
This is the solution I believe
that we need to come up with.
Well, that's very, dogmatic
language, very firm language.
It may be perceived as
pushy or boorish
from the other side.
This is what you
have to accept.
We need to try and be a little
bit more inviting and
collaborative in our language.
So I think a better word
than solutions is
to talk about options.
Be more inviting, more
suggestive in our language.
Perhaps an option here, what we
could try is, let's think
about an option that we could
solve this problem with, or
could we try.
This is the sort of language
that invites the other side to
consider to participate in
designing the solution.
And then we come up with
something that we both had
some input into.
And so using the word options
is more preferable to using
the word solution.
So when we use this
more collaborative
language, we get by in.
We get the other side buying
into the outcome
and designing it.
So how can we apply this
knowledge that there's a
difference between positions
and interests?
Really the answer to that
question lies in what we
choose to respond to
in an negotiation.
So, for example, if another side
makes a very positional
claim or a positional statement,
we could, of
course, and maybe it's human
nature to some extent, respond
with our own position.
All right, if you're going to
say that, then we're not going
to accept anything less
than whatever it is.
So we can make the negotiations
start to escalate
and your position can be matched
with my position.
And we can get into a slaying
match, and we can be like two
goats on the edge of a
cliff banging heads.
What we want to do is we
want to be a little bit
smarter than that.
The other side gives us a
position, we might either
choose to ignore that position
and we might divert the
conversation away from that.
Or we could probe into
the interests that
sit behind a position.
And this is essentially by
asking why questions, asking
the other side why they're
taking that
position why they want.
You ask them to justify it.
Ask them to explain it.
Give us some more
information what
sits behind that position.
And when we do that, they're
starting to share their
interests, that is why they've
taken the position.
And we can now start to veer the
conversation more towards
our interests.
Of course, positions are very
common in negotiation.
If we take an enterprise
agreement that occurs between
employers and employees on a
cycle of usually two or three
years an enterprise bargaining
agreement is renewed, what
usually happens before that is
the union that represents the
employees or the employees
will issue what's
called a log of claims.
They'll write a letter to the
employer at the start of the
negotiations saying what their
claims are, what the salary
increase they want, the
conditions that they want
amended, and so on.
And the employer then responds
to that log of claims.
Some people call that
an ambit claim.
If it's a inflated claim that's
unrealistic, it's
referred to as an ambit claim.
Really what we're talking about
here is a position.
And it's very common in
group-based negotiations.
Because the groups negotiate
before they come to the table,
they settle on a position, and
then they come to the table
with that position.
And it's why enterprise
bargaining agreements are
often very positional.
They start from two quite
extreme positions and they
might end up being more
interest-based but they often
start in quite an adversarial
manner, which is I guess
implicit in that domain or that
arena of negotiation.
We want to win, we've
got a choice.
Try to stay away from
positions if we can.
Because it has the potential to
make that conflict escalate
and the parties get very stuck
in a positional style of
negotiation.
So we've looked at this issue
of language in this topic.
We've drawn a distinction
between
positions and interests.
And I've made the broad comment
that as a general
rule, we try to negotiate
around interests, the
underpinning concerns.
We've also drawn a distinction
of giving you an example
between solutions and options.
And we need to use our language
carefully when we're
negotiating to create the
right mood, to create a
collaborative environment, and
to move the negotiation
towards resolution.