So I mentioned in the
last topic the importance
of bridging the
gap between knowing
about effective
communication skills
and actually using those
communication skills.
And I think it's an interesting
observation of some people's
over confidence in
their skills that they,
when you talk about
communication,
they say, oh, yeah, we know
all of this sort of stuff.
We don't need to do this.
And then when you
watch them negotiating,
there's some serious
problems with the way
that they communicate.
So you just think
about it yourself,
the last time you
had a real doozy
of an argument
with your partner,
or a close friend,
or a family member.
You think about the character
or your own communication,
would you change anything in
the way that you communicated?
I suspect most of us would.
We've got some regrets about
the way that we communicated.
And what's going on here?
It's the pressure of
the interaction that's
causing our communication
skills to break down.
So we want to be
able to make sure
that, just like a sportsman
on the day of the big game,
that our skills show
up when we need them.
So how do we bridge this gap
between knowing and doing?
There's an interesting thing
about communication skills
in conflict resolution that
we need to be conscious of.
And that is the idea
that we all have
very predetermined or strong
predispositions to how
to manage conflict, what
works and what conflict means.
It's quite a profound event for
many of us to be in conflict.
And so because of this,
we have reliable scripts.
We have reliable
styles of negotiating.
We have things that
we fall back on.
And what we want to do is to be
able to be conscious of having
a broader range
of skills that we
can use that are
going to be effective.
In one of the earlier
units in module three,
I talked about Morton Deutsch.
And he's a scholar who
drew the distinction
between destructive and
constructive conflict.
And in a lot of
Deutsch's writings,
he really emphasizes
the importance
that, particularly in
conflict resolution,
you need to be able to not only
learn about conflict resolution
skills and methodologies, but
you also need to practice them.
And why is this so important?
Well, one of the fundamental
points here is many of us will,
when we try to use
conflict resolution skills,
we'll feel as though we are
in some ways being weak.
That when we're in
conflict we need
to really prosecute
the conflict.
We need to be hard.
We need to be firm.
We need to really fight.
And that can be very
counterproductive
if we're actually trying
to resolve the conflict.
We also can sometimes
be exposed to advice
that isn't necessarily
all that helpful.
Let's take, for example, we've
got a conflict going at work,
and we go home at
night, and we want
to try and debrief or
download with our partner
or flatmate or a friend.
And often what you'll find
is that that person becomes
what's been called
a scriptwriter.
That person tells you what
you should say the next day,
and they're very strong,
and they're very assertive.
And they tell you what
you have to go in and tell
that person the next day.
Well, I always say
to my students,
well, that's very easy with
a glass of wine in your hand.
But you're the one who has
to go to work the next day
and face that
person and actually
put that advice into practice.
And sometimes that's not quite
as easy as it sounds at night.
So what we want to do is we
want to develop the ability
to take our knowledge
of conflict resolution
and negotiation
skills, and we want
to be able to make sure that
they turn up when we need them.
How do we do that?
So, let's consider the
example of Ann and Joe--
go back to that case
study for a moment.
Let's imagine Ann is having a
meeting with Joe the next day.
So the previous evening, she
and her partner do a role play,
and they think about
how the negotiation is
going to play out.
And Ann plans what
she is going to say.
Well, of course
there's a possibility
that it could all go a
pear-shaped the next day,
and Ann could end
up yelling at Joe,
and it could end up being
a big slanging match.
There's no definite way that Ann
can avoid that from happening.
But she can do the best that
she can do in the pre-phase
where she's planning
what she is going to say.
She's thinking about what
emotions she might have.
And she's thinking a little
bit about what his response is
going to be, what Joe's
response is going to be.
So she's readied herself
for the situation.
And she's thought about a few
contingencies, some what-its.
So how do we build this gap
between knowing and doing?
One of the things I think
a lot of people don't do
is that they don't debrief
after a negotiation.
I think what Ann could do is
then after the negotiation,
she says, well, how did that go?
What skills did I use?
Did I stick to my plan?
Did I plan effectively?
And what could I do next time?
And if you're doing
this by yourself,
you might want to even develop
a bit of a learning journal
where you make notes after
each important negotiational
conversation.
Work out what you tried to
do, what actually happened,
and what you might try and
do differently next time.
And this is a way of starting
to build self-awareness
and some self-discipline
about sticking to your plan
and also planning
more effectively
in your negotiation.
So think about this gap
between knowing and doing.
And think about putting into
practice the skills that you've
learned in this module
and also that you
plan to use when you go and
try and negotiate or resolve
a conflict.