http://open.umich.edu/sites/default/files/py4inf-01-intro.pdf https://youtu.be/G721cooZXgs
Hello.
And welcome to Python for Informatics.
Right now we're going to cover Chapter
One.
I'm Charles Severance from the University
of Michigan.
And I'm the author.
And I'll be your lecturer, for this online
lecture of the first chapter of the book.
This lecture and my slides, and the book,
as a matter of fact, are all open.
Open content, open materials.
They're copyright Creative Commons
Attribution.
And this video recording is also
copyright Creative Commons Attribution.
It's important to be explicit about
copyright, and
so I say it right at the beginning.
So, computers basically want to be
helpful.
They are programmed.
[SOUND] Matter of fact, this is a
microprocessor.
This is really just an electrical part.
It's got wires and circuits inside of it.
And somebody spent a lot of engineering
time, to make it so that these pins in the
back take instructions from us, from
operating systems,
from the hard drive, from the memory.
Instructions come into here and then
results come out.
It's really sort of a very programmable
hand
calculator and it's our job to put
instructions in.
This thing, in a sense, is wired to
be curious about what's next, right?
It's like
It, it's, like, tell me what you want to
do next.
What do you want to do next?
What do you want to do next, and after
that, what do you want to do next,
and it just happens to do that a
billion or so times a second.
And, so that's sort of the, the low-level
piece, and, but you can also think, if
you have, like, a PDA, something like
this,
all the buttons on here are some kind of,
you know, "what's next?"
Right?
Each of those is sort of something begging
for my attention, some application
developer who's built a
really cool application and says please
use me, please
click me, I am sort of nothing without
you.
We humans are the things that sort of
cause computers to start doing
something and this will sit here happily
until I caused it to do something.
Now, [SOUND] whoa!
Whoa.
Hope it's still okay.
Yeah, it seems to be fine.
Seems to be fine.
Takes a lickin', and keeps on tickin'.
So, these, anyone can use, right?
They say even animals can use a Macintosh,
smartphone.
And so you don't have to be a programmer.
But to get this to do what you want
you need to learn a different language,
and we need to
learn the language of the instructions to
tell it what to do.
So, that's what we're going to do.
We're going to learn how to talk to this.
Yo!
because it's asking us a question, we have
to give the answer.
So, what's a programmer?
A programmer is somebody who
writes a program, which is a script or a
set of instructions that tell
one of these kinds of things what it is
that they're supposed to do.
And sometimes you're running a program
like Moodle, an open source
learning management system, or Sakai,
another open source learning management
system.
And sometimes you'll even get paid to do
that, right?
Sometimes you do it for free, sometimes
you
get paid, sometimes you write things for
yourself.
And and but, if you think about it, all
these
applications on my iPhone, somebody's
making some money off of these.
They may not be able to quit their job,
but a surprising number
have been able to quit their job or
start
small companies, maybe not gigantic
companies, but small companies.
So these people that can put
applications inside of our computers
are programmers, because they understand
the way that we talk to these computers.
And part of what I'm going to try to do is
to get you to move from
the mindset of the end user who thinks of
this as something just to click on
to the mindset of the programmer, who's
kind of
on the inside trying to get out to you.
So that's, as we sort of move from user to
programmer, we move from outside to inside
and we think
of the world out there and it's like what
are
they going to put, push, what button are
they going to push.
So here's kind of a picture of that.
So on the outside, we're users, we click
on buttons, we click
on websites, we click on buttons on our
phones, et cetera, et cetera.
But what's really going on inside all of
that is there's a computer with
a bunch of hardware inside of that, and it
has inside of it data,
networks, other information. And software
is what makes all that make sense.
And so, part of what I want you to do is
I want you to stop
thinking about how to use these things
from
the outside, and we move to becoming a
programmer.
We're someone on the inside.