https://youtu.be/3Kz7itcfciI
We all collect interesting
moments just by going about
our daily lives.
And if we think about those
moments as the things that
matter to us, then they can
become our subject matter or
our subject that matters.
Frederick Sommer, in a famous
talk he gave at the Chicago
University in 1970 called &quot;An
Extemporaneous Talk,&quot; had this
to say about that: &quot;If you find
yourself going to the zoo
too often, it's because
you belong in the zoo
in the first place.
You're at home there.&quot;
Now neither Fred nor I is
suggesting that you go and
photograph zoos.
I mean, you might, but basically
what Frederick is
saying here is that the places
that you feel most comfortable
doing the things that you do
most often are generally the
things that matter
to you the most.
So if you're not certain or if
you're unsure a little bit
about the kinds of things
you might want to be
photographing, think about the
sorts of places you visit the
most, the people that you
respond to well, and the sorts
of activities that engage you
more than anything else.
And that's probably the subject
that matters to you.
Finding a subject is a creative
act in and of itself.
The way that we go through our
world, we have certain
experiences, and those
experiences become the things
that we value.
And therefore, they're the kinds
of things that we might
want to be photographing.
Photography is such as a
vernacular activity.
There's so many photographs out
there that you might be
fooled into thinking that
there's nothing left to
photograph.
That's not true.
You photograph the sorts of
things that you want to
photograph because it's related
to the experiences
that you have.
In this topic, I'm going to give
you some ideas of how to
find the sorts of subjects that
you might be interested
in and how to then relate that
to the kinds of photographs
that you might want to take.
Now photography is a
technologically determined
medium, and I'm a firm believer
that the more you
know how to use the mechanical
and the digital aspects of
your camera, the greater your
scope for creating and making
the sorts of photographs
that you want to take.
Our first subject can be the
external subject, and it can
literally mean either outside or
it can mean places that we
visit and places that we see
in our everyday life.
It might mean a walk
around the city.
It could even mean bushwalking
through a natural environment.
But there's a way that you
respond to things that live
outside, or external to
yourself, that becomes our
first subject.
I travel and photograph a lot,
but I'm a slow traveller.
I like to take my time, and I
consider the journey to be the
thing of most value to me.
So I photograph along the way.
When I'm looking for external
subjects, I like to have an
idea in my head about exactly
what it is that I might be
looking for.
Nevada Joe is one such image.
As I was travelling through the
desolate outback landscape
of Nevada, I was looking for a
particular type of image that
played on that humour of
civilisation just passing
through, rather than cementing
itself in a location.
And you can see here the sign
splits the image right down
the centre.
You've got the pink bar on the
one side and then the desolate
landscape receding off
into the distance
on the other side.
External subjects can also be
things that you discover and
that are sitting there for
the camera, waiting to be
photographed.
The idea of the tourist is a
cemented way of thinking about
subjects in photography, and in
this particular image here,
I was looking for something that
referenced the desolation
and the destruction of
that particular site.
And I wanted to make a nice
parallel between the car and
the engine interior and
the engine exterior.
But in this instance, I was on
a bus, and you can't always
get the things that you want,
and sometimes you simply make
do with the best opportunity
that you have.
Our external subjects often need
wide lenses or lens that
have a wider than our normal
field of view.
This gives us a way of framing
and composing images to fit a
fair amount of detail in there
and also to give an expansive
overview of the scenes that
we might be looking at.
Now the second category of
subject is the opposite of
external, which is
the internal.
When something is an internal
subject what we're essentially
referring to is our emotional
response to the things that we
see, but it also means how we
might have an idea in our head
and be searching or seeking for
certain topics, certain
subjects, that respond to the
thing that we're referring to.
Internal subjects can also
be quite reactionary, and
sometimes you come across
certain things that either
you're interested in or that
simply catch your eye.
Sometimes an internal subject
can actually be someone's
insides, as in &quot;Baseball
Player,&quot; shot inside a glass
case, inside a building, of
the inside of the subject.
An internal image can also be
one that has been planned and
meticulously laid out and set
up to explore a certain way
that you want to portray
or investigate an idea.
This particular image by
Australian artist Darren
Sylvester, &quot;If all we have is
each other, that's OK,&quot; from
2004, depicts a scene where
the idea of happiness
overpowers everything else and
that as long as you're with
your friends, everything
will be OK.
Now Darren didn't stumble
across this scene and
photograph it.
He actually consciously set
everything up, including the
lighting, including the
positioning, the makeup, the
KFC on the bench.
Everything is meticulously laid
out to portray exactly
that moment that he was trying
to reproduce as a way of
exploring the certain idea
that he was developing.
In this particular instance,
Darren had a remembrance or a
memory of enjoying KFC
with his friends.
Now as banal as that may sound,
what he was trying to
explore is that relationship
between friendship and youth
and consumerism and the sorts
of things that can sometimes
take hold of us in culture and
the way that we might respond
to something like that.
Darren has skillfully set this
up and used, most likely, a 50
millimetre lens to reproduce
the focal length of human
vision so that it almost seems
like we're sitting there at
the table with them and
participating in that moment.
Subject is subjective, and it's
sometimes elusive, so we
need to pay attention to the way
that we are constructing
or responding to the
things that we see.