https://youtu.be/-ziBKNm8QOQ
Digital images are significantly
sharper than
analogue images.
The level of detail that modern
cameras can resolve in
a file is extraordinary and
allows us the flexibility and
the option to create all sorts
of amazing images.
But the acutance and sharpness
of an image is a really
important point, because
get it wrong, and
your images will fail.
Get it right, and your
images will sing.
They will look amazing.
So in this particular topic,
we're going to explore some of
the debates around sharpening
and some of the ideas that you
might want to explore.
But also, I'm going to show
you a couple ways that I
sharpen and explain to
you why I sharpen in
the way that I do.
Acutance in an image is
a beautiful thing.
Acutance refers to the sharpness
of contrast in the
edges of our files.
So when we look at how we might
sharpen an image, we're
looking specifically at ways
to increase the contrast of
those edges as a way of
exploring different options
for spatial relationships.
And sharpening can be a global
adjustment, in the same way
that we looked at colour
correction.
And in fact, it should be
a global adjustment.
But it can also be a local
adjustment that allows us to
do pretty amazing things with
the way that we might position
certain elements within
our image.
Now, this is important,
something that I
need to point out.
Sharpening will not
increase focus.
If your image is out of focus,
no amount of sharpening in any
image-editing application
will correct for that.
Sharpening is about enhancing
the optical resolution and the
way that image was captured.
Something that's a little bit
ironic is that the tool we use
in Photoshop to sharpen
is actually
called the unsharp mask.
And it's called an unsharp
mask because it's about
looking at ways of edging out
that contrast and identifying
those edges so that
we can control
the amount of intensity.
So in analogue terms, an unsharp
mask used to be one
that would blur the edges of
our image so that we could
sharpen or increase
contrast there.
One of the questions that
we have when it comes to
sharpening and one of those
things that's a bit of a
debate is just how many times
do we sharpen an image.
I think we need to sharpen
three times.
Remember, when we capture a
photographic image using a
digital camera, we are actually
converting a readout
of the intensity of lights
on the photo cells.
And that's then converted
into those numbers.
So I think every time you make
one of those conversions,
there's a little bit of
loss that occurs.
And sharpening is one of the
ways we correct for that.
So when we first open
up our images, I
think we need to sharpen.
And when we print our images,
different paper types rely on
different amounts
of sharpening.
So we need to sharpen there.
The last type of sharpening
that we do is actually the
middle type, which is when
we address those spatial
relationships with different
types of local sharpening.
So the first stage of sharpening
is about the global
correction.
And if you look at this image
here, you can see the before
and after of the two
spines on the book.
The before shot is the
raw file, taken
straight off the camera.
The after shot is where I've
applied a certain amount of
sharpening to that image.
And that difference is
quite astounding.
You can easily see just how much
clarity and definition a
small sharpening adjustment
can put into our images.
Now, for stage two, where it's
the local adjustments and the
sharpening for spatial
awareness, I'm going to show
you a bit of a video.
And you can see exactly
what I mean.
So in this image, everything
seems to be relatively clear.
The image is sharp.
It's being corrected.
The colour and the tone
is all right.
But the her Ned Kelly and the
his Ned Kelly outfits, they
just need a little
bit of clarity.
Likewise, the his magazines
and the her magazines--
they're so humorous.
It's such a funny scene that I
really want to bring up some
of that intensity and some
of that clarity in there.
So under here, I'm going to
duplicate that layer.
I'm going to call it a sharpen
layer or sharpening layer.
And then rather than use the
unsharp mask, I'm going to use
this selection here called
the high pass philtre.
If I set that radius, which
is defining the edge and
sharpening the edge to around
10 pixels, that's OK.
You can see all those
edges in there now.
Then I just need to change this
blending mode down to
soft light.
And I have a layer which
has applied that
sharpening to my image.
It's not a huge amount
of sharpening.
It's just enough to give us
that effect of what we're
particularly looking for.
All I need to do now is
put on a layer mask.
And I'm going to hide everything
on that mask so
that the image is
back to normal.
So the Reveal All, white;
Hide All, black.
You can see that down there.
So if we choose our brush here
and we select white as our
colour to brush in, then we
can apply or add in that
sharpening layer through the
mask and apply that density
and acutance in the him outfit,
in the her outfit, in
the his magazines, the
her magazines.
And just increase the overall
spatial awareness in that
particular image.
When I turn that on and off,
you can see the difference
that that makes just by simply
looking at that.
And you can see the mask there
applying that sharpening.
If I come in and look at the
image at 100%, you'll be able
to see exactly what
I'm talking about.
So there's the sharpening
effect.
And I'll turn that off.
And that's quite dull
in comparison.
But it's just giving me
slightly more spatial
awareness so that when I look
at this particular image,
those two elements really stand
out off the screen or
off the print.
So the last stage of sharpening
is when we print.
The reason that we sharpen for
print is that not all paper
types are the same.
Remember that the conversion,
when we go from analogue to
digital, is the same
applies here.
We're going from digital
back to analogue.
And in this case, it's going
to be ink on paper.
Given that some papers are more
contrast than others,
some papers are harder,
softer.
We can print on beautiful
watercolour papers.
We can print on sharp, glossy
photographic papers.
So your choice of paper will
determine the kind of
sharpening that you use.
In this image, you can see
here I'm just trialling a
certain range of sharpening.
So I've used different
parameters
for the unsharp mask.
And I'm just testing to see
which one is most appropriate
on the printed surface.
When I've made that choice, I'll
then make a full print
with that sharpening applied.