https://youtu.be/6GEJurfPKFY
Trong bài học này, chúng ta sẽ học về Photoshop
và cách hoạt động của
ứng dụng chỉnh sửa hình ảnh này
Tôi sẽ không giảng nhiều về Photoshop
Có đến khoảng 6.3 triệu video trên Youtube
bạn có thể xem để học về
tất cả mọi thứ
Tôi sẽ giới thiệu với các bạn từ ngữ
và thuật ngữ bạn cần biết để theo kịp nội dung
để bạn tự học theo tốc độ của mình
và tự quyết định xem mình cần tập trung học phần nào
Ứng dụng chỉnh sửa hình ảnh như Photoshop
có lợi ích là giúp chúng ta hình dung
và hoàn thiện bức hình
theo cách mình muốn
Tôi không nghĩ là bạn cần là chuyên gia Photoshop
Tôi cũng không nghĩ bạn cần
tập trung vào tất cả
hiệu ứng đặc biệt và mọi công dụng của nó
Chắc chắn là tôi không biết hết những thứ đó
Tôi chỉ cần biết những gì cần thiết
và cách làm những gì
tôi muốn làm được
Trong video này, chúng ta sẽ cùng quan sát giao diện Photoshop
và cách sắp xếp các cài đặt
và các mục trong bảng chọn
Lý do chúng ta học những điều này là vì tôi không cho rằng
Photoshop là một giao diện dành riêng cho nhiếp ảnh
Và chúng ta cần dành một chút thời gian để tìm hiểu
Điều quan trọng là Photoshop có gì
và được cài đặt sẵn những gì
Tôi nghĩ nó không thực sự hữu ích
Thực ra tôi có tạo một phần mềm riêng
có tên là Nhiếp ảnh Mỹ thuật (Fine Art Photography)
Các bạn có thể thấy được khác biệt rõ rệt
giữa hai cài đặt giao diện
Phần mềm của tôi phân bố đủ các công cụ tôi thấy cần
ngay trước mắt để làm nhiếp ảnh
Đây là
Đây là quang đồ (histogram)
Dưới quang đồ là mọi thông tin
về dữ liệu và số liệu cần thiết
do Photoshop cung cấp
Dưới phần đó là phần lịch sử
và phần lịch sử này giúp tôi quay lại một số layer
và.... để thực hiện những thay đổi cần thiết
trên hình ảnh
Bên dưới đây, tôi có tất cả các công cụ
Mỗi cái giúp tôi chỉnh sửa ảnh
như dùng nhiều hiệu ứng để tô màu hay cắt bỏ, xóa bỏ
một số khuyết điểm trong ảnh của tôi
Mọi công cụ ở đây đều khá quan trọng
Chúng ta cần chắc chắn biết rõ công dụng của từng công cụ
khi chỉnh sửa ảnh
The Zoom tool here, obviously,
takes me into one image pixel
equals one screen
pixel or 100%.
Khi nháy đúp chuột vào phím tắt nho nhỏ hình bàn tay này
chúng ta có thể thấy được toàn bộ hình ảnh trên màn hình
Điều quan trọng ở đây là
Ở phía bên này, tôi có thanh tính năng
thông báo cho tôi biết những gì
đang hoạt động ở thời điểm này
trong trường hợp này, nó là một layer điều chỉnh cong.
Qua đó, tôi thấy được
hình ảnh của tôi thay đổi thế nào khi tôi chỉnh sửa
Phía trên đây, chúng ta có thanh bảng chọn
Mỗi bảng chọn cho phép chúng ta tương tác với
Photoshop hoặc với máy tính
Nếu tôi chọn layer nền này
sau đó tôi nghĩ ra và muốn chọn những lựa chọn khác
example, maybe sharpen, you can
see that there are a whole
range of menus that I can
choose from down here.
Now, the important thing
is the dot, dot, dot.
Each of those three dots, any
menu item with that, means
that we have more options.
I can choose sharpen
edges here.
And I'm sure it's sharpening
the edges.
It tells me that it has
sharpened the edges.
But I have no control over what
is an edge or, in fact,
how much sharpening happens.
If I come down and choose the
Unsharp Mask, for example,
those three dots tell me that I
have more options that I can
interact with.
So they are generally much
better in terms of the tools
that you might want
to be using.
One of the things that is
awkward with Photoshop is that
there are multiple ways that
you can do the same thing.
However, there are two
distinctive characteristic
methods in Photoshop that we
need to be aware of and we
need to preference one
over the other.
One option is that it's
destructive and that every
single move you make is
calculated and fixed as one of
those moves.
The other way is
non-destructive, where you
build up your image through
using multiple layers.
And any point in that process,
if you make a mistake, or if
you decide you don't like
something, you can
always remove it.
Let me show you what I mean.
Here in this landscape image, we
can say some rather amazing
mountain ranges in the
background and some really
atmospheric moody sky.
Now, I think these ranges need
a little bit more contrast.
I think they could do
with some punch.
And that sky over there
certainly needs burning down a
little bit.
So there's a little bit of work
that we can do to lift
the quality of this image.
I'm going to use the Adjustment
menu over here.
There are my tonal
adjustments.
There are my colour
I'm going for Curves, which
allows me to plot a new map of
the tones in my image.
But look, the problem is that I
can't position that anywhere
on my screen without
having it overlay
across parts of my image.
So I can't really see the image
and the adjustment that
I'm making at the same time.
That's one of the first
problems with
working this way.
But we'll just have to make
due and see how we go.
So I'm going to drop
down the shadows.
I'm going to lift up
the highlights.
I'm going to lock
off the centre.
And yes, I now have more
contrast in my image.
The sky is slightly
more ominous.
The mountain ranges are
certainly more dynamic.
So that's, essentially,
achieved what I was
hoping it would do.
I click OK.
And then I'm done.
The problem is that at some
point, maybe it's next week,
maybe it's even a month later.
I might come back and think,
it's not quite what I wanted.
It's OK.
But maybe I've gone too far.
And I just need to pull that
back a little bit and readjust
some of those things.
So back to Adjustments.
Back to Curves.
But my curve is now
a straight line.
So I don't have the curve
that I adjusted.
I'm stuck with a new curve.
But I can just reverse that.
I can lift the shadows.
I can drop the highlights.
That seems to do what it
says it's going to do.
I can fix that centre point.
I turn that on and off.
And yes, I've reduced
the contrast.
But what I'm doing is I'm
reducing contrast on an image
that I've already increased
the contrast on
in the first place.
So it's not quite what I'm
really interested in doing.
It is, in fact, it's a
destructive method.
And it's one that I would
certainly avoid.
It's not what I would
recommend.
OK.
Let's do it the other way.
Let's go back in history
to the start.
And let's look at how we might
do this building the image
rather than reducing it.
So instead of doing the
adjustment on the image, I'm
going to add a new
adjustment layer.
Same thing.
There are more tones.
There are my colours.
I'm going to choose Curve.
I can even name it if I want--
Contrast.
Hit OK.
And then over here you can
see, first of all,
I've got a new curve.
But it's not covering
up my image.
It's actually a new layer in
Photoshop that's about to do a
very, if not the same thing that
I did before, reduce the
shadows, increase
the highlights,
lock off the midtones.
There's my contrast.
There's the ominous sky.
There is more presence
in the mountains.
I've done the same thing
that I did before.
Except this time, if I've
gone too far, the
curve is still there.
It's always there.
It's saved with the image.
I'm not reducing or destroying
the image in any way.
I'm building on it and adding
new information.
That's the advantage of using
this particular method,
whereas the other method, once
it's done, you've permanently
altered the original image.