https://youtu.be/kiX-mlvrMQ4
One of the great things we can
do with our photography is we
can share it, and we can show
it to other people.
And we can look at other
people's work and develop that
sense of community around the
sorts of things that we like
photographing, but also
just as photographers.
It's really important
that we do this.
I don't think you can really
improve your photography
without looking at other
people's work and without
having other people look
at and even comment on
your work as well.
One of the really important
things about doing this course
is that you engage in that idea
of sharing your work.
So we've set up that Google+
account, and I can't emphasise
enough that you really need to
start looking at, putting your
work out there, and hoping and
letting other people comment
on that as well.
But don't just put
your work up.
Every time you put an image
up, I think it's important
that you look for and comment
on someone else's image so
that you get that sense of
ongoing dialogue about how it
is that you're all learning
the sorts of things that
you're learning, but also how
you want to comment on
photography.
Now, I don't want to impose
rules on this, but I think
there's a couple of things that
are really important.
Praise is nice.
It's great to have people
praise at work, but
ultimately, it's not
very critical.
And I'd be more interested in
you being critical of how you
respond to the work that
people are putting up.
It doesn't mean they
have to be harsh.
It doesn't mean that you have
to be insulting or any of
those things, but be critical
about the sorts of things that
you're looking at.
The rise of social networking in
the last decade means that,
more than any other time in our
history, we have access to
more images and lots of
photography that will help us
to navigate our own
experiences of
this wonderful medium.
So have a look at some
of these sites.
They're in your list
of resources at
the end of this topic.
And check out the sorts
of things that you
want to check out.
You'll notice that lots of
things are keyworded and
categorised into certain
types of photography.
It will help you to develop the
way that you want to look
and respond through your own
photography and help you to
see how other people are
doing the same thing.
When you feel that you've got
better at your photography, or
when you feel more confident
about the kinds of images that
you're taking, you can even
start to enter competitions.
You can start to get your work
out there and see how other
people, who are probably more
used to responding to
photographs and looking for
certain things, how they can
respond and what they think
about your images.
Now, the other thing that I
think is really important is
that you can look at all those
social networking sites, and I
would encourage it.
But there are other locations
that you can visit and other
websites and physical locations,
like galleries,
that will help you to see the
way that other people using
photography.
Galleries are a particularly
interesting perspective
because they condense.
And they have some kind of
review process, so they really
only put up the best kind of
work that they consider to be
in relation to the sorts of
things they're looking for.
Most capital cities around the
world will have some kind of
photography gallery.
I know in Australia that at
least four of our major cities
have a photography gallery
that is of a really high
calibre and that shows
amazing work.
New York, London, Paris, most
of the major cities do the
same thing.
A lot of the cities in
America as well.
So I suggest that you start
looking at more professional
locations as well as the social
networking locations,
and get a real sense of what
photography is and how you can
engage with it.