https://youtu.be/e3gQAAF5DNU
In this topic, we're looking
at global adjustments.
We talked about that earlier,
there being the two types of
adjustments that we might use.
Global adjustments affect
the entire image.
And it's usually the way that
we might control contrast,
density, colour saturation,
correct for colour, and
overall edits to the entire
image to either lift it and to
make it more in line with how we
might have visualised that
image or to simply
make corrections.
The way that we do global
adjustments is entirely
dependent on you.
You might have a particular type
of working that you like.
Myself, I prefer to
use curves, as we
saw in the last topic.
But it's entirely up to the way
that you like to work as
to which type of edits
you choose.
Now, the way that you think
about global adjustments is
quite important.
We want to use a type of tool
that allows us to do exactly
what it is that we need to do.
And sometimes, that's making
the correction or sometimes
it's lifting the image and
achieving a certain feel or a
certain type of emotional
response to the way that you
think that image should be.
In Cairo, you can see that
there's a before and after.
In the before, the image
is quite flat.
Even though all the detail is
there-- even though I've got
black and I've got highlights
and there are midtones--
overall, that image is
lacking in contrast.
And it is slightly flat.
In the after image you can see,
through a simple tonal
adjustment, that contrast
is increased.
And I still have blacks
that I can see into.
I still have highlights.
But I have an overall image that
is much more satisfactory
in terms of the kinds of ideas
it's trying to convey.
You can now easily and
definitely see that long, hard
line where civilisation
meets the desert.
Colour correction is another
type of global adjustment that
pretty important in the way that
we work with our images.
In Hagia Sophia, you can
see the before image.
The stone is too green, and
it doesn't quite do
what it needs to do.
It's not quite cold enough.
And so what I need to do in
looking at this particular
image is I need to remove
some of that green.
And I need to make it colder
and more like stone.
But at the same time, I need
to make sure that I'm not
introducing a colour cast that
might be displeasing to the
way that we see that stone.
Also, in the foreground now,
you can see the ghost-like
image moving through.
So I want to make sure that
I maintain that particular
element of the image, as it adds
to the narrative of the
story that I'm trying to tell.
So by making a simple
colour adjustment--
and in the after image, you
can definitely see that--
it's much more like
a stone would be.
There's that coldness to it.
It's harder.
It has that emotional feeling
that you're more in line with
how a particular church
like that might seem.
When you're working with
Photoshop, you need to make a
choice about how you're going
to do those kinds of edits.
Now, a good friend of mine,
Les Walkling,
had a wonderful way of
describing two types of ways
of working in Photoshop, which
actually also translates quite
nicely into there are two types
of people in the way
they use Photoshop.
The first one are the
slider people.
And they generally opt for the
kinds of tools where it's
basically sliding adjustments
and you can see the response
directly on the screen.
And things like brightness and
contrast, colour balance, hue
saturation--
they're all slider controls that
we can use that allow us
to make those individual
adjustments quite easily.
And we can use all of those as
adjustment layers so we can
build and layer up our
image as we go.
The other type of user
is the curve user.
Now, the curve user is a little
bit more mathematical
in the way that they
think about things.
They like the precision of how
they might make those edits.
And they like to do as much as
possible with one simple tool.
So you can edit the red, green,
and blue-- which is
your tonal channel--
in curves.
Or you can select each of those
individual channels, and
they become your colour balance
adjustments in that
particular dialogue box.
So if you're a slider person,
fantastic, if there's no
preference over one
or the other.
But think about yourself in
terms of the way that you
might like to use
those controls.