https://youtu.be/c9AlaF9bXH4
What's really interesting is
that photography and computers
have a unique shared history.
beginnings and intersects
quite nicely now through
contemporary photography.
In 1839, Fox Talbot created
the negative-positive
photographic process.
At the same time, or around the
same time, Charles Babbage
was inventing and coming up with
the differential engine,
which was a way of calculating
the difference between two
numbers, which began as
the modern computer.
You will have heard me say this
before in this course.
But to be a better photographer,
I believe you
absolutely must understand the
connection between hardware
and creativity.
You really need to know that
connection between the devices
that you're using and how
you need to use them.
On that topic of photography and
technology, there's a nice
ongoing relationship that
photography has with
technology, which is to say that
it's always existed using
the highest technology
of the time.
Back in the 1830s and
1840s, it was
through optics and chemistry.
As we shifted into the
mechanical and industrial era,
it was through that
mechanical device.
As we moved then into the
electronic era in the '80s and
'90s, photography was right
at the forefront with
electronics.
And now as we're moving into the
digital age, photography
is right there, as well, using
that kind of technology as a
way of making photographic
images.
We need to realise that the
role that computers are
playing with photography is
becoming more and more
critical and relates to how we
use our cameras and how we
might equip ourselves for
a digital darkroom.
It's also worth noting that
even our cameras have
incredibly powerful computers
inside them that are
processing and dealing with
those photographic images as
we are capturing them.
And if you trace back that
history of digital
photography, yes, the megapixel
count goes up, so
that our cameras are capturing
more and more detail and more
data, making bigger images.
But the computers inside the
cameras are also becoming
increasingly more powerful
to process those images.
Of all the devices that we use
in our digital darkroom, the
monitor is probably the most
critical and certainly
something that we should
never overlook.
When we use our monitor,
that's how
we're seeing the image.
And that's how we're editing
the image on our screen.
So a monitor that can give us
good acutance and sharpness,
that can give us increasingly
more accurate colour
separation and saturation, as
well as a good strong tonal
scale, is an incredibly
important
part of that process.
And I would recommend that you
pay attention to the way that
your monitor is set up and make
sure that you can see all
of that information that is in
the photograph and that is
indeed visible on the monitor.
In this image that you'll see
on the screen now, you can
tell that there is a difference
between monitor A
and monitor B. Monitor A
is the correct image.
Monitor B has contrast
that is way too high.
And you can see that whilst
those numbers are the same--
the red, green, and blue values;
the hue saturation and
brightness--
they're exactly the same in
monitor A and monitor B--
the rendition of tone in monitor
A is more accurate,
whereas in monitor
B, it's too dark.
Therefore, you can't see
that shadow detail.
However, there is an interesting
comparison that we
need to make here between the
image on the monitor-- or the
monitor image--
and the enlarger in a
traditional darkroom.
What we see on the monitor
is not the end result.
If we're making prints, we can't
actually see a print on
the screen.
We need to use our judgement and
make the monitor work for
us so that we are able to make
those edits and make an
accurate print.
It is important to note,
however, that if the monitor
is not your end result, if you
do want to make beautiful
prints, then the monitor cannot
give you the texture of
the paper, the viewing distance,
or the physicality
of that print.
If you are interested in setting
up a digital darkroom,
there are a couple of
other considerations
to take into account.
Once you've got the monitor set
up, you'll need a computer
that is relatively fast and
able to process lots of
information.
So the CPU is important.
RAM is really critical because
all of our images
get stored in RAM.
So the more of that you have,
the easier it's going to be to
work with your images.
And then a fast hard drive
is also important.
You can talk to your computer
specialist about these things.
Tell them you want something
for photographic imaging.
But the only other thing to
consider is that whilst you
can work with slower machines,
and that's fine, but relating
to that photographic experience
is important.
And capturing images is an
instantaneous moment.
So we don't want to be sitting
around waiting for hours
whilst our images are processing
or doing the sorts
of things that we
need it to do.
Back in the beginning days of
digital photography, in the
early '90s, I can remember
making a very simple tonal
adjustment and then having to
go get a cup of tea while I
waited for the computer
to process that.
It's interruptive.
And it doesn't make for
a flowing photographic
experience.