https://youtu.be/-ziBKNm8QOQ
Những bức hình kĩ thuật số sắc nét hơn
đáng kể so với
những tấm hình Analog.
Mức dộ chi tiết máy ảnh
hiện đại có thể ghi lại trong
một file là rất lớn và
cung cấp chúng ta sự linh hoạt và
các lựa chọn để tạo mọi kiểu
hình ấn tưởng.
Nhưng độ phân giải và sắc nét
của một tấm hình thật sự là
một điểm quan trọng, bởi vì
nếu chỉnh sai,
những bức ảnh của bạn sẽ không đùng được,
Nếu chụp đúng, những
tấm hình của bạn sẽ có giá trị.
Chúng sẽ trông rất tuyệt vời.
Do đó, trong chủ đề cụ thể hôm nay,
chúng ta sẽ tìm hiểu về một vài
tranh luận xung quanh độ sắc nét
và một vài ý tưởng mà bạn
có thể muốn nghiên cứu.
Nhưng tôi cũng sẽ chỉ
bạn vài cách mà tôi
làm sắc nét và giải thích với
bạn lí do tôi làm sắc nét
như vậy.
Độ phân giải của một tấm hình là
một yếu tố quan trọng.
Độ phân giải liên quan tới sự sắc nét
của độ tương phản ở những
mép tiếp xúc trên những tấm hình.
Do vậy, khi chúng ta nhìn vào cách chúng ta có thể
làm nét một bức ảnh, chúng ta đang
đang chú tâm tìm cách
tăng độ tương phản của
những mép tiếp xúc, giống như
đang nghiên cứu các lựa chọn khác nhau
cho những mối tương quan.
Và làm sắc nét có thể là một điề chỉnh
tổng thể, giống như
khi chúng ta nhìn vào việc
điều chỉnh màu.
Và thật ra, nó nên là một
sự điều chỉnh toàn diện.
Nhưng nó cũng có thể là sự điều
điều chỉnh cục bộ cho phép chúng ta
làm những thứ khá ấn tượng theo
cách mà chúng ta có thể đặt
vài thứ nhất định vào trong
tấm hình của mình.
Bây giờ, tới phần quan trọng,
có vài thứ tôi
cần lưu ý.
Làm sắc nét sẽ không
làm tăng độ rõ nét.
Nếu tấm hình của bạn bị mất nét,
làm sắc nét bằng bất cứ giá nào với bấy kì
phần mềm chỉnh sửa nào
cũng sẽ không sửa được điều đó.
Làm sắc nét là làm tăng
độ phân giải quang học và
cách thức mà bức hình được chụp.
Có một điều khá
hài hước đó là công cụ chúng ta dùng
trong Photoshop để làm sắc
nét lại được
gọi là "mặt nạ giảm nét".
Và lí do nó được gọi như vậy là vì nhìn dưới
góc độ mài đi những đường nét
của phần tương phản và xác định
những đường nét đó để
chúng ta có thể kiểm soát
cường độ tương phản.
Do đó, đối với ảnh Analogue, một mặt nạ
giảm nét là cái
làm nhòa đi những đường nét của
tấm ảnh, để chúng ta có thẻ
làm nét hay tăng
độ tương phả ở đó.
Một trong những câu hỏi mà
chúng ta gặp khi nói đến
làm nét, và một trong những
điều còn khá gây
tranh cãi là chúng ta làm nét
một tấm ảnh bao nhiêu lần.
Tôi nghĩ chúng ta cần lầm nét
ba lần.
Nhớ là, khi chúng ta chụp một
tấm ảnh sử dụng một
máy ảnh kĩ thuật số, thật ra chúng ta
đang chuyển đổi dữ liệu
về cường độ ánh sáng
trên các điểm ảnh.
Và sau đó, chúng được chuyển đổi
thành những con số.
So I think every time you make
one of those conversions,
there's a little bit of
loss that occurs.
And sharpening is one of the
ways we correct for that.
So when we first open
up our images, I
think we need to sharpen.
And when we print our images,
different paper types rely on
different amounts
of sharpening.
So we need to sharpen there.
The last type of sharpening
that we do is actually the
middle type, which is when
we address those spatial
relationships with different
types of local sharpening.
So the first stage of sharpening
is about the global
correction.
And if you look at this image
here, you can see the before
and after of the two
spines on the book.
The before shot is the
raw file, taken
straight off the camera.
The after shot is where I've
applied a certain amount of
sharpening to that image.
And that difference is
quite astounding.
You can easily see just how much
clarity and definition a
small sharpening adjustment
can put into our images.
Now, for stage two, where it's
the local adjustments and the
sharpening for spatial
awareness, I'm going to show
you a bit of a video.
And you can see exactly
what I mean.
So in this image, everything
seems to be relatively clear.
The image is sharp.
It's being corrected.
The colour and the tone
is all right.
But the her Ned Kelly and the
his Ned Kelly outfits, they
just need a little
bit of clarity.
Likewise, the his magazines
and the her magazines--
they're so humorous.
It's such a funny scene that I
really want to bring up some
of that intensity and some
of that clarity in there.
So under here, I'm going to
duplicate that layer.
I'm going to call it a sharpen
layer or sharpening layer.
And then rather than use the
unsharp mask, I'm going to use
this selection here called
the high pass philtre.
If I set that radius, which
is defining the edge and
sharpening the edge to around
10 pixels, that's OK.
You can see all those
edges in there now.
Then I just need to change this
blending mode down to
soft light.
And I have a layer which
has applied that
sharpening to my image.
It's not a huge amount
of sharpening.
It's just enough to give us
that effect of what we're
particularly looking for.
All I need to do now is
put on a layer mask.
And I'm going to hide everything
on that mask so
that the image is
back to normal.
So the Reveal All, white;
Hide All, black.
You can see that down there.
So if we choose our brush here
and we select white as our
colour to brush in, then we
can apply or add in that
sharpening layer through the
mask and apply that density
and acutance in the him outfit,
in the her outfit, in
the his magazines, the
her magazines.
And just increase the overall
spatial awareness in that
particular image.
When I turn that on and off,
you can see the difference
that that makes just by simply
looking at that.
And you can see the mask there
applying that sharpening.
If I come in and look at the
image at 100%, you'll be able
to see exactly what
I'm talking about.
So there's the sharpening
effect.
And I'll turn that off.
And that's quite dull
in comparison.
But it's just giving me
slightly more spatial
awareness so that when I look
at this particular image,
those two elements really stand
out off the screen or
off the print.
So the last stage of sharpening
is when we print.
The reason that we sharpen for
print is that not all paper
types are the same.
Remember that the conversion,
when we go from analogue to
digital, is the same
applies here.
We're going from digital
back to analogue.
And in this case, it's going
to be ink on paper.
Given that some papers are more
contrast than others,
some papers are harder,
softer.
We can print on beautiful
watercolour papers.
We can print on sharp, glossy
photographic papers.
So your choice of paper will
determine the kind of
sharpening that you use.
In this image, you can see
here I'm just trialling a
certain range of sharpening.
So I've used different
parameters
for the unsharp mask.
And I'm just testing to see
which one is most appropriate
on the printed surface.
When I've made that choice, I'll
then make a full print
with that sharpening applied.