https://youtu.be/6GEJurfPKFY
In this topic, we're going to
look specifically at Photoshop
and how it operates as an image
editing application.
I'm not going to teach you a
lot of things in Photoshop.
There are, well, there are about
6.3 million videos on
YouTube that you can watch to
learn how to do all sorts of
specific things.
What I will do though is I will
give you the language and
terminology that you need in
order to be able to follow
these things up, so that you can
learn at your own pace and
decide what it is that you
need to know more about.
Image editing applications,
like Photoshop, have the
advantage of allowing us to work
with that visualisation
process and complete our images
the way that we think
they need to be finalised.
Now, I don't think you need to
be an expert in Photoshop.
I don't think you need to
focus on all the special
effects and everything that
it can actually do.
I certainly don't know
those things.
I just need to know what I need
to know and how to do the
things that I want
to be able to do.
In this video, we're looking at
Photoshop's interface and
the way that it lays out
all of its settings
and its menu items.
The reason that we're doing this
is because I don't think
Photoshop is a particularly
photographic interface.
And it needs a bit of work.
The essentials is what
it comes with.
That's preloaded in Photoshop.
I don't think it's particularly
useful.
I've actually created my own,
which I call Fine Art
Photography.
You can see here that there's a
big difference between those
two main interface settings.
Mine has all of the controls
laid out that I feel I need to
see in order to work
photographically.
There's my navigator.
There's my histogram.
Underneath my histogram, I have
all of the information
that I need in terms of the
data and numbers that
Photoshop tells me.
Down below that, I also
have my history.
And my history lets me go back
through certain layers and
levels to make different changes
as I need to work
across the image.
Down here, I have
all of my tools.
Each of those allow me to do
local adjustments, such as
painting in different effects or
editing out or brushing out
certain imperfections that
my image might contain.
Each of these tools are
quite important.
And we should make sure that we
know what each of those do
as we work through.
The Zoom tool here, obviously,
takes me into one image pixel
equals one screen
pixel or 100%.
A nice little shortcut there--
the hand tool, double-click
back, so we can see the entire
image on the screen.
Now, here's the important
thing.
Over on the other side, I have
my properties, which tells me
what is acting at that
particular time, in this case,
a curve adjustment layer,
so that I can see what's
happening to my image as I'm
making the adjustments.
At the top here, we
have our menus.
Now, each of our menus allows
us to interact either with
Photoshop or with
our computer.
And if I choose the background
layer down here and then I
come up and choose one of these
particular options, for
example, maybe sharpen, you can
see that there are a whole
range of menus that I can
choose from down here.
Now, the important thing
is the dot, dot, dot.
Each of those three dots, any
menu item with that, means
that we have more options.
I can choose sharpen
edges here.
And I'm sure it's sharpening
the edges.
It tells me that it has
sharpened the edges.
But I have no control over what
is an edge or, in fact,
how much sharpening happens.
If I come down and choose the
Unsharp Mask, for example,
those three dots tell me that I
have more options that I can
interact with.
So they are generally much
better in terms of the tools
that you might want
to be using.
One of the things that is
awkward with Photoshop is that
there are multiple ways that
you can do the same thing.
However, there are two
distinctive characteristic
methods in Photoshop that we
need to be aware of and we
need to preference one
over the other.
One option is that it's
destructive and that every
single move you make is
calculated and fixed as one of
those moves.
The other way is
non-destructive, where you
build up your image through
using multiple layers.
And any point in that process,
if you make a mistake, or if
you decide you don't like
something, you can
always remove it.
Let me show you what I mean.
Here in this landscape image, we
can say some rather amazing
mountain ranges in the
background and some really
atmospheric moody sky.
Now, I think these ranges need
a little bit more contrast.
I think they could do
with some punch.
And that sky over there
certainly needs burning down a
little bit.
So there's a little bit of work
that we can do to lift
the quality of this image.
I'm going to use the Adjustment
menu over here.
There are my tonal
adjustments.
There are my colour
I'm going for Curves, which
allows me to plot a new map of
the tones in my image.
But look, the problem is that I
can't position that anywhere
on my screen without
having it overlay
across parts of my image.
So I can't really see the image
and the adjustment that
I'm making at the same time.
That's one of the first
problems with
working this way.
But we'll just have to make
due and see how we go.
So I'm going to drop
down the shadows.
I'm going to lift up
the highlights.
I'm going to lock
off the centre.
And yes, I now have more
contrast in my image.
The sky is slightly
more ominous.
The mountain ranges are
certainly more dynamic.
So that's, essentially,
achieved what I was
hoping it would do.
I click OK.
And then I'm done.
The problem is that at some
point, maybe it's next week,
maybe it's even a month later.
I might come back and think,
it's not quite what I wanted.
It's OK.
But maybe I've gone too far.
And I just need to pull that
back a little bit and readjust
some of those things.
So back to Adjustments.
Back to Curves.
But my curve is now
a straight line.
So I don't have the curve
that I adjusted.
I'm stuck with a new curve.
But I can just reverse that.
I can lift the shadows.
I can drop the highlights.
That seems to do what it
says it's going to do.
I can fix that centre point.
I turn that on and off.
And yes, I've reduced
the contrast.
But what I'm doing is I'm
reducing contrast on an image
that I've already increased
the contrast on
in the first place.
So it's not quite what I'm
really interested in doing.
It is, in fact, it's a
destructive method.
And it's one that I would
certainly avoid.
It's not what I would
recommend.
OK.
Let's do it the other way.
Let's go back in history
to the start.
And let's look at how we might
do this building the image
rather than reducing it.
So instead of doing the
adjustment on the image, I'm
going to add a new
adjustment layer.
Same thing.
There are more tones.
There are my colours.
I'm going to choose Curve.
I can even name it if I want--
Contrast.
Hit OK.
And then over here you can
see, first of all,
I've got a new curve.
But it's not covering
up my image.
It's actually a new layer in
Photoshop that's about to do a
very, if not the same thing that
I did before, reduce the
shadows, increase
the highlights,
lock off the midtones.
There's my contrast.
There's the ominous sky.
There is more presence
in the mountains.
I've done the same thing
that I did before.
Except this time, if I've
gone too far, the
curve is still there.
It's always there.
It's saved with the image.
I'm not reducing or destroying
the image in any way.
I'm building on it and adding
new information.
That's the advantage of using
this particular method,
whereas the other method, once
it's done, you've permanently
altered the original image.